<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed draft interview">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2009/07/30 LL</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2011/11/29 PS Added headnote and made corrections.</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014/03/12 EK clean regs</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-02-09 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1932-01-17">
			<supplied resp="MSPP">17 Jan 1932</supplied>
		</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>Questions and Answers by Mrs. Margaret Sanger at Conclusion of her
				Speech</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp064317</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Papers</title>, Library of Congress</bibl>
			<bibl>Library of Congress Microfilm, 65:380</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="BERBE">Berkowitz, Bernard</name>
			<name id="AUD">Audience members</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>This is a transcription of questions from the audience and Sanger's responses following a
			speech Sanger gave to the <org>New History Society</org> at the <org>Park Lane
				Hotel</org>, <place reg="New York, NY">New York</place>, on January 17, 1932. For
			the text of the speech, see "<xref from="129037.xml">My Way to Peace</xref>." Sanger
			made several corrections and comments by hand. The transcriber also made one handwritten
			comment, included because it suggests the content of part of one of Sanger's answers
			that went untranscribed.</p>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="access to" level3="international"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="class-based"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="morality of"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Oregon"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation"
			level3="Postal Code and Regulations"/>
		<index level1="birth rate" level2="efforts to reduce"/>
		<index level1="eugenics"/>
		<index level1="eugenics" level2="birth control and"/>
		<index level1="eugenics" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="eugenics" level2="negative"/>
		<index level1="fertility limitation" level2="of physicaly disabled and diseased"/>
		<index level1="France" level2="birth control in"/>
		<index level1="immigration" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="mentally disabled and diseased" level2="birth control and"/>
		<index level1="Netherlands, the" level2="birth control in"/>
		<index level1="population growth" level2="standard of living and"/>
		<index level1="sterilization" level2="candidates for"/>
		<index level1="&quot;unfit&quot; to reproduce" level2="descriptions of"/>
		<index level1="world peace" level2="MS on"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>QUESTIONS, &amp; ANSWERS BY <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">MRS. MARGARET
				SANGER</person> AT CONCLUSION OF HER SPEECH:-</head>
		<p><q who="AUD">1. I heard it stated that the intellectual and gifted classes sterilize
				themselves. Is there anything to prove that they are sterilized, and that their
				small birth rate is a matter of choice?</q></p>
		<p>There is nothing that will confirm that the intellectuals are sterilized. It is a
			question of <del>choice</del>
			<add>proper knowledge</add>. The people of these classes usually are more ambitious.
			They go to Law Schools and colleges, and marry at a later age thus postponing
			parenthood, but there is nothing in the statistics to show that they are sterilized.
			However, it is better <add>&amp; more</add> possible for them to keep up their standards
			of living and to give to their children all that they require.</p>
		<p><q who="AUD">2. At the coming <org type="conference" reg="Second Geneva Naval Conference"
					>Geneva Conference</org>, will this matter of birth control be taken up into
				conjunction with disarmament?</q></p>
		<p>No. But it should.</p>
		<p><q who="AUD">3. What nation was the first to <add>practice</add> birth control?</q></p>
		<p><place>France</place>.</p>
		<p><q who="AUD">4. In how many states of the <place>United States</place> can birth control
				information literature be legally distributed?</q></p>
		<p>Such literature cannot go through the United States mails. However, the theory and
			history of birth control may be sent by mail in printed form, but letters conveying the
			practical information, the kind that tells what you want to know, is strictly
			forbidden.</p>
		<p><q who="AUD">5. How do you propose to distribute this information and advice in view of
				these restrictions?</q></p>
		<p>We hope to change the law so that physicians may receive up to date literature and
			medical supplies, and be able to enlighten the public.</p>
		<p><q who="AUD">6. Would it not be better, instead of practicing birth control, to reduce
				the hours of labor and increase pay, thus solving the unemployment situation and
					<del>providing</del> thus provide for the surplus population?</q></p>
		<p>I think we would all like to receive a decrease in <supplied resp="MSPP">hours</supplied> and an increase in pay. The
			point is, doesn’t one bring about the other? If you can look into this very deeply, you
			will find out that while it may help primarily, it will not solve the problem
			ultimately, but only lead to a further increase in population. We are suffering because
			of child labor. A child competes with its own parents in industry, and that is why the
			population has been multiplying in order to increase the earning power of the family,
			and has made this problem so acute. This system must be changed, and we have got to have
			birth control.</p>
		<p><q who="AUD">7. Is it not a fact that <place reg="Netherlands">Holland</place> is
				the most peaceful country in the world today because she practices birth
				control?</q></p>
		<p>Yes. Holland was the first country to organize the information on birth control.
				<place>France</place> started it very early at the time of <person
				reg="Bonaparte, Napoleon">Napoleon</person> by distributing contraceptionary advice
			and information, but although the idea was good, she was not as efficient as Holland who
			had the most excellent results to show for it in 40 years. Her death rate has gone down
			considerably. Holland is a peaceful country.</p>
		<p><q who="AUD">8. What is <place reg="Soviet Union">Russia</place> doing today about this
				birth control problem?</q></p>
		<p>In Russia, while the government does not have any provision concerning birth control, or
				<add>for</add> the facilities of distributing scientific information and advice, any
			individual desiring <del>this</del> it may receive instruction and information on his or
			her individual health. When they become married in Russia, they are questioned as to
			where they are going to live, what are their plans for a livelihood, how many children
			they expect to have, etc. (please add to this)</p>
		<p>The labor condition in Russia today is more satisfactorily advanced than in any other
			country in the world.</p>
		<p><q who="AUD">9. What is your idea about immigration?</q></p>
		<p>I believe that it would be better for us to keep the doors closed for another 10 years,
			but not for all time. At least until we have pulled ourselves together; until we have
			our own back yards cleaned up and put in order.</p>
		<p><q who="AUD">10. Is it not unsafe to distribute information on birth control through the
				mails for fear it might fall into the hands of the younger people who are not
				entitled to it, and who might abuse it causing their morals to be corrupted?</q></p>
		<p>We cannot get immoral by knowledge.</p>
		<p>We have clinics where they may receive adequate information for their individual needs.
			This can only be given when the individual comes in person to receive medical
			information from the doctors directly, and we must instruct and encourage the people to
			do this.</p>
		<p>Morality and union never beckon on the outside. There is nothing immoral in knowledge. It
			is from the beginning and from within. After 2,000 years of control over our youth, if
			the church is still afraid to trust our younger people with knowledge, and keep them in
			ignorance and fear, then I must say and confess that they must have been a failure.<lb/>
			(Grand Applause).</p>
		<p><q who="AUD">11. You say that birth control leads to peace. Then why is it that
					<place>Australia</place> and <place>New Zealand</place>, where there is much
				birth control going on, are the must warlike nations, while France has furnished
				less men for wars?</q>
			<add>? Questionable about A. &amp; N.Z.</add></p>
		<p>When talking about controlling the birth rate, it doesn’t necessarily mean that you don’t
			have strong men and a <del>good</del>
			<add>larger</add> population. It is nature through which you control the birth rate. In
			Holland it gave them an increased population, but a slowly increasing population. You
			can increase the population slowly and absorb it easily and without bad results.
			Controlling the birth rate doesn’t mean a decrease in population, but a sturdy healthy
			quality of human beings as in Holland where the men have increased in height from 4 to 5
			inches, with a marked improvement in stature and physical health.</p>
		<p><q who="AUD">12. What can the public do to help you change the laws on birth
			control?</q></p>
		<p>A great deal. People should write to their representatives and Senators in <org
				reg="United States Congress">Congress</org> stating what it may mean to us as a
			principle toward peace. Most of our congressmen are not conscious of this movement, and
			will not act unless we call it to their attention, and we can do it by writing to our
			senators and representative of our state.</p>
		<p><q who="AUD">13. Why not ask all of these people here tonight to write? Well, I would
				like it very much.</q></p>
		<p><q who="AUD">14. Wouldn’t birth control lead us to the possible destruction of the human
				race?</q></p>
		<p>
			<add>
				<q who="BERBE">Note: Please supply answer which dealt with something about an
					instinct of self-preservation.</q>
			</add>
		</p>
		<p>We protect our health and that of our children. The birth rate has gone down in certain
			classes that have had the good things in life. The families that live in poverty and
			ignorance send their children to factories, and they have the worst times. There is a
			better chance of happiness and advancement through means of birth control.</p>
		<p><q who="AUD">15. Would it be advisable to have a health certificate issued before
				marriage?</q></p>
		<p>That is not altogether enough. Only those interested would want this, to insure
			themselves. But if the morons, the feeble, and the diseased who could not secure such a
			certificate, wouldn’t require it at all because they would go and live together and have
			children anyway.</p>
		<p><q who="AUD">16. Have you any definite plan so that the intellectual classes might
				multiply about 700 times in order to improve our society?</q></p>
		<p>What do we need a large population for? It is better to have a number of people to whom
			you could insure a greater amount of happiness. That is what we want.<lb/>
			(Applause)</p>
		<p><q who="AUD">17. In <place>Oregon</place>, a law was passed a few years ago
				requiring that a health certificate be issued before marriage. If those who wanted
				to get married and were unfit went to another state, thus eluding this law, couldn’t
				they be punished for it?</q></p>
		<p>No. They could thus elude the <del>Oregon</del> law, and there is no law against any
			Oregon residents indulging in this practice.</p>
		<p><q who="AUD">18. To what extent have you succeeded in teaching birth control to mental
				defectives?</q></p>
		<p>Most women who come to clinics and other health stations want means of safeguarding their
			health and that of their families. We have a very small percentage of mental defectives
			that are cognizant of the fact that they should not have children. The question of
			methods makes a great deal of difference, and we advise sterilization as the best
			remedy. </p>
		<byline>MARGARET SANGER<lb/> Chairman of the <org>National Committee on Federal
				Legislation for Birth Control.</org></byline>
		<byline>Respectfully submitted:<lb/><person reg="Berkowitz, Bernard">Bernard
				Berkowitz</person>, Recorder<lb/>The New History Society<lb/>.</byline>
	</docBody>
</doc>
