<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2010/03/02 AC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-11 CH fix errors</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1935-06-DD">Standard Date</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Birth Control in Soviet Russia</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp101867</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title>, June 1935</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Library of Congress Microfilm</title> LCM 128:506</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="population" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="politicians" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="Europe" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="eugenics" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="efforts to increase"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="Soviet Union"/>
        <index level1="abortion" level2="in Soviet Union"/>
        <index level1="abortion" level2="frequency of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Birth Control in Soviet Russia</head>
        <p>SO MANY conflicting reports about the practice of birth control and the spread of
            abortions in <place reg="Soviet Union">Russia</place> have been circulated, that I
            decided to make a brief tour last summer and ascertain the facts for myself, as well as
            time would allow.</p>
        <p>I visited dispensaries, hospitals, clinics and <org
                reg="Okhrana Materinstva I Mladenchestva">Institutes for the Protection of
                Motherhood</org> in <place reg="Leningrad, Soviet Union">Leningrad</place>, <place
                reg="Moscow, Soviet Union">Moscow</place>, <place reg="Stalingrad, Soviet Union"
                >Stalingrad</place>, <place reg="Odessa, Soviet Union">Odessa</place> and elsewhere.
            Contrary to the oft-quoted warning that I would see only what I was supposed to see, I
            found that I was able to see anything that I asked to see, and many things that I was
            not supposed to see.</p>
        <p> To understand the Russian birth control situation, and the abortion situation, for the
            two are connected, one must keep in mind the attitude of Soviet Russia toward its women.
            This would delight the heart of the staunchest feminist. Equal rights are a settled and
            accepted fact. Woman is equal to man in every occupation, in sports, in the arts, in
            marriage . . . in all activities. When pregnancy begins this equality ceases.</p>
        <p> Then the woman becomes a protegee of the State. Both the mother and the child are under
            the protection and care of the government, to an extent perhaps never before equalled in
            history.</p>
        <p> As might be expected, given this attitude and the Russian social and political
            philosophy, there are no laws against birth control, and no religious objections. The
            right of a woman to have birth control instruction is clear. And this right need not be
            bulwarked, as in our country, by “health reasons,” “economic reasons,” “eugenic
            reasons,” but is granted as a simple human right.</p>
        <p> It is on this ground that abortions are allowed, though under restrictions to safeguard
            the health of the woman. Abortions must be performed in hospitals under proper
            conditions. The woman must remain in the hospital three days, and must stay at home for
            the following seven days. She receives full pay during this period of absence from
            work.</p>
        <p> Abortions are discouraged, however, and a woman who presents herself for a first
            abortions is urged not to have it. Birth control advice is given largely as a means of
            lowering the tremendous number of abortions. The total number is not known, but the
            number for Moscow alone is roughly estimated at 100,000 per year.</p>
        <p> Birth Control advice is usually given at the <org>Women’s Consultation Centers</org>,
            where women are urged to go not only for medical advice, but for legal, domestic and
            occupational problems as well. Here (as in the dispensaries and hospitals in practically
            every city, town and village I visited) there are posters warning women against
            abortions and urging them to practice contraception instead.</p>
        <p> While this seemed most convincing and encouraging, I was disappointed to find that the
            actual materials available at the birth control clinics were very poor, or that
            materials were lacking altogether. Physicians in charge are familiar with all the
            methods used throughout the world, but no effort is being made, apparently, to import
            any mechanical or chemical supplies. Those manufactures in Russia have not proved
            satisfactory. Qualified manufacturers are needed.</p>
        <p> I was also disappointed to find that research on immunization, which was begun several
            years ago, has apparently discontinued. This is particularly unfortunate in Russia. With
            supplies so poor in quality and so inadequate, the techniques generally used elsewhere
            in <place reg="Europe">Europe</place> and in this country, cannot be followed.</p>
        <p> All the officials with whom I discussed the matter stated that as soon as the economic
            and social plans of Soviet Russia are realized, neither abortions nor contraception will
            be necessary or desired. A functioning Communistic society will assure the happiness of
            every child, and will assume the full responsibility for its welfare and education.</p>
        <p> Abortion, as I have said above, is discouraged and is looked upon as a temporary
            measure. For the present, birth control is encouraged, and better methods would be
            welcomed. It is my impression, however, that Russia does not want a controlled
            population; on the contrary, she wants an increased birthrate. But every medical man and
            woman with whom I talked endorses birth control as a means of lessening abortion, as a
            fundamental right of all women, and as a health measure.</p>
        <p> In summary: theoretically, there are no obstacles to birth control in Russia. It is
            accepted, not on economic grounds, but on the grounds of health and human right.
            Practically, supplies are few and are of poor quality. Russia’s need is for the
            importation and manufacture of tested and reliable supplies. In this respect <place
                reg="United States">America</place> is far ahead. On the other hand, we could well
            take example from Russia, where there are no legal restrictions, no religious
            condemnation, and where birth control instruction is part of the regular welfare service
            of the government. </p>


    </docBody>
</doc>
