<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed draft article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2010/04/28 AC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-11 CH clean regs and other errors</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1938-07-06"><supplied source="MSPP">06 Jun 1938</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Birth Control</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp101839</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congeress</bibl>
            <bibl>Library of Congress Microfilm 128:382</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp>
                <name id="MOSGR">Moscowitz, Grover</name>
                <name id="BIB">Bible</name>
            </resp>

        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="Asia" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="birth control"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Comstock act"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Federal"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="medical community and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods"/>
        <index level1="China" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="England" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Europe" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="family size"/>
        <index level1="India"/>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="New York City" level2="birth control in"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Birth Control</head>
        <byline>By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></byline>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub"><emph rend="underline">THE SITUATION AND NEED in 1914.</emph></head>
            <p>To a new generation now coming of age, the question often arises: “Why all this fuss
                about Birth Control? Everybody knows it. Anyone can get it. Everybody practices it.”
                Often the more conservative and eugenically-minded remark: “The trouble is that the
                wrong people are using it and the people who should practice Birth Control are not
                doing so.” Occasionally someone in the group will ask forlornly, “If Birth Control
                continues, won’t our civilization be doomed?”</p>
            <p>These remarks indicate a lack of knowledge of the history, needs and the ultimate aim
                of the Birth Control movement. Among those old enough to be married in 1914, or even
                as late as 1920, these comments could not possibly have taken place. The term “Birth
                Control” was not coined until 1914, and did not become generally used until 1916
                when our educational campaign was first launched. Then when an intelligent couple
                became aware of its meaning and desired to apply the knowledge to their own lives,
                they asked, sought, and looked in vain for practical information. Indeed, it was
                considered rather “indelicate” for a woman to voice such a request to her family
                doctor, while the husband surreptitiously consulted the druggist behind closed
                doors.</p>
            <p>The responsibility for bringing a child into the world (like famine, pestilence, and
                disease) was laid upon the shoulders of <name type="deity">God</name> and provision
                for it was expected from the same source. Seldom did parents assume that the birth
                of a child could be a voluntary act on their part. The health of the parents and
                their ability to provide for children did not determine the size of the family.
                Nature and chance were the sole dictators of the birth rate.</p>
            <p>The puritanical intolerance then prevailing on this subject was a reflection from the
                biblical view that children were a penalty meted out to atone for man’s
                    <add>original</add> error in the <place>Garden of Eden</place>, and a woman’s
                suffering at childbirth was the fulfillment of the Biblical injunction “<q who="BIB"
                        ><add>that in pain and sorrow</add>” <del>in pain and travail</del>
                    <del>labor</del> shall she <del>bring forth</del>
                    <del>bear children</del></q>. This together with the edict from Genesis that man
                shall increase <add>should “<q who="BIB">be fruitful</q></add>
                <q who="BIB">and multiply and replenish the earth</q>”, form<add>ed</add> the
                bulwark of public opinion that the Birth Control movement had to meet in 1914.</p>
            <p>The effort to break down this abysmal ignorance and confusion did not gain its
                national momentum until 1921 when the famous <org>Town Hall</org> Meeting <add>at
                    the time of the <org reg="American Birth Control Conference, 1st">First National
                        Birth Control Conference</org>,</add> in <place rend="New York, NY">New York
                    City</place>, was closed by the police.</p>
            <p>The national publicity, during and following this outrageous procedure enabled the
                public to get a clearer idea as to what Birth Control really meant; how it differed
                from abortion, infanticide and other crude barbaric methods of population control.
                By defining Birth Control as “the conscious control of the birth rate by means that
                prevent the conception”, emphasis was placed on <emph rend="underline"
                    >prevention</emph> rather than interference of life, and on <emph
                    rend="underline">control</emph> rather than limitation.</p>
            <p>This definition opened new horizons of thought. The idea that a child could be
                consciously conceived and brought into the world by choice rather than chance was
                described by <person reg="Shaw, George Bernard">Bernard Shaw</person> as the most
                revolutionary idea of the 20th century.</p>
            <p>Not only the people living in tenements, slum and rural districts were without
                knowledge of Birth Control but even the middle and upper classes were
                surreptitiously using methods that were often injurious and far from reliable.
                    <del>This situation existed</del>
                <add>While millions of women had an overwhelming desire to have only the number of
                    children they could properly care for, yet there was a shyness and a hesitancy
                    and a reticence in making this need known.</add> It must be recalled that in
                contrast to the voluminous literature and enormous trade in commercial
                contraceptives which exists today, there was at that time practically no literature
                for the general public that presented the subject of sex, marriage, or birth, to say
                nothing of contraception, in a wholesome, scientific spirit. Indeed, there was
                scarcely a vocabulary in which these subjects could be decently discussed.</p>
            <p>Medical journals avoided the subject; medical text books were equally guiltless;
                medical societies refused to even consider the subject. While over all loomed the
                confusing laws, both Federal and State, which classed the subject of contraception
                with abortion, obscenity and pornography. For over 60 years the Federal statutes in
                particular remained an obstacle to the progress of the movement, making it a
                question of privilege and not of right for a doctor to use the mails and common
                carriers to obtain any available literature or supplies from abroad. He could warn a
                patient against endangering her life by another pregnancy, but he could not give her
                the practical information that she needed. This then was the state of affairs which
                young people entering upon marriage had to face <add>at that time</add>.</p>
            <p>A personal survey of 150 hospital clinics in Greater New York in 1918 revealed that,
                with one exception, none of these clinics would give contraceptive information to a
                woman, though she suffered from an acute case of tuberculosis where another
                pregnancy constituted a threat to her life.</p>
            <p>Did women die? Yes, they did die from this neglect. Thousands and thousands of them
                died each year. Little children, particularly new-born babies, were snuffed out of
                life when the mother died, or because their vitality was too weak to survive.</p>
            <p>The main thing that had to be done was to arouse the public to action. This was no
                easy task, considering the prevailing attitude toward the subject of birth and
                sex.</p>
            <p>To even utter the words “Birth Control” frequently brought the police into action.
                Meetings, called to discuss a change in the law, were closed before we had said a
                word. Public halls and even hotel auditoriums were refused us, and even when local
                groups were sufficiently acquainted with the subject to inform the officials that
                the law would not be violated, meetings nevertheless were conducted with half a
                dozen policemen standing the halls, and several plain clothesmen taking down every
                word the speaker uttered. Nursing infants in the arms of their mothers were taken
                out of the halls because the word “abortion” was mentioned by the
                    speaker<add>!</add> Any attempt to frankly answer the question
                    <add>frequently</add> asked by the audience as to where contraceptive
                information could be obtained could not be replied to unless one was willing to
                suffer arrest.</p>
            <p>Letters, hundreds of thousands of letters, from poor, worried, harassed mothers
                pleading for advice could not be answered without violating Federal laws. A letter
                from a mother of twelve children with only three surviving might come begging for
                knowledge to save those three little lives by not having others come too fast. To
                reply to such a letter, giving her information, or directing her to a doctor in her
                community who might help her, or <add>even</add> sending medical information to
                    <add>her own</add> a doctor to enable him to advise her, any and all such action
                subjected the writer to the possibility of five years in a penitentiary or a $5000
                fine!</p>
            <p>Absurd? Of course, it is absurd. And that is exactly the reason why the Birth Control
                movement has grown so rapidly and has made such phenomenal progress during so short
                a period of time.</p>
            <p>But this progress did not come easily. A study of the subject in other countries had
                to be made. Facts and statistics had to be gathered. Conflicting opinions raged.
                During the early years of agitation, before a constructive program could be
                launched, there took place a period of <gap reason="illegible" extent="two words"/>
                arrests, <del>violations</del>, <add>law suits, challenges, <gap reason="illegible"
                        extent="one word"/> jail sentences,</add> street meetings, all of which were
                a constant source of publicity, sometimes good, sometimes confusing. Upon my return
                from <place reg="Netherlands">Holland</place> and <place>England</place> in 1915 a
                four-point program was begun. In <place>Europe</place> where I had gathered my
                knowledge and facts, I also gleaned a new vision for the movement in <place
                    reg="United States">America</place>. The program now was <del>began</del> to
                agitate, educate, organize, and legislate to effect the establishment of clinics
                where contraceptive information could be obtained by the working classes.</p>
            <p><del>Their problems were presented and the American public listened.</del>
                <add>I soon found</add> the problems affecting the working class were precisely the
                problems of individuals in every class. No mother in this whole country would choose
                of her own accord to willingly bring a feeble-minded, crippled, defective, or sickly
                child into the world. <del>Of that I was</del>
                <add>My love for my own three children made me</add> certain <add> of that</add>. To
                avoid such catastrophes, millions of mothers pleaded constantly for some means to
                enable them to space the birth of their children, to give them a chance to grow
                healthy, to keep them out of factories and workshops until they had finished their
                schooling, and to give them a better start and chance in life than they had had
                themselves. These mothers pleaded for the information to protect their own health
                and often to preserve their lives so that they might live to bring up the children
                already born. They asked for some means to enable them to keep their families
                small.</p>
            <p>INSERT SECTION 2 <del>From the beginning</del>, the masses, especially the working
                people, were with me. But they had no influence to support our program. Those few
                intellectuals who did see eye to eye with me counseled me against attempting a
                national program without money, prestige, or influential support. “It can’t be
                done”, they would say. “You can’t make human nature over. People don’t want to
                control their sex lives. They won’t bother to do what they are advised to do. The
                poor are just natural breeders, like rabbits and pigs. Let them alone.” Again when I
                tried to enlist the support of the medical profession and asked what information I,
                as a nurse, could bring to these needy mothers, the answer was: “Let them use
                self-control. Sleep in separate rooms. Abstinence! Continence!” But such advice did
                not answer the need. When followed, it often broke up happy homes, and resulted in
                sundering apart loving parents from each other and their cherished children.
                Psychiatrists could tell untold stories of depressed and broken lives as a result of
                this unwise advice.</p>
            <p>The question remained. How to go about it to awaken the public and especially the
                women of America, a large number of whom already freed from the burden of
                child-bearing, with leisure and opportunity to enter the front ranks of the suffrage
                movement and to initiate and organize other activities in clubs and educational
                    centers<add>?</add> How to get these women to see and feel the problems of the
                millions of working women less fortunate themselves? This was my task. Would they
                listen? Not always. Did they do anything? Not always. Some of them helped. Here and
                there a few courageous women gathered around them fearless groups to take a stand to
                help broaden our sphere of activity, but in the mass, the organized strength of
                women was sought for many years in vain. It was not until 1935 <add>twenty years
                    later</add> at <place reg="Detroit, MI">Detroit</place> that the <org>General
                    Federation of Women’s Clubs</org>, representing <del>three</del>
                <add>two</add> million women, endorsed by <del>a vote of 327 to 18</del>
                <add>an overwhelmingly favorable vote</add> our Bills then before <org
                    reg="United States Congress">Congress</org> to exempt the medical profession
                from the restrictions of the Federal statues.</p>
            <p>Was it because these fortunate, intelligent, civic-minded women did not believe in
                birth control? Not at all. The great majority of them believed absolutely in it as
                their own small families proved, and stated their belief in their private
                conversations. But to take a public stand--as a member of a club-- was a different
                matter. There has grown up in America a new psychology among organizations which
                tends to inhabit individual members, also members of Boards, from committing
                themselves to anything that might be considered controversial. The old, pre-war,
                free, discursive, controversial attitude towards civic problems has been superseded
                by a desire to have everything cozy and comfortable, unruffled, and above all else,
                harmonious and peaceful within club ranks. The result has been a stultifying
                deadliness which has hampered the clear thinking and the honest expression of
                opinion among the individuals in these groups. This unfortunate attitude still
                dominates many philanthropic and social welfare community agencies.</p>
            <p>In spite of these obstacles, however, the educational campaign waged by the
                    <org>National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control</org> from 1929
                to 1937 succeeded in enlisting the public support not only of the General Federation
                of Women’s Clubs, the <org reg="Natonal Young Woman's Christian Association"
                    >National Y.W.C.A.</org>, the <add><org>Committee on Marriage</org> &amp;
                    the</add> Home of the <org>Federal Council of Churches of Christ in
                    America</org>, <org>the Central Conference of American Rabbis</org>, the
                    <org>Congregational Church of America</org>, <add><org
                        reg="National Women's Medical Association">the National Women’s Medical
                        Assoc </org></add>but of almost a thousand other <add>important</add>
                organizations, representing medical, religious and public endorsement of almost 25
                million adult men and women. This great weight of public opinion was reflected in
                the far-reaching decision handed down in November, 1936, by the U.S. Circuit Court
                of Appeals which upheld the right of the medical profession to give contraceptive
                advice “<q who="MOSGR">for <del>the promotion of the general health</del>
                    <add>purpose of saving life or promoting the</add> well-being of their
                    patients.</q>” <add>The U.S. Government, though its Attorney General accepted
                    this court decision and issued appropriate instructions establishing the
                    legality of confiscated materials.</add> With its legal objectives achieved and
                clarified by this decision the National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth
                Control disbanded. <del>Six months later</del>
                <add><org>The American Medical Association</org></add> in June, 1937, <del>the
                    A.M.A.</del> adopted the recommendations of its <org
                    reg="American Medical Association Committee on Contraceptive Practice">Committee
                    on Contraceptive Practices</org>, recognizing the medical importance of Birth
                Control and urging its inclusion in the curricula of medical colleges. I am
                frequently asked if I am not proud of the great progress made in this movement
                during my lifetime. <add>3</add> I do recognize that we have achieved and
                accomplished excellent results in a short time; nevertheless, I feel that from the
                viewpoint of the unchecked, maternal deaths, the loss of child life, the
                hopelessness and helplessness and misery of millions of parents still unable to
                obtain Birth Control information, <del>I feel </del>the battle is not yet won. We
                are still on the firing line. the ultimate victory--our goal since 1916--the
                democratization of birth control knowledge--making it available to the poor as well
                as to the upper classes--still remains to be won.</p>
            <p>But meanwhile, with our work still unfinished, we must meet the arguments and
                opposition of those who fail to realize that they are viewing at this time a vast
                chance in the mores of the American people that is still in process. The complaint
                is made that we are producing faster from the illiterate, ignorant, indigent,
                diseased classes, and outbreeding the intelligent, responsible elements of our
                society. We often hear that the college graduates, the professional classes, are not
                giving the nation the number of children needed to guarantee brains and stamina for
                the nation’s future. Shall the answer be a cradle competition between the two
                groups? Shall we beat the tom-toms and sing idyllic songs of the pleasures and joys
                of motherhood, while thousands die unnecessarily during child-birth? Shall we tax
                and tax and tax the healthy population so that the derelict population can increase
                their numbers? This is National suicide. <del>I cannot <gap reason="illegible"
                        extent="one word"/> firmly my conviction that this is the way to national
                    suicide politically, economically and physically.</del>↓</p>
            <p>The further contention is made that more consumers are needed to put the wheels of
                industry into action, when already millions of consumers are unable to consume or to
                purchase what has already been produced. Yet we compel this same group of
                non-employed, non-producers, non-consumers to add more and more and yet more to the
                population, <add>until today more than half the babies born each year are born to
                    this <gap reason="illegible" extent="one word"/>
                </add> A large proportion of this group will always remain unemployed owing to the
                increasing labor-saving inventions which have for the past generation displace those
                who have only labor power to sell. The future will not need more hands, but more
                brains. It is to quality of population and not to quantity that we should now direct
                our attention.</p>
            <p>Why not give to these groups, the one-third of the nation that is poorly-fed, poorly
                housed and poorly clothed, those living in thousands of tent colonies and migratory
                camps, those gleaning only the meagrest necessities of life, the share-croppers, the
                cotton pickers, the beet-field workers, the same knowledge now available to the more
                fortunate portions of the population? Open the doors of knowledge to them, and see
                how quickly they will avail themselves of it! Note how their conditions will
                improve. Present to them the value and harmlessness of birth control and
                sterilization, and it will not need a college degree for them to understand and
                accept it voluntarily and gladly.</p>
            <p>Perhaps the greatest contribution which any of us can make to our country is a
                constructive idea to promote its welfare. But it is the responsibility of those in
                power to see that that idea is not hampered through classes. Birth Control is no
                longer a theory. It is here to stay, because it represents a fundamental application
                of intelligence to human life. Its values have been recognized by eminent
                physicians, sociologists, scientists, and civic leaders throughout the world.</p>
            <p>It is now for those in power to decide whether the acknowledged benefits of birth
                control to the individual will be extended to the masses. It is the failure to
                extend the knowledge to all classes that constitutes the threat or menace to our
                civilization--not the knowledge itself.</p>
            <p>Certainly birth control knowledge has been accepted by the intelligent and upper
                classes. All progress seems to start there, but it does not need to remain there. It
                is the exclusiveness of this knowledge which has upset the quality of population. To
                carry this knowledge to the <del>masses</del>
                <add>people</add> is the duty of those who assume the civic responsibility of
                directing public welfare. We must still replace with vision and courage the fears of
                timid officials of government agencies and boards of philanthropy and others who
                dictate policies affecting the great masses. From now on the responsibility
                    <del>of</del>
                <add>for</add> the quality of the nation must be laid at their doors. We have made
                birth control knowledge available; we have made materials accessible. Thousands and
                thousands of records testify to the value of these methods to individual welfare. To
                secure the inclusion of such service in county, state, national health programs is
                the only way that all those who need such information will be enabled to obtain it.
                When this is done, then truly we can say “Our battle is won.” Meanwhile the
                educational work done in America continues to accomplish much and its influence is
                    <gap reason="illegible" extent="two words"/> felt abroad as well. The words
                “birth control” have encircled the globe. Its ideas and practice have been eagerly
                accepted by the masses in nearly every country of the world. In some of the more
                progressive countries, as in England, birth control service has already been
                incorporated in the <gap reason="illegilbe" extent="three words"/> Infant and
                Maternity Welfare Centers sponsored by the <org>British Ministry of Health</org>.
                    <org>The Chinese <gap reason="illegible" extent="two words"/> Medical
                    Association</org> has recommended similar action: the <org>Indian Medical
                    Association </org>has likewise taken a progressive stand. Birth Control is not a
                matter of theory among the tragic millions in the Orient. It is welcomed as a
                practical solution to a desperate human need. We have taken to the Orient a simple
                inexpensive easily used method that has already helped to solve some of the problems
                of brining aid to the poorest. <add>New horizons stretch before us as a wider
                    understanding of population problems awaken those who look for international
                    peace to consider the population factors underlying national policies that lead
                    to wars &amp; national agressions. (continue with 8)</add>
            </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">SUMMARY OF ACCOMPLISHMENTS</head>

            <p>The general, national breakdown of secrecy and reticence, not only on the subject of
                birth control but in relation to the entire field of sex education.</p>
            <p> A sane, scientific approach to all questions of sex psychology.</p>
            <p>An increasing recognition of birth control as a part of prevented and public health
                procedure.</p>
            <p> Magazines and publications openly treating the subjects with frankness and editorial
                implications of importance to public welfare.</p>
            <p>National public poles taken among all classes of population reveal 87% desire
                extention of birth control service <add>under medical guidance</add>
            </p>
            <p>Same polls reveal clarification in public mind that birth control is not
                abortion.</p>
            <p>Nearly 400 birth control clinics established under medical supervision.</p>
            <p>Hospitals, social agencies, county and state public health projects have begun to
                include birth control subjects <add>practice.</add>
            </p>
            <p>American Medical Association has recognized contraception as medical project
                    <add>importance.</add>
            </p>
            <p>American government through its Attorney-General accepts court decision as law.</p>
            <p>Birth Control has spread to the Orient, <place>China</place>, <place>Japan</place>,
                    <place>India</place>, <place>Malay</place>, <place>Burma</place>,
                    <place>Indo-China</place>, <place>Egypt</place>, as well as to other countries
                in the near East. <add>&amp; <place>Europe</place>.</add>
            </p>
        </div>

    </docBody>
</doc>
