<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed draft article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2009/07/06 PN</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-10 ch CLEAN REGS</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1930-00-00">1930</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Do Women Want Children?</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp101918</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
            <bibl>LCM 128:683</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="SOC">Socrates</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
            <name id="BAKPO">Baker, Polly</name>
            <name id="BIB">Bible</name>
            <name id="LAT">Latin</name>
            <name id="DELFL">Dell, Floyd</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="men" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="maternal feelings"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
        <index level1="family size" level2="men and"/>
        <index level1="death rate" level2="decline of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head><del>Should</del>
            <add>Do</add> Women Want Children?</head>
        <byline>by <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">MS</person></byline>
        <p>“<q who="SOC">And what about the procreation of children?</q>” <person>Socrates</person>
            ask this question in one of the dialogues of <person>Plato</person>; <del>but</del>
            <add>and</add> from that day to this men seem to have found no satisfactory answer--no
            answer, at any rate, satisfactory to those upon whom the chief burden of procreation
            falls. Do Men Want Children? This is the question asked and answered in these pages by
                <person reg="Russell, Bertrand">Bertrand Russell</person> and <person
                reg="Dell, Floyd">Floyd Dell</person>. Mr. Russell seems to say “No”: Mr Dell quite
            emphatically says “Yes!” But neither of them, unless my memory deceives me, realizes
            that the question they are seeking to answer, sinks into utter irrelevance until a more
            important one has been answered. That is: Do Women Want Children? </p>
        <p>On the part of Messrs. Russell and Dell, as on the part of most intelligent people, there
            lies the unconscious assumption that <add>all</add> women do want babies; and beneath
            this assumption, another to the effect that any woman who does not desire to become a
            mother is abnormal, neurotic and morbid. The joys of motherhood have been so
            persistently advertized, the charms of babyhood so colorfully and so sentimentally
            depicted, that it has become almost sacrilege to warn young men and women standing at
            the threshold of life to stop, look and listen. Yet those of us who are convinced that
            such a warning is an imperative necessity at the present moment, do not aim to minimize
            traditional reverence for parenthood, but rather to develop and to intensify the sense
            of its solemn responsibilities.</p>
        <p>Do women want children? I have about come to the conclusion that the only satisfactory
            answer to such a question is that of the <person reg="Unknown">old professor</person>
            who, likewise confronted with a difficult and practically unanswerable question, said:
                <q who="UNK">“Yes–-in the sense that they do! And no–-in the sense that they do
                not!”</q></p>
        <p>Some do; some do not. But what all women want--and I have never in my long and varied
            experience found one who did not--is the right to decide for themselves whether they
            shall undertake maternity or not, <del>and how,</del> and where, and when. This <add>is
                a</add> new attitude. In the old days the ordinary woman was incessantly engaged in
            childbearing. There was no <del>cessation</del>
            <add>relief</add> from this incessant slavery. </p>
        <p>But woe to any woman who dared to bring children into the world without the consent and
            sponsorship of some lord and master! Her task was undertake unquestioningly the
            biological role–-his to make the decision. <q who="BAKPO">“I have brought five fine
                children into the world, at the risk of my own life,”</q> Miss <person
                reg="Baker, Polly">Polly Baker</person> pleaded before a Court of Judicature in the
            colony of <place>Connecticut</place> in the eighteenth century, some years before the
            outbreak of the American Revolution. The poor girl was unmarried. Twice she had been
            compelled to pay heavy fines for being an unmarried mother; and twice she had been
            publicly whipped for wanting–-and having–-children without benefit of clergy. Now she
            was before the august court for bringing a fifth child into the world. <q who="BAKPO">“I
                have maintained them well by my own industry, without burdening the township, and
                would have done it better, had it not been for the heavy charges and fines I have
                paid. Can it be a crime–in the nature of things, I mean,”</q> so the indignant Polly
            Baker went on, <q who="BAKPO">“Can it be a crime to add to the number of the king’s
                subjects, in a new country that really wants inhabitants?</q>” </p>
        <p>Her only offence was indeed that she had wanted to have children and had had them. It is
            recounted that Polly Baker’s defence of her course was so effective that the Court
            dispensed with her punishment, and one of the judges married her the next day! They
            lived happily ever afterwards, the old account states, and Polly’s character became
            irreproachable–-she had twenty more children by the Judge! </p>
        <p>Now the case of Polly Baker seems to indicate that woman are willing to suffer disgrace
            and punishment in fulfilling the biblical injunction to increase and multiply. I
            suspect, however, that in her eloquent plea to the colonial court of judicature, poor
            Polly was making a virtue of necessity, and that her plea in defence of free and
            independent maternity had been composed by some clever <person reg="Franklin, Benjamin"
                >male lawyer</person>. But that defence, clever as it was, would not be
                <del>applicable</del>
            <add>valid</add> today. There is no pressing need to add to the number of the <person
                reg="George V (England)">King</person>’s subject, nor to that of the American
            commonwealth. Our country is no longer a young one, nor in need of people, as
            immigration laws and the unemployment crisis sufficiently indicate. Populations have
            increased beyond the dream of the ancients. Vast new continents have been discovered and
            settled. Despite the checks of pestilence and famines and wars, and that of a decreasing
            birth-rate in all civilized countries, there is no actual decrease in the number of
            people, but a constant increase. In other words, it is no longer necessary as a racial
            duty to <q who="BIB">“increase and multiply.”</q>
        </p>
        <p>Add to these considerations the significant fact that science is actually lengthening the
            span of life--so that for each individual born into this world the chance of survival
            and of living to a ripe old age are becoming more and more certain, and it becomes an
            inevitable conclusion that in future generation will succeed generation at a much
            retarded rate. In certain countries where the birth- and death-rates are inordinately
            high, there may be approximately four generations to a century; among civilized people
            this has been reduced to three. But we may now look forward to an era when there will be
            no more than two generations, or even less--to the century. In other words, the
            death-rate will be appreciably decreased. And this decrease will <foreign
                rend="underline" lang="LAT">ipso facto</foreign> bring about a decrease in the
            birth-rate. When there is no need to replenish the extravagant wastage of human life by
            the procreation of new lives, there will be less coercion and compulsion exercised upon
            womankind to produce them. When that state is definitely established--in brief, when
            there is more free-will and less compulsion, we shall be able to decide whether woman
            want children. </p>
        <p>At least they will be free to decide <add>for themselves</add>--a privilege that is far
            too restricted today, despite all our boasted enlightenment and progress. Looking into
            the future--and it is quite futile and silly to discuss these crucial racial problems
            from any other point of view than that of the future well-being of the race--it is
            impossible to avoid seeing the approach of a period when all potential parents--husbands
            and wives alike--will be compelled to sacrifice their individual caprice and desire in
            the interests of the good of the racial community at large. The question will not be
            then; “do men want children?” or, “do women want children?” but rather: Who is best
            fitted to hand on the torch of life to the future generations? </p>
        <p>With their innate genius for visualizing and dramatizing the basic truths of life in
            symbols of telling beauty, the Greeks established the great race torch (or
            Lampadephoria) in honor of the god <name type="deity">Prometheus</name>, who was said to
            have conferred the gift of the divine fire upon the human race. This race was run at
            night. The great torches were lighted at the altar of <name type="">Eros</name>, and the
            race was run in relays. Each contestant passed on his torch undimmed to his successor.
            Here is a beautiful and striking symbol of parenthood, the most sacred and the most
            serious of all human functions. But we should not neglect the full significance of this
            beautiful ritual. Those who ran the race were fitted by training to carry the lighted
            torch; to compete in the race was not an honor indiscrimately conferred. It was not a
                <soCalled>“free for all.”</soCalled>
        </p>
        <p>Today, with the vast amount of sentimentalizing over motherhood and babyhood, and the
            deliberate minimizing of its dangers and hazards, parenthood is too often <del>
                <supplied resp="MSPP">endured</supplied>
            </del>
            <add>undertaken</add> lightly and irresponsibly. Many young women who are quite strong
            enough to endure the physical ordeal of pregnancy, are deplorably unfitted for the even
            more important task of raising their children after they are born. In 1865 <person
                reg="Trollope, Anthony">Anthony Trollope</person> wrote: <q who="TROAN">“I must
                protest that American babies are an unhappy race... They are never punished; they
                are never banished, snubbed, and kept in the background... and yet they are wretched
                and uncomfortable.”</q> We may pride ourselves upon the progress we have made in
            improving the behavior of our children. But who can deny the fact that those young
            people who enter parenthood with the sophisticated carelessness with which they might
            enter a speakeasy are usually found quite incapable of coping with the complex problems
            of infant behavior? And is any crime quite so despicable as the ruining or blighting of
            a child’s whole future by the neglect of early discipline? Anthony Trollope may have
            been unjust in his criticism of American parents; but even today, he is worth repeating
                <del>in his interrogation</del>
            <add>when he asks</add>: <q who="TROAN">“Can it be, I wonder, that children are happier
                when they are made to obey orders, and are sent to bed at six o’clock, than when
                allowed regulate their own conduct?”</q> Parenthood does not end with having a baby.
            It merely begins there!</p>
        <p>It may be indeed important, as Floyd Dell claims it is, to seek the road of
            self-development and self-realization through the winding path of parenthood; but we
            need not look far afield to come to the realization that the vast majority of fathers
            and mothers in this great country were quite oblivious of any such motives--those or any
            other. Parenthood was thrust upon them--the child was a <q who="DELFL">“little
                accident”</q> to use Mr. Dell’s profitable title. What I have been battling for
            these twenty years or more is conscious, responsible parenthood–and more particularly
            consciousness motherhood. And so our intial question: Do Women Want Children? must be
            resolved into its component parts. If and when they do, they must know how, and when and
            where. And if they do not, they must be empowered to refrain from motherhood, without
            sacrifice of reputation and dignity, until the auspicious moment arrives. For it has
            been, and still is, chance, irresponsible, thoughtless motherhood and fatherhood that
            cause the miseries and tragedies of the world--not the much-condemned and blamed
            childlessness that seems so wicked to unctuous critics of our morality--so many of them
            childless themselves!</p>
        <p>To those who perpetuate the old fallacy that every woman wants children and if she wants
            them ought to have them, I am always tempted to repeat the words of a penetrating
            American thinker who has long been dead and forgotten. <q who="UNK">“Probably there is
                no greater humbug in the world,”</q> he said, <q who="UNK">“than that which deludes
                the woman who thinks it is a gay thing to have a baby, hit or miss, damned or saved.
                Nevertheless, it is a humbug which nine-tenths of our people love to get
            into.”</q></p>
        <p>These words are as true today as they were in the nineteenth century when they were
            spoken. In spite of the admirable strides made by science and gynecology during this
            century, maternity remains an extremely hazardous occupation in these United States. The
            maternal mortality rate, from all puerperal causes, remains, according to the reports of
            the <org reg="United States Children's Bureau">Children’s Bureau</org> of our federal
            government, higher than that in any civilized country of the globe; and statistics were
            obtained from no less than twenty-one of these in a recent survey.</p>


    </docBody>
</doc>
