<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/06/13 CE</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-18 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1937-06-00">June 1937</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Birth Control: The Doctor's Duty</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp101902</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Clinical Medicine and Surgery</title> (June 1937), pp.
                242-244.</bibl>
            <bibl><title>LCM</title>128:0591</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="DICRO">Dickinson, Robert Latou, Dr.</name>
            <name id="FAIHE">Fairchild, Henry Pratt, Dr.</name>
            <name id="NCMHS">Survey of the National Committee on Maternal Health</name>
            <name id="USCCA">United States Circuit Court of Appeals</name>
            <name id="WILJO">Williams, John Whitridge, Dr.</name>
            <name id="WILPR">Willson, Prentiss J., Dr.</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>For other versions, see Library of Congress Microfilm, 128:0623A,
            128:0623B, 128:575, 128:0620, and <title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title>,
            S71:0940.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits and risks"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="in marriages"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Comstock act"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="legal cases"
            level3="U.S. V. One Package of Japanese contraceptives'"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="legalization of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="medical community and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="research"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="socioeconomic benefits of"/>
        <index level1="child spacing"/>
        <index level1="family planning"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="infant"/>
        <index level1="physicians" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="population growth" level2="natural resources and"/>
        <index level1="population growth" level2="regulation of"/>
        <index level1="population growth" level2="standard of living and"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="government" level3="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="government" level3="public health programs"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Birth Control: The Doctor's Duty</head>
        <byline>by <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>, <place
                reg="New York City, NY">New York City</place></byline>
        <p>Hundreds of articles, thousands upon thousands of words, have been written about birth
            control since the term was coined in 1914. But the idea behind all the pros and cons is
            as simple as all truth. Birth control is the use of scientific knowledge to remove blind
            chance as the chief deciding factor in the birth of children and to control the birth
            rate by means that <emph>prevent</emph> conception. Scientific methods of birth control
            involve the use of chemical and mechanical methods of contraception.</p>
        <p>The history of the concept of conscious control of conception goes back more than a
            hundred years, to the writings of <person reg="Malthus, Thomas Robert">Robert
                Malthus</person> and <person reg="Mill, John Stuart">James Mill</person>, and man
            has attempted, from earliest antiquity, to save himself from the consequences of his own
            fertility. War, famine, pestilence, infanticide, abortion, and sexual customs dictating
            periods of enforced abstinence have, through the long centuries, acted as checks upon
            population and the birth rate.</p>
        <p> A survey of the sociologic and moral roots of the birth control movement has no place in
            this article, for our concern is with today and tomorrow. We should remember, however,
            that her is no upstart, twentieth century idea, born of industrialism, modern unrest,
            and other factors, that it is sometimes the fashion to deplore. The human race has been
            conscious of this problem since earliest written history, and in all stages of
            civilization. The reason is not far to seek. The amount of the earth’s surface capable
            of supporting life is strictly limited. On the other hand, Nature, to insure survival,
            has equipped living creatures, mankind among them, with a disproportionate physiologic
            capacity to increase and multiply. The result, as <person
                reg="Fairchild, Henry Pratt, Dr.">Professor Henry Pratt Fairchild</person> has
            pointed out in his article “<title type="article">Population and War</title>,” is that
                “<q who="FAIHE">every species in existence periodically produces offspring at a rate
                which, if there were nothing to stop it, would overflow the earth is a very few
                generations</q>.”</p>
        <p>The hazards of survival in the vegetable and animal kingdoms maintain the balance. With
            man, the same checks held population increase and means of subsistence in equilibrium
            well into modern times. But the magnificent achievements of medical and other sciences
            have dramatically changed the picture--and no one would wish to set back the clock.</p>
        <p>The young men and women who are entering the medical profession today take their place in
            a noble assemblage, join the ranks of those who have succored mankind, and it is because
            of this very fact that the problem of conscious control of the birth rate--birth
            control--is peculiarly their problem and their responsibility.</p>
        <p>I can do no better than to go to the heart of the matter by quoting the challenging
            statement of the late <person reg="Williams, John Whitridge, Dr.">J. Whitridge
                Williams</person>, M.D., beloved and revered by physicians throughout the
            country.</p>
        <p>“<q who="WILJO">Where should we stand as medical men?</q>” Dr. Williams wrote, in the
                <title type="journal">Journal of the American Medical Association</title>, nearly
            nine years ago (issue of Oct. 27, 1928). “<q who="WILJO">I hold that it is just as much
                our duty to give contraceptive advice when medically indicated as it is to advocate
                the employment of any other prophylactic measure. . . If we feel that such advice is
                necessary, we must give directions as to how it can be made effective, for if we do
                one without the other we are failing in our duty as physicians and in great part are
                wasting our time</q>.”</p>
        <p>Is the young doctor sent out of medical school today (to say nothing of those graduated
            in past years) equipped to give effective advice on contraception? Unfortunately we
            cannot answer with a clear affirmative. For though the medical indications for
            conception are many and clear cut, a thorough grounding in contraceptive technic is not
            included in the curriculums of all medical schools.</p>
        <p>In 1933, the <org>National Committee on Maternal Health</org> made a survey of 76 Grade A
            medical schools, inquiring into the teaching of contraception and sterilization. Thirty
            schools reported no contraceptive teaching, though some were planning for it and
            approved it in principle. The accompanying table shows the total number of schools
            teaching the subject, and the method of instruction.</p>
        <p>The survey’s findings were summed up (in part) as follows: “<q who="NCMHS">Many of the
                Grade A medical schools are including both contraception and sterilization in their
                courses of instruction to students, but no school appears to have laid out a
                definite course in either subject as part of its curriculum. The subjects are taught
                by occasional lectures or clinical instruction or both, and usually in the senior
                year</q>.”</p>
        <p>No survey has been made since 1933, but it is safe to state that, though recent graduates
            may be better equipped in this field of preventive medicine than their older colleagues,
            they themselves still feel the inadequacy of their training. Physicians and students
            welcome the opportunity of observing technic at birth control organizations for not only
            lay, but technical data, and have been quick to see the value of the <title
                type="journal">Journal of Contraception</title>, a pioneering periodical for members
            of the medical and scientific professions.</p>
        <p>There is, however, ample evidence of steady and increasing support of birth control and a
            recognition of its place in preventive medicine and public health. Organized medical
            groups, as well as individual physicians, have gone on record in support of the
            principles of birth control and the movement to wipe out legal restrictions, which
            latter was the major objective of the <org>National Committee on Federal Legislation for
                Birth Control</org>. Nearly one hundred medical bodies took such action, among them
            the <org>American Gynecological Society</org>; the <org>American Neurological
                Association</org>; the <org
                reg="American Medical Association, Section of Obstetrics, Gynecology and Abdominal Surgery"
                >Section of Obstetrics, Gynecology and Abdominal Surgery of the American Medical
                Association</org>; the <org reg="American Medical Women's Association">Medical
                Women’s National Association</org>; <org reg="Florida Medical Association">State
                Medical Associations of <place>Florida</place></org>, <org
                reg="Maine Medical Association"><place>Maine</place></org>, <org
                reg="Michigan State Medical Society"><place>Michigan</place></org>, and <org
                reg="Connecticut State Medical Society"><place>Connecticut</place></org>; many
            County Medical Societies; and the <org reg="New York Academy of Medicine"><place
                    reg="New York City, NY">New York</place></org> and <org
                reg="Cincinnati Academy of Medicine"><place reg="Cincinnati, OH">Cincinnati</place>
                Academies of Medicine</org>.</p>
        <p>Individual physicians, in their writings, in testimony at hearings on birth control
            bills, and in their generous service in birth control centers and on medical advisory
            boards of birth control organizations, have shown a keen awareness of the urgency of the
            birth control problem. <person reg="Willson, Prentiss J., Dr.">Dr. Prentiss J.
                Willson</person>, of <place reg="Washington, D.C.">Washington, D.C.</place>,
            chairman of the <org>National Medical Committee on State and Federal Birth Control
                Legislation</org>, gave testimony before a sub-committee of the <org
                reg="United States Senate Judiciary Committee">U.S. Senate Judiciary Committee</org>
            in 1934, which would, I think, be echoed by every thoughtful physician. As such it
            merits detailed quotations:</p>
        <p>“<q who="WILPR">The list of medical indications for contraception is a rather formidable
                one. Among chronic diseases there are heart and kidney disease, tuberculosis,
                syphilis, diabetes, chronic or potential chorea, several types of anemia, and
                exophthalmic goiter. There is a whole list of disease conditions of the female
                organs, which, because of the risk of abortion or extra-uterine pregnancy, indicate
                contraception. Nervous and mental disorders, such as epilepsy, paralysis,
                feeblemindedness, multiple sclerosis, and various types of psychoses and neuroses
                furnish additional and well-recognized indications, according to the consensus of
                medical opinion. . . I venture the opinion that the question of control of
                conception is doubtless one of the major problems affecting the married women of
                America. My experience teaches me that, in the absence of sane and safe methods of
                contraception, under the stress of the present economic situation, married couples
                are going to resort to some method of birth control. Many of these are harmful,
                either in a physical sense, because of damage done to the delicate tissues of the
                generative tract, or through the production of neurotic states, many of which I have
                had occasion to see, due to this cause. Here lies the crux of the whole argument in
                favor of placing birth control in the hands of the medical profession of this
                country</q>.”</p>
        <p>Birth control is indicated in still another field--one which makes it (or rather
                <emph>should</emph> make it) a routine part of postnatal care. It is needed for
            child spacing. Medical authority holds that a period of at least two years (possibly
            three), should elapse between the birth of children, so that the mother can adequately
            recover from the drain of pregnancy and childbirth and give care, including nursing if
            possible, to the newborn child. In advocating a three-year interval I have often put it
            thus graphically for lay audiences: One year for nursing and infant care; one year for
            the woman to be herself, an individual; and one year to plan for, conceive and carry the
            new child.</p>
        <p>The <org reg="United States Children's Bureau">U.S. Children’s Bureau</org>, in its
            studies on “<title type="book">Causal Factors in Infant Mortality</title>,” showed the
            definite relation between child spacing and infant mortality. Children born one year
            apart die at the rate of 146.7 per thousand--a rate which is reduced to 98.6 when the
            interval between births is two years, and drops to 86.5 for the three-year interval. The
            mother, the older children, and the infant all suffer when children come too close
            together. From this point of view alone, birth control is indicated <emph>for every
                married woman of childbearing age</emph>.</p>
        <p>I have made mention several times of legal restrictions. In 1873, <org
                reg="United States Congress">Congress</org>, at the instigation of <person
                reg="Comstock, Anthony">Anthony Comstock</person>, passed laws classing “prevention
            of conception” with obscenity, and forbidding the importation of contraceptive <gap
                reason="illegible">illegible</gap> or materials or their transportation within the
            country by mail or common carrier. <place>America</place> has paid dearly for this
            blunder, for it has clouded and confused an issue which should have rested on medical
            findings; it has tied the hands of physicians, retarded research, and doomed countless
            women to ill health and death. The birth control movement, particularly during the past
            seven years, has been largely focused upon securing legislation to exempt the physician
            from these restrictions, so that, as Dr. Williams stated, “<q who="WILPR">he might carry
                out his duty as a physician</q>.”</p>
        <p>The gradual build-up of public support, the better understanding of the real meaning of
            birth control and its constructive possibilities, have borne fruit, due in large part to
            efforts attendant upon securing the passage of a birth control bill; but the Courts,
            instead of the Congress, have clarified the law and handed down to the American
            physician his bill of rights in the field of contraception.</p>
        <p>In a <name reg="United States v. One Package of Japanese Pessaries" type="case">test
                case</name> on the importation of contraceptive materials, sent to <person
                reg="Stone, Hannah Mayer"> Dr. Hannah M. Stone</person> from <place>Japan</place>
            for research purposes, the <org
                reg="United States Circuit Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit">U.S. Circuit
                Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit</org> ruled that the intention of the
            Comstock statue “<q who="USCCA">was not to prevent the importation, sale or carriage by
                mail of things which might intelligently be employed by conscientious and competent
                physicians for the purpose of saving life or promoting the well-being of their
                patients</q>.” This decision marks a milestone in the birth control movement, and (I
            venture to say) in the history of preventive medicine. Contraceptive advice may now be
            given by physicians in their public as well as their private practice. Every hospital
            and dispensary, every Public Health Agency, every welfare organization may, and should,
            now include birth control in its services.</p>
        <p>The century-long groping for sane control of births is over. The legal obstructions have
            been surmounted. Science has given us reliable and harmless methods of contraception,
            and research is developing even better and simpler methods. Freed from the taint of
            being classed with obscenity, birth control can now be used by the wise physician to
            promote a well-rounded married life for his patients. The necessity for child spacing,
            for family planning in accordance with health and income, all point toward the place of
            birth control as a necessary part of medical practice.</p>
        <p> Whether the physician is a “family doctor” or a “specialist,” he will be faced with the
            necessity (if he is to carry out the highest dictates of his calling) of advising his
            patients on this most fundamental issue.</p>
        <p>“<q who="DICRO">The three great strides of medicine are towards the control of pain in
                labor and operation, the control of infection in obstetrics and surgery, and the
                control of communicable diseases</q>,” said <person reg="Dickinson, Robert Latou"
                >Dr. Robert L. Dickinson</person> some years ago, addressing the <org><place
                    reg="New York, NY">New York</place> Academy of Medicine</org>. “<q who="DICRO"
                >These three advances, made in the face of opposition and indifference on the part
                of the organized profession, are now its common pride and glory. A fourth control,
                the control of conception, needed to safeguard life, health, and happiness, though
                now suspect and maligned, will take its place of honor with these others. Courage
                and wisdom were required to restrain the forces of disease and death. A greater
                courage and a higher wisdom are called for within our profession to undertake a
                guiding part in the control of life</q>.”</p>
        <p>I know that the doctors of America, and particularly those young and eager newcomers who
            this year enter the profession, will rise to the challenge of this greater courage and
            higher wisdom.</p>
        <p>17 West 16th St.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
