<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed draft review">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2003/07/08 KSM</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/04/22 CH correcting after research</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/27 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-10 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1920-00-00">
            <supplied resp="MSPP">1920</supplied>
        </docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><title>Problems of Population and Parenthood: A Review by Margaret
                    Sanger</title></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp101904</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl> Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
            <bibl>LCM 128:0637</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
            <name type="ID-STOMA" id="STOMA">Marie Stopes</name>
            <name id="BNBC">British National Birth-rate Commission</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>Corrections made by hand by <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>.
            Sanger may have submitted this review to the <title>New York Tribune</title>; Published
            version not found. For an earlier draft of the review see LCM 128:634.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="opposition to"/>
        <index level1="Cox, Harold"/>
        <index level1="England" level2="fertility rates"/>
        <index level1="fertility rates" level2="in England"/>
        <index level1="population" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="population" level2="British Empire and"/>
        <index level1="population control" level2="government policies" level3="in England"/>
        <index level1="Stopes, Marie C."/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Problems of Population and Parenthood: A Review by Margaret Sanger</head>
        <p>The "<title type="book">Problems of Population and Parenthood</title>" is the second
            report of the <org rend="underline">British National Birth-rate Commission</org>,
            1918-1920. It is an exhaustive tome consisting of many hundreds of pages and is divided
            into two parts: the evidence taken for and against the control of Parenthood; and the
            findings of the Commission. To the cursory reader this is a splendid-looking effort
            toward a (solution) or one of the fundamental problems of the human race. Upon closer
            examination, however, we find two interesting facts that rather take away some of the
            value. In the first place, this Commission is <emph rend="underline"
                >self-appointed.</emph> One would imagine that <del>if</del>this Commission had
                <del>not</del> been appointed by the <org reg="United Kingdom Government">British
                Government</org>, <del>
                <unclear>at least it</unclear>
            </del>and operated and functioned under <del>some indirect</del><add>direct</add>
            sanction of official interest. <del>But such is not the case.</del> The people involved
            gathered together under this <del>distinctly Anglo-Saxon</del>title on their own
            initiative. Even if <del>there</del>
            <add>this</add> were so, we might not object were it not for the second weakness: among
            the forty-<del>one</del> members of the Commission ten are clergymen; eight are medical
            men; <del>only</del> two <del>are</del> biologists; <del>thirteen</del>
            <del>and</del>twelve are women <add>whose interests are social-reform work;</add>the
            balance being laymen of varying import. Naturally the findings of such a self-appointed
            group <del>of enthusiasts</del>must be retrograde and reactionary. It is a curious
            example of the credibility of mankind that it accepts the opinions of unscientific minds
            upon purely scientific subjects!</p>
        <p>The deeper we go into this massive book, the more amazed we become. The witnesses called
            before the Commission represent some of the most vital levels of thought in
                <place>England</place>, and <place reg="United States">America</place>. Among the
            host we find <person reg="Webb, Sidney">Sidney Webb</person>, <add>Judge <person
                    reg="Neil, Henry">Neil</person> and</add>, Judge <person
                reg="Lindsey, Benjamin Barr">Lindsey</person>
            <add>of <place reg="United States">U.S.A</place></add> Sir <person
                reg="Doyle, Arthur Conan">Arthur Conan Doyle</person>, Sir <person
                reg="Osler, William">William Osler</person>, Dr. <person reg="Stopes, Marie">Marie
                Stopes</person>, Sir <person reg="Haggard, H. Rider">Rider Haggard</person>, Mr.
                <person reg="Cox, Harold">Harold Cox</person> the editor of the <title
                type="journal">Edinburgh Review</title>, <add>Mrs. <person reg="Booth, Evangeline"
                    >Booth</person>
                <org>Salvation Army</org></add>, <person reg="Lloyd-George, William">W.L.
                George</person>, and many, many others.<del>What a hodge-podge of individuals. The
                list of witnesses almost reads as though the Commission had put alot of names in a
                hat and chosen them blindfolded, not and again luckily finding a significant
                individual.</del></p>
        <p>Yet even with this, the hopeful student might seek to find real good in <emph
                rend="underline">any</emph> effort to solve the problem. Unfortunately, every page
            but adds to the conclusions already listed. Many problems are taken up, but the
            essential one concerning the population question and the fall of the birth rate and its
            effect upon the country was <del>not convincing</del>
            <add>neither thorough nor convincing</add> Having proved <add>what is already
                known</add> that the birth rate <emph rend="underline">had fallen</emph> in England
            they next proceed to <del>reluctantly</del>discuss the <emph rend="underline"
                >causes</emph>. These are classified under infant mortality, venereal diseases and
            birth control. Much of the evidence taken deals with the classification of the causes of
            infant mortality, and a large proportion is found to be due to the infection of infants
            by parents with venereal diseases! On this subject much valuable evidence was given by
            Sir William Osler and Sir <person reg="Donkin, Bryan">Bryan Donkin</person>. They
            pointed out that if these diseases are to be checked they must be dealt with as diseases
            and the moral consideration entirely eliminated. If everyone could be persuaded to live
            clean lives the problem would be solved, but in the meanwhile as this conduct seems
            impossible for all people we cannot adopt measures to prevent the disease and at the
            same time retain the risk of incurring them as a deterrent to immorality. And the
            findings of the Commission resulted in a whitewashing of the prevalent system which
            permits the cure of venereal diseases, but provides no adequate method to prevent
            them!</p>
        <p>The evidence taken on birth control was particularly interesting. It was pointed out that
            the conscious use of artificial methods to prevent conception were employed by the
            better classes, upper middle and artisan classes, while the population is recruited from
            the lower or unfit! The question of the use of these methods, and how far they are
            injurious to health seemed to be the bone of contention. Dr. Marie Stopes made an
            excellent report and as she is <del>one of the greatest living</del><add>an able</add>
            biologist <add>having made a special study of birth control</add> her testimony and
            experiences are valuable. Harold Cox's testimony was also intelligent and far-reaching.
            The only suggestion given by various other witnesses was such as to invite the
            production of still greater <del>hords</del> hordes of <del>the unfit</del><add>unwanted
                progeny</add>. No suggestions were given to stop the production of the unfit or
            diseased, or feeble minded. There was some talk of the motherhood pension system--in
            other words the placing of a premium on motherhood, rather than the control of the
            unfit. One suggestion was immigration to the Colonies, as if these parts of the world
            desired their ranks to be recruited by the feeble minded, the physical and mentally
            unfit, etc. One witness carried on the idea, or maybe more, that the Empire should have
            a greater volume of population in order to hold its preeminent position in the sun. In
            other words, as someone recently said: <add>The Commission asked the women of England
                to</add> enter into a "<q who="BNBC">cradle competition to save the Empire</q>."</p>
        <p>Need it be said that the conclusions of this Commission are worthless? They merely
                <del>carry on</del><add>sanction</add> what is in existence to-day and put the seal
            of approval on the unscientic control of birth and population. The interested reader
            will do well to read the various resolutions made by different groups on the subject of
            voluntary restriction of the birth rate. (See pages clxii-clxvi). It is unfortunate that
            we are unable to treat this section at length because of the limits of space. The
            Commission condemned <add>the practice of</add> birth control.</p>
        <p>Dr. Marie Stopes objected to the grounds upon which this decision was predicated and
            addressed a letter to each signer of the Reservation against birth control: "<q
                who="STOMA">As possibly you are aware, I consider that the question of the right use
                of sound hygienic methods of Birth Control as one of the very greatest
                importance.</q>" She goes on to say that she noticed that this particular member had
            signed the reservation against birth control:"<q who="STOMA">Had the grounds of your
                objection been stated to be a religious or moral conviction, I should,
                    <del>have</del>
                <add>of</add> course, have had <add>no</add> more to say, but you state above you
                signature that you base your condemnation of all scientific methods of control on
                'medical evidence</q>."</p>
        <p>Dr. Stopes inclosed a self-addressed and stamped envelope for reply and a ready-prepared
            slip. In their replies not one quoted a page of the report containing medical evidence.
            In fact, there is not a line of reliable evidence throughout the report which would
            substantiate the decision against birth control. It is only one of the glaring
            weaknesses and ill-devised work of this self-appointed body of <del>enthusiasts</del>
            <add>non-experts</add>.</p>
        <p>One sentence in the report seems to me to give the key to the Commission's entire state
            of mind: "<q who="BNBC">It is for the women of the Empire to save the Empire by securing
                its continuance for the fulfilment of its beneficient mission in the world</q>."
        </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
