<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed review">

  <mepHeader>
    <prepDate>2003/07/08 KSM</prepDate>
    <prepDate>2004/04/22 CH corrections after research</prepDate>
    <prepDate>2004/07/27 CH</prepDate>
    <prepDate>2004/08/09 CH</prepDate>
    <prepDate>2014/03/05 EK cleanup</prepDate>

    <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
    <docDate value="1920-00-00">1920s</docDate>
    <docTitle>
      <titlePart>The Control of Parenthood: A Review By Margaret Sanger</titlePart>
    </docTitle>
    <idno>msp101906</idno>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>
        <title>Margaret Sanger Papers</title>
      </bibl>
      <bibl>LCM 128:0636</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>

    <respStmt>
      <resp>
        <name id="COXHA">Cox, Harold</name>
        <name id="HRIHA">Haggard, H. Rider</name>
        <name id="MARJA">Marchant, James</name>
        <name id="WAKHE">Wakefield, Henry Russell</name>

      </resp>
    </respStmt>
  </mepHeader>
  <headNote resp="MSPP">
    <p>This review may have been submitted to the <title>New York Tribune</title> for publication;
      published version not found. A duplicate copy appears on LCM 128:639.</p>

    <index level1="population control" level2="government policies" level3="in England"/>

  </headNote>
  <docBody>
    <head>The Control of Parenthood: A Review by Margaret Sanger</head>
    <p>The book entitled: "<title>The Control of Parenthood;</title>" edited by Mr. <person
        reg="Marchant, James">James Marchant</person>, with an introduction by the <person
        reg="Henry Russell Wakefield">Bishop of Birmingham</person>, contains an excellent study of
      the population question. It brings together the opinions of several of the most distinguished
      Englishmen and women who are experts in their own particular subject. They here present with
      great care the various aspects of this century-old controversial subject. It is one of the few
      books in which the arguments for and against the conscious control of Parenthood are given.
      The subject is treated from the biological, economic, social, religious, Imperial and racial
      aspects, and at least two authorities are chosen to present or refute each of these. The
      argument by Sir <person reg="H. Rider Haggard">Rider Haggard</person> for the dominance of the
      British Empire by increase of population, is most ably answered by Mr. <person
        reg="Cox, Harold">Harold Cox</person> in his essay on the economic side of the subject.
      Altogether the book is the best and clearest presentation of the subject in the English
      language. </p>
  </docBody>
</doc>
