<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Draft Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/06/08 CE</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-18 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1937-05-20">20 May 1937</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Bermuda and Population Policy</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp108951</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Library of Congress Microfilm</title>, 11:1171</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="DILTH">Dill, Thomas Melville, Lieutenant-Colonel</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>For another version, see Margaret Sanger Microfilm, S71:0935.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to" level3="international"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="international"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="efforts to reduce"/>
        <index level1="Bermuda" level2="government" level3="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="infant"/>
        <index level1="population" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="population growth" level2="regulation of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <p>Here is one spot on Earth where statesmanship is in action. The <org
                reg="Bermuda Department of Health">Health Department</org> invited me to come here
            and give a series of talks to the groups who constitute the leaders in various clinic
            and educational activities.</p>
        <p>It is encouraging to find here officials in <org reg="Government of Bermuda"
                >Government</org> positions with courage to act and vision to see that certain
            actions now can prevent adverse, deplorable conditions later on. This is one of the
            garden spots in the world with a lovely climate and quaint charming traditions of
            locomotion--the horse &amp; buggy and the bicycle. White washed houses built of coral stone
            are 250 years old. The population is about 30,000, having increased 10,000 in less than
            ten years. There are 19 square miles and “<q who="DILTH">a density of population</q>,
            said <person reg="Dill, Thomas Melville">Col. Dill</person>, <q
                who="DILTH">beaten only by <place>Malta</place>, <place>Hong Kong</place> and
                    <place>Gibraltar</place></q>.”</p>
        <p>The first meeting took place in a committee room of the <org
                reg="Bermuda House of Assembly">House of Assembly</org>. Members of the House of
            Assembly and of the <org reg="Bermuda Legislative Council">Legislative Council</org>
            with members of the Board of Health and
                <person reg="Browne, Arthur Heber">His Lordship, the Bishop of
                    <place>Bermuda</place></person>, listened attentively to the address. Col. Dill
            was in the Chair.</p>
        <p>The death rates here are declining owing to able medical care. The colored population has
            a higher birth rate than the whites. But 60% of the population is colored. Birth rate in
            1936 for white population was 16.4, for colored 29.2. While the death rates for the same
            year were: whites 8.8--colored 9.6. Infant mortality: whites 45.8--colored 52.9. The
            increase is far too rapid for future peace and comfort. Since <place reg="United States"
                >U.S.A.</place> refuses to allow alien immigration thus bars out a large proportion
            of the population who went to U.S.A. for service (comestic) each year.</p>
        <p>The conditions here at present are good. There is no unemployment--no relief. It is a
            tourist place and as long as people of wealth travel, Bermuda can be prosperous and
            happy. But is to the future that one must look and the present Governor, <person
                reg="Hildyard, Reginald John Thoroton">Lt. Gen. R. J. T.
                Hildyard</person>, an army man of strong personality, is keen and anxious to see
            that the population of Bermuda shall keep its standards high and retain the conditions
            of harmony, respect, peace and good will toward each other it now attains.</p>
        <p>This can be done it is agreed providing the population increases slowly and not rapidly,
            allowing for higher educational facilities and the assimilation of the population into
            the system now prevailing. There are no income or inheritance taxes in Bermuda. The
            average wage for unskilled workers is $15 to $18 a week (L 3.10)</p>
        <p>If any one desires to see what can come to people in an overcrowded land, just take a
            trip to <place>Puerto Rico</place> and see for oneself the appalling conditions that
            breeding and increasing regardless of conditions can bring humanity to. At last Puerto
            Rico has come to its senses and the legislation <supplied>passed?</supplied> a law
            allowing birth control to be taught to its people.</p>
        <p>Bermuda is fortunate in having statesmanship at its head. My congratulations and best
            wishes. Let us watch and see what the future will bring.</p>
        <byline><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></byline>
    </docBody>
</doc>
