<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2002-08-06 KH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2002-08-15 KH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/04/22 CH correct after research, also lots of tagging errors</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/23 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/26 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/08/09 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/08/13 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007/06/25 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2001/03/11 CH Entered corrections suggested by Andy Carloff.</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-18 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-22 CH added contextual headnote</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/12/9 EK Correct proof + update index</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1916-04-00"> Apr-July 1916</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Birth Control</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp128002</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
            <bibl>Margaret sanger Papers Microfilm, LCM 129:12</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="SACSA">Sachs, Sadie</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <sourceNote/>
    <headNote><p>Much of this text was drawn from the <title type="speech">Hotel Brevoort
                Speech</title><xref from="128167.xml">Jan. 17, 1916</xref>. The draft was one of the
            texts <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger</person> used during her American speaking
            tour in 1916. For other speeches given on that tour, see <title type="speech">Chicago
                Address to Women</title>, <xref from="236132.xml">Apr.-May 1916</xref>, <title
                type="speech">Birth Control and Society</title><xref from="101859.xml">Apr.-June,
                1916</xref>," and "Condemnation is Misunderstanding," <xref from="128003.xml"
                >Apr.-Jun. 1916</xref>. No final version was found. al speaking tour in 1916.</p>
        <p>Emendations to the text were made by hand by Margaret Sanger. Entire paragraphs struck
            out, most likely for shortening the speech have not been deleted from this version.</p>
        <p>Sanger added a note reading: "<q>Original speech given by MS in 1916--this was the first
                public utterance on the whole subject &amp; was delivered 119 times in one
                year--</q>"</p>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="speaking tours, 1916 (United States)"/>
        <index level1="abortion"/>
        <index level1="child labor"/>
        <index level1="mentally disabled and diseased"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="morality of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="class-based"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"/>
        <index level1="birth control clinics and leagues"/>
        <index level1="physicians" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="Woman Rebel, The"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="freedom and rights of"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
        <index level1="France" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Netherlands, the" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Scotland" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="censorship"/>
        <index level1="Roosevelt, Theodore"/>
        <index level1="race suicide"/>
        <index level1="Sachs, Sadie"/>
        <index level1="neo-Malthusianism"/>
        <index level1="Malthusian League (Dutch)"/>
        <index level1="Malthusian League (English)"/>
        <index level1="Knowlton, Charles"/>
        <index level1="Besant, Annie"/>
        <index level1="Knowlton, Charles"/>
        <index level1="Wilson, Woodrow"/>
        <index level1="Jacobs, Aletta"/>
        <index level1="Rutgers, Johannes"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head><add>Birth Control</add></head>
        <p><del>To me</del><add>I believe that</add> birth control is the <del>keynote</del>
            <add>signal</add> of a new social awakening. To me it is not <del>only</del>
            <add>merely</add> an economic expedient, <del>but</del> it is also a great social
            principle, interlocked with the veryspiritual progress of the race itself and its
            future. That is why it seems to me that this meeting is in harmony with the basic idea
            of birth control, because it brings together all of us social workers of such diverse
            outlooks and temperaments, which indicates that it is an idea vital to us all.</p>
        <p>I realize keenly that many of those who understand and would support the birth control
            propaganda if it were carried out in a safe, sane manner, cannot sympathize with or
            countenance the methods I have used in my attempt to arouse the working woman to the
            fact that bringing a child into the world is her greatest responsibility. I know that
            physicians and scientists have a great technical fund of information. For years and
            generations they have had all the technical information on the subject. There is nothing
            new, nothing radical in the idea of birth control. <person>Aristotle</person> advocated
            it, <person>Plato</person> advocated it, all our great and modern thinkers have
            advocated it. It is an idea that must appeal to any mature intelligence. Yet all this
            scientific and technical discussion has had the effect of producing more and more
            technical discussion, all very necessary and very stimulating to that very small group
            of women and women who could understand it. But all during the long years while this
            matter was being discussed, advocated, refuted by the scientists, the people themselves,
            the poor people especially were blindly, desperately practicing family limitation just
            as they are practicing it today, but to them birth control does not mean what it does to
            me. To them it has meant the most barbaric methods. It has meant the killing of babies,
            infanticide, abortion, in one crude way or another, for women from time immemorial have
            tried to avoid unwanted motherhood. We all know the tribe of professional abortionists
            which has sprung up and profited by this terrible misfortune. We know, too, that when
            the practice of abortion was put under the ban of the church, the alternate evil, the
            foundling asylum, with its horrifying history sprang up. We know too that when the laws
            against imparting knowledge to <del>control birth</del>
            <add>prevent conception</add> were passed, <add>in this country</add> thousands of women
            were forced into the hands of midwives and cheap abortionists unless they would bear
            unwanted offspring, with the consequence that there is no other country in the world
                <add>today</add> which has so large a number of abortions nor as large a number of
            deaths resulting therefrom as the <place reg="United States">United States of
                America</place>. <add><del>No</del> laws make crime to prevent by knowledge.</add>
            It is a conservative estimate that 250,000 abortions are performed each year in this
            country, while about 50,000 deaths result therefrom, and all this time our quacks and
            abortionists roll in wealth while our law makers close their Puritan eyes.</p>
        <p><add>Difference in B.C. &amp; abortions</add></p>
        <p>How often have I stood at the bedside of a woman in childbirth and watched the tears flow
            in gladness and heard her sigh of relief and words "<q>Thank <name type="deity"
                    >God</name></q>" when she was told that the child was born dead. <del>What can
                man know of the agony of carrying beneath one's heart a little life which every
                instinct tells the mother it cannot survive</del>, For even when it is born alive
            the chances are that it will die within the first year. We know that there are 300,000
            babies under one year of age which die in the United States every year from poverty and
            neglect, while 600,000 parents remain in ignorance of how to prevent 300,000 more babies
            from coming into the world the next year to die of poverty and neglect. A few simple
            words of advice on how to control birth would enable these people to avoid this horrible
            slaughter! In my fourteen years' experience as a trained nurse I found that 75% of the
            diseases of men and women were the result of ignorance concerning their sex functions.
                <del>So great was this ignorance among girls and women concerning their bodies that
                I decided to devote myself to the study of women's diseases.</del> I took up
            gynecological and obstetrical nursing and then I found <del>the great discovery</del>
            that knowledge to control birth was obtained and practiced by the women of
                <del>wealth</del>
            <add>means</add> while the poor women were kept in ignorance of this knowledge. I found
            that these poor women had emphatic views on the crime of bringing children into the
            world to die of hunger, and would rather risk their lives through abortion rather than
            give birth to children they could not feed, clothe and care for.</p>
        <p>It is not an uncommon thing to see <add>groups</add> of women forming in line outside a
            doctor's office any evening after working hours, between 6 and 8 o'clock, on the lower
            East Side of <place reg="New York City, NY">New York City</place>.</p>
        <p><add>90% women married 95% have more than 2 children 99%religious</add></p>
        <p>These women go there <del>and</del>
            <add>to</add> face the tortures of abortion rather than condemn an unborn child to
            poverty, <del>and</del>
            <add>while</add> all this time our wise men and sages and scientists are discussing the
            subject of birth control among themselves. Their ideas are sterile, <add>for</add> they
            have not influenced or effected the tremendous facts of life among these women, the
            working women, the disinherited.</p>
        <p>You all know the <del>life</del>
            <add>lives</add> of the children of the cotton mills of the South, <del>of the boys in
                the mines</del>,<add>wend their weary way to work</add>,of the children working in
            the canning industry <add>go carts</add> but do you know that in New York City there are
            thousands of little infants between <add>under school age</add> 3 and 5 years of age who
            toil far down in sub-cellars beneath the earth. There they sit cross-legged upon heaps
            of rags, their little backs are bent, their faces bloodless, their little fingers keep
            busy curling feathers, making artificial flowers, or rolling cigarettes. Year in and
            year out they toil in places where the sun has never shone. This work is
                <add>slavery</add> forced upon them because they are invariably members of large
            families who need their pitiful earnings. The same applies to child labor everywhere.
            Statistics show us that the majority of child hands of factories and mills of <place
                reg="Lowell, MA">Lowell</place> and <place reg="Fall River, MA">Fall River</place>,
            Mass., come from parents who average nine living children.</p>
        <p>We also find from records concerning the women of the under-world that 85% of these come
            from parents who also average nine children, and later discoveries have found that 50%
            of these girls have been found to be mentally defective. Many of them at the age of 22
            or 23 years have the intelligence of <del>children</del><add>child</add> not over 8 or 9
            years. Can we not see how difficult it is for this girl with <del>the</del>
            <add>an</add> adult body and child's mind to compete in the struggle of life against the
            more intelligent and better born? We know too that the fertility of the mentally
            defective parent is four times that of the normal parent. In <del>New York City</del>
            <add>all larger cities</add> today there are <del>10,000</del>
            <add>thousands</add> feeble-minded girls living in prostitution, clamoring at the doors
            of <del>charities</del>
            <add>the State</add> to take them in and care for them and protect them from the life of
            degradation which they have been leading. The institutions for the feeble minded are
            full and overcrowded. There is no room for these. Are not our feeble minded institutions
            and insane asylums monuments to careless and reckless breeding? Is it not time that our
            physicians, scientists, social workers and sages, is it not time that they face this
            array of facts and stop quibbling in hair-splitting debates over woman's morality. I say
            this because you all know that the principal objection in the minds of these people
            against the idea of birth control for the working woman, is that it may have a tendency
            to decrease her standards of morality. Solicitude for woman's morals has always been the
            cloak that authority has worn in its age-long conspiracy to keep her in bondage!!<add>
                suffrage--young girl--pest</add></p>
        <p>When I was in <place>Spain</place> a year ago I found that the Spanish woman was far
            behind her European sisters in readiness or even desire for modern freedom. Upon
            investigation as to the cause of this I was told that there are 5,000 villages and towns
            in Spain with no means of transportation except donkeys over bridle paths, and that all
            attempts at building roads and railroads into Spain met with strong opposition of the
            clergy and the government on the grounds that roads and railroads would make
            communication easy thereby bringing the women of the country towns into the cities where
            they would become immoral! Do we who have roads and railroads think that our women are
            less moral than the Spanish women? Certainly not. Yet we in this country are after all
            only just emerging from the fight for the higher education of women which met with the
            same opposition early in its day. We now know that education has not done all the
            dreadful things to woman that its opponents predicted were going to result, and so shall
            we find that knowledge to control birth which has been in the hands of the wealthy women
            of this country for the last 25 years, so shall we find that it will not tend to lower
            their standards of morality, for if the women of wealth have withstood this
                <add>test</add> have we <add>any</add> reason to think that the working women will
            use it less wisely?</p>
        <p>Statistics show us that the birth rate of any quarter is in ratio to its wealth, and
            further give us figures to prove that in large cities the rich districts have a birth
            rate of one-third of that of the poor districts. In <place reg="Paris, France"
                >Paris</place> for every 1,000 women between the ages of 15 and 50 the poor
            districts yield 116 births, while the rich districts yield 34 births. In <place
                reg="Berlin, Germany">Berlin</place> conditions are approximately the same. For
            every 1,000 women of similar ages there are 157 births in the poor quarters and 47 in
            the rich quarters. The same applies to <place reg="London, England">London</place>,
                <place reg="Vienna, Austria">Vienna</place>, New York, in fact to all large cities
            the world over, which can be inferred that one class of women use means to control birth
            which is condemned when taught to the other class. But the menace of our civilization
            and problems of today are not the stationary birth rate among the upper class as much as
            the tremendous increase of the poor and diseased population of this country. </p>
        <p>Many of my friends will object to this statement because it seems to clash with
                their economic theories, but there are always objections from some quarter; for
                every ideal created there is a <person>Herod</person> born to kill it.</p>
        <p>To me the question of birth control is by far the most important question that the
            working people can touch upon, and it should have gone hand in hand with labor
            organization for the past 25 years. Had this been done we should not have had to face
            the great problems of unemployment and child labor which we are facing today. It has
            been my experience that the woman with an income of $10. a week does not desire a large
            family. I have worked among thousands of them. I have found them with 7, 8 and 9 living
            children, and I have never yet known one of them to desire another mouth to feed. On the
            contrary I have found them in constant terror of the coming of another baby and
            submitting to unwanted childbirth only because of their ignorance. Picture a woman with
            five or six little ones living on the average workingman's wage of $10. a week. Another
            baby is coming as fast as nature can manage it. She is already broken in health and
            spirit, a shadow of the lovely woman she once was. Where is the man or woman who would
            reproach me for trying to put into this woman's hands knowledge to prevent giving birth
            to any more? Is this action on my part to be called immoral? Am I to be persecuted and
            classed as immoral because I advocate small families for the working women while Mr.
                <person reg="Roosevelt, Theodore">Roosevelt</person> can go up and down the length
            of the land shouting and urging this class of women to have large families and is
            neither arrested nor molested, but considered by all society as highly moral?<del> But I
                ask you which is the more moral, to urge a working woman to have only those children
                she desires and can support or to delude her into bearing cannon fodder for the
                munition makers and professional jingoes?</del></p>
        <p><unclear>illegible</unclear> administratioon closed drug shops <place>New
            Zealand</place></p>
        <p>Let us ask ourselves which is America's definition of morality.</p>
        <p>We in America are inclined to think that all advanced ideas must come from
                <place>Europe</place>, but it is interesting to find in my studies abroad that the
            idea of birth control as it is propagated today throughout the world had its
                <del>incentive</del>
            <add>impetus</add> from a book written in America. This book was called "<title
                type="book">The Fruits of Philosophy</title>" and was written by Dr. <person
                reg="Knowlton, Charles">Chas. Knowlton</person> of <place reg="Boston, MA"
                >Boston</place>, Mass. over 80 years ago. <add>It was driven out of U.S.A
                &amp;</add> It wandered about the globe for 40 years before it finally found its way
            into a book seller's shop in <place>Bristol, England</place>. The book seller was
            arrested for selling it and pled guilty to the charge. <person reg="Besant, Annie">Annie
                Besant</person> and <person reg="Bradlaugh, Charles">Charles Bradlaugh</person>, two
            ardent advocates of liberty, took the case out of the book seller's hands and fought it
            out in the English courts. Previous to this time there had been a great deal of
            agitation on the small family question by the followers of <person
                reg="Malthus, Thomas Robert">Malthus</person>. The Malthusian advocates believed in
            small families but the methods advanced for bringing about this result were continence
            and late marriage. Dr. Knowlton's book, taking into consideration the normal nature of
            man, advised on the contrary early marriage with means to control birth, which coming at
            the time it did appealed to the reason of a more advanced generation. The trial of Mrs.
            Besant and Mr. Bradlaugh aroused all England and every lover of liberty came to their
            support. The trial lasted three days. It was heard before a special jury, they were
            found guiltyand sentenced to six months' imprisonment. So great, however, was the
            agitation and indignation at this example of legal censorship that the charges were
            dismissed on a legal technicality.</p>
        <p>40,000 of these books had been sold through England for six pence apiece, and it was
            brought out at the trial that the charges would never have been brought had the book
            been kept within the bounds of the restricted class by a high price. <del>To what extent
                this trial of Annie Besant and Charles Bradlaugh won for the English people the
                right of free press can be judged from the summing up of Mr. <person
                    reg="Coleridge, Bernard John Seymour">Justice Coleridge</person> on an obscenity
                and blasphemy case two years ago.</del>(Insert).</p>
        <p>The English people had been fighting for 35 years to gain that decision. It has not been
            won without effort, struggle and sacrifice, for in England as in America the people
            recognize that there is an ever increasing power in the state, the tendency of which is
            to decrease the liberties of the people, and it behooves each generation to grapple with
            this power and to challenge it if we would hold the liberties gained for us by our
            forefathers. We must not expect that these liberties will be given to us easily. We must
            be prepared to take what each new generation needs and fight to hold them. This is what
            the English people have been trying to do. They have been struggling for 35 years to
            hold what Annie Besant and Charles Bradlaugh gained for them through that prosecution
            and trial.</p>
        <p>Unlike us, the English love for liberty is greater than their dislike of personality. No
            matter how much they may dislike a person fighting for liberty, they stand squarely
            behind him, never giving the government an opportunity to silence a voice merely because
            the person behind it has been unpopular or objectionable to certain elements of the
            community. It has been this spirit that has triumphed over the censors and has given far
            greater personal freedom to them than we have in America</p>
        <p>When I arrived in England a year ago I found the greatest interest among the English
            people in our <name type="law" reg="United States Criminal Code, Section 211"
                    ><del>Comstock</del>
                <add><org reg="United States Post Office">Post Office</org></add> laws</name>, which
            contributed to keep the people of this country in ignorance on the subject of birth
            control. To my amazement I found that the same group of <add>conservative tho</add>
            ardent advocates of birth control <add>were</add> most enthusiastic and overjoyed when
            they found that our obscenity laws had <add>at last</add> been violated. They at once
            went about to interest and influence the support of every man and woman in England of
            learning and of high standing to back me up in my fight for this freedom. You all know
            of the letter written to the <person reg="Wilson, Woodrow">President of the United
                States</person> in my behalf by these people, protesting against <del>the</del>
            <add>my</add> persecution <del>where this knowledge was concerned</del> and insisted
            that we are the only civilized country in the word whose laws make it a crime to spread
            this knowledge. This letter was signed by such prominent men as <person
                reg="Wells, H. G.">H.G. Wells</person>, <person reg="Bennett, Arnold">Arnold
                Bennett</person>, <person reg="Murray, Gilbert">Gilbert Murray</person>, <person
                reg="Maude, Aylmer">Elmer Maude</person>, <person reg="Carpenter, Edward">Edward
                Carpenter</person> and many others, and a great deal of interest was also shown in
            my case by <person reg="Shaw, George Bernard">Bernard Shaw</person>, <person
                reg="Galsworthy, John">John Galsworthy</person>, <person reg="Ellis, Havelock"
                >Havelock Ellis</person>, who wrote me, and all <del>seemed to take a great </del>
            <add>took an active</add> interest in the work which was being carried on in this
            country.</p>
        <p><del>In England it has only been within the past three years that the birth control
                league has been openly able to defy the laws to the extent of openly giving out the
                information to the people who requested it.</del> Up to this time and during all
            those <add>30</add> years they <del>had</del>
            <add>have</add> worked among the educators only, with the object of getting behind them
            so strong a group of men and women that the government would not dare attack them. In
            this they have been successful and now their object is to establish clinics among the
            working women where knowledge can be given free of charge as has been done for the past
            30 years in <place reg="Netherlands, the">Holland</place>. <add>working class
                untouched</add></p>
        <p>Immediately after the trial of Annie Besant and Charles Bradlaugh the same group of men
            and women who had been interested in carrying on this agitation formed what is known
            today as the English Neo-Malthusian League, which advanced the methods advocated in Dr.
            Knowlton's book instead of the Malthusian practice as advocated by Thomas Malthus. Their
            first work was to publish a paper and to spread these ideas into other countries in
            Europe, and Holland was the first to become interested in the subject and invited Dr.
                <person reg="Drysdale, Charles Robert">Drysdale</person>, the president of the <org
                reg="Malthusian League">English League</org> to speak at its Medical Congress in
            Amsterdam. The following year a league was formed in Holland and a woman physician, Dr.
                <person reg="Jacobs, Aletta">Aletta Jacobs</person>, opened a clinic in Amsterdam
            and announced that all women who desired this information could obtain it from her free
            of charge. This was a daring and brave thing to do on the part of Dr. Jacobs. She was
            maligned and insulted by the members of her own profession, but she stood firmly to her
            principles and continued to do this work among the women of Holland. From that time on
                <del>a</del>
            <add>the</add> number of clinics increased, particularly in the working districts. Today
            there are 52 such clinics, with nurses in charge, and the medical profession has
            practically handed this work over to the nurses. Birth control work in Holland is better
            organized than in any other country in the world. It is the only country in the world
            where the government has not prosecuted those advocating the idea; with the result that
            the men and women with ideals have been able to put their energies into the building up
            of the <add>league</add> instead of wasting their energies and time fighting the
            government authorities. Today the <org reg="Malthusian League(Dutch)">Dutch league</org>
            has 5,000 members. Practically every well known man and woman in Holland gives this work
            his unanimous support. They send out 7,000 pamphlets a year, in three different
            languages, English, Dutch, and Esperanto, giving all instructions to control birth.
            Although the work of the league is not sanctioned by the government, it has behind it so
            intelligent and unanimous a public opinion that the authorities <del>dare</del>
            <add>have</add> not <add>attacked</add> it.</p>
        <p>A few years ago it was given a royal decree by the government as a great public utility,
                <del>as</del>
            <add>and</add> the result of 30 years' work has been that the general death rate of
            Holland has <add><emph rend="underline">slowly!</emph></add> fallen to be the lowest of
            any country of Europe, while the infant <add>mortality</add> of Amsterdam and <place
                reg="the Hague, Netherlands, the">the Hague</place> is the lowest <del>in</del>
            <add>of</add> any <add>cities</add> in the world. This is not due to either the
            philanthropic societies or the work of the State. But it is purely the result of the
            individual responsibility of the Dutch people toward their offspring. Holland proves to
            us beyond the shadow of a doubt that the practice of birth control leads to race
            improvement instead of race suicide because the increase in population has accelerated
            as the death rate has fallen.</p>
        <p>This work has been mainly in the hands of <person reg="Johannes Rutgers">Dr.</person> and
                <person reg="Rutgers, Wilhelmina Hoitsema">Mme. Rutgers</person> of the Hague. This
            little man and woman have devoted their entire lives to spreading this information among
            the people, and also to teaching the nurses how to carry on this work of the care and
            hygiene of the human body. To me Dr. and Mme. Rutgers are more important to the welfare
            of the Dutch people than either the king or the queen <add>of Holland</add>. All the
            nurses who are sent out to do this work are instructed by Dr. Rutgers and from him take
            their course of training. He then sends them into the district where they are most
            needed. He holds in his hands the records of the birth and death rate of the various
            sections throughout Holland, and whenever he sees that the death rate in rising he at
            once sends a nurse into that district to establish a free clinic. These clinics soon
            become self-supporting for the Dutch people believe in paying their way as they go along
            and so open and frank are the men and women of this little country concerning this
            subject that they would no more think of bringing children into the world that they
            could not feed, clothe and care for than we would buy an automobile or a piano, or any
            other luxury which we knew we could not afford to <del>pay for</del>
            <add>buy</add>. This instruction is given to every woman married or old enough to be
            married, with the consequence that the young people are able to marry early and
            commercialized prostitution is practically unknown among them today.</p>
        <p>In France on the other hand, although the knowledge of birth control has been universally
            disseminated since the time of <person reg="Bonaparte, Napoleon">Napoleon</person> it
            has never been organized along scientific lines so as to benefit those who most need it.
            The upper class women, as in this country, have ready access to it, while the poor
            continue to multiply because of their imperfect knowledge. This leads to a high infant
            mortality, which rather than a low birth rate is the real cause of the
                <del>decreasing</del>
            <add>stationary</add> population of France.</p>
        <p>We in America should learn a lesson from this, and I would urge immediate group action
            for the forming of clinics in the industrial centers of this country where the poor
            women are over-burdened with large families. Instead of our charity organizations,
                <del>our</del>
            <add>instituting</add> baby nurseries, Better Baby leagues, Little Mother leagues, which
            at their best are simply alleviations for their present distress, would it not be better
            to help these women <del>and the most of these babies</del> to help themselves by giving
            them the knowledge to control birth, thereby preventing their bringing into the world
            children to fill the orphan asylums and other institutions of charity?</p>
        <p><del>To me </del><add>Our present day</add> society and all its well-intentioned
            palliatives are in this respect like the quack who attempts to cure a cancer by burning
            off the top while the deadly disease continues to spread underneath.</p>
        <p>I have never felt this more strongly than I did three years ago after the death of a
            patient on my last nursing case. This <person reg="Sachs, Sadie">patient of
                mine</person> was the wife of a <person reg="Sachs, Jake">struggling working
                man</person> and the mother of three children. She was suffering from the results of
            an attempted abortion performed upon her by herself. She lived on Grand St., the main
            thoroughfare of New York down-town Ghetto. I found her in a very serious condition and
            for three weeks both the attending physician and myself labored night and day to bring
            her out of the valley of the shadow of death. We finally succeeded in restoring her to
            her family circle. I remember well the day I was leaving. The doctor, too, was making
            his last call. As the doctor put out his hand to say good-bye to her, I saw that she had
            something to say to him, but was timid and shy about saying it. I started to leave the
            room to leave them both alone, but she said "<q who="SACSA">No, don't go. How can both
                of you leave me without telling me something that I can do to avoid a future illness
                such as I have just passed through?</q>" I was interested to hear the answer of the
            physician, and came back and sat down beside her. To my amazement he answered her
            question lightly, and jokingly, put her aside by telling her that there was nothing that
            she could do as long as there were laws upon the statute books, and he advised her to
            get her husband to change the laws.</p>
        <p>Three months later I was aroused from my sleep at midnight. A telephone call from the
            husband of the same woman, requested me to come immediately, that she was dangerously
            ill. I arrived to find her beyond relief. Another conception had forced her into the
            hands of a cheap abortionist and she died at 4 o'clock the same morning, leaving behind
            her three little children and the frantic, helpless husband.</p>
        <p>I arrived home as the sun was coming up from the roofs of that human beehive and I
            realized how futile my efforts and my work had been. I, too, like the philanthropist,
            the social worker and the quack had been dealing with the symptoms rather than the
            disease. I threw my nursing bag into the corner and announced to my family that I would
            never take it up again, that I would never take another case until I had made it
            possible for the working women in America to have the knowledge to control birth. I
            decided I had no moral right to respect a law,--a worn-out piece of parchment,--obsolete
            in every respect, I had no right to respect above human life, and I decided to violate
            it wholesale. I found to my surprise that there was almost no scientific knowledge
            available on this subject in this country. I decided to go abroad to study the question
            there.</p>
        <p>My first stop was at <place reg="Glasgow, Scotland">Glasgow</place>, where I went to find
            out what municipal ownership had done for the women and children of Glasgow, and I found
            that every advantage advanced through this administration were all of benefit to those
            who had small families. For instance, the model tenement houses owned by the
            municipality were built for those not having more than two or three children, while the
            men and women who had five, six, nine or ten children were compelled to live in the
            outskirts of the city, and huddled in the surroundings of their industry. It was the
            same with every other advantage to be gained through municipal ownership, and when I saw
            the women with shawls over their heads, <del>a</del>
            <del>baby</del><add>babies</add> in their arms and two or three little ones dragging at
            their skirts, walking through the streets at midnight calling and chanting the cry of
            help and asking for bread, my heart failed me with courage to remain longer in this
            model city, and I left to investigate conditions in France. There I found that the women
            of France, as in Holland, had done more for themselves in five years through the
            knowledge of birth control than municipal ownership had done in twenty years' time for
            the women of Glasgow!!</p>
        <p>I hurried back to America to urge women here to help me to do this important work. I
            asked several prominent women, suffragists, feminists, and others, whom I knew not only
            believe in the idea of birth control but practiced it. I requested these women to help
            me to do this work which I thought would strike at the root of the evil. I tried to get
            fifty women to go on record with me to make a test case in the courts but I was told to
            wait until we got the vote, I was told to wait until I became better known, but the
            cries of thousands of suffering women would not let me wait.</p>
        <p>I started to publish the <title type="journal">Woman Rebel, The</title><xref
                from="128167.xml">Jan. 17, 1916></xref>. I am not going to take up your time to tell
            you about it. You all know of its brief existence. They tell me that it was too radical,
            badly written, hysterical, defiant, to all of which I plead guilty, but as I became more
            and more convinced of the necessity of birth control I felt myself in the position of
            one who has discovered that <del>the</del><add>a</add> house is on fire and I found it
            was up to me shout out the warning-- Should we criticize the tone of the voice which
            shouts out the alarm? I might have taken up the policy of safety, sanity and
            conservatism, but would I have gotten a hearing? Is there not a great deal in the theory
            in all modern life that if one desires bread you must <del>make a
                demand</del><add>ask</add> for cake? This was my <del>belief</del>
            <add>theory</add> when I started <del>to edit and</del> publish the Woman Rebel.</p>
        <p>It was necessary in order to bring the attention of the people to this <del>issue and to
                its</del> necessity to make the demand so flamboyant that it would arouse attention
            and interest. You know of the suppression and confiscation by the post office
            authorities. You know of the indictments handed down by the Grand Jury against me. You
            know that many postponements of my trial and the final dismissal of the case by the
            government, and I am reluctant to call it a victory, for what has victory meant to me in
            this case. It has meant months and months of persecution by spies and detectives, prying
            into every phase of my activity, coming into my home in the guise of comrades and
            friends. It has meant the exertion of the meanest and most despicable methods in trying
            to suppress the message of birth control, as it has meant the opening of all my private
            letters and the invasion of every constitutional right which we are supposed to enjoy in
            this country. It would be impossible for me to enumerate all the hindrances and the
            tricks our benevolent government put in my way the months I was publishing the paper.
            Indictments were the last weapons in the strenuous campaign to stamp out the idea of
            birth control. I am glad to say the very reverse of what was intended has occurred for
            the same authorities who two years ago adjudged me "<q>lewd and
                <add>licentious</add></q>" now pay me the pretty compliment that I am not a
            disorderly person, but why did the authorities change their minds? Because of the
            thousands and thousands of letters of protest which came to them from all parts of this
            country, and <del>I</del> convinced them that birth control is too vital a demand in the
            United States today to be suppressed through the persecution of an individual,
                <del>which</del> proves to us again that the courts, no matter how powerful, cannot
            combat a strong and intelligent public opinion. My fight with the government has been to
            arouse interest in the subject of birth control and in this at least I feel I have been
            victorious. Some of us may only be fit to dramatize a situation to focus attention upon
            objectionable laws then those more experienced in constructive organization can gather
            together all this sympathy and interest which has been aroused and organize and
                <del>educated </del><add>direct it.</add> The work now before us is to crystallize
            this interest into action, not only for the repeal of the laws but for the establishment
            of free clinics throughout the industrial sections of this country.</p>
        <p><del>Can we not form here tonight a birth control league to carry on this work. Such a
                league would be a <add>rallying point</add> for the progressive thought in this city
                and would focus interest on the local necessity for this work. Such a
                    clinic<add>League</add> would enable the working women to help themselves and to
                do away with charity, which at its best can give only temporary relief.</del> Birth
            control will <add>shelter</add> women from incessant child bearing. This must be done
            for her before she can participate in social life. Through it will she triumph over
            nature's and man's laws which have kept her in bondage, just as man has triumphed over
            nature by the use of electricity, ship building, bridges etc. Through it will she
            triumph over the laws which have made her a child-bearing machine and in her triumph
            over these she will not only free herself but she will also free <del>her
                children</del><add>the child</add>, for in her own emancipation will be that of the
                <del>children</del><add>childs</add>. She holds them both within her own hands. In
            her triumph over these she will develop her personality and individuality
                <del>to</del><add>&amp; prepare</add> with man for the emancipation of the race.</p>
        <p>In Europe they <del>tell me</del><add>say</add> that to some extent the failure of the US
            to produce a proportionate number of great men is a disquieting feature of civilization.
            Two hundred years have elapsed since the settlement began to take permanent shape. The
            population is now immense. The opportunities for education are unprecedented. Yet the
            native born men of real eminence, of world wide fame, are very few in number.</p>
        <p>Hitherto the development of the race has been unconscious. We have had no responsibility
            for <del>the</del>
            <add>its</add> right course! Now in the 20th century <add>1916.</add> in the fullness of
            time, let us be children no longer-- let us fashion the human race with an intelligent
            consciousness <del>&amp; let us face the facts of this vital racial &amp; social needs
                &amp; stand squarely to meet our responsibilities &amp;</del> Birth Control is both
            a social and a racial need. Let us face the facts of this vital need and stand squarely
            to meet our responsibilities.</p>
        <p>Birth Control will free the woman it will free the child. Thru it we shall produce a race
            of quality instead of quantity. Woman must triumph over the laws which have made her a
            child bearing machine <add>bondage</add>. Only in <gap reason="deleted"
                extent="one word"/>
            <person reg="Paine, Thomas">Thomas Paine</person>
            <gap reason="illegible" extent="rest of sentence"/></p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
