<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/04/16 VS initial tags</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1939-02-00 ">February, 1939</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Havelock Ellis - On His 80th Birthday</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp128157</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Havelock Ellis - On His 80th Birthday</title><title
                    type="journal">Journal of Contraception</title> February, 1939</bibl>
            <bibl><title>LCM</title> 129:565</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="ELLHA">Ellis, Havelock</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">Journal of Contraception, February, 1939, pp. 27-30. This article included
        descriptions of <person reg="Ellis, Havelock">Ellis</person> by Adolf Meyer, Robert
        Dickinson, Ira Wile, Will Durant, and John Haymes Holmes. Only the portioned authored by
        Sanger is transcribed below, as well as a joint statement made by multiple authors,
        including Sanger. For a typed draft, see LCM 129:565. 
        <index level1="Ellis, Havelock"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <byline><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></byline>
        <div>
            <p> “...I climbed up the stairs, and, with the shyness of an adolescent, full of fears
                and uncertainties, lifted the huge brass knocker. The figure of Ellis himself
                appeared in the door. He seemed a giant in stature, a lovely, simple man in
                loose-fitting clothes, with powerful head and wonderful smile. He was fifty-five
                then, but that head will never change--the shock of white hair, the venerable beard,
                shaggy though well-kept, the wide, expressive mouth and deep-set eyes, sad even in
                spite of the humorous twinkle always latent...</p>
            <p> “We sat down and quiet fell. I tried a few aimless remarks but I stuttered with
                embarrassment. Ellis was still. Small talk was not possible with him; you had to
                utter only the deepest truths within you. No other human being could be so silent
                and remain so poised and calm in silence. . .</p>
            <p> “Soon appeared a large tray, laden with tea, cakes, and bread and butter, and we sat
                down before the humming flame and talked and talked; and as we talked we wove into
                our lives an intangible web of mutual interests. I began to realize then that the
                men who are truly great are the easiest to meet and understand. . . Ellis pasted no
                labels on himself, had no poses. made no effort to impress. He was simply, quite
                un-selfconsciously, what he was. . .</p>
            <p> “Ellis has been called the greatest living English gentleman. But
                    <place>England</place> alone cannot claim him; he belongs to all mankind. I
                define him as one who radiates truth, energy, and beauty. I see him in a realm above
                and beyond the shouting and the tumult. Captains and kings come and go. Lilliputian
                warriors strut their hour, and boundary lines between nations are made and unmade.
                Although he takes no active share in this external trafficking, he does not dwell
                apart in an ivory tower of his own construction.</p>
            <p> “This Olympian seems to be aloof from the pain of the world, yet he has penetrated
                profoundly into the persistent problems of race. Nothing human is alien to his
                sympathy. His knowledge is broad and deep; his wisdom even deeper. He makes no
                strident, blatant effort to cry aloud his message, but gradually and in
                ever-increasing numbers, men and women pause to listen to his serene voice. . . </p>
            <p> “To Havelock Ellis we owe our concept of that Kingdom of <name type="diety"
                    >God</name> within us, that inner world which hides all our inherent
                potentialities for joy as well as suffering. Thanks to him we realize that happiness
                must be the fruit of an attitude towards life, that it is in no way dependent upon
                the rewards or the fits of fortune. Like <person reg="Francis of Assisi, Saint">St.
                    Francis of Assisi</person>, he teaches the beauty of nature, of his brother the
                sun and his sister the moon, of birds and fish and animals, and all the pageantry of
                the passing seasons.</p>
            <p> “I have never felt about any other person as I do about Havelock Ellis. To know him
                has been a bounteous privilege; to claim him friend my greatest honor.”</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> From a Joint Statement</head>
            <p> Havelock Ellis was born eighty years ago today, on February 2, 1959, in
                    <place>Surrey, England</place>, the son of a British seaman, and the last of a
                long line of English clergymen, mariners and merchants. Though Ellis is known for
                the wide range of his culture and interests, for his distinction as critic and
                writer, for his rare personal charm, and for his brad humanity, he will perhaps be
                best and longest remembered for the work to which, at an early age, he had dedicated
                his life and energy - that of bringing the human sex psychology within the scope of
                science. His seven monumental volumes of <title type="book">Studies in the
                    Psychology of Sex</title> have probably served more than any other single work
                to bring sex out of the atmosphere of ignorance and prudery into the clear light of
                science, and will always remain an incomparable critical digest of the scientific
                knowledge of the subject up to contemporary times.</p>
            <p> The scientific study of sex is nowadays accepted almost without question, but the
                destruction of old taboos and prejudices was not accomplished without hardship and
                sacrifice. The appearance of Ellis’ first volume of the Studies in 1897 was followed
                by a prosecution for the distribution of what the judge described as a “filthy
                publication” ... <q who="ELLHA">“I am a student,”</q> wrote Ellis in his memorable
                    <title type="book">Note on the Bedborough Trial</title>, <q who="ELLHA">“and my
                    path has long been marked out. I may be forced to pursue it under unfavorable
                    conditions, but I do not intend that any consideration shall induce me to swerve
                    from it.” </q> His life achievement is the best testimony to the success of this
                early resolve.</p>
            <p> We hope that Havelock Ellis will for many years continue to exercise his great and
                good influence. His life and work remain an inspiration not only to us but to future
                generations as well.</p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
