<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Draft Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2002-01-10 EK</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2002-08-15 KH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2003/08/14 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/23 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/08/09 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007/06/25 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2015/01/14 clean regs + correct proof EK</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1916-01-17">17 Jan 1916</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>
                <supplied resp="MSPP">Hotel Brevoort Speech</supplied>
            </titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp128167</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
            <bibl><title type="mf">Library of Congress Microfilm</title>, LCM 129:588</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp id="MSPP">MSPP</resp>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
        <p>Margaret Sanger gave this speech on the evening before her <title>Woman Rebel</title>
            trial was to begin. Handwritten corrections by Margaret Sanger.</p>
        <index level1="abortion"/>
        <index level1="birth control movement" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="Woman Rebel, The" level2="suppression of"/>
        <index level1="Woman Rebel, The" level2="arrests and trials"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="propaganda and publicity"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="class-based"/>
            </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head><add>Hotel Brevoort</add>
            <add>Maiden Speech</add>         
        </head>
                <p>It seems to me that this evening and this gathering are significant and important, not
            only because the idea of birth control has brought together <del>all of us</del> workers
            of such diverse outlook and temperament, but especially because
            of the time chosen for it--the eve of my trial. . . .<del>and because of the dignified and
                representative intelligence which has supported me in this battle</del>.</p>
        <p><del>FOR</del> I realize keenly that many of those who understand and would support <del>the</del> birth control propaganda if it were carried out in a safe and sane manner, cannot
            sympathize with nor countenance the methods I have followed in my attempt to arouse <del>the</del>
            working women to the fact that bringing a child into the world is the greatest
            responsibility.</p>
        <p>They tell me that <title type="pamphlet">The Woman Rebel</title> was badly written; that
            it was crude; that it was emotional, <add>and</add> hysterical; that it mixed issues;
            that is was defiant, and too radical.</p>
        <p>WELL, to all of these indictments I plead guilty! I know that <del>any, and
                perhaps</del> all of you are better able to cope with the subject than I am. I know
            that physicians and scientists have a great technical fund of information--greater than
            I had on the subject of family limitation.</p>
        <p>THERE is nothing new, nothing radical in birth control. <person>Aristotle</person>
            advocated it; <person>Plato</person> advocated it; all our great <del>and</del> modern
            thinkers have advocated it!</p>
        <p>It is an idea that must appeal to any mature intelligence.</p>
        <p><del>But</del>
            <add>Yet</add> all this scientific and technical discussion has <add>only</add> had the
            effect of producing more technical and scientific discussion--all very necessary and
            very stimulating to that very small group of men and women who could understand it.</p>
        <p>BUT, all during the long years <del>while</del> this matter <del>was being</del>
            <add>has been</add> discussed, advocated, refuted, the people themselves--<del>the</del> poor
            people especially--were blindly, desperately practicing family limitation--just as
            they are practicing it today.</p>
        <p><del>BUT</del> To them birth control does not mean what it does to us.</p>
        <p>TO THEM it has meant the most barbaric methods. It has meant the killing of
            babies--infanticide,--abortions,--in one crude way or another.</p>
        <p>WOMEN, from time immemorial, have tried to avoid unwanted motherhood.</p>
        <p>WE ALL KNOW the tribe of professional abortionists which has sprung up and profited by
            this terrible misfortune.</p>
        <p>WE KNOW, TOO, that when the practice of abortion was put under the ban by the
            church, <del>the</del>``
            <add>an</add> alternate evil--the foundling asylum, with its horrifying history--sprang
            up.</p>
        <p>THERE IS NO NEED to go into the terrible facts concerning the recklessness, the misery,
            the filth, with which children have been and still are being brought into the world.</p>
        <p>I merely want to point out the situation I found when I entered the battle.</p>
        <p>ON THE ONE HAND, I found the wise men, <del>the</del> sages, <del>the</del> scientists,
            discussing birth control among themselves.</p>
        <p>But their ideas were sterile. They did not influence nor affect the tremendous facts of
            life among the working classes and the disinherited!</p>
        <p>HOW COULD I <del>APPROACH</del>
            <add>Bridge</add> THIS CHASM? How could I reach these people? How could I awaken public
            opinion to this tremendous problem?</p>
        <p>I MIGHT HAVE TAKEN up <del>the</del>
            <add>a</add> policy of safety, sanity and conservatism--but would I have got a hearing?</p>
        <p>AND AS I BECAME MORE AND MORE CONSCIOUS of the vital importance of this idea, I felt
            myself in the position of one who has discovered that a house is on fire; and I found
            that it was up to me to shout out the warning!</p>
        <p>THE TONE OF THE VOICE may have been indelicate and unladylike, and was not at all the
            tone than many of us would rather hear.</p>
        <p>BUT THIS VERY GATHERING--this honor you have thrust upon me--is ample proof that
            intelligent and constructive thought has been aroused.</p>
        <p>SOME OF US may only be fit to dramatize a situation--to focus attention upon obsolete
            laws, like this one I must face tomorrow morning.</p>
        <p>THEN, others, more experienced in constructive organization, can gather together all this
            sympathy and interest which has been aroused, and direct it.</p>
        <p>I THANK YOU for your encouragement and support. <del>AND</del> MY REQUEST TO YOU TONIGHT
            is that all you social workers--so much better fitted to carry on this work than I--that
            you consider and organize this interest.</p>
        <p>THIS IS THE MOST NEXT IMPORTANT STEP AND ONLY IN THIS WAY CAN I BE VINDICATED!!</p>
        <p>
            <add>Let us put <place reg="United States of America">U S. of A</place> upon the map of
                the civilized world!</add>
        </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
