<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed draft speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/02/26 VS initial tagging</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/02/28 CH Proof tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/03/04 VS correct tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-11-14 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1932-02-19">19 Feb 1932</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>
                <supplied resp="MSPP">My Way to World Peace</supplied>
            </titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp129035</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl> Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress </bibl>
            <bibl>Library of Congress Microfilm, 130:190-197</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="JAP">Japanese Government</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
            <name id="ROSFL">Rose, Florence</name>
            <name id="MSPP">Margaret Sanger Papers Project</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>This is a revised version of Sanger's Jan. 17, 1932 speech "<xref from="129037.xml"
                    ><title type="article">My Way to Peace</title></xref>," given to the <org>New
                History Society</org>. This version may not have been published or given as a
            speech. Interlineations were made by hand by Margaret Sanger.</p>
        <p> A note was attatched to this draft from Sanger's secretary, <person reg="Rose, Florence"
                >Florence Rose</person>. It reads:</p>
        <q who="ROSFL">
            <p> WELL, HERE'S THE REVISED VERSION OF "MY PLAN TO PEACE"</p>
            <p> All the figures need checking: many of them <emph rend="underline">cannot
                    possibly</emph> be right. Their figures were wrong in many cases, I knew, and I
                used mine where I had them--but I did not exert myself to catch them when taking
                notes, as I felt sure you had the statistical data somewhere.</p>
            <p> I EXPECT TO HAVE THE <org reg="Russell Sage Foundation">RUSSELL-SAGE</org>
                <xref from="321976.xml">ARTICLE</xref> BY TOMORROW NOON FOR YOU.</p>
            <p> Like the Scotchman and his tight shoes--it feels so good when you take them off--it
                feels grand to at least have this preliminary work down! At any rate, it isn't as
                bad as the version they presented as your talk!</p>
            <p> F.R.</p>
            <p> Hope you had a good time today!</p>
        </q>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="class-based"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="definitions of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="mainstreaming of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="population and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="religion and"/>
         <index level1="birth control movement" level2="goals and strategies"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="increase in"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="efforts to reduce"/>
        <index level1="child spacing"/>
        <index level1="family size" level2="class-based"/>
        <index level1="&quot;feeble-minded&quot; persons" level2="fertility and birth rate of"/>
        <index level1="immigration" level2="U.S. policy"/>
        <index level1="Italy" level2="overpopulation and"/>
        <index level1="Italy" level2="population policies of"/>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="overpopulation and"/>
        <index level1="National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control"/>
        <index level1="overpopulation" level2="threat to peace as"/>
        <index level1="population growth" level2="regulation of"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="population growth in"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <byline>Mrs. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>, Chairman of
                <org>National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control</org>, 17 W. 16th
            St., <place reg="New York, NY">New York City</place>.</byline>
        <dateline>
            <date value="1932-02-19"/>
        </dateline>
        <p> Mr. <person reg="Unknown">Chairman</person>, Ladies &amp; Gentlemen:</p>
        <p> In this day of great world upheaval it is natural that there should be drawn up various
            plans and proposals as to the means of world peace. My way to world peace is not the way
            of moratoriums, reparations, or tariffs; it is not the way of Versailles treaties; my way to peace is the way of
            the people. My way is to direct and control the population through birth control.</p>
        <p> There is probably no other subject that has such a practical significance,
                <add>which</add> at the same time cuts so deeply into the foundations of social
            evolution and world peace, as birth control. Birth control is a keynote, – it is a
            signal of a new moral awakening; a moral responsibility, not only for those children who
            have already been born; a responsibility not only for those that are about to be born;
            but for those who have not yet been conceived. It is not only a health and economic
            expedient; it is a great social <del>measure</del>
            <add>principle</add>, and that <del>measure</del>
            <add>principle</add> is interlocked and interwoven with the spiritual progress of the
            race, and its future.</p>
        <p> The definition of birth control is, “the conscious control of the birth rate by means
            that prevent conception of human lives”. When you prevent the conception of human life,
            you do not have to destroy human life. You do not destroy,-–you do not interfere with
            the development of human life, because there is no life to interfere with or to destroy.
            It is no more an interference with life to prevent conception than to remain single or
            to live in celibacy. We say “<emph rend="underline">control</emph>”. When you control
            the birth rate you do not have to limit it, any more than when you control your own
            furnace; you do not put out the fire. You merely adjust its temperature to the
            requirements of the weather, <del>(you do not have to put the fire out)</del>
            <add>considering the time of the day and the season</add>. When you control your
            automobile, you do not necessarily have to stop the engine. And when you control the
            size of your family, you do not have to <emph rend="underline">limit</emph> yourself to
            one or two children, but you control <del>it</del>
            <add>the number</add>; first according to the state of the mother’s health affecting the
            possible inheritance of the child; second, according to the father’s earning power; and
            third, according to the standards of living that you wish to maintain. <del>When</del>
            We say conscious control – I wonder if any of us can imagine what it is going to mean
            when the human <del>voice</del>
            <add>race</add> is conceived <add>consciously</add>, not just as a result of casual
            accident – the reckless abandon of the moment – <del>but</del>
            <add>when it</add> is consciously <del>planned for</del>
            <add>desired,</add> and <del>consciously</del> conceived <add>consciously</add>. I tell
            you my friends, we <del>don’t know what is</del>
            <add>can only glimpse at the wonders that will be be</add> before us, when that
            possibility becomes a reality.</p>
        <p> You hear people say, “<q who="UNK">Why control the birth rate? There is plenty of room
                in the world and in this country <add>for unlimited population</add></q>”. What we
            need is a more equal distribution of the necessities of life<add>, a new social
                system</add>. <del>The control of nature is not the control that we desire today,
                because there are only two ways of controlling the population in that way; either by
                increasing deaths, or by decreasing births.</del></p>
        <p> Let us regard this. Population has always been controlled. From the beginning of time, –
            back as far as we know anything about the human race, there has been control of
                <del>numbers</del>
            <add>population</add> by the <del>control</del>
            <add>methods</add> of Nature. <del>Which</del>
            <add>This</add> is not the control we desire today. There are only two ways to control
            population – either <del>increase</del>
            <add>to decrease</add> the birth rate or <del>decrease</del>
            <add>to increase</add> death rate, and all through the history of mankind, population
            has been controlled by <del>the death method</del>
            <add>increasing the death rate</add>. Nature has been the most ruthless advocate of
            birth control <del>through</del>
            <add>by</add> this method. She has accomplished it through famines, pestilences,
            diseases, floods and wars. Nature thrusts to the wall the old, the weak, the maimed, the
            mentally deficient, until she perfects her type. Only the fit and strong are able to
            survive through the way of nature.</p>
        <p> This <del>might have been</del>
            <add>doubtless is</add> an excellent way <add>for Nature</add> to perfect <add>our</add>
            civilization. But today, whether we like it or not, we no longer <add>allow</add>
            control <add>of</add> the population through nature’s method of increased death rates.
            Civilization has progressed beyond that. <del>Now</del> With the <del>development</del>
            <add>advance</add> of Christianity; with the <del>development</del>
            <add>organization</add> of Charity and <add>development of</add> Humanitarianism, we
            have <del>turned</del>
            <add>thrust</add> aside the hand of nature, we have interfered with nature’s methods, we
            will not allow these methods to operate. Civilization takes <del>into the race</del>
            <add>care of</add> the old, the feeble, the mentally deficient, <add>the diseased, the
                insane, the morons</add> and makes it almost imperative for them to <del>exist
                and</del> increase <del>their numbers</del>
            <add>and multiply</add>. Defectives are <del>now</del>
            <add>fast</add> breeders<add>.</add>
            <add>The feeble minded woman is </add>three times as <del>fast</del>
            <add>fertile</add> as normal <del>mothers</del>
            <add>women</add>. This constitutes a real menace to our civilization. There is no doubt
            that those privileged to carry on the torch of civilization are <add>comparitively
                in</add> lessening <add>in</add> numbers <del>than bear to those who have become on
                the race</del>
            <add>while at the same time they carry the financial burdens of the unfit</add>.</p>
        <p> We find, according to psychological tests made by Professor <person
                reg="Starr-Meyer, William">William Starr-Meyer</person> a few years ago, that only
            15,000,000 out of a population of 165,000,000 could be classified as intellectuals and
            it was found that 85,000,000 had the minds of juveniles under 14 years of age,
            45,000,000 were just average and 15,000,000 were known to be feeble-minded. The great
            majority of the feeble-minded, the degenerates and the morons do not live in
            institutions but are <del>mothers</del> living in homes and multiplying rapidly. Is
                <place reg="United States">America</place> then, safe for democracy? In this
            country, the feeble-minded, if they are twenty-one years of age, have the power to vote
            and their vote is just as good as that of the fifteen percent who are intellectuals.
            Isn’t it time to do something about this?</p>
        <p> We have today what <del>is called</del><add>scientists call</add> a differential birth
            rate: <add>or</add> in other words <add>a difference in the birth rate of two groups in
                our population</add>, For the last <del>two</del> generations <del>perhaps</del>, a
            certain number of people, mainly the fifteen percent intellectuals have been controlling
            their birthrate – that is the group with the small families. They have, perhaps, two or
            three or four children, but in that group, the greatest number of children achieve
            maturity. Here, consideration is given to the mother’s health, <add>to the child's</add>
            education and to the possible development <add>of talents</add> of the children.
                <del>and</del> It is from this group <add>that</add> we find the <del>most</del>
            children going to <add>high</add> schools<add>,</add>
            <del>the longest. Their children go</del> to colleges, universities and eventually
                <del>they fill</del>
            <add>filling</add> the best positions in society.</p>
        <p> The other group <add>of large families</add> struggles in poverty and in ignorance. Here
            we find that poverty and <del>ignorance</del><add>lack of birth control</add> go hand in
            hand. We find the mothers broken on the wheel of <del>poverty trying hard to find
                out</del><add>maternity</add>, <add>everywhere they ask</add> what they can do to
            prevent bringing another human being into this world. The fathers become desperate<del>
                when unemployed</del><add>, and dismayed</add>. <del>They become over-burdened and
                morally unfit.</del> It is in this group that we have almost all the great social
            problems of the day. You have slums, overcrowding, high maternal and infant morality,
            child labor, illegitimacy, illiteracy. Many in this group are not only unemployed, but
            unemployable, I found, while working among this group, that it is not their fault that
            they have more children than they can decently provide for. I found an awakening
            consciousness on the part of these <del>women to</del><add>mothers and a desire to</add>
            have only the number that they could decently take care of, but, because of their
            poverty, they found every door closed against them.</p>
        <p>
            <add>Because</add> These <del>are the</del> mothers <del>who</del> have to go to public
            institutions, hospitals, etc., for medical advice and care, and <del>when</del> they are
            taken to the hospital to have their babies or to have abortions performed,
                <add>when</add> they as what they can do <emph rend="underline">not</emph> to have
            any more <del>and</del> they are told that it is against the law to give them this
            information; <add>or</add> that it is immoral and against the laws of nature. Yet, all
            the time, the wives of professional classes are obtaining information to enable them to
            limit their families.</p>
        <p> What do we do about these <del> evils of society</del>
            <add>problems</add>? We do not like them; we try to legislate them out of existence. We
            have been trying for over fifty years to do away with child labor, yet, have we done it?
            A few years ago, we had several million children under fifteen years working in the
            United States. <del>Mainly, </del>These children are taking the place <add>of
                adults</add> and competing with their fathers and mothers in industry
                <del>just</del>
            <add>mainly</add> for <add>a</add> daily existence. Behind them are more and more
            children forced out of schools and homes, little children who should be getting their
            education <del>for the sake of</del>
            <add>in preparation for</add> the future of the race. It is a long story, that of child
            labor. Go to the beet fields of <place>Colorado</place> or to the cotton fields of the
            South and you will see the devastating effects of ignorance <del>ethics</del>
            <add>of birth control and child labor</add>. The child labor committee worked valiantly
            to try to legislate this evil out of existence, but it cannot succeed until Birth
            Control Clinics are in operation in these sections; until the mothers of these children
            have the proper scientific information necessary to control their power of
            fertility.</p>
        <p> One can go through almost all of <del>these</del>
            <add>our</add> social problems and <del>you</del> can see at a glance how they are
            interwoven <del>and how they</del>
            <add>with and</add> pivot around the question of birth control. Let us consider together
            two more problems connected with the welfare of the race. Take the simple question of
            maternal mortality. Every physician will tell a mother who has heart disease or kidney
            disease that she should not go through child-birth again. If she <del>does</del>
            <add>should</add> become pregnant <del>again</del>, according to <del>the law</del>
            <add>medical ethics</add>, it is legal to interrupt this condition <add>to save her
                life</add>. But instead of <add>them</add> instructing her in the means of
            contraception, she is sent back to her home with only a <del>statement that the doctors
                will not be responsible for her life if she should</del>
            <add>warning not to</add> get into that condition again. She then goes back to her
                <del>children</del><add>home</add> in a fearful and nervous condition with a death
            sentence hanging over her head<del>, and in a weakened state of mind</del>. Can you
            imagine the effect <add>that</add> this <add>fear</add> creates in a home and what it
            means to the husband and children? Every <del>sick</del> mother should be protected by
            the best information possible.</p>
        <p> We move from the mother problem to the infant problem. There we find conditions just as
            bad; there the mortality is even larger. Approximately 200,000 little children never
            reach their first birthday; ninety-five percent of them are unwanted and the large
            majority of them die from causes <del>of</del><add>due to</add> poverty and neglect.
            There is not one person here who believes that we can do away with this problem next
            year or the following year – and yet the state allows these mothers to remain in utter
            ignorance of how to prevent the coming of 200,000 more lives next year and the next
            year, who are doomed in advance to die from causes of poverty and neglect.</p>
        <p> Our <org reg="United States Children's Bureau">Children’s Bureau</org> tells us
                <del>that</del>
            <add>from</add> some of their statistics <del>with</del>
            <add>that</add> this question of <del>unfit</del><add>infant</add> mortality
                <del>has</del>
            <add>is concerned with</add> three <del>very</del> vital factors. The first is the
            father’s wage. As it goes up, a larger number of the children survive – if it goes down,
            a larger number of children die. Second, is the spacing of children in a family. <del>In
                other words,</del> Where two or three years elapse between the birthdays of
            children, they have a better chance to survive and develop. The mother has had an
            opportunity to recuperate and rebuild her health. The family income has been stretched
            out over the intervening period of years to meet the family needs. We know that the
            spacing of children determines their chances of survival –that the second child has a
            better chance to live than the fifth, and the fifth a better chance to live than the
            twelfth, certainly. We have the astounding statistics that sixty percent of percent of
            all the twelfth children born in this country <del>are doomed to</del> die before they
            reach their first birthday. In other words, about six out of every ten children who are
            twelfth in their family <del>are doomed to</del> die before they breathe their first
            breath. What a waste of child life! <del>And</del>
            <add>Waste</add> of mother power! <del>Which</del>
            <add>Both of these</add> might have been put into the constructive forces <del>in this
                world</del>
            <add>of race building</add> instead of making <del>of our</del> women <del>only</del>
            incubators or child-bearing machines, which is, what women <del>have been throughout the
                ages</del>
            <add>become when they are ignorant of birth control</add>.</p>
        <p>
            <del>While</del>
            <add>We know</add>All of <del>this</del><add>these statistical facts</add>
            <del>we know</del>, and we <del>should</del> try to alleviate some of the conditions but
            our efforts are only palliative. We can correct them only to a certain degree. We give
            free lunches<add> to children</add>, educational care, do everything possible to keep
            them alive. <del>You</del><add>We</add> rescue a child <del>to live</del><add>and bring
                it</add> through its first years, <del>and</del> then <del>you</del><add>we</add>
            have to battle again to carry <del>them</del><add>it</add> through the succeeding years
            and <del>then</del> when it becomes fourteen, it secures working papers and starts to
            compete with his father in industry thereby creating labor problems. Thus all workers
            become their own rivals in <del>trade</del><add>the labor market. The law of supply and
                demand dominates their existance</add></p>
        <p> How stupid the labor organizations have been to recognize the power of limited numbers
            in a union, but <add>to fail</add>
            <del>not</del> to recognize <del>how illogical it is to permit themselves to become
                their own rivals</del><add>the same principle in their families</add>.</p>
        <p> It seems to me there is no greater cruelty than bringing a child into this
                world<del>,</del>
            <add>when the parents are diseased or</add> when there is no provision for its care<del>
                when the parents are diseased</del>. When studying law or when
                <del>preparing</del><add>contemplating</add>
            <del>to take</del><add>training</add> the robe of priesthood or entering <del>even</del>
            <add>law or</add> the least of the professions, <del>you have to</del>
            <add>one must</add> study carefully to fit <del>yourself</del>
            <add>oneself</add> for <del>your</del>
            <add>one's</add> duties. But anyone can become a father or mother. It makes no
            difference how unprepared <add>or how unfit</add> one <del>might</del>
            <add>may</add> be – no difference what one can earn – one can have <del>as large a</del>
            <add>any</add> number of children <del>as wanted</del>. Let us consider the children
            born of diseased parents. If we know we had to pass through other human bodies in order
            to reach another world, would we <add>not</add> be most particular and careful to choose
            the kind of parents we should have? We would be more than particular, so why should we
            not be just as particular about our obligations to the children we expect to bear?</p>
        <p> It is not only a personal question, not only a question affecting family welfare but is
            also a question affecting world affairs.</p>
        <p> In 1924, the United States Government came to the realization that there was a serious
            population problem in this country. We were not so much concerned about the number of
            people as about the quality of the population. The <org>United States Government</org>
            therefore put a <title type="law"><rs reg="Immigration Act of 1924">ban</rs></title> on
            immigration. No alien could enter who had certain diseases or was feeble-minded,
                <add>or</add> illiterate, or who came here for the practice of prostitution. There
            is a very long list of undesirable <del>aliens who cannot come into</del>
            <add>qualities which ban aliens from</add> this country. Furthermore, <add>if</add>
            incase some of them do get in, these undesirable qualities are indicated within five
            years, these individuals can be deported. This is a good law. We do not want undesirable
            types to stain the blood stream of the Nation, but, if it is <add>right that</add>
            undesirables, <del>that they</del>
            <add>shall not</add> come <add>into the country</add> from without, then why isn’t it
            equally important that they <add>not</add> increase and multiply <del>from</del> within
            the country? They propagate the same undesirable qualities that we are trying to keep
            out <del>of</del>
            <add>by</add> our immigration laws. These laws of the United States Government cause a
            great upheaval in <place>Europe</place> and have disturbed the flow and flux of
            population throughout the whole world. Since we have had a selective quota of
            population, you can imagine what it has meant to some of those countries that had free
            entry into our country for so many years. Let us consider two countries that are no
            longer able to find a place for their surplus population in the United States.</p>
        <p> There are two countries that we must call danger spots in the world:
                <place>Italy</place> and <place>Japan</place>. These two countries have a very acute
            population problem. Japan is a country mostly mountainous with a population of
            67,000,000 of people and with a territorial area not quite as large as
                <place>California</place>. She cannot possibly feed her population and has never
            tried to reduce her birth rate and density of population which is very heavy indeed.
            There are only about 148 square miles and over 400 human beings are crammed into each
            square mile. It means that Japan, not being able to expand in other countries who would
            not have her<add> people</add>, had to look for other outlets for her large
            over-population. <place>South America</place> was willing to take care of part of this
            surplus population, but not all the ships that Japan has could take her surplus
            population to South America. Japan cannot accommodate them all at home and South America
            can only accommodate a small percentage.</p>
        <p> Japan has an inadequacy of the most important natural resources, <del>but</del><add>and
                although</add> she has a good water power and a <add>large</add> textile industry
                <del>which however, is</del><add>even these are</add> insufficient for that great
            population for which she must provide. <place>Manchuria</place> had all that
                <place>China</place> wanted and lacked in raw materials, and at the first
            opportunity she marched right into Manchuria at the psychological moment when the rest
            of the world was busy at home with its own problems, and it seems that there she will
            stay. She has <del>acclaimed</del><add>proclaimed</add> that “<q who="JAP">Might is
                Right</q>”, and says: “<q who="JAP">What are you going to do about it</q>?”;
                <del>and</del> it is now indeed too late to do much about it.</p>
        <p> Now let us look at Italy who has 119 square miles with a population of 41 millions of
            people, with over 340 people to a square mile. In 1921 the population was 28 millions at
            the rate of 548 people per square mile. The birth rate in 1921 was 30.4, and in 1927 it
            was 26.4. On top of this population which she could not provide for with the world
            against her immigration, she had 4 to 5 thousand additional human beings being born into
            her population annually. Over 25% of Italy’s natural increase was coming into this
            country every year. <place>France</place> received 6 or 7 percent of Italy’s increase,
            but France has curbed this percentage because of her unemployment problems. Italy is
            unable to till her own home areas. She has low standards of living and a slight margin
            of life. Her water power might be developed but at a great expense. She has very little
            iron ore and other raw materials. If she <del>would</del><add>should</add> build up her
            textile industry she would have strong competition <del>in</del><add>from</add>
            Japan.</p>
        <p> Neither the industrial nor the agricultural possibilities of Italy can provide for her
            people, yet we know that Italy is increasing; that her <person reg="Mussolini, Benito"
                >dictators</person> call upon her to increase and multiply; and I read
                <add>that</add> there is now a law in Italy providing that every woman must report
            to a health station periodically to show cause why she has not had a baby every two
            years. However, this condition of population today <del>have</del>
            <add>has</add> not been brought about by dictators alone. <del>We</del>
            <add>And although we</add> have only recently become conscious of the importance of
            birth control and its relation to overpopulation, with the facts of science and
            knowledge that we have today, it seems to me that any dictator who insists upon
            increasing the population by force, <del>such a person</del> should be made to account
            for it at the world court of human justice.</p>
        <p> Other countries are doing their best to adjust their populations. <place>Germany</place>
            is today doing all possible to keep her birth rate down and avert a recurrance of the
            conditions of 1914. France is now trying to compete with Germany by boosting up her
            birth rate. France increases her numbers fearing that Germany will come across the
            border to invade her. It is absurd for France to thus compete with Germany whose
            proportionate majority is so great that France will not catch up to her even in 10
            years. France’s death rate – both infants and maternal – is very high, and she should
            decrease this death rate instead of trying to increase the present population.</p>
        <p>
            <place>England</place> also had an acute problem of over-population and unemployment, so
            she decided to send her surplus people to some of her colonies in order to remedy the
            situation. But it did not work out properly. These people were not happy in the wilds of
                <place>Australia</place> and <place>Canada</place> because of the different
            environment and climatic conditions. They did not have the resistance and vigor to
            withstand the climate. The colonies were therefore obliged to send them back to England
            saying: “We can’t use your slum population. They can’t stand the rigors of the climate.”
            It all comes back to the “quality” of the human being.</p>
        <p> My way of peace is a way of birth control. It can be applied in three ways: First, by
            continence – not marrying. This however, should not be recommended because it implies
            the abandonment of the natural marriage relationship <del>which</del>
            <add>and</add> very often results in the break-up of family life. Second, by
            sterilization. This method is recommended by physicians only in extreme cases where
            other forms of contraception are not possible. <del>for</del>
            <add>It is</add> For those who have not the mental equipment or moral character to use
            means of contraception, and yet who should be given help to prevent their bringing more
            children into the world. There you have chemical and mechanical methods over which the
            whole controversy on birth control has been waged.</p>
        <p> It is to these methods that the <org>Roman Catholic Church</org> objects. An analysis of
            the <person reg="Pope Pius XI">Pope</person>’s recent Encyclical, “<title type="article"
                >On Chaste Wedlock</title>” reveals that they countenance <del>intercourse</del>
            <add>marital intimacies only for propogation or</add> under certain conditions where
            there can be no possibility of conception.</p>
        <p> Now, my way to peace is to apply the same constructive knowledge to this subject that
            has been applied to industry and to the world of life itself.</p>
        <gap reason="missing" extent="several pages"/>
        <p> This is part of the program that we are trying to bring about now. We hope that a
            falling birth rate will do its part to avert future wars, and to maintain world, as well
            as international, peace. We want to make it possible for people to have the best
            scientific information available. We want the medical profession to take this
            responsibility and to distribute information in <del>their</del> public and private
            practice. We want women to be free from the fear of pregnancy. We want children to be
                <add>conceived and</add> born in love, and <add>to</add> be given heritage of a
            sound body and a sound mind.</p>
        <p> We believe that through Birth Control, untold millions can be relieved of misery and
            unhappiness. We believe this is the first and most important step we must take if we
            would bring peace on earth and good will to men and scatter it over the face of the
            world.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
