<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2003/06/09 SB</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2003/08/07 CH Index</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/23 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/26 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/08/09 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/08/13 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007/06/25 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-07 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1916-07-00">
            <supplied>Jul 1916</supplied>
        </docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>The Fight for Birth Control</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp130266</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Birth Control News</title>, July 1916, 3</bibl>
            <bibl>LCM 135:213B</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="birth control" level2="morality of"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="infant"/>
        <index level1="working classes" level2="women and girls"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="opposition to"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>THE FIGHT FOR BIRTH CONTROL</head>
        <byline>By Margaret H. Sanger</byline>
        <p>Concern for woman's morals is the cloak behind which hypocrisy and ignorance have always
            hidden in their age-long effort to keep woman in subjection. In <place>Spain</place>
            today, improved means of transportation are opposed on the ground that they would make
            it easier for women to get to the large cities and lead immoral lives!</p>
        <p>Woman working side by side with man today demands that the old moral code be revised and
            that moral questions be freely discussed. The fight for birth control is a fight for
            moral freedom and equality.</p>
        <p>Every department of life is open to investigation and discussion except the shaded valley
            of sex. Woe to him who dares explore that forbidden realm! No matter how pure his
            motives or how serious the ills he seeks to cure, slander, persecution and imprisonment
            await him who ventures to throw the light of knowledge into that cave of darkness.</p>
        <p>Anyone who has seen at first hand the misery and ignorance of the poor must recognize
            that birth control is one of the livest issues of the day and that it affects deeply the
            future welfare of the race.</p>
        <p>Three hundred babies under one year of age die annually in this country from poverty and
            neglect, while 600,000 parents are kept in ignorance of how to prevent the birth of
            300,000 more to die in the same way the following year.</p>
        <p>Women of the working class consider it wrong to bring children into the world to die of
            hunger and privation. They prefer to risk their lives through abortion, if need be,
            rather than give birth to children they cannot properly feed and clothe. A few simple
            words of advice would avoid the horrible slaughter of abortion going on in this country
            today.</p>
        <p>The <place reg="United States">United States</place> is the only country where it is
            unlawful to give information regarding birth control. </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
