<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Interview">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014-12-19 Initials task</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger,Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1948-02-02">Add date in standard format</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>"Too Many People" Radop Interview</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp143743</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title>Journal if published</title> or archival collection if not</bibl>
			<bibl> Library of Congress Microfilm 130:636</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name/>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>This rought transcript of a radio discussion between Sanger and Mr. Wiesel and Mrs. Petch
			with hand written corrections and additions by Sanger and other unidentified people,
			possibly Dorothy Brush.</p>
		<index level1="xxxx"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Too Many People- Station H H 2 S- Radio Port Au Prince: Margaret Sanger.</head>
		<p>Wiesel: Introduction</p>
		<p> Sanger: Thank you, Mr. Wiesel. I am glad to have this opportunity to speak from Haiti on
			this vital question of world population. For the first tim ein hidtory people of
			thinking of an international program for population control. It is significant that a
			United Nations delegate at the International Health Conference said, "The control of the
			birth rate is as important as control of the atom bomb" Population is a large and vague
			word- but when you think about it <del>more carefully</del> it simply means people. Our
			leaders disagree on this problem of people. Some leaders want many more people to
			populate their countries. They give prizes and rewards to mothers of big families. They
			think of national welfare in terms of how many nationals they have of military age.
			Other experts disagree <del>with this philosophy, because they</del> believe that
			unlimited masses of people are meaningles-- and dangerous. What this world needs, they
			explain, are more productive, creative people <del>who are</del> able to <del>contribute
				to our civilization.</del>. These experts are alarmed at this swarming millions of
				<del>unproductive</del>, defective human life <del>that is</del> multiplying with
			such senseless violence. They explain that this is a finite earth. Space is increasingly
			limited. Food resources are becoming alarmingly <del>limited</del>. Must the productive
				<del>people</del> have less to eat in order to feed more and more unproductive
				<del>mouths</del>?We have learned, <del>the experts explain that we must</del> plan
			the size of our families according to our resources, the next step is to plan the number
			of people our countries can support.</p>
		<p>Wiesel: Are there figures to suggest how thst number ?</p>
		<p>Sanger: It takes a 100 acres of tillable land to give meat to nine people once a day....
			100 acres of grazing land to give milk to forty children once a day.... and 100 acres of
			tillable land to give bread or cereal to 280 people once a day. </p>
		<p>Wiesel: The last war then did not diminish the population by much?</p>
		<p>?: There are many more people on this earth now in the last 150 years than there were
			during ALL the <emph>millions</emph> of years that man has lived on this planet... The
			earth is only so big -- there's only so much foodto go around -- only so much soil to
			grow it in. <del>So we have to begin to think about our population
				problem</del>.<del>The</del> millions who were killed in the last war...
				<del>and</del> still the population soared --- while all the time the food to
			support all these people fell off. </p>
		<p> Petch: But, why has this starttling rise in population happened so fast -- and in such a
			short time Mrs. Sanger?</p>
		<p>Petch: <del>And now that doctors can keep us from dying</del> as fast and as young as our
			ancestors used to die, --- <del>you mean</del>, theres nothing to stop people from
			multiplying as a violent rate? </p>
		<p>Sanger: <del>You see</del> wars and germs killed off our ancestors quite effectively --
			so there was a real balance between the number of people <del>who used to be born</del>
			and the number who died to make more room for them.... <del>but wars alone don't hold
				down population</del>. <gap/>
			<del>Mrs. Petch</del> if this rise in population keeps up we are going to increase at
			the frightening rate of 200 million every ten years.... <del>And despite</del>
		</p>
		<p><gap/> Western Europe is sick from the population <del>binge</del> it began a century
			ago. And we're all concerned with the problem of teeming Asia-- wracked by famines,
			constant hunger and disease. Don't forget as we gain more control over the death rate
			through our increasing medical knowledge ---- there will be still more people. There
			just are not resources to give people the food and clothing and shelter they must have.
			And the more people there are -- the less each person can expect to get.</p>
		<p>Petch: But why <del>do you think that</del> most countries are so anxious for a high
			birth rate?</p>
		<p>Sanger: <del>You know Hitler hsd a powerful propaganda machine. I believe without
				realizing it people everywhere have absorbed his doctrine that there is an actual
				connection between numbers and power.</del> Look what happened with the Axis
			nations: they were all explosively over-populated even before World War I. In the 1920's
			serious-minded Japanese and Italian officials tried to apply breaks to their terrific
			rate of growth. But the militants won ouy. They knew that over population made their
			countries ripe for military dictatorship and conquest. Men want to fight <del>for</del>
			bread for their children.</p>
		<p>Petch: And then of course at <del>the very opposite extreme to the Axis we have</del> the
			vastly over-crowded countries like China and India.</p>
		<p>Sanger: Yes --- <del>we've been dreadfully confused on this problem of populations:</del>
			China and India's tremendous birth rates are certainly no sign of strength or
				<del>national virillity</del>. You know Mrs. Petch when I hear people quote ffrom
			the Bible "Be fruitful and multiply"-- I want to remind them of another Biblical saying
			-- "Thou has multiplied the nation, and not increased the joy." That's from Isaiah in
			the 9th chapter, 3rd verse.</p>
		<p>Petch: But, Mrs. Sanger isn't there strength in numbers? And doesn't our national
			security depend on it?</p>
		<p>Sanger: If America's safety depends on numbers we would have beaten at the start of both
			world wars. You know what a decisive factor the United States actually was in modern,
			technological warfare. It is the quality of <del>men</del> that counts. In fact our
			national -- and international security depends on this -- and by quality I mean man's
			intelligence and ingenuity and foresights --- but most of all man's humanity. That is
			what will count in our fight to survive and achieve a stable world peace. We won the
			last war because we had a surplus of good over and above the needs of our own daily
			living. We can win the peace because we have enough goods to keep people fed and clothed
			and housed. Happy, well-fed people <del>are not led</del> by warmongers. They would
			think it a poor bargain to give up their freedom to dictators who promise them bread if
			they have bread - and freedom to eat it in! That's the best combination for peace. </p>
		<p>Wiesel: You speak of an economy of population for the future, may I ask if you think we
			are utilizing the present population as effectively as we could?</p>
		<p>Sanger: No indeed.</p>
		<p>Sanger: Technically trained people are badly needed in many parts of the world. We keep
			saying that in the case of certain skills and professions, a nation will have to wait
			for a whole new crop of babies to grow up before the trained group are availible in
			large enough numbers. I'd like to see an International Placement Bureau -- a labor pool
			of skills and professions. Individuals from this pool could be sent to any part of the
			world where they are needed.</p>
		<p>Petch: But how could you start this Labor Pool of professions and skills?</p>
		<p>Sanger: Just think of all the highly trained men and women wasting away in the Displaced
			Persons Camps! It's criminal to waste people like that. If they could be made availible
			according to their skills, to the countries that need those techniques, it would be one
			way of solving their probem.</p>
		<p>Petch: <del>You know Mrs. Sanger, I've lived a great deal</del> in Scandinavia--
				<del>where</del> your idea has been attempted on a national scale. It's been very
			successful. Those contries are really a small scale model of what you hope to do on a
			world scale, aren't they? </p>
		<p>Sanger: Yes, so far only smal countries with no imperialistic ambitions like the
			Scandinavian lads have attempted this planning of their people.</p>
		<p>Petch: And they certainly have found that it made for happiness and plenty for all their
			citizens. Everyone had a fair share of food and jobs and homes. </p>
		<p>Sanger: When the great powers recognize the truth -- that it's the caliber of people and
			not the quantiy of people that matters, they will begin planning their populations. When
			that day comes, no nation will have more people than it's resources can take care of
			satisfactorily.</p>
		<p>Sanger: There are courageous, farsighted people throughout the world who believe that the
			time has come for less waste in people, <del>Mrs. Petch</del>. They are deeply concerned
			with the swarming millions of unproductive, defective human life that is multiplying
			with such uncontrolled velocity. You see once we <del>stop thinking</del> that numbers
			mean strength we have to change our attitudes. In modern war and in modern peaceful
			society, it takes ability and skill and education to function. Numbers no longer mean
			strength in war or in peace! </p>
		<p><del>Petch: Where are your conference delegates coming from Mrs. Sanger?</del></p>
		<p><unclear/> And while you were helpping to solve their problem the countries that employed
			them would be helped back on their feet. It's an extroidinary idea, Mrs. Sanger.</p>
		<p>Sanger: <del>They have accept Hitler's propaganda that only growing nations are strong,
				and so they think that nations with a stable or a declining population must be "old"
				and on their way out</del>.</p>
		<p><del>Petch: Yes -- I'm afraid a great many of us believe that. But isn't there some truth in
			the idea of a growing nation?</del></p>
		
	</docBody>
</doc>
