<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed draft document">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2012-04-10 AW Initial Tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2012-05-14 CH Proofed tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2012-05-30 AW Corrected tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-10 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1921-00-00"><supplied>1921</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied>League of Nation Speech Notes</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp130859</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Library of Congress, Margaret Sanger Papers</bibl>
            <bibl>Library of Congress Microfilm 20:385</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="BERFR">Bernhardi, Friedrich von</name>
            <name id="DIXAR">Dix, Arthur</name>
            <name id="ALBWI">Wirth, Albrecht</name>
            <name id="FRYDA">Frymann, Daniel</name>
            <name id="GER">German</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>This document was drafted for <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>,
            probably by a secretary. No final version has been found.</p>
        <p>Handwritten corrections and margin notes by Margatret Sanger.</p>
        <index level1="Asia" level2="overpopulation and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="population growth and"/>
        <index level1="League of Nations"/>
        <index level1="overpopulation" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="population" level2="war and"/>
        <index level1="venereal disease"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="health of"/>
        <index level1="working classes" level2="fertility of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head rend="underline">LEAGUE OF NATIONS--PROPOSED PLAN OF ARGUMENT.</head>
        <div>
            <p>(Note: Study of the articles of the Covenant of the <org>League of Nations</org>
                indicates that the subject of Birth Control may be presented to the Council only as
                a matter which (1) affects the peace of the world, and (2) concerns the prevention
                and control of disease. Accordingly the scope of the argument that follows has been
                limited to the questions of population and of public health.)</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <p>The Birth Control Movement affirms:</p>
            <p rend="blockquote">That adjustment of population to the means of subsistence is a
                fundamental requirement of world peace.</p>
            <p rend="blockquote"> That in any large population a low birth rate is a necessary
                condition of social progress.</p>
            <p rend="blockquote">That dissemination of scientific birth control information through
                the medium of clinics by the medical profession is the most logical method of
                checking over-population and of improving the race.<add>use term "control of the
                    birth rate"</add></p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub" rend="underline">Population and War.</head>
            <p>Pressure of population is one of the most potent and compelling factors making for
                    <add>modern</add> war. This fact <del>has been</del>
                <add>is being</add> recognized <del>through the ages</del> by statesmen and military
                leaders. Until the pressure of population is relieved at the danger points, the
                problem of war cannot be settled. The problem is a matter of the life or death of
                civilization. </p>
            <p>The world is astoundingly ignorant of the present rate of population growth. In the
                year 1800 there were less than 850,000,000 people <add>on the globe</add>. Since
                that time the population has more than doubled. Estimates of the annual increase
                range from twelve millions to twenty millions. Assuming an increase of one per cent
                annually, the world’s population, now approximately 1,700,000,000, would be in 1970
                2,796,000,000, in 2021 4,598,000,000, and in another 100 years 12,437,000,000. </p>
            <p>No intelligent student of the subject believes that population will continue
                indefinitely to increase with the rapidity of geometrical ratio, but it requires no
                particular gift of prophecy to see that if the tendency of population remains
                unchecked, we will soon be upon a situation where an unsuccessful struggle for
                decent maintenance will have become the lot of most men throughout the earth, as it
                is their lot now in the most densely populated parts of it. The only possibility
                that anyone suggests that might prevent this otherwise inevitable development is
                some <foreign rend="underline">deus ex machina</foreign> in the form of inventions
                of chemistry that will furnish food for mankind in some altogether unnatural and now
                unknown way. No man of reasonable caution can rely upon this as offering any
                probable solution of the problem. It is altogether probably that it offers no
                prospect whatever for the furnishing of a food supply for the world greatly beyond
                what <emph rend="underline">can</emph> be produced by methods now in use. </p>
            <p>Excluding the arctics, the world’s land area is 33,000,000,000 acres. The
                    <org>International Institute of Agriculture</org> at <place reg="Rome, Italy"
                    >Rome</place> has determined the proportion of cultivated land to total area in
                the most populous countries. On the average it is about 40 per cent. There are
                therefore about 13,000,000,000 acres available for food production. A reasonable
                maximum for the world’s future population is one person for each 2.5 acres on 40 per
                cent of the land area of the globe. This gives a figure of 5,200,000,000. Under the
                most optimistic assumptions as to production and distribution of food that it is
                reasonable to make, the world can support,then, but 5,200,000,000 people, and these
                people must content themselves with the limited dietary and the few material
                necessities which form the current standards among the peasantry of
                    <place>Europe</place>. </p>
            <p>The effect of over-population on a community depends to a great extent on its
                temperament. Where the masses are apathetic, either by nature or by religious
                resignation, they usually die off without protest or struggle, and do not as a rule
                menace surrounding nations. But in proportion as the people are high-spirited and
                rebel against evil conditions, they exert a pressure against other countries, which
                leads to international rivalry and sooner or later to war. </p>
            <p>Such a people so conditioned are always receptive to militaristic propaganda.
                    <place>Germany</place>’s congested multitudes were taught to believe that they
                were surrounded by enemies, that the open spaces of the world had been preempted,
                and that Germany had to expand forcibly in order not to perish. The need of
                territorial expansion to accomodate the rapidly increasing surplus of population was
                put forward by German militarist writers as a justification for war. Their slogan
                was “<q who="BERFR">biological necessity,</q>” and it was accepted as an article of
                faith by the German people.</p>
            <p>General <person reg="Bernhardi, Friedrich von">von Bernhardi</person>, in his book
                entitled “<title type="book">Germany and the Next War</title>,” published in 1911,
                says:</p>
            <p rend="blockquote"><q who="BERFR">Strong, healthy and flourishing nations increase in
                    numbers. They require a continual expansion of their frontiers. They require new
                    territory for the accomodation of their surplus people. Since almost every part
                    of the globe is inhabited, new territory must as a rule be obtained at the cost
                    of its possessors; that is to say by conquest, which thus becomes a law of
                    necessity.</q></p>
            <p><person reg="Dix, Arthur">Arthur Dix</person>, writing in 1901, says:</p>
            <p rend="blockquote"><q who="DIXAR">Because of the German people now increase at the
                    rate of eight hundred thousand inhabitants a year they need both room and
                    nourishment for their surplus.</q></p>
            <p><person reg="Wirth, Albrecht">Albrecht Wirth</person>, writing also in 1901,
                says:</p>
            <p rend="blockquote"><q who="ALBWI">In order to live and lead a healthy and joyous life
                    we need a vast extent of fresh arable land. This is what imperialism must give
                    us.</q></p>
            <p><person reg="Frymann, Daniel">Daniel Frymann</person> in 1911, in his book entitled
                    “<title type="book"><foreign lang="GER">Wenn ich der Kaiser
                    ware</foreign></title>,” which had an enormous circulation, says:</p>
            <p rend="blockquote"><q who="FRYDA">It is no longer proper to say that Germany is
                    satisfied. Our historical development and our economic needs show that we are
                    once more hungry for territory.</q></p>
            <p>The birth rate, in spite of its decline in the last few decades, is still too high in
                every country of Europe, with the possible exception of <place
                    reg="Holland, Netherlands">Holland</place>, to permit of adequate provision for
                all the newcomers. Consequently the death rates continue high and there is a greater
                or less proportion of the population in nearly every country in a state of chronic
                destitution. In eastern nations such as <place>India</place> and
                    <place>China</place>, with their enormous birth rates, the death rates are
                appalling, indicating a constant state of semi-starvation in the great mass of the
                people. </p>
            <p>Asia’s population today is estimated at 900,000,000. In the past the evil of
                ever-population was countered by war, misgovernment, pestilence and famine. During
                the last century, however, most of <place>Asia</place> has come under European
                political control, with consequent diminution of government abuses, decrease of
                disease and lessening of famine. The enormous death rate has fallen to proportions
                comparable to the low death rate of western nations. But the birth rate has been
                maintained, with a startling increase of population. </p>
            <p>Even those Oriental countries which have kept their independence have adopted Western
                life-conserving methods, thereby experiencing accelerated increase of population.
                This is notably true of <place>Japan</place>. </p>
            <p>The population of Japan during the centuries of her isolation remained at a virtually
                constant level. Emerging from her isolation about the middle of the nineteenth
                century, Japan’s population was approximately 56,000,000, showing that it has more
                than doubled in a little over half a century. </p>
            <p>Japan’s total area is less than that of the state of <place>California</place>. Most
                of her territory is mountainous and unfit for cultivation. The density of her
                population is estimated now at 2,688 per square mile -- more than four times the
                density of <place>Belgium</place>, which is Europe’s most thickly populated country. </p>
            <p>As Asia continues to pile up excess people there will be an increasingly prodigious
                outward thrust of surplus Asiatics from congested centers toward countries emptier,
                richer and with higher standards of living, such as <place reg="United States"
                    >America</place>, <place>Australia</place> and <place>Canada</place>. </p>
            <p>Let the situation develop naturally and the only relief for the overpopulation of the
                world lies in wars of the strong against the weak for a place in the sun, in
                pestilence and other great disasters, and in the inevitable increase in the disease
                rate and the death rate that are sequences of the degradation and misery of
                overpopulation.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub" rend="underline">Public Health.</head>
            <p>Physicians generally recognize that, in order to safeguard the health of the
                community, conception should be prevented when either parent is afflicted with a
                transmissible disease, such as tuberculosis, syphilis, serious nervous and mental
                diseases, chronic alcoholism and morphinism. For humanitarian as well as health
                considerations, doctors agree that conception should not take place in the case of
                women suffering from diseases of the lungs or heart, diabetes, chronic kidney
                disease and haemophillia, or if the pelvis is unduly contracted. </p>
            <p>In most countries, however, the law makes it illegal for physicians to instruct their
                patients in contraceptive methods. At the same time, the law recognizes the
                interruption of pregnancy as legal and justifiable in order to save the lives of
                women suffering from tuberculosis, nephritis, cardiac diseases, or from conditions
                whose fatal progress would be hastened through continued pregnancy. It is manifestly
                contrary to every principle of modern preventative medicine that there should be
                interference with the judgment and action of physicians where it seems rational and
                medically sound to give advice as to the methods of preventing a condition
                containing a hazard to life. </p>
            <p>Public health is concerned not only with the prevention and control of disease, but
                ultimately with every factor which contributes to the health of individuals in all
                walks of life. Therefore when it is evident that the health and happiness of the
                intelligent and well-to-do are increased by the practise of limiting the number of
                their offspring, the authorities concerned with the health of the community will see
                the urgency and wisdom of extending the practise to individuals on more modest
                intellectual and economic levels. Among the advantages gained are a higher standard
                of living, the proportionately greater attention received by each child in a small
                family, and the better health of the parents, particularly the mother. </p>
            <p>In order to meet the terrifying economic combination of a large family and a small
                income, the wives of industrial workers often are forced themselves to enter
                industry. Under these circumstances a pregnancy is peculiarly demoralizing. Industry
                has no partiular place for the expectant mother, nor has the pregnant woman any
                particular contribution to make to industry. Even though a good worker, she is at
                best an unstable asset. Her metabolism is profoundly changed and she frequently
                shows an abnormal sensibility to fatigue, which is not diminished by the realization
                of the additional physical and economic burden about the fall upon her shoulders. </p>
            <p> At this point the problem of hyper-fecundity may become directly associated with
                that of venereal disease. In their dread of further pregnancies women, both in
                industrial and non-industrial life, often feel compelled to wink at extra-marital
                sex relations on the part of their husbands. </p>
            <p> It is well known that the rate of infant mortality increases with the size of the
                family. Occasionally there is observed a wealthy and intelligent family where the
                parents, because of unusual vigor and particularly by reason of the physical
                strength of the mother, have been able to rear a large number of children. In some
                instances all have survived and grown up healthy and strong, but these instances are
                rare. On the other hand, large families among the ignorant, poor, underfed and badly
                housed, tuberculous, degenerate, alcoholic and vicious are extremely common. Among
                these the infant mortality is very great. The same holds true of the mortality of
                school children coming from such families. The history of many cases has revealed
                with surprising regularity that the tuberculous individual, if a member of a large
                family, is one of the later born children. The explanation is obvious. When the
                mother is worn out by frequent pregnancies and weakened by work which often
                continues up to the very day of confinement, the child comes into the world with
                impaired vitality, its main inheritance being a physiological poverty which leaves
                it less resistant not only to tuberculosis but to all other diseases of infancy and
                childhood. </p>
            <p> Among the poor the larger the family the more congested are the living quarters, and
                the more unsanitary the environment. The increase of the family heavily taxes the
                earnings of the parents, and as a result malnutrition and insufficient clothing
                enter as factors to predispose the children to tuberculosis or cause a latent
                tuberculosis to become active. The result of this condition in the United States is
                that out of 200,000 persons that die annually of tuberculosis, 50,000 are children.
                It is estimated that 65 per cent of women suffering from tuberculosis, even when
                afflicted only in the relatively early and curable stages, die as a result of
                pregnancy. </p>
            <p> Nearly all of the infectious and communicable diseases are more prevalent in the
                congested precincts of the poor, especially in the overcrowded homes containing
                large families. The propagation of syphilis and gonorrhea by contact infection,
                other than sexual, is usually avoided in the homes of the intelligent and
                well-to-do, but these diseases are almost invariably communicated to the innocent in
                the homes of the ignorant and poor. Gonorrheal infection from parent to child or
                from one infected member of the family to another is responsible, according to
                government statistics, for the 52,272 blind persons in the United States. </p>
            <p> That insanity, idiocy, epilepsy and alcoholic predisposition are often transmitted
                from parent to child is now universally admitted. At least 20 per cent of all
                feeble-minded children are the offspring of drunkards. </p>
            <p> Of the mothers, married and unmarried, who have become chronic invalids or lost
                their lives by resorting to abortive measures to rid themselves of an unwelcome
                child, no statistics are available. Various estimates place the number of abortions
                performed annually in the United States at from 500,000 to 3,000,000. The reason
                abortion is practised on such an enormous scale in the United States is because of
                laws prohibiting not only the manufacture and sale of contraceptives but even the
                dissemination of any information concerning them. Contraception as a rule is
                practised only by intelligent persons in easy circumstances. the poor, lacking
                information on the subject, resort to abortion. </p>
            <p> No great clearsightedness is necessary to perceive that the great masses of
                ignorant, thoughtless, stupid and vicious people, the offspring of families
                impoverished by too many children, are as injurious to the community as they are
                harmful to themselves. </p>
            <p> It has taken Nature unknown millions of years of painful struggle to evolve Man, and
                to raise the human species above that helpless bondage to reproduction which marks
                the lower animals. But the health of nations and their standard of intelligence are
                still at the mercy of accidental multitudes born into a life in which they are
                hopelessly superfluous. No single reform, capable of such immediate and widespread
                application, would add so greatly to the well-being and happiness of the human race
                as that of intelligent limitation of offspring. Birth Control, properly established,
                would go further to eliminate poverty, sickness, insanity, crime and war than any
                other remedy proposed.</p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
