<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Interview">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2011/05/23 CE</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2011/06/21 CE Corrections</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-03-18 CH clean regs</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1928-09-28">28 Sept 1928</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>Minute Interviews with Noted Women</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp140848</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="journal">Unknown newspaper</title>, Sept. 28, 1928</bibl>
			<bibl>Library of Congress Microfilm, 57:189A.</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name/>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP"><p>The clipping was found in a scrapbook with no newspaper identified. It may have been published in San Francisco.</p>
		<index level1="birth control"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="economic benefits and risks of"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits and risks"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"/>
		<index level1="child spacing"/>
		<index level1="family planning"/>
		<index level1="women" level2="health of"/>
		<index level1="women" level2="maternal feelings"/>
		<index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
		<index level1="working classes" level2="birth control and"/>
		<index level1="working classes" level2="living conditions of"/>
		<index level1="working classes" level2="women and girls"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>MINUTE INTERVIEWS WITH NOTED WOMEN.</head>
		<byline>
			<ital>By <org reg="Newspaper Enterprise Associates">NEA</org> Service</ital>
		</byline>
		<p>Healthier mothers, better-cared-for children, and happier marriages are benefits that
			would accrue from a universal knowledge of birth control, according to Dr. <person
				reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>.</p>
		<p>“The idea of birth control coming to the poverty-stricken mother is the most important
			factor in her overworked life. When her babies come too close together in the years of
			her young motherhood, she is not able to get her full strength.</p>
		<p>“She cannot give them the proper care and attention her heart longs to give.</p>
		<p>“If she has three years at least between the births of children, life will be different
			for her and her babies. She should be well and strong and normal psychologically--fully
			recovered from the strain of bearing one child before she has another.</p>
		<p>“Finances also should be considered before the family is increased. There should be money
			enough in the bank to carry them all through any emergency that might occur.</p>
		<p>“Increasing the family should be a voluntary thing because the children that arrive that
			way are wanted children for whom preparation has been made and for whom the family
			budget and family health provide.”</p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
