<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>07/28/2003 SR Initial Tag</prepDate>
		<prepDate>08/06/2003 CH Proofed Tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>05/08/2012 AW Corrected Tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-04-09 CH clean regs</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-21 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1923-10-29">29 Oct 1923</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>Address of Welcome to the Middle Western States Birth Control
				Conference</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp143237</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
			<bibl>Library of Congress Microfilm 122:9</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
			<name id="SCHTH">Schroeder, Theodore</name>
			<name id="FREJO">Freschi, John J. </name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>With this address, Sanger opened the <org>Middle Western States Birth Control
				Conference</org>, held in <place reg="Chicago, IL">Chicago</place> at the <org>Drake
				Hotel</org>. Additions were made by Margaret Sanger by hand. The chair of the
			meeting was Horace Bridges.</p>
		<index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="biography"/>
		<index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="speaking tour, 1922 (Japan)"/>
		<index level1="birth control movement" level2="history of"/>
		<index level1="birth control movement" level2="goals and strategies"/>
		<index level1="women" level2="enslavement of"/>
		<index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
		<index level1="Woman Rebel, The"/>
		<index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Comstock  Laws"/>
		<index level1="Brownsville Clinic"/>
		<index level1="birth control clinics and leagues"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Address of Welcome</head>
		<byline>MRS MARGARET SANGER</byline>
		<p>Mr. Chairman, Ladies and Gentlemen: It is my pleasant duty to express a cordial welcome
			on behalf of the <org>American Birth Control League</org> to you all, and especially to
			the delegates, the friends and others who have come from the various cities to attend
			this conference and to assist us by their counsel, wisdom and experience. I also want to
			take this opportunity to thank the Chairman, Mr. <person reg="Bridges, Horace">Horace
				Bridges</person>, and I must say that I have never heard an address given so
			briefly, so exquisitely, so beautifully, and covering the subject so comprehensively as
			he has done in his few minutes of introduction. I wish there were more people who could
			hear him.</p>
		<p>Great and significant events have occurred in the world since the first Birth Control
			League was formed in the <place reg="United States">United States</place> something less
			than ten years ago. I have been asked by friends recently coming to the movement, and by
			some friends who have long been in the movement, to tell you to night something of the
			vicissitudes, something of the early struggles, something of the barrier, that we have
			had to fight in order to bring this subject of Birth Control before the American people
			for discussion, and it seems to me that this might be a fitting occasion to do this,
			because tomorrow and the next day the various sessions of this conference shall be
			devoted to the discussion of the subject from various angles. There shall be
			presentation of papers by some of the most distinguished men and women in the country.
			So that it seems to me that I might take you with me, if you will bear with me and be
			tolerant of the pronoun "I", which must be interjected into the details of this
			evening's discourse.</p>
		<p>It is a well-known historical fact that the idea of Birth Control is as old as history
			itself. Far back through the ages, through the various stages of barbarism, savagery,
			and even in civilization, there has always been an attempt on the part of man to control
			the size of his family, to control the number of people in the clan, in his tribe. The
			methods that were used were not those that we wish to tolerate today. These were the
			methods of infanticide, the abandonment of children, the killing of babies, and
			foetuscide. Civilization as we know it today does not believe in those methods of
			controlling the population, and at the same time civilization does not supplant an
			alternative which makes these conditions and these methods necessary.</p>
		<p>The only means that have been used today are agencies that are legislative and
			ameliorative. These agencies have been established for the purpose of reducing the
			misery, the unhappiness and the squalor, the disease, that is here with us. But I do not
			believe that either of these agencies are effective in producing or bringing about the
			most desired results. I believe that only through birth control, or the knowledge of how
			to prevent conception, can the most effective measures be brought about. For birth
			control is the key to the greatest of human problems, the problem of reconciling
			humanitarianism with greatest improvement.</p>
		<p>Today we know that this great, fine impulse of humanitarianism brings about a dysgenic
			effect, where, with the application of birth control, it could produce a eugenic effect.
			These measures, both legislative and ameliorative, or rather these agencies, could be
			brought about and made of great use in the country and in the world, if there was
			accompanied with them, going hand in hand, information to control birth, and it would
			make the multiplication of the unfit and of the diseased cease.</p>
		<p>When we look out upon the world today, we must recognize that there is already the
			practice of birth control going on among us. It is as <person reg="Dawson, Bertrand"
				>Lord Dawson</person> said in the <place reg="London, England">London</place>
			conference, birth control is here to stay, and I say the only trouble with it is that it
			is not practiced far enough. It is only practiced by one group in society, the group
			that we must call the small family group. The other group, the large family group, has
			not the benefit of this knowledge.</p>
		<p>Up to 1912, when I first came into this work, there had been no group, and to my
			knowledge no individual, who had attempted to bring this idea of family limitation into
			the large family group, or to interest or advise its practice there. We know for the
			last quarter of a century that the small family group has been perpetuating itself, but
			also in that group we find conditions that we all approve of. We find there health,
			wealth, comfort, leisure, possibilities of development. We find in that group, while
			there are only a few children, two, three or four, these are the children that get the
			best care, that are usually brought through to maturity, and are given the advantages of
			state and of society. These are the children who eventually fill the universities and
			the colleges, and it is from this group that every one is clamouring that they should
			produce more of their children.</p>
		<p>And, on the other hand, the large family group has also perpetuated its conditions. It
			perpetuates from generation unto generation its misery, its ignorance, its poverty, its
			disease. For there we see all of the problems that we have got today. We see the problem
			of <del>daily</del>
			<add>child</add> labor, we see the problem of slums, we see our infant mortality,
			maternal mortality, we see practically every condition that we are trying to ameliorate,
			that we are trying to legislate against, there snuggled closely in that group and
			perpetuating themselves continually.</p>
		<p>There is another condition there that to me is very serious, and that is that the women,
			the mothers, in one group do not wish to have the large families that are forced upon
			them. I found that they did not want to have more children than they could take care of,
			any more than the women, the mothers, in the small family group. But because of
			ignorance, because of the lack of knowledge, they had to resign themselves to either one
			thing or the other, that is, to having children as fast as nature sends them, or to
			resort to illegal operations. I found, especially in my work as a trained nurse, that
			this condition was very prevalent. I found it was so prevalent that it was almost
			abhorrent, and yet the women would come to me and say "<q who="UNK">What else can one
				do?</q>"</p>
		<p>I happen to be born of a large family. I happen to be one of that large family group. My
			own parents had eleven living children, so I knew something from the beginning of all
			the problems that are constantly there perpetuating themselves with large families. I
			lived in a <place reg="Corning, NY">small factory town</place>, and there I saw
			constantly girls and boys who came of my age, sometimes younger, year after year leave
			school and have to take their place beside their father in the factory. Always behind it
			was another baby that came into the family to force the older one out to compete with
			his father for his daily bread.</p>
		<p>I had a very peculiar childhood, because I came from parents who were Irish, and
			sometimes I think it is a very great burden to be given, <person
				reg="Higgins, Anne Purcell">two Irish parents</person> (Laughter). Someway we are
			always wanting to change <del>them</del>
			<add>things</add>. We never are quite satisfied with things as they are. My <person
				reg="Higgins, Michael">father</person> was a great philosopher. He was a poet. He
			had the possibilities of a sculptor. And there was one thing that he taught his
			children, and that was to be true to themselves, to think their own thoughts, to pray
			their own prayers to their own <name type="deity">God</name>. And last, to give back to
			society the benefit of your experience as you live in life. He also told us again and
			again that the object of life was to hold fast to a dream, to get a dream and then make
			that dream come true. With this peculiar kind of a philosophy, this strange kind of a
			religion, I was launched out upon the world to compete for my daily experience.</p>
		<p>And so, after several years of nursing, after I had finished training, I found myself
			applying some of my father's philosophy to my life work. It was very difficult for
			anyone to live among the working people, to see their agony, to see their misery, to see
			their unhappiness, and not to try to apply something to help them remove it.</p>
		<p>I found women in almost every walk of life, I saw them go through agony, needless agony,
			to bring forth dead children. I saw them go through that agony, and they were glad and
			said "<q who="UNK">Thank God</q>" when they were told that their baby was born dead. And
			when you look about you and use your reason you realize that they were right. This
			mother instinct knew in the first place that she had no moral right to have children
			that she could not take care of. Again and again these women said to me "<q who="UNK"
				>Why should I bring a child into the world when those I have already cannot be
				fed?</q>" And then sometimes they grew rebellious with me, a social worker, and
			others who came to them, and they said "<q who="UNK">If you would tell us what you tell
				the rich women, we would be much happier.</q>" (Applause)</p>
		<p>It was impossible to go on, year in and year out, without coming to some conclusion about
			these conditions. It was impossible for me to keep on going back and seeing these women
			and finding what they were doing, and not be able to help them. And I shall never forget
			the case that I had last. Some of you may have heard this before, but I am going to tell
			it to you again. That was the last case I ever took in the nursing world, and I think
			the last I ever shall take.</p>
		<p>It was the case of a woman, who was a <person reg="Sachs, Sadie">young woman</person>, a
			little over thirty years old; her husband was thirty-two. They were a kind and loving
			couple and devoted to the three children, ages five, three, and one and one-half. They
			lived in the congested quarter of <place reg="New York, NY">New York</place>, and lived
			in two small rooms. The father at that time was earning Twelve Dollars and a Half a
			week, which was a small wage even for those days. And this mother had repeatedly said to
			her friends, to neighbors and others who had come to her, that it would be impossible
			for her to get on if she had to have an increase in her family. And so when I was called
			to her to look after her it was to rescue her out of a death bed. She had attempted to
			perform an operation upon herself, and when I was called in it was a case of septicemia.
			We had a very great struggle, the doctor and I, to bring this woman back to life, and
			again and again neither of us thought it was possible. I remember of going eighty hours
			without a wink of sleep, until the crisis was past. I slept partly on the floor, near
			this woman, so that she would not be disturbed, and so I could keep track of her
			pulse.</p>
		<p>And then finally it was over and we had won the victory, and every one was glad. The
			neighborhood rejoiced, and the day came when both the doctor and myself were dismissed.
			But when we were going before we went, this woman, sitting there with her children, her
			face pale and haggard and very much worried, had something on her heart and something on
			her mind, <del>and she</del>
			<add>had something to say but</add> did not know how to say it. But finally the <person
				reg="Unknown">Doctor</person>, who was very cheerful, very grateful to himself that
			he had brought this woman out of the valley of death, said to her "<q who="UNK">There is
				one thing you cannot do, and that is to get into this condition again.</q>" And she
			said "<q who="UNK">Yes, I know it, but Doctor, what am I going to do?</q>" <q who="UNK"
				>What are you going to tell me so that I will not get that way again?</q>" And then
			the doctor patted her on the back and tried to make the best of it, but nevertheless he
			went away without telling her what to do. And then she turned to me and said "<q
				who="UNK">Oh, you are a woman, you have children, you know, you understand. Surely
				you will tell me what to do.</q>" And I too, although I had been a trained nurse, I
			must confess that I was very ignorant, I had no idea what to tell this woman or how to
			make it understandable. And so I followed the doctor's attitude. I closed the door and
			left that woman there to her misery and to her fate.</p>
		<p>Oh, I wonder if any of you have ever been haunted, haunted by a face, haunted by remorse!
			And as I went on in my work for the next two or three months, this woman's face would
			come before me as I sat down quietly to read, or when I was unoccupied by other duties.
			And then it was only a few months later that I was called again to the telephone, and
			this anxious husband begged me to come as quickly as possible, that his wife was very
			ill. And back I went, only to find that we were both too late, this poor little woman
			had again become pregnant and had again resorted to one of the cheap doctors in her
			neighborhood, and this time she could not make the fight. This time she lost. And then I
			came there and I saw what really had happened. I saw a bed, these children being torn
			away to orphan homes, I saw this poor, frantic young <person reg="Sachs, Jake"
				>father</person>, who was just as innocent, just as ignorant as she was, and just as
			helpless. I saw that whole condition, and from that I saw the whole panorama of our
			social life today, and I went home and I knew then, though that woman had died, that in
			her death she had given birth to a new idea that was going to free other women from such
			hardship. (Applause)</p>
		<p>Now, it is all very well to have an idea, but the thing is, how to get that idea over to
			the people. In the first place, there was nothing that you could call it. I hadn't any
			knowledge that there was such a <del>lead</del>
			<add>League</add>, or that this idea had been already formed into <del>leads</del>
			<add>League</add>, and that it was being carried on as an educational work in other
			countries. But it was a most important thing for us or for me to find some
				<add>[name]</add>or handle that could be used for this instrument to free
				<del>womanhood</del>
			<add>womankind from maternal bondage.</add></p>
		<p>Now, I found a little later that his idea in <place>England</place> was called
			"Neo-Malthusianism." That didn't seem so easy. In <place>France</place> I found it was
			called "Conscious generation," in <place>Germany</place> and in <place reg="Netherlands"
				>Holland</place> it was called "New Generation," but none of these seemed to be
			words or names that would convey to an American headline public an idea rapidly.</p>
		<p> So the first thing that it was necessary to do was to get a name, and to get a name that
			would speak for itself. <del>Now, that is not easy, because here we were, generations
				before me, and this thought had never been concentrated.</del> For months and months
			I concentrated on what this should be called, how you could call out to the people and
			tell them what was happening, how you could convey the idea in <del>an item of</del> a
			few words to the public. <del>Because</del> I felt that it was absolutely necessary to
			call out from the housetops to the American people what I knew, what I saw and what I
			believed. And then one evening I gathered a few people together, just a little group of
			men and women who were with me, who were interested in doing something to help get this
			thought over. It was not by any means an easy thing to do, although our friends all
			agreed that something should be done.</p>
		<p>It is not always so easy to do the thing that is before us. But after an evening's
			conversation, after juggling with words, after taking an inventory of everyone's
			vocabulary, it came like a flash out of the nowhere into the here, the words "Birth
			Control." They came like lightening, as a bugler of the dawn, they came as a battle
			cry.</p>
		<p>Now, to me, the idea in the words "birth control" were the best that had been conceived,
			because as our chairman said, it meant control, not limitation. When you say
			"limitation" that narrows the idea, but "control" is a far bigger word, and I have never
			been able to understand what the prejudice is against the word. I often think I would
			like to have those persons who dislike the word psychoanalyzed and see what is the
			matter with them.</p>
		<p>At any rate it was one thing, and it seemed to me that was victory <del>won</del>
			<add>one</add>, to get a name that would convey your thought, <del>a victory won</del>.
			But that was not, oh, half the battle. In the first place, having resolved to give up my
			work, it was not an easy matter to try to interest others to give money and
				<del>half</del>
			<add>help</add> financially and morally to put over an idea that was so new. It was not
			at all easy to do that. I went to ten of the most prominent women in <place
				reg="New York, NY">New York</place>, and asked them if they would go on record with
			me to write a booklet or a pamphlet giving out this thought, and conveying the idea in
			simple English to the American public.</p>
		<p>Would you believe I could not find one woman in New York City who would do it? The answer
			came back "<q who="UNK">Wait until we get the vote.</q>" Wait, wait, wait. Nobody said
			"do," everybody said "don't." Again, I asked different people if they wouldn't give
			something toward getting out a publication, and again my heart was filled with hope by
				<person reg="Schroeder, Theodore">an attorney</person> who wrote and said he would
			come to see me. He was very much interested in free speech, and he believed that I had
			struck at the root of a great many of our social problems, and consequently he and I
			arranged for a meeting, where I thought, as he had a certain financial backing, it might
			be possible to make s hort day of this. When I met him he went over the pros and cons of
			the matter with me, and he said "<q who="SCHTH">Do you understand and realize that there
				are laws against conveying this idea to the public?</q></p>
		<p>Well, this was quite new to me. I said "Laws!" He said "<q who="SCHTH">Yes, there are
				laws in practically every state in the <place reg="United States">Union</place>, as
				well as Federal laws.</q>" He said, "<q who="SCHTH">Do you know that this means
				jail, means prosecution?</q>" Well, that didn't sound very well. But before the
			evening was over I still wanted to go on with this work. And as strongly as he argued,
			as vivid a picture as was presented, I still felt that something within one that drives
			you on and makes you go, and it was impossible to give up the idea. So finally the
			lawyer looked at me, very seriously, and he said "<q who="SCHTH">I will back you with
				the publication if you will do something for me first?</q>" I asked him what it was.
			He said "<q who="SCHTH">If you will stay for six months and by psycho-analyzed, I will
				stand behind you.</q>" My kind old father, who had been so anxious for me, in my
			youth, to have <add>a dream</add> and make that dream come true, came on a visit to New
			York, the first in forty years, to take me home to put me in a retreat where I could
			rest from some shock he was sure I must have had.</p>
		<p>So it was that one had to fight every step of the way. There were no friends, there was
			no one to help, there was no one to say "do." So I sold the little home I had, where my
			children played, and I sent them on to a small boarding school, and I took the money and
			I decided to study this subject from every angle before I launched a national campaign.
			I went to <place>Europe</place>, I went to England, to France, to Holland, to
				<place>Spain</place>, and I studied in the <org>British Museum</org> from the time
			the gates opened, which was 9:00 o'clock, until 7:00 o'clock at night, for more than
			eight hours. I went to Holland and took a course of instruction. I went to Spain to see
			what they were doing there. I went to France, and studied this subject from away back to
			the time of <person reg="Bonaparte, Napoleon">Napoleon</person>.</p>
		<p>So I came back equipped, not only with information but also with such distinguished men
			behind me as <person reg="Wells, H. G.">H. G. Wells</person>, <person
				reg="Bennett, Arnold">Arnold Bennett</person>, <person reg="Ellis, Havelock"
				>Havelock Ellis</person>, and others. And then I was amused to find that with those
			names behind one it was not half so difficult to find some American women who would go
			on record with <del>one</del>
			<add>you</add>.</p>
		<p>My first attempt at a publication was to discuss the theory of the subject. Yet only just
			to talk about the subject in a theoretical way seemed to offend the government, and with
			nine small publications, each of them was confiscated and each of them meant an
			indictment. Now, at the Federal Court it means five years imprisonment with every
			indictment, if you are convicted, so by the time I was through saying what I had to say
			in even a small way, 45 years in the penitentiary hung over me.</p>
		<p>Then again began a great deal of agitation to get the American public to see what one was
			trying to do to enlighten them with the facts, and I am glad to say it was only a very
			short time when the <org reg="United States Government">Federal government</org>
			dismissed the whole nine cases, because as a matter of fact they had nothing that was
			illegal in those indictments. It was simply that they were afraid of the words and
			hadn't themselves known the law.</p>
		<p>Now, with 45 years of imprisonment wiped off the slate, you would think that one would go
			back into <del>the</del>
			<add>your</add> maternal corner and stay there. But having been to Holland I realized
			now as I had never realized before that all the discussion and talking, and all the
			pamphleteering and the publications I could get to the people were not going to help the
			women that I wanted to help. Many of those women could not read a pamphlet or a book, so
			that no matter what I did to get the Federal law changed, there were those <add>poor
				weary ignorant</add> women that would not benefit by <del>that change</del>
			<add>that change of that law</add>.</p>
		<p>Those women wanted someone to talk to. They had to be instructed personally. They had to
			be taught. And I knew that many of them could not read, thousands of them could not read
			English, and it takes <del>too high</del> an intelligence to follow <add>printed</add>
			plans and directions, <del>and I knew that was not the way for me to work</del>
			<add>while oral instruction is far simpler</add>. So, having found clinics established
			in Holland, I decided that the thing was to show the government, and especially the
			government of <place>New York</place> State, and the courts, that the establishment of a
			clinic was the proper way to disseminate this information, and <del>have</del>
			<add>give</add> it there privately where women may come <add>for instruction.</add></p>
		<p>And so I established a <org reg="Brownsville Clinic">clinic</org> in the District of
				<place reg="Brooklyn, NY">Brownsville, Brooklyn</place>, in the midst of a very
			thickly populated section. It was there where the infant mortality was highest, and it
			was there where the greatest amount of money was spent for charity. It was only a short
			time that this little clinic was allowed to stay, about ten days, but within that ten
			days, 488 women came and applied and were personally instructed in means to prevent
			conception.</p>
		<p>We had to have <del>that interpreted </del>
			<add>an <person reg="Mindell, Fania">interpreter</person></add>, and we also had to have
			a trained <person reg="Byrne, Ethel Higgins">nurse</person>, <del>and yet this did not
				suffice</del>. There were baby carriages and women in line for nearly two blocks
			around this little place. We took their records, we took their names, we took
				<del>record of</del> the wages that their husbands made, the number of children they
			had already had, the number of miscarriages.</p>
		<p>We had facts and data that, when they came before the court, made a profound impression
			upon the judges, and one of the judges refused to come up the next day to try the case,
			he was so impressed. Nevertheless, the law was the law, and that was a distinct
			challenge to the law. This was done openly and knowingly. One of the <person
				reg="Freschi, John J.">judges</person> said "<q who="FREJO">If you will promise not
				to go on with this work, your case may be dismissed. We want you to obey this law,
				and if you will promise this there will be no further prosecution.</q> I said in
			reply that it was impossible for me, knowing the suffering that I knew of, to respect
			such a law. It was impossible. (Applause) And so thirty days in jail was not very much
			for the satisfaction of helping 488 women. And many of those women have come to us since
			and told how much this has meant in their lives.</p>
		<p>In one case there came to us a woman whose husband was about to leave her. She had grown
			cold and indifferent. She was afraid of him, she was afraid of his caress, afraid of his
			touch. She felt that something was going to happen to break up that little family.
			Someone read in the paper that there was such a place <add>as the clinic and</add> sent
			her there, and she came to us for help. Three years later she returned, her arm locked
			in that of her husband, on their way to the moving pictures, and they said that they had
			never been so happy, that their home life was happy, they had had no more children, and
			they felt that they owed a great deal of their happiness to the establishment of that
			little clinic.</p>
		<p>From 1914 to 1917 were three years of constant agitation. Those of us who sat down to
			think out this campaign decided that there were four stages through which to pass, four
			courses to pursue: Agitation, education, organization and legislation. Those were four
				<unclear resp="MSPP">epics</unclear> or four periods that we must pursue.</p>
		<p>So those first years, with agitation, it meant imprisonment, jail, hunger strikes, it
			meant meetings being stopped, it meant everything that was disagreeable, most
			disagreeable. And then we began, from 1917 to 1922, a course of education. We had been
			able to have some books and pamphlets reprinted. We established a magazine to carry
			forth this message, and it jumped from 2,000 the first year to 10,000 within two years.
			This has conveyed the message for our association or our league. We have since that time
			created practically a literature in the United States. I do not mean that we personally
			have done it, but I mean the agitation and the thought going out has brought back to us
			an entirely new literature which was not in existence when we began in 1914.</p>
		<p>From 1922 to 1925 is to be a special time for organization. Just a few years ago, after
			that <org reg="Birth Control League of America">first little league</org> had broken up
			on account of the war, we again formed another league, which <del>was</del>
			<add>is</add> a national league with its headquarters in New York City. From that we
			have gone out and organized similar leagues all over the world. We have a branch league
			in <place>Canada</place>, another in <place>Mexico</place>, another in <place
				reg="Honolulu, HI">Honolulu</place>, two in <place>Japan</place>, two in
				<place>China</place>, and there are also similar leagues and organizations in
			practically every country in Europe, although <add>some of</add> those were in existence
			before we began this work.</p>
		<p>Perhaps the greatest victory that I have been able to see was the invitation to go to
			Japan and to bring the message of Birth Control to the Japanese people. It seemed to me
			that that was indeed part of the dream coming true, because those who oppose this idea
			almost always say "<q who="UNK">If the white race practices birth control, and the
				yellow race does not, it is going to mean the wiping out of our civilization.</q>"
			So I was overjoyed when I received an invitation from a group called "<org>Kaizo</org>",
			which means "Reconstruction" <del>"Group"</del>, similar you might say to our <title
				type="journal">New Republic</title> group in America. They asked me to come to Japan
			and deliver four lectures on the subject of "War and Population."</p>
		<p>I of course was delighted to do so. When I heard that I had been preceded by <person
				reg="Russell, Bertrand">Bertrand Russell</person>, and that I was to be followed by
			such distinguished persons as <person reg="Einstein, Albert">Einstein</person> and H. G.
			Wells, I felt greatly flattered that I was to go into such good company.</p>
		<p>Everything seemed to go very well until I got to <place reg="San Francisco, CA">San
				Francisco</place>. When I reached San Francisco and applied for a visa to my
			passport, I was told most courteously by the <org reg="Japanese Consulate">Japanese
				Counsel</org> that that morning he had received a cable from his home office saying
			that if Mrs. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger</person>, the birth control advocate,
			applied for a passage to Japan, that it was to be refused her. So then I asked if it
			were possible to go without delivering the lectures, and he cabled back, and back again
			came the world "<q who="UNK">No.</q>" So it seemed for a time as if it were impossible
			to get into Japan.</p>
		<p>I heard, however, that the boat I was going on was sailing also to China, and that on
			that boat were more than 150 representatives from the <org
				reg="Washington Naval Conference">Peace Conference</org> at Washington. These were
			some of the most distinguished men of Japan. It seemed to me that it was absolutely
			necessary to get into Japan, and at the same time to get onto that boat with these
			delegates. So I booked my passage, not for Japan, but for China, and I was only on board
			a few days when the Japanese Group came to me and asked if I would speak to them in the
			first class passage or saloon. I of course was delighted to do this, and immediately
			after this address had been given, <person reg="Hanohawa, Mr.">Mr. Hanohawa</person>,
			who is now the Japanese representative in this country, cabled to his home office,
			saying that he had heard this address, and he believed that the Japanese Government
			would be making a very great mistake if it did not raise the ban <del>over it
				doors</del>, and also <del>if it did not</del> listen attentively to the message
			that was to be given. (applause)</p>
		<p>I will not attempt to tell you all the pros and cons, and the difficulties that awaited
			me in Japan, but needless to say, after a great deal of questioning by the authorities
			who came out to meet me, I was finally allowed to enter Japan, and I was also allowed to
			give thirteen lectures while I was there. There was only one other person who was better
			known in Japan, who was an outsider, and that was the <person
				reg="Edward, Prince of Wales">Prince of Wales</person>.</p>
		<p>Every paper throughout the entire Empire was filled with something about birth control.
			That does not mean that everyone agreed with the idea. Not at all. But nevertheless
			there was such a fine, liberal group there--that to me is the hope of Japan--that they
			insisted upon making it possible for one to say one's say. And also out of the 101
			magazines that came out the 1st of April, 88 of these magazines carried a principal
			article on the population question. <del>So that</del> It is said that <del>while</del>
			98 per cent of the population of Japan are <del>il</del>literate,
				<del>nevertheless</del>
			<add>and</add> 95 per cent of the people know something today about birth control.</p>
		<p>We also formed leagues there, and before the disaster the work was going on very
			beautifully. The same with China, although there was not the same opposition. In China
			the students from the <org reg="Peking University">Government University</org>
			<del>begged</del>
			<add>requested</add> me to address them. And the interesting thing to me was the
			difference in the two languages. In Japan, one had to stand three hours to deliver a one
			hour address. In China, you stood a half an hour to deliver an hour's address, on
			account of the different of languages.</p>
		<p>Naturally, I was nearly exhausted and worn out when I left Japan, but in China they
			gathered together a large student body of 2500 persons, mostly men, as there were very
			few women <add>students</add> in <del>China</del>
			<place reg="Peking, China">Pekin</place> attending the university. Later on in the
			evening the chancellor of the university held a meeting at his home, where there were
			some of the distinguished professors of Pekin, and that night before we left an
			organization was formed, and a little pamphlet, called "<title type="book">Family
				Limitation</title>", that some of you might have heard of, was <del>written</del>
			<add>read</add>. Some of them stayed up that night and translated it into Chinese, and
			the next morning it was on the press, and five thousand of these pamphlets were being
			distributed among the men and women of China. That shows quick action. It shows how an
			idea goes, is taken, and <del><gap reason="illegible" extent="one word"/></del>
			<add>quickly</add>
			<del>act</del>
			<add>acted</add> upon <del>it so quickly</del>.</p>
		<p>From China I went to London to attend the <org
				reg="International Neo-Malthusian and Birth Control Conference, 5th">International
				Conference</org>, and there it was indeed a most inspiring occasion, because there
			were delegates there from every country in Europe. There were such men as Lord Dawson
			and Sir <del>William Archer</del>
			<add><person reg="Lane, William Arbuthnot">Arbuthnot Lane</person></add> attended the
			conference, and H. G. Wells held a reception for the delegates at his home, and we were
			all inspired and encouraged to go back to our various countries and to carry forth the
			message in unison with those who were holding the conference in London.</p>
		<p>By the way, at that conference we invited the next international conference to assemble
			in the United States in 1925, and while <place reg="Portland, OR">Portland,
				Oregon</place> has been chosen as the place, some still believe that San Francisco
			might be a better place. Already delegates from China, <place>India</place>,
				<place>Norway</place>, <place>Sweden</place>, and from many other countries are
			planning and preparing to attend.</p>
		<p>Now, in conclusion I want to say that these have been disturbing times. I think, if the
			war had not been on, that this work would have been for ahead of any other movement in
			the United States. As it is, we are gaining headway constantly. We had made a tremendous
			change in public opinion, even in the last three or four years, and we have here at this
			conference represented many welfare organizations; but I am quite certain that there
			could be a great improvement among the welfare organizations, as far as this idea is
			concerned.</p>
		<p>Again, we have the medical profession that still must be educated. (Applause) But from
			the requests that have been sent in to attend the medical conference tomorrow night it
			sounds encouraging, because there are more than six hundred requests for medical men and
			women to come and attend the conference tomorrow night, where we will have discussed the
			methods of contraception. That will be discussed tomorrow night, <del>and our</del>
			<add>the</add> audience is limited to the medical profession <del>only</del>.</p>
		<p>It is, after all, to the medical profession that we must look for the greatest benefit to
			this work, because when it comes right down to it, it is a question of technique,
			contraception technique. We cannot really bring about the best results with this idea or
			with this work until the medical profession are ahead of us, as we have been ahead of
			them in the past. The idea and the education of the public is far beyond the medical
			profession's work today. By that I mean we are ready for birth control, and they are not
			ready to give us what would make birth control practicable.</p>
		<p>The only opposition that is left is the religious opposition. That is opposition that we
			get here and there individually, but really we have broken down the great barriers of
			opposition, with the exception of official religious bodies. The people themselves are
			really with us.</p>
		<p>Now, it may surprise you to hear me say that, but I want to tell you that at a <org
				reg="Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau">research clinic</org> that was
			established in New York, we have a proportion like this: Thirteen Protestant women,
			Twelve Catholic women, Eleven Jewish women, who come to us constantly for advice. Now,
			this shows you that that is an idea that is going to stand, in spirt of race, color or
			creed. (Applause)</p>
		<p>And I think what Lord Dawson said is very applicable to the church. He said at this
			London conference, he asked the church to approach this question of birth control in the
			light of modern knowledge and the needs of a new world, unhampered by traditions that
			have outgrown their usefulness. I think that could be applied to practically all
			opposition today.</p>
		<p> Now, friends, why are we here? Why are we holding this conference? We are holding it
			because we are asking your help, just as women for the past ten years have been
			appealing to me, so we come out here and appeal to you. I have had from the 1st of
			January to the 1st of October 58,432 letters addressed to me personally from women
			asking for information. Think of it! Twenty per cent of those women come from the State
			of <place>Illinois</place>. Now, to me that is a sign of intelligence, high
			intelligence, because only a woman who is intelligent and who is rising out of the
			lowest depths of degradation and poverty and misery, who has the conscious
			responsibility of controlling her offspring, will inquire.</p>
		<p>Shall we not answer that call? Shall we thrust that woman back into degradation when she
			is asking for help to get out of it? I think not. I think you will agree with me that
			she should be helped, and that every hand in this state should be reached out to help
			her help herself, because that is what she wants. These women ask in these letters for
			health, for just a little time to space their children; they ask for a little time so
			they can gain, as they say, their real strength.</p>
		<p>Some of them say they have never known what it is to have one night's sleep from the
			night they were married until the present day. Some of them call out and say, "<q
				who="UNK">My husband is leaving me, because I cannot endure his presence or the
				sight of him while this fear of pregnancy hangs over me.</q>" Some of them say they
			have never had a new dress; old clothes, old shoes, old things have been passed on to
			them from others. Some of them say they have not been to the neighbor's house in five
			years, that is only a half-mile away. They tell of the drudgery, of the enslavement that
			they endure, and in reading those letters I am convinced that these women are enduring a
			slavery that the black race of this country never endured. </p>
		<p>You feel, when you finish reading those letters, that you are almost broken. And do you
			know, it does break us. We have to keep on changing, because of course I cannot possible
			read all these letters. No human being could. My desk is piled high, in various groups,
			some of one thing and some of another.</p>
		<p>And do you know that we have had girls in that office who have broken down mentally and
			physically just from reading those letters? One girl, 26 or 27 years old, came out to
			Chicago. She couldn't endure it any more. Perhaps she is here tonight. She is working
			now with the soldiers who have come back from war maimed and broken. She wrote back to
			one of the co-workers in our office and she said: "<q who="UNK">As bad as this work is,
				it is not as bad as you are doing there. Because here we have everyone to help these
				men, societies, clubs, organizations, churches, everybody is reaching out a hand to
				give to these men. But it broke my heart to see that no one was helping those poor
				mothers.</q>"</p>
		<p>That is the message I have for you here in Illinois. I have come to you to appeal to you
			to help us. Help us help these women. Let us make a better world. Be the first on record
			in this state to open clinics, not one but dozens of clinics, where we can tell these
			women to come and be advised. Give them the hope that they are reaching out for... These
			women are bent, they are bowed, they are broken, and they want your help.</p>
		<p>Now, I believe that by birth control we <add>can</add> remove untold misery. I think that
			through it we can remove poverty, we can do away with slums. I think we can have
			children conceived in love and reared through the aid of science for the development of
			humanity. I believe also that through it we can change not only the quality of the race,
			but the thinking of the race, and bring about peace on earth, good will to men,
			(Vociferous applause)</p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
