<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed draft article ">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2004/08/01 MPL</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/08/07 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007/06/27 CH Oxygen Update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2001/03/11 CH Entered corrections suggested by Andy Carloff.</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/09/07 EK proofing corrections entered</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-26 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1918-00-00"><supplied resp="MSPP">1918</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>The War and Birth Control</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp143453</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>The Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
            <bibl>Library of Congress Microfilm 131:119</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="NCM">Nineteenth Century Magazine</name>
            <name id="GORWI">Gorgas, William</name>
            <name id="CR">Contemporary Review</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="Australia" level2="birth rates in"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="war and"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="decline in"/>
        <index level1="England" level2="birth rate in"/>
        <index level1="eugenics" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="France" level2="death rate in"/>
        <index level1="Hungary" level2="birth rate in"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="infant"/>
        <index level1="New York City" level2="mortality rate" level3="infant"/>
        <index level1="New Zealand" level2="birth rates in"/>
        <index level1="race suicide"/>
        <index level1="venereal disease"/>
        <index level1="venereal disease" level2="prevention of"/>
        <index level1="venereal disease" level2="and war"/>
        <index level1="World War I" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="World War I" level2="population and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>The War and Birth Control.</head>
        <p rend="underline">Points for an article.</p>
        <p>There are two special reasons in war-time for pushing to make birth control information
            legal:--one that it means positive race conservation; the other that war has always
            increased venereal disease and unless phenomenal improvement is made, the return of the
            soldiers will result in a menacing increase in the birth of diseased and defective
            children.</p>
        <p>As to the first reason:--race conservation, the following points should be
            emphasized:--</p>
        <p rend="blockquote">Contrary to the popular notion that birth control means possible race
            suicide, its results are just the contrary. It lowers the birth rate, but lowers the
            death rate <emph rend="underline">MORE</emph>, particularly the infant death rate. See
            the enclosed statistical leaflet for proof. (This table might be used to illustrate the
            article.)</p>
        <p/>
        <p rend="blockquote">War increases the civilian death rate. The most deaths are where the
            highest birth rate prevails. It is paradoxical but true that the best way to increase
            the population and lower the death rate is to lower the birth rate.</p>
        <p/>
        <p rend="blockquote"><place>England</place>'s experience has been that in "<q who="CR">1915,
                in wartime, deaths carried off more British babies than British soldiers. Therefore,
                the obvious way of repairing the wastage of war is to save the babies. Since five
                million young adult males of the country are under arms, and many thousand get
                killed every year, while the war lasts, the birth rate must drop. It is, therefore,
                more important than ever to preserve the lives of the children who are born</q>."
                (<title type="journal">Contemporary Review</title> for July)</p>
        <p/>
        <p rend="blockquote">It is of equal importance that only those should be born who can be
            given a decent amount of health and care. If babies are born only to die, the parents
            are needlessly depleted, the population is not increased and the race is not conserved.
            Too many babies means a cruel waste of babies.</p>
        <p/>
        <p rend="blockquote">In <place>Hungary</place> before the war, 340 babies out of every 1000
            died. Now the rate has risen to 500 out of every 1000. Since the war began over
            1,172,000 babies have died in that one country. Birth control information is not
            prevalent in Hungary. Its birth rate is one of the highest in <place>Europe</place>.</p>
        <p/>
        <p rend="blockquote">In <place>France</place>, the general death rate has jumped from 19 a
            1000 to 39 a 1000 since the war began. Only one third of these deaths were in the
                army.<del> The civilian</del><add>The increase in the civilian</add> deathrate
                <del>has therefore doubled.If this</del> can happen in a country which has had free
            birth control <add>information</add> for half a century, what will be the increase in an
            ignorant country like ours which prohibits the information, if the war should drag on
            for two or three years?</p>
        <p/>
        <p rend="blockquote">Dr. <person reg="Baker, Josephine">Josephine Baker</person>, of the
                <org>New York Mayor's Committee of Women on National Defense</org> reports that
            already the war conditions have raised the baby death rate. <place reg="New York, NY"
                >New York City</place> has held the American record for the reduction of infant
            deaths. Since the establishment of the <org reg="New York City Bureau of Social Hygiene"
                >Bureau of Child Hygiene</org>, of which also Dr. Baker is the head, the rate has
            dropped from 144 to 89 per 1000. If birth control information had been free it might
            have dropped to the figure of the world record, 70 per thousand, which is held by
                <place>Australia</place> and <place>New Zealand</place>, in which countries
            contraceptive information has long been free.</p>
        <p>As to second reason:--the probable increase in venereal disease, the following are the
            chief points:--</p>
        <p/>
        <p rend="blockquote">The history of all previous wars has shown that they have added to the
            total of venereal disease. All the army authorities, particularly in this country, are
            endeavoring to make this war show a better record. In some camps they have been very
            successful, in others the situation is much worse than anything in civil
                <supplied resp="MSPP">life</supplied>.</p>
        <p/>
        <p rend="blockquote">For <add>a</add> three year period previous to the war, (Jan. 1st, 1912
            to December 31, 1915) 857 of every 1000 applicants for enlistment in the regular army
            were rejected because they were unfit, and nearly 200 out of every 1000 men were
            rejected because of venereal disease. In other words nearly 1/5 of the men were found
            infected.</p>
        <p/>
        <p rend="blockquote">Surgeon General <person reg="Gorgas, William">Gorgas</person> states
            that for a 12 week period ending December 7th last, there were reported from the 31
            cantonments 21,742 <emph rend="underline">new</emph> cases of venereal disease. The
            number of previous uncured cases was not reported. The total number of men then in camp
            was not stated.</p>
        <p/>
        <p rend="blockquote"> (Note:-- I am trying to find out, so the ratio may be
                <del>different</del> Determined.) Official reports of January 18th showed that the
            highest rate for venereal disease in any of the camps was <place reg="Camp Pike, AK"
                >Camp Pike</place>, in <place>Arkansas</place> where over half of the men were
            infected. The rate was 56.7 per thousand. The lowest rate was <place
                reg="Camp Upton, AK">Camp Upton.</place> where there were only 4 <emph
                rend="underline">new</emph> cases for that week.</p>
        <p/>
        <p rend="blockquote">Apparently the conditions in the allied armies are worse than ours.
            Surgeon General Gorgas states "<q who="GORWI">that during the first 18 months of the
                war, one of the great powers had more men incapacitated from service by venereal
                disease <emph rend="underline">contracted in the mobilization camps</emph> than in
                all the fighting at the front</q>."</p>
        <p/>
        <p rend="blockquote">The conservative English Magazine, the <title type="journal">Nineteenth Century
                Magazine</title> for September, 1917 says of the British army, "<q who="NCM">from
                all parts of our empire, a million men have come overseas. Over one-third of that
                million becomes infected with venereal disease every 12 months</q>."</p>
        <p/>
        <p rend="blockquote">Conditions in the trenches are such that whatever, infection there is,
            may be rapidly spread, and many men may become diseased who have not willingly subjected
            themselves to the chance of infection.</p>
        <p/>
        <p rend="blockquote">It is to be hoped that the authorities will be able to control the
            situation, so that the returned soldiers will not be more diseased than they were before
            they went to war. But to just the extent that they do <emph rend="underline">not</emph>
            succeed, to just that extent will there be a most menacing increase in the birth of
            diseased children during the first few years after the war. If as is predicted, we send
            from three to five million men to <place>France</place>, this possible condition when
            the men come back is ample cause for anxiety.</p>
        <p/>
        <p rend="blockquote">If, however, the legal restrictions preventing the circulation of birth
            control information are removed before the end of the war, we shall then be free to
                <supplied resp="MSPP">help</supplied> the home-coming soldiers and their young wives to
            understand how they may defer the conception of their children until the danger period
            of the venereal infection is conquered.</p>
        <p/>
        <p rend="blockquote">Under peace conditions, the proportion of babies born diseased or
            defective because of venereal taint is sufficiently appalling. To let the war raise that
            rate is a social disaster which must be avoided if possible.</p>
        <p/>
        <p rend="blockquote">The nation is going to need the sturdiest kind of a race to meet the
            necessities of the reconstruction period following the war. Obviously this is no time to
            have the strength and resources of parents depleted by having more children than they
            can provide with fair health and care, or to have a next generation handicapped
                <add>and</add>below the par.</p>
        <p/>
        <p>BS&amp;AU/12646</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
