<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed draft article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2012-04-12 AW Initial Tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2012-04-13 CH Proofed tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2012-05-14 CH Second Proof</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2012-05-30 AW Corrected Tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-10 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1923-00-00"><supplied resp="MSPP">1923</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>The Unity of American Motherhood</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp143446</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Library of Congress</bibl>
            <bibl>Library of Congress Microfilm 131:82</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="JAMWI">James, William</name>
            <name id="FRABE">Franklin, Benjamin</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>This article was likely written in 1923. It bears a "<org>Brandt &amp; Kirkpatrick</org>" stamp, a
            literary agency that represented Sanger from 1921. It changed its name to <org>Brandt &amp;
            Brandt</org> in 1924.</p>
        <p>Additions were made by hand by Margaret Sanger.</p>
        <index level1="motherhood"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="infant"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="maternal"/>
        <index level1="United States Children's Bureau"/>
        <index level1="woman suffrage"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="freedom and rights of"/>
        <index level1="working classes"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head rend="underline">THE UNITY OF AMERICAN MOTHERHOOD</head>
        <byline>By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></byline>
        <p>“<q who="JAMWI">The Mothers! The Mothers! Ye are all one...</q>” So wrote the late
                <person reg="James, William">William James</person> in a beautiful letter to his
                <person reg="James, Alice Gibbens">wife</person>. This great <emph
                rend="underline">unity of motherhood</emph> we need today more than ever before.
            Today and tomorrow and the day after tomorrow the greatest need of our country is and
            increasingly shall be for great men and great women. We cannot produce them without
            great mothers. And motherhood can be made strong and great only as we recognize its
            unity, only when we come to the realization that the degradation and enslavement and
            neglect of any of our mothers or potential mothers means the enslavement and the
            degradation of all.</p>
        <p>But let us not make the mistake of thinking that we can protect American motherhood by a
            bath of pathos, a debauch of sentimentality. Today, as a nation, we are too prone to
            worship catchwords and catchphrases. We <add>only</add> pretend to hold motherhood
            sacred. “Motherlove” presented on the stage or the screen is always “sure fire stuff”.
            Yet our intelligence cannot, or does not, keep pace with our emotions. The pitiless
            statistics of the <org reg="United States Children's Bureau">Children’s Bureau</org> of
            the <org reg="United States Department of Labor">Department of Labor</org> reveal the
            painful fact that the people of the <place>United States</place> of America are more
            careless and wasteful of Motherhood than any of the great civilized countries of the
            world. We have a higher maternal death rate than any of the other principal countries.
            In <unclear resp="MSPP">1911</unclear> we lost more than 25,000 women in childbirth.
            Most of these deaths might have been prevented. Within the first year after birth, one
            of every ten babies born is foredoomed to an early death. In respect to the well-being
            of the mothers, upon which depends the very health and strength of our future
            generations, our public conscience has not yet been truly awakened. The maternal
            mortality rates and the infant mortality rates are the greatest disgrace of American
            civilization. </p>
        <p>What are we to do?</p>
        <p>Upon this point, I disagree with most of the so-called feminists. Shall we pass laws?
            Should we concentrate upon political and legislative action? Shall we extend our
            maternity centers and milk stations? Must we increase our donations to organized
            charities and philanthropies? Must the state and federal governments assume a
            supervision and paternal control of mothers and babies? Shall we demand larger and
            larger appropriations for the upkeep and maintenance of institutions for the unfit and
            the feeble-minded? These are but a few of the questions that arise immediately when one
            begins to probe into the complex facts of this great problem. </p>
        <p><del>At such a moment as the present one, when</del>
            <add>Now that</add> American women are <del>for the first time</del> experiencing the
            privilege of the vote, they are, perhaps, too ready to accept it as a magic power, an
            “open sesame” to every form of social and political justice. Too many of the new leaders
            of American women have forgotten, or have never realized, that the vote is valuable only
            as the expression of power and consolidation of interests. If votes are not cast with
            the aim of crystallizing organized and unified power, they are practically thrown away.
            Therefore before concentrating upon and placing all faith in piecemeal political
            measures, -- particularly for the “protection” of mothers and children, the greatest
            present necessity is to awaken and unite American motherhood, to arouse in American
            mothers an acute consciousness of their great and inalienable function. Only thus can
            American women be brought to a realization of their central role and enormous
            responsibility. </p>
        <p>Not through superimposed and external <unclear resp="MSPP"><del>political</del></unclear>
            remedies, nor through charitable or paternal ministrations, can we truly protect the
            mothers of our future generations, <del>It is</del>
            <add>but</add> only by awakening in them a sense of their own responsibility and by
            liberating their intelligence. We can protect American motherhood only by permitting it
            to protect itself. When American women come to the realization of this profound yet
            simple truth -- <emph rend="underline">the great unity of Motherhood</emph> -- they
            shall have taken the first great step in self-education and freedom. </p>
        <p>Then and then only can the enfranchisement of woman assume any importance in the
            political development of our country. For then the votes of women will become the
            expression of a great creative power. This is the power of Motherhood, a free and
            fearless Motherhood, by and through which will come a new race of strong men and women. </p>
        <p>In thus liberating the oldest power in the world and in creating a new one, American
            women are not called upon to break with the great traditions of America. The word
            “Americanization” means something quite different from that supposed by its noisiest
            adherents. </p>
        <p>If it means anything worth while, it can only mean the expression of the pioneer spirit.
            Our whole history has been the dream of an endless conflict -- the inspiring drama of
            frontiers. Our pioneers have pushed undaunted onward, from coast to coast, crossing
            mountains, plains and deserts, forward always into the unknown, confront<add>ing</add>
            courageously, bitter uncompromising realities, surmounting formidable hardships,
            performing daily acts of heroism that were not recorded only because they were so
            unconsciously and so unflinchingly <del>performed</del>
            <add>accomplished</add>. And in this great drama of the pioneer spirit, the women were
            equal protagonists with the men.</p>
        <p>The spirit of these forgotten pioneers is the cornerstone, if not the whole foundation,
            of our present national strength and hardihood. But with the advent of prosperity and
            sophistication, our women have, it seems to me, been <del>related</del>
            <add>relegated</add> to a secondary role. There is a tendency today, among our advanced
            feminists, to stress the limitations of our pioneer “foremothers”. We hear that they
            were crude, uneducated, limited, religious bigots, lacking in all the <del>finer
                susceptabilities and graces</del>
            <add>modern ability to organize and agitate</add>. They were “unawakened.” They had
            never heard of “Woman’s rights”. they did not vote and they did not even want to vote. </p>
        <p>Perhaps this is, in the narrow sense, the truth. But let us never forget that they were
            facing sterner realities and greater hardships than the great majority of American women
            face today. They lived on another level; they were simpler, more primitive, yet with a
            keener instinctive sense of their great and inalienable function. So closely and so
            completely were they the comrades and companions of their men -- because comradeship and
            equality were the stern necessities of the frontier -- that the insistence upon petty
                <add>(personal)</add> ethical rights, or such luxuries as “The vote” simply never
            entered their heads. </p>
        <p>Am I too idealistic, too eulogistic, in this tribute to the pioneer mother? Upon what
            evidence, it may be asked, am I so certain of their greatness? By what test, except that
            of legend and tradition, can I claim so much for them?</p>
        <p>These questions may well be asked. The answer seems to me irrefutable. It is that these
            women became the mothers of strong men. <person reg="Hanks, Nancy">Nancy Hanks</person>,
            the mother of <person reg="Lincoln, Abraham">Abraham Lincoln</person>, is perhaps the
            classic instance. Today we have passed the stage of defaming this great mother -- great
            in spite of her lack of “education” and culture. Look into the lives of the great
            majority of great Americans and you will find an exceptional mothers. Abraham Lincoln
            was the son of a “pioneer” mother. <person reg="Twain, Mark">Mark Twain</person> was the
            son of <person reg="Clemens, Jane">another</person>. Only the strong could survive
            the hardships of frontier life. And there can be no doubt that it was these very
            hardships that brought out all that men and women possessed of indomitable courage and
            bravery, and that human strength was thus enabled to perpetuate itself. </p>
        <p>They, indeed, were the lucky ones, in spite of their crudity, their lack of
            sophistication and social refinement. We American women of today are less fortunate in
            that our national prosperity does not call into play all that we possess of latent
            strength and courage. </p>
        <p>Today the whole situation for the American woman and the American mother has changed.
            Life is more complex. As a nation we have become rich. And more and more it has devolved
            upon the mother of the American family, even among the working class, to serve as the
            external and living advertisement of the hus band’s prosperity. American mothers, who
            under the rough and ready conditions of pioneer life, were veritable towers of strength,
            have <add>almost</add> succumbed to the insidious disease of comfort and luxury. </p>
        <p>Prosperity is a great test of character. And it is the American woman<del>hood</del>,
            rather than American man<del>hood</del>, who <add>today</add> bears the great burden of
            national prosperity. The <del>great</del> pressing problem is: shall we lie back in
            comfort and luxury, and, taking a detached sentimental interest in the less fortunate
            women and children, throw out the doles of charity or support superficial palliatives?
            Or shall we take up the great task of the pioneer American womanhood, facing
            courageously the new and tremendous problems of the future? There <del>is</del>
            <add>should be</add> no alternative. There is but one answer.</p>
        <p>To reconquer their <del>great</del> central place in American life, to produce the great
            Americans that are so increasingly necessary as th United States becomes the
                <del>great</del> leader in world affairs -- for this role is being thrust upon us by
            history -- the <emph rend="underline">unity of motherhood</emph> is the first essential
            for American women. This duty cannot be shirked. </p>
        <p>The investigations and reports of the Children’s Bureau of the Department of Labor
            indicate how closely bound up with the welfare of children is the welfare of mothers. To
            produce a race of strong and vigorous children it is necessary to create a race of
            strong and healthy mothers. Where then shall we begin?</p>
        <p>Most of the already organized efforts to solve this endless problem have concentrated
            upon the child. Yet these attempts to lessen the hideous rate of infant mortality have
            shown themselves to be wasted effort, unless they take into consideration also the
            inspection and supervision of expectant mothers and provide pre-natal care for the
            children. But even this, as any intelligent person my see, is not enough. As long as the
            potential motherhood of the country is being drained and wasted in the most ignominious
            industries, as long as the life blood of the mothers of the future and the creators of
            the America of tomorrow is being stitched into ready-made clothes, wrought into cheap
            embroideries and laces, into feathers and hideous artificial flowers, into sham furs and
            all sorts of tawdry fineries with which more “prosperous” women bedeck themselves, all
            these superficial attempts at “Child welfare” will be in vain. </p>
        <p>As long as these working women and mothers, in seeking to escape the monotonous slavery
            of such industries, are thrust into the “industry” of motherhood -- but
                <del>motherhood</del>
            <add>a maternity</add> no less monotonous and unrelieved, because it is a matter of
            blind instinct -- we shall discover, if we have not already discovered, that all efforts
            to establish maternity centers and milk stations, all efforts to decrease the casualties
            among these battalions of babies cannot touch the real <del>cause</del>
            <add>root</add> of the problem.</p>
        <p> Too long have all our efforts at social betterment been directed by the heart instead of
            the head. Love and sympathy are great dynamic powers. But too often our kindness has
            exactly the same effect, put into practice, as cruelty. If we cannot see it, it is
            because the majority of us are socially so near-sighted. It is a commonplace of social
            workers that the only charity that is worth while is that which helps people to help
            themselves; but in the working out of the various schemes <del>at</del>
            <add>for</add> amelioration of mothers and children, what efforts are being made to
            awaken among poor victimized mothers the sense of responsibility and power, of
            self-reliance and self-respect? Social workers are fond of repeating that “<q
                who="FRABE">an ounce of prevention is worth a pound of cure</q>”. But to prevent we
            must strike at the very roots of social evils. And to find these roots, we must
            understand the factors in the situation <add>that</add> confront us. A <personRef
                reg="Unknown">great mathematician</personRef> has said that no less important than
            the solution of a problem is the statement of the factors comprising it. </p>
        <p>Applying this to the great problem of American motherhood, upon which our whole future as
            a world power and leader depends, we very soon must come to the conclusion that our most
            pressing need today is a great revaluation of motherhood.</p>
        <p><emph rend="underline">We must lift motherhood out of the mire.</emph></p>
        <p>As long as American women drift unprepared and unwillingly into the greatest profession
            in the world, as long as they look upon maternity not as the fulfillment but the penalty
            of woman’s nature, as long as they look upon childbirth merely as an inevitable
            affliction, as long as they accept the coming of children with dumb and fatalistic
            resignation, we may rest assured that the <emph rend="underline">quality</emph> of the
            American men and women who are through such a channel brought into <del>our</del>
            <add>the</add> world, <emph rend="underline">will continue to deteriorate</emph>. </p>
        <p>But when we are brave enough to liberate the mothers and the potential mothers of
            tomorrow from fear, when we awaken in them a sense of responsibility and freedom, which
            must go hand in hand, of self-reliance and self-respect, we shall find less and less
            need for outside interference, for organized charities and philanthropies. We shall find
            the quality of children improving, instead of deteriorating. Released <del>of</del>
            <add>from</add> her unwilling burdens, liberated from the fear of becoming again and
            again the victim of blind chance, the mothers of tomorrow <del>may</del>
            <add>will</add> become the mothers of hardy children.</p>
        <p>This is no idle Utopian vision. Already we are developing a fine race of such mothers,
            intelligent, self-reliant, radiant. They are the creators of our future. All that they
            lack at present is this great sense of the <emph rend="underline">unity of
                motherhood</emph>. It is for these American women to <emph rend="underline"
                >socialize</emph> their motherhood, to widen the sphere of their beneficent
            influence among the less fortunate and less enlightened. <del>Enlightened</del>
            <add>Intelligent</add> self-interest demands this. The future of their children is bound
            up with the future of all American children. For if our American stock, <del>our</del>
            <add>the</add> boys and girls <add>of any of us</add>
            <del>are</del>
            <add>is</add> to be “marked down”, permitted to deteriorate, such a degradation will
            affect the whole community. </p>
        <p>Thus the <emph rend="underline">unity of motherhood</emph> is the great ideal. Upon this
            basis the intelligent woman may befriend the less fortunate, approaching <del>her</del>
            <add>them</add> with reverence and respect, teaching <del>her</del>
            <add>them</add> and without condescension, <add>influencing <del>her</del> them</add>,
                <del>but with the</del>
            <add>arousing them to a </add> sense of their tremendous importance to the future of
            America and the world. </p>
        <p>“<q who="JAMWI">The Mothers! The Mothers! Ye are all one...</q>”</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
