<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2010/02/24 AC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/03/14 EK clean regs</prepDate>

        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1935/00/00"><supplied>1935?</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>New Deal for Women</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp143737</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Library of Congress, Sanger Papers</bibl>
            <bibl><title>MSM</title>LCM 131:0050</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="ELLHA"> Ellis, Havelock </name>
            <name id="DICRO">Dickinson, Robert Latou</name>
            <name id="BRYLO"> Bryan, Louise Stevens</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Another draft of this speech titled "Hereditary Factor" can be located
            on LCM</p>
        <index level1="prostitution" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="poverty" level2="family size and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="economic benefits and risks of"/>
        <index level1="mentally disabled and diseased"/>
        <index level1="pregnancy" level2="fears of"/>
    </headNote>

    <docBody>

        <div>
            <p>Forgotten Man– Today we witness the stirring among the masses toward male solidarity
                emancipation as this country has not seen since its discovery.</p>
            <p> But is it not time some voice should be raised in behalf of the FORGOTTEN WOMAN–that
                a New Deal should be made for those forty-three million (43,000,000) women of
                child-bearing age, whose life’s happiness and development depends absolutely upon
                knowledge to control that function?</p>
            <p> A New Deal for the Mother immortalized in Poetry, but cruelly neglected in fact–the
                Mother whose life is shadowed by the constant fears of pregnancy but whose appeal
                for knowledge is denied.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <p>Prostitution can not be fought by laws or espionage. Without birth control
                prostitution can not be fought with success.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <p>Hordes of human beings hurled into existence through self-indulgence, accident, or
                casual ignorance. This power of parenthood–with divine potentialities–has been
                diverted from its course into cruel and ruthless exploitation.</p>
            <p> The benefits of birth control are direct and indirect.</p>
            <p> The indirect effects are specially though not exclusively concerned with its action
                of stabilizing the growth of population. The political Economist, the Sociologist
                are concerned.</p>
            <p> The Physician, Social worker, Parents and Individuals are interested in its direct
                influence. <list>
                    <item>1 The Individual </item>
                    <item>2 The Family</item>
                    <item> 3 The Race</item>
                </list></p>
            <p> We must bring home to the minds of thinking people the vital significance of the
                hereditary factor in each individual life. As we see the truth we must have the
                courage to proclaim it. It is a stirring and encouraging fact that within the past
                twenty years, knowledge of birth control has been demanded by all groups of people;
                that the truth shall no longer be concealed; that the facts of life shall be faced
                with unswerving courage; and that ignorance and prejudice shall no longer be allowed
                to menace the lives and happiness of the whole of one people. Many outposts have
                been captured. The citadel of opposition must be overcome with the weapons of fact,
                persuasion, and of unconquerable truth, for truth is greater than half-truth, as
                knowledge is nobler than ignorance.</p>
            <p> Wholesale human misery can and will be prevented when we apply the certainty of
                modern science to our problems instead of the baseless superstitions of medieval
                theology.</p>
            <p> If we shall take a broad outlook of the present Social and Economic problems, we
                must see that:</p>
            <p>
                <emph rend="underlined">First</emph>–Habits, customs and tradition of a large part
                of our population are distinctly dysgenic, owing mainly to centuries of erroneous
                and false ideas.</p>
            <p>
                <emph rend="underlined">Second</emph>–That to continue the rate of growth of
                population is the most momentous issue before the nations of the world today. It
                transcends all mere political controversy such as tariffs, taxes, currency which can
                be dealt with by Congresses and Legislatures. But the real life of a Nation, the
                life of the years ahead depends upon the application of the science of life to the
                basic problem of the quality of life itself.</p>
            <p> We have come to the Crossroads. Which path shall we choose–Strength and Efficiency
                or Degeneration and Decay?</p>
            <p> Birth Control and National Strength must stand or fall together. No longer can we
                build on the fertility of the physically and mentally unfit. Their upkeep and
                maintenance has already created a burden under which the Nation begins to stagger.
                Billions of dollars each year has been spent to preserve them with all the ingenious
                and kindly resources that modern humanitarian instinct could command.</p>
            <p> We have allowed and encouraged the procreation and multiplication of the physically
                and mentally and socially unfit and preserved them at the cost of the skilled and
                professional classes until the balance has become unequal to the task.</p>
            <p> A Nation rises or sinks on the physical or mental quality of its citizens. It cannot
                thrive when its fundamental structure is based on defective stock, the increase of
                morons, feebleminded, psychopathes, diseased slum populations.</p>
            <p> It is the mentally weak, the dull, who sap the vitality of the Nation. Their
                increase becomes a menace to all legislative or social progress. They become the
                hordes of unemployables, easily exploitable, too weak and ill-equipped to earn a
                livelihood unaided. They continue to use up the energy and resources of life,
                without contributing anything to advance our civilization.</p>
            <p> We cannot separate the basic quality of life from the economic and fundamental
                wealth of our Nation. The two are interlocked and react upon each other in the
                closest fashion. Only our politicians and self-seeking opportunists fail to
                recognize this. It is not necessary to speak with detailed precision on the minor
                variations of statistical result. The actual insane may be one million instead of
                two. The mentally defective may be 35 million instead of 50 million. The
                unemployables. The unemployables, sick, diseased, may be more or less than our
                statistics quote, but the fact remains clear, and, all honest investigators will
                admit, that one-fourth f those who make up this Nation are physically or mentally
                unfit to carry on the heritage of our civilization. It is this group who combat and
                weigh down the advance of the Nation. A Nation can only survive in this inter
                struggle when its units are each fit to carry its equal share.</p>
            <p> Had birth control been applied to the problems of poverty, maternal and infant
                welfare, overcrowding, delinquency and dependency twenty years ago, many of the
                social and economic conditions we are faced with today would not have arisen. It is
                the stubborn opposition of medical superstitions which hold progress back. It is the
                opponents of this humane cause who have increased human misery and at whose doors
                the death of women in child-bearing and abortions should be laid. They take their
                stand against birth control but in doing so they must recognize and admit that they
                also stand for unnecessary and inexcusable waste of mothers’ lives the crowding out
                of child life, the stunting and dwarfing of child development; the conditions of
                overcrowding; the increase of abortions; in armies of unemployed and
                unemployables.</p>
            <p> The increasing hordes of feeble-minded children, mental defectives, insane parents
                and physical and mental weaklings–they have put forth no program to deal with these
                fundamental factors of life.</p>
            <p> Future generations will look upon their ignorance and arrogance as enemies of the
                poor, who while living in comfort themselves exploit the fears and superstitions of
                the poverty stricken masses for their own power and wealth</p>
            <p>
                <person reg="Ellis, Havelock">Havelock Ellis</person> says:</p>
            <p> "<q who="ELLHA">Birth control beyond all reasonable doubt, is, with the feelings and
                    ideas at present prevailing in our civilization, the only method we possess of
                    effecting that restriction of the population, which is required in order to make
                    human life on earth fairly livable.</q>"</p>
            <p> The birth control movement spread and is now everywhere accepted by the enlightened
                and intelligent of all nations in practice if not in principle.</p>
            <p> To this fact comes the complaint that birth control is practiced among the best
                class of the country. Well, why not? A beneficial and progressive measure must be
                applied where initiative and capability exist. It need not end there. Laws compel
                the poor to apply for medical knowledge to public institutions.</p>
            <p>
                <person reg="Dickinson, Robert Latou">Dickinson</person> and <person
                    reg="Bryant, Louise Stevens">Bryant</person> “<q>all birth control is self
                    control.</q>” "<q who="DICRO"> and <q who="BRYLO"/>The final justification for
                    the practice of birth control is, that in it we possess what may now be the only
                    instrument left us for moulding the future race.</q>” </p>
            <p> The history of the Woman’s Movement in this era, when it shall be written, will
                record a strange and illogical fact which will be difficult for future generations
                to believe or even to understand. The fact that the Woman’s Movement for
                emancipation has kept itself apart from any cause which advocated sex reform, sex
                hygiene and birth control.</p>
            <p> It will be unbelievable for any enlightened forward thinking person to understand
                this because it is just that difference in sex–the biological burden or function of
                child bearing and rearing which rests so definitely on her that has caused less
                efficiency in woman and consequently her unequal economic position in Society.</p>
            <p> Woman has struggled upward for her rights and she has won them one by one, but until
                she has her biological freedom over the laws of child-bearing her other prizes so
                hardly won can do little for her onward march in civilization. The function of
                procreation must be under her control for the woman who is constantly submerged in
                the fears of pregnancy can never be qual in social or political efficiency to
                men.</p>
            <p> Were it not for the few women who through wealth and the position of influence or or
                those living childless or unmarried lives, the Woman’s Movement would still be
                struggling for her equal place in the social strata.</p>
            <p> Are there any women today anywhere in political, commercial or professional
                leadership with large families? No. It is only because they have had this function
                under complete control that they have been able to rise to any heights in
                educational cultural stature of our modern life.</p>
            <p> The leading women in the political movement while accepting the practice of birth
                control for themselves have been most punctilious in keeping their news and opinions
                on this subject cloistered with those which their ecclesiastical fathers handed down
                to them. They left the work of refuting certain claims about sex and sin, and shame
                to <emph rend="underlined">men</emph>. It was such writers as <person
                    reg="Carpenter, Edward">Edward Carpenter</person>, Havelock Ellis, <person
                    reg="Force, August">August Force</person> and others equally courageous, who
                dared to awaken and arouse public interest in the beauty, power and magnitude of the
                sex impulse and to dissociate it from indecency, obscenity and pornography. The
                younger people today are accepting these views which are forging ahead with other
                advanced ideas. They all link together in a chain giving strength to a higher phase
                of consciousness by which the human race will advance and evolve. </p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
