<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed draft article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2012-04-02 AW Initial Tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2012-04-04 CH Proofed Tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-04 EK clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1920-00-00"><supplied resp="MSPP"
            >1920</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Charity Begins at
                Home</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp143433</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
            <bibl>LCM 131:30</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>This article, intended for the <title type="journal">Birth Control
                Review</title> was never published.</p>
        <index level1="child welfare"/>
        <index level1="children" level2="education of"/>
        <index level1="society" level2="responsibility and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <byline>By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>, Editor of the <emph rend="ital">Birth
            Control Review</emph></byline>
        <p>Yes, not only should charity begin at home, but what is far more important, responsibility should begin at home. If each man and woman would live up to the obligation of the highest instincts in
            their natures, there would be little need of charity.
                <del>Each</del>
            <add>All</add> of us would be able to give of <del><gap
                    extent="one word" reason="illegible"/></del>
            <add>ourselves</add> and our substance so freely and unconsciously
            that the thought of dependence or of charity would have but small
            place in the thought of the world.</p>
        <p>All modern life makes for social responsibility. We can no longer be
            concerned with our own private interests alone. We have learned that
            our own interests can be secured only in the security of our
            neighbor’s.</p>
        <p>It is impossible in modern city life to have pure water for your own
            family’s use, unless your neighbor is also provided with pure water.
            The same principle applies to milk, other foods, drugs -- virtually
            all our necessities. So it is with our health we <del><gap
                    extent="one word" reason="illegible"/></del> have
            associations and public health measures in order that all may have
            the benefit of cures or, better still, of preventive measures. The
            same situation is observed in education. To protect our children,
            our neighbors and society, we must do our part in instructing our
            children and in providing general education for them. We must pay
            special attention to personal and social hygiene, to such training
            as will make our <del>children</del>
            <add>children’s lives</add> of value to themselves and to
            society.</p>
        <p><del>In these days it is more than ever true that we do not live to
                ourselves alone. Our social responsibilities daily become</del>
        </p>
        <p>If we allow children to go into a polluted world, our work is undone.
            So, not <del>charity</del> only charity, but something that precedes
            charity must begin at home. We must first recognize in ourselves our
            responsibility to the community -- we must provide for the education
            of the children of our neighbors, of our fellow citizens.
            We cannot escape our social responsibilities without danger to
            ourselves. More than ever is it true that we do not live to
            ourselves alone. </p>
        <p>Eevery day, our lives become more closely intertwined, one
            with another. Society is often and aptly compared to a chain -- it
            is not stronger than its weakest link. We must see to it that the
            links which we, personally compose, are as strong as they can be
            made. And while we are doing this, we must do our utmost to help
            others to make their own links strong -- for our own links are
            useless without the cooperation of others.</p>
        <p>Charity begins at home that it may have the more to give.
            Responsibility beings at home that it may there gather strength
            through the discharge of its first obligations, to help in the
            discharge of the general responsibility.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
