<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed draft article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2009/08/03 LL</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-03-10 CH cleaning regs</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-20 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1928-00-00"><supplied resp="MSPP">1928</supplied></docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>Politics Makes Strange Bedfellows</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp143775</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
			<bibl><title type="mf">Library of Congress Microfilm</title>, 130:0729B</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<name id="BIB">Bible</name>
			<name id="WARPJ">Ward, Patrick J.</name>
			<name id="RUSJO">Ruskin, John</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<index level1="Catholic Church" level2="political influence of"/>
		<index level1="Catholic Church" level2="birth control and"/>
		<index level1="Catholic Church" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="religion and"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<p> Politics makes strange bedfellows, Surely there have been none stranger than the
			liberals, the “progressives”, the champions of freedom who are supporting Governor
				<person reg="Smith, Al">Smith</person> because of his stand on prohibition. Verily
			they are straining at a gnat and swallowing a camel. In all tolerance and in all
			respect, to brush aside the religious aspect of this campaign is to remain stupidly
			satisfied with a superficial tolerance, and to ignore its profounder and most
			interesting aspects. “<q who="BIB">As a man thinketh, so is he...</q>” No one, surely,
			would say that Governor Smith, if elected, would act in a manner disloyal to the great
			church in which he was born and brought up. He cannot go against its edict.</p>
		<p>Father <person reg="Ward, Patrick J.">P.J. Ward</person>, of the <org
				reg="National Catholic Welfare Conference"> National Church Welfare Council</org> of
				<place reg="Washington, DC">Washington, D.C.</place> has defined the attitude of the
				<org reg="Roman Catholic Church">Catholic Church</org> concerning the moral and
			habits of non-Catholics. The Catholic Church, he has declared is the depository of
			eternal truth, the Kingdom of <name type="deity">God</name> on earth. She is responsible
			for the morals of the entire human race. “<q who="WARPJ">It is her duty to interfere and
				block all legislation that will adversely affect the morals of non-Catholics, as
				well as Catholics, because she feels that these are her children, though they have
				been led astray by error. The Catholic Church never loses the hope that
				non-Catholics will be some day counted in the fold. Therefore, it is necessary to
				supervise all social and moral legislation.</q>”</p>
		<p>The same authority has assured us that the Catholic Church is opposed to Birth Control
			because it interferes with the plan of God, “<q who="WARPJ">who intends that people who
				marry may do so for the purpose of procreation or may live in each other’ love in
				strict continence, like brother and sister. Marriage without the desire and
				responsibility of parenthood, or not lived in strict continence, is immoral and
				sinful.</q>” Such is the attitude of the National Catholic Welfare Council
			concerning Birth Control. Would Governor Smith dare or care to oppose its mandates in
			wielding a powerful opposition in any legislation involving the conscious control of
			procreative faculties aiming toward racial health, or toward the improvement of child
			life and the decreasing of infantile and maternal mortality rates? No. His mind,
			admirable as it may be, is oriented in the direction of his church. It is attuned to the
			closed world of pre-ordained Catholic morality, which refuses to recognize that one
			man’s virtue may be another’s sin, or that in the realm of ethics the last word has not
			yet been uttered.</p>
		<p>The question is not merely one of Governor Smith’s liberality or open-mindedness. It is
			of powerful institutional forces, which will evitably and with quiet power unconsciously
			direct his activity. Let us not forget the career of <person reg="Mitchell, John Purroy"
				>John Purroy Mitchell</person>. The frying-pan of Prohibition may be uncomfortable;
			but shall we on that account, caste away the precious freedom of our hard-earned “<q
				who="RUSJO">ethics of the dust</q>” for a closed world of an alien and imprisoning
			morality? </p>

	</docBody>
</doc>
