<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed statement">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2010/04/28 AC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2010/04/29 CH proof and correct</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-11 CH correct errors</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1938-11-12">12 Nov 1938</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Statement After Tour of Southern States</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp143780</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
            <bibl>Library of Congress Microfilm 130:754</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <index level1="mortality rates" level2="infant"/>
    <index level1="mortality rates" level2="maternal"/>
    <index level1="population growth" level2="regulation of"/>
    <index level1="poverty"/>
    <index level1="Southern States"/>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>This is a press release issued by the <org>Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau</org>.
            A handwritten addition was made by one of Sanger's secretarial staff. </p>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Statement from Mrs. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>,
            Director</head>
        <div>
            <p>On my return from a recent tour of several Southern states, I am more than ever
                convinced that it must become a necessary government function to provide birth
                control service through public health agencies to those who cannot afford the
                services of private physicians. Civic officials and leaders of social welfare
                organizations where I visited all regard birth control as the most immediate and
                important step in the solution of the problems of the various blighted areas, to
                halt “human erosion”. Everywhere meetings were overcrowded, not
                by the curious, not by those seeking personal information, but mostly by officials
                and those actively working among the indigent and the unfit, who sought knowledge
                and a fresh viewpoint for constructive social work.</p>
            <p>In one community I visited, 50% of the total area was designated as
                    blighted</soCalled>”, yet this area contains 54% of the population,
                58% of the child population 10 years of age and under, 67% of the white and 83% of
                the children appearing in <org>Juvenile Court</org>s on delinquency charges, 82% of
                the relief clients, 80% of the tuberculosis cases, 70% of the infant and maternal
                mortality among the white population, and 90% among the colored. This is the area of
                poor housing, inadequate income, dependency and disease. Yet this area is only one
                of thousands throughout the nation. Any slum section of <place
                    reg="New York, NY">New York</place> or <place reg="Chicago, IL"
                    >Chicago</place> would reveal the same conditions, in practically the same
                proportion, creating similar problems.</p>
            <p>While it is true that the <org reg="United States Government">Federal
                    Government</org> is spreading out its protective hands and building new homes
                for the occupants in these slum sections, it is the consensus of opinion that
                environment alone will not change the habits of this population, and within 10
                years, with their unchecked potency for child-bearing, there will naturally be an
                extension of the problem, and an even greater tax burden placed upon the small
                portion of the population left to pay the bills.</p>
            <p>It is now known that 13 of the Southern States have populations of which over 97% are
                native-born, providing an unparalleled opportunity for a reconstruction program to
                improve not only the environment but the innate quality of our national life. Here
                indeed is material to excite the imagination.</p>
            <p> I found nothing but the most receptive attitude on the part of the people themselves
                towards receiving birth control advice, and also I found the will to give this
                service among those in closest touch with the human need. But obstacles come from
                the top, from a few officials and arrogant clergymen who set their wills against
                public good, and intimidate nurses, social workers, and medical agencies from
                providing this service to parents who vainly ask it. It is at their doors that the
                increasing human misery in these groups must be laid. They are trying to solve 20th
                century problems with the dogma of the dark ages, and men and women everywhere must
                refuse them this power.</p>
            <p>Very soon there will be a request made to <org reg="United States Congress"
                    >Congress</org> by the Federal Government for a new appropriation of
                $850,000,000 to improve public health. No doubt a large portion of this huge sum
                asked of the tax-payers, will be sought to increase existing health and welfare
                services for mothers and children. No greater service could be given to the mothers
                and to the children among that enormous group of 20,000,000 individuals dependent
                upon some form of public aid, than to provide birth control knowledge to enable them
                to help themselves by not adding to their own misery through increasing the number
                who must share it. In 1937, out of the 2,000,000 babies born in this country,
                1,100,000 were born to parents on relief with incomes of less than $1000 a year.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Three Suggestions</head>
            <p>It behooves, therefore, the mean and women who have the welfare of the future of this
                country at heart to ask, nay to demand, of their Representatives in Congress, that
                included in the provisions of this legislation must be the right of these parents to
                obtain birth control information through health agencies supported by public funds.
                Such a measure will not only give constructive, immediate relief to millions of
                families, and prevent additional suffering, but would be the greatest forward step
                ever taken on a national scale to raise the level of intelligence of the nation’s
                population, and the quality of life.</p>
            <p>There are two other suggestions I would like to make: (1) Throughout the country our
                institutions are overcrowded with the insane, the feeble-minded, and the diseased.
                Thousands of human beings, buried alive, who can contribute nothing to their
                generation other than to use up the vital energies of those who must care for them.
                The cost of maintaining our derelict population is nothing compared to the loss of
                creative effort which might be utilized in other channels. Why should our Benevolent
                Federal Government not make a constructive investment in the quality of our future
                citizenship by offering pensions to all those in the child-bearing age with
                transmissible or hereditary diseases who will agree to sterilization? Here truly is
                a system of pensioning that will bring its own reward.</p>
            <p>Couple this with another appropriation <add>as an aid to marriage</add> for those
                healthy, intelligent young men and women, skilled artisans, professionals,
                agriculturists, who wish to marry and would welcome a family, if only there were
                some provision to tide them through possible emergencies in first few years until
                they could become entirely self-supporting. Money spent of a population of sound
                minds in healthy bodies that must inevitably promote and insure individual and
                national welfare. </p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
