<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/06/03 RT initial tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/02/06 CH Added more detail</prepDate><prepDate>2014-11-10 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1937-01-15">15 Jan 1937</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Town Hall Award Acceptance Speech</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp143744</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
            <bibl>LCM 130:643</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="JORDA">Jordan, David Starr</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Sanger was given the <org>Town Hall Association</org>'s Award of Honor
            in 1936. She spoke at a meeting of the Association in <place reg="New York, NY">New York
                City</place> on January 15, 1937. Other speakers included Rabbi <person
                reg="Goldstein, Sidney E.">Sidney E. Goldstein</person>, <person reg="Hurst, Fannie"
                >Fannie Hurst</person>, <person reg="Little, Clarence Cook">Clarence Cook
                Little</person>, <person reg="McCracken, Henry Noble">Henry Noble
            McCracken</person>, and <person reg="Fairchild, Henry Pratt">Henry Pratt
                Fairchild</person>. For additional coverage of the event, see "<title type="article">Mrs. Sanger Gets Town
            Hall Medal</title>," <title type="journal">New York Times</title>, Jan. 16, 1937. For an additional draft, see LCM
            109:241B.</p>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="awards"/>
        <index level1="freedom" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Comstock Act"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="freedom and rights of"/>
        <index level1="United States Congress" level2="MS on"/> 
        <index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits and risks"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>

        <p>I want to thank you for the honor you have conferred on me tonight, not only in my own
            name, but rather as a representative of those millions of men and women whose lives we
            must go on struggling to “enlarge and enrich.”</p>
        <p>I am pleased, I am happy to have this fine tribute to my humble efforts, toward the
            enlargement and enrichment of life, because it seems to me that these words are
            precisely what I have aimed to do, and because these words contain the whole meaning of
            the Aims and Objectives of the Birth Control Movement, indeed the whole of the meaning
            of Civilization itself.</p>
        <p>How can the lives of the masses be enlarged and enriched except through Freedom.
            Freedom--that word which has been ringing down the ages, chased form place to place,
            from country to country, round and round the globe. Freedom-- so difficult to get, but
            far more difficult to hold. Freedom for the individual, but also for the human
            family--the Community. Thus in fighting for this spiritual quality we link our own
            personal efforts with the great aim of fulfilling human destiny and thereby broaden our
            own lives and enrich our own experience.</p>
        <p>Nearly a quarter of a century ago, I awakened to the bitter realization that the Mothers
            of this country were enslaved victims of old prejudices and stupidities. I realized that
            laws passed by <org reg="United States Congress">Congress</org> during a Puritanical era
            had resulted in compelling women, in fact, conscripting them, to the slavery of
            childbearing. They were denied freedom of knowledge--they were slaves of laws and
            tyrannies.</p>
        <p>The suffering, the mental agony, the damaged bodies, the needless sacrifice of women’s
            lives aroused my determination to “speak out” for these mute mothers, too inarticulate
            to speak for themselves.</p>
        <p>In <place>India</place> there is a proverb. “<q who="JORDA">Knowledge is to know what to
                do: Skill is knowing how to do it; Virtue is the doing it.</q>” Well, I had neither
            the knowledge, nor the skill, but I knew that something had to be done about it. Then
            the greatest obstacles were discovered--the barbed wire entanglement--the Federal laws
            which had been placed on our law books and tied up the whole subject of Birth Control
            with that of obscenity, indecency and pornography.</p>
        <p>It has taken nearly twenty-five years to clear away these barbed wire entanglements.</p>
        <p>Congress that made the error should have corrected it, but ever timid and fearful,
            thinking of votes, ignoring women’s sufferings, it was the <org>United States Circuit
                Court of Appeals</org> that cut through these barriers and separated at last the
            idea of decent scientifically controlled contraception from the stigma of the immoral
            and obscene.</p>
        <p>If one could sum up the misery and unhappiness in homes resulting from the deaths of the
            3 million mothers and 15 million babies whose lives have been needlessly sacrificed
            since the Federal law was passed sixty-three years ago, it would make countless
            thousands mourn.</p>
        <p>Now at last the shaky part of the laws gives us a Freedom which makes possible the free
            flow of knowledge to women and men which can make possible the Enlargement and
            Enrichment of millions of lives.</p>
        <p>It makes possible the spread of scientific knowledge of the elements of sound breeding.
            It makes possible the creation of a new race; a new generation brought into this world
            consciously conceived. It makes possible the breeding out of human weeds--the defective
            and criminal classes--the breeding in of the clean, strong and fit as instruments to
            carry on the torch of human destiny.</p>
        <p>Only thus can we link our own limited individual lives with the whole future of
            humanity.</p>
        <p>We look tomorrow to lives lived without fear, without anxiety, to lives of free men,
            women and children, instead of the slaves crippled by ignorance, injustice and
            tyranny.</p>
        <p>In accepting this great honor you have conferred on me tonight I do so, not so much as a
            recognition of achievement completed, but as the symbol of your faith in the importance
            of the task that still confronts us, of your support and encouragement in the great work
            for the Enlargement and Enrichment of the lives of millions of mothers and children who
            can now be reached.</p>
        <p>Let us who desire to live richly--dangerously--dedicate ourselves to these great
            aims--the Enlargement and Enrichment of Life in the deepest as well as the broadest
            sense of these words, in consecrated service to the fulfillment of the realization and
            perfection of the Human Race.</p>
        <p>For only in these terms can our own smaller lives gain real meaning and direction.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
