<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2009/08/04 LL</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2009/08/06 CH proof and correct</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2011/03/11 CH Entered corrections suggested by Andy Carloff.</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-03-12 CH clean regs and errors</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1928-03-15">15 March 1928</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Engineer's Auditorium Speech</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp143774</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Papers</title>, Library of Congress.</bibl>
			<bibl>LCM 130:0725B</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger</person> gave this address at a mass meeting
			sponsored by the <org>American Birth Control League</org>, <org>New York Woman's City
				Club</org>, <org>Junior League</org>, <org>New York City League of Women
				Voters</org>, and other organizations, held in <place reg="New York, NY">New
				York</place>'s <org>Engineering Auditorium</org>, at 33 West 39th Street. Held in
			support of <name type="law">New York Assembly Bill 1084</name>, others appearing with
			Sanger were <person reg="Halpern, Rose">Rose Halpern</person>, <person
				reg="Wile, Ira S.">Ira S. Wile</person>, <person reg="Reiland, Karl">Karl
				Reiland</person>, and <person reg="Jones, Eleanor Dwight">Eleanor Dwight
				Jones</person>. For another excerpt from this speech, see "<xref from="302113.xml"
				>Engineer's Auditorium Speech Excerpt</xref>," Mar. 15, 1928.</p>
		<index level1="immigration" level2="U.S. policy"/>
		<index level1="population growth" level2="regulation of"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<p> It has long been hoped by some of us that a sound international population program might
			be advanced. We have seen that manuala broader bird’s eye view of the problem was
			necessary if it was to fit international and modern conditions. It was quite natural
			that the militarist should look upon the subject only with a view of armies; the
			demographer with the number of births, deaths, marriages in a given city, country over a
			given period.</p>
		<p>The anthropologist is concerned with the division into races within a population,
			especially in respect to their adaptability and the effect of social selection and
			colonization, while the economist, biologist and statistician--each expert in his own
			line--was bound to propose measures according to the limits of his inquiries;
			consequently, formidable errors were bound to arise when it came to practical
			issues.</p>
		<p>It was with this in mind that I went to <place>Europe</place> for the objects of bringing
			together scientists from various countries of different departments to correlate their
			views, experiments and programs, and to establish, if possible, a permanent organization
			for further studies and research along population lies.</p>
		<p>This <org reg="International Union for the Scientific Study of Population Problems"
				>Population Union</org> has now been launched and it is hoped that there will be a
			recognition through their studies of the fact that there can be no solution to the
			population problem without the recognition of the human factors which make this problem.
			I refer to the parents who produce populations--and especially the mothers who bear and
			rear the children.</p>
		<p>The intelligent thinkers in Europe, many with whom I had conversed, believe that the
			empty spaces on the globe are becoming rare; that populations are so increasing in every
			country that governments are at a loss to know how to deal with the problems arising
			therefrom; that Europe is today faced with a problem of having more men than bread, and
			this problem has become acute, because of the attitude of the <place reg="United States"
				>United States</place>, <place>Australia</place> and <place>Canada</place> in their
			recent immigration legislation.</p>
		<p>It is now recognized that each country needs its own available food supply. Each country
			is guarding its own labor market, fearing unrest, unemployment and revolution. Soon
			every nation will reserve its potential resources for its own people, and already most
			of the European countries have overdrawn on their margin of self-sufficiency.
				<place>Germany</place>, <place>Italy</place>, <place>Poland</place> and all the
			central European countries should be encouraged to limit their population to their
			natural resources, but they are all dreaming of colonization, for colonization over seas
			was the solution of overpopulated Europe since the conquest of the Atlantic.</p>
		<p>There is no doubt that this has made civilization almost worldwide, and yet, there are
			doubts that this solution was of permanent value, for we now see that economic greed
			caused nations to overlook fundamental principles, and the future potentialities of
			nations have been sacrificed for immediate gain.</p>
		<p>Colonial expansion is still the dream of those militarists who clamor for big battalions
			of babies, and we see from the past that colonization has aroused a hatred of peaceful
			nations against the white race, and everywhere in <place>Asia</place> is the growing
			determination to free themselves from their political domination.</p>
		<p>Immigration legislation in the United States has caused much bitterness in Europe, for
			there is current a feeling that various nations have expended through generations much
			of their most valuable human material in order to furnish America with ready-made
			workmen--skilled in the arts and crafts--thereby impoverishing herself of valuable
			stocks, with the obvious results of creating a rival, today more powerful than all of
			Europe combined.</p>
		<p>America, on the other hand, considers that she has been overstocked with undesirable
			elements; that her dream of the melting-pot of assimilating the various races, colors,
			grades of mentalities through education by an American type of intelligence, has not
			succeeded. She now regrets her mistake, and has established a rigid system of
			immigration barriers for her own national and racial protection; and one can assume that
			from the <name type="law">Immigration Act of 1924</name>, the <org>United States
				Government</org> recognizes that there is a population problem in this country; that
			the resources of the land are limited; that unrestricted population increase through
			unrestricted immigration is bound to invite disaster to the social and racial life of
			the country. Consequently, a bar is raised to the free entrance of aliens into the
			United States, and even, when by the quota such aliens are given permission to enter the
			country, there are still social considerations to be grappled with.</p>
		<p>The government claims the right to exclude immigrants whose condition is likely to be a
			source of danger to the well-being and happiness of the country. Thus there are excluded
			all idiots, imbeciles, feeble-minded persons, epileptics, insane persons, persons of
			psychopathic inferiority, persons afflicted with tuberculosis in any form, or with any
			loathsome, dangerous or contagious disease, paupers, professional beggars, vagabonds,
			persons likely to become a public charge, polygamists, anarchists, criminals,
			prostitutes, or persons coming to U.S. for purposes of prostitution, or for any other
			immoral purpose. There are also provisions for the exclusion of illiterates, or of
			persons 16 years of age, physically capable of reading, but who cannot read English or
			some other language. All are refused admission into U.S.A. The procedure for the
			enforcement of these restrictive and selective measures is mandatory. Detailed
			regulations are laid down for the examination of these immigrants before entry, and for
			their deportation in case of exclusion.</p>
		<p>The government goes even further than this, for even after entrance the government
			reserves the right to pursue the policy of selection in such cases of criminals or those
			who have become a public charge--even five years after entry--are liable to deportation
			at any time.</p>
		<p>In no other immigration country is the restrictive policy carried out so far as in U.S.A.
			This rigid policy of the U.S. Government is the result of its short-sightedness in the
			past, for while this government never openly encouraged immigration, she took up a
			neutral attitude toward the question until 1914. She was much like the parents who--not
			really knowing what shall happen if their family continues to grow--nevertheless do
			nothing to prevent it. She now has had to adopt a negative, selective quota where she
			might have in the past adopted a positive, selective quota, and this country would today
			have been in a position to deal intelligently with some of the intricate problems that
			she is today unable to face. </p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
