<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed interview">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/06/12 MM</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1948/02/00"><supplied resp="MSPP">Feb 1948</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Title of the document</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp143743</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library Of Congress</bibl>
            <bibl> Library of Congress Microfilm LI30:636</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>This rough transcript of a radio discussion between Sanger and Mr.
            Wiesel and Mrs. Petch with handwritten corrections and additions by Sanger and other
            unidentified people, possibly Dorothy Brush. </p><index level1="Japan"
            level2="overpopulation and"/><index level1="Japan" level2="overpopulation and"/><index
            level1="Italy" level2="population policies of"/><index level1="India"
            level2="population policies of"/><index level1="India" level2="overpopulation and"
            /><index level1="slums"/><index level1="England" level2="population policies of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head><title rend="underline">TOO MANY PEOPLE</title></head>
        <byline><emph rend="underline">Station H H 2 S - Radio Port Au Prince: Margaret
                Sanger</emph></byline>
        <p><emph rend="underline">Wiesel:</emph>Introduction</p>
        <p>Sanger</p>
        <p>Thank you, Mr. Weisel. I am glad to have this opportunity to speak from Haiti on this
            vital quesiton of world population. </p>
        <p>For the first time in history people are thinking of an international program for
            population control. <add>Congress</add>It is significant that a United Nations delegate
            at the international Health Conference said, "The control of the birth rate is as
            important as control of the atom bomb."</p>
        <p><add>Congress</add></p>
        <p>Population is a large and vague word -- But when you think about it <del>more
                carefully</del> it simply means people. Our leaders disagree on this problem of
            people. Some leaders want many more people to populate their countries. They give prizes
            and rewards to <add>fathers</add> mothers of big families. They think of national
            welfare in terms of how many nationals they have of military age. Other experts disagree
                <del>with this philosophy, because they</del> believ<del>e</del><add>ing</add> that
            unlimited masses of people are <add>a brake on; civilzation</add> meaningless -- and
            dangerous. What this world needs, they explain are more productive, creative people
                <del>who are</del> able to <del>contribute to our civilization</del>
            <add>accelerate progress</add> These experts are alarmed at the swarming millions of
                <del>unproductive</del>, <add>dependant</add> defective human life <del>that is
            </del> multiplying with such senseless violence. They explain that this is a finite
            earth. Space is increasingly limited. Food resources are becoming alarmingly
                <del>limited.</del>
            <add>scarce</add> Must the productive <del>people </del>have less to eat in order to
            feed more and more <add>of the</add> unproductive <add>?</add>
            <del>mouths?</del>
            <add>Since</add> We have learned, <del>the experts explain that we must</del>
            <add>to</add> plan the size of our families according to our resources, the next step is
            to plan the number of people our countries can support. <gap reason="deleted"/></p>
        <p><add>This very summer an international congress of investment scientists + distinguished
                people ? to this danger are meeting in England to discuss world population and world
                resources. Population seems like an ? ?</add></p>
        <p><add><emph rend="underline">Wiesel</emph> Are there figures to suggest how that number
                could be arrived at (2)</add></p>
        <p>SANGER: It takes 100 acres of tillable land to give meat to nine people once a day....100
            acres of grazing land to give milk to forty children once a day....And 100 acres of
            tillable land to give bread or cereal to 280 people once a day. <add> and people
                increase while the amount of land remains the same</add> Millions of people <gap
                reason="torn"/>
            <supplied resp="MSPP">meat</supplied> or cow's milk.</p>
        <p><add>Wiesel: The last war than did not diminish the population by much? </add>
        </p>
        <p>There are more people on the earth now in the last 150 years than there were during ALL
            the <emph rend="underline">millions </emph> of years that man has lived on this
            planet... The earth is only <emph rend="underline">so</emph> big -- there's only <emph
                rend="underline">so</emph> much food to go around -- only so much soil to grow it
            in. <add>of course </add><add>and we now have 10% less food per person than before the
                war.</add>
            <del>So we have to begin to think about our population problem.</del></p>
        <p><gap reason="deleted"/>the millions <del>who</del> were killed in the last war...
                <del>And</del>
            <add>but</add> still the population soared ---- while all the time the food to support
            all these people fell off, <add>as farm lands were ruined, sometimes terrain, by
                war.</add></p>
        <p>PETCH: But why has this startling rise in population happened so fast -- and in such a
            short time Mrs. Sanger?</p>
        <p>MISSING LINE genuinely effective method of death control.... </p>
        <p><del>PETCH:</del><add>Wiesel:</add>
            <del>And now that doctors can keep us from dying</del>
            <add>We do not die</add>as fast and as young as our ancestors used to die<add>,</add>
            --- <add>? and so</add><del>you mean</del>, there's nothing to stop people multiplying
            at a violent rate?</p>
        <p>SANGER: <del>You see</del><add>Before medicine</add> wars and germs killed off our
            ancestors quite effectively -- so there was a real balance between the number of people
                <del>who used to be</del> born and the number who died to make more room for
            them.... But <add>not now.</add><del>wars alone don't hold down population.</del><gap
                reason="torn"/></p>
        <p>SANGER:<del> Mrs. Patch</del>
            <del>i</del><add>I</add>if this rise in population keeps up we are going to increase at
            the frightening rate of 200 million every ten years... <del>And despite</del> Western
            Europe is sick from the population <add>(orgy).</add><del>binge</del> it began a century
            ago. And we're all concerned with the problems of teeming Asia -- wracked by famines,
            constant hunger and disease. Don't forget as we gain more control over the death rate
            through our increasing medical knowledge ---- there will be still more people. There
            just are not resources to give people the food nad clothing and shelter they must have.
            And the more people there are -- the less each person can expect to get.
            <add>??</add></p>
        <p><emph rend="underline">Wiesel</emph></p>
        <p> Yet we hear cries of alarm from (4) many native informed. They are losing out in the
            birth rate race. In fact most European countries still are taking official reform to
            encourage more babies.</p>
        <p>Sanger</p>
        <p>Yes, while those who are alive are starving.</p>
        <p>PETCH: But why <del>do you think that</del><add>are</add>most countries <del>are</del> so
            anxious for a high birth rate?</p>
        <p>SANGER: <del>You know Hitler had a powerful propaganda machine. I believe without
                realizing it people everywhere have absorbed his doctrine that there is an actual
                connection between numbers and power. </del><add>Its not the people Its the
                Militarists, Mr. Petch<del>desoite his downfall</del></add>leaders in complicated
            countrer</p>
        <p>SANGER: Look what happened with the Axis nations! They were all explosively
            over-populated even before World War 1. In the 1920's serious-minded Japanese and
            Italian officials tried to apply brakes to their terrific rate of growth. But the
            militarists won out. They knew that over-population made their countries ripe for
            military dictatorship and conquest. <add>What makes</add> Men want to fight
            <add>?</add>, <del>for</del>
            <add>lack of</add> bread for their children. <add>The cry for land is the cry for the
                cry for ? The cry for ? is the cry for war.</add></p>
        <p>PATCH: And then of course at <del>the very opposite extreme to the Axis we have</del>
            <add>There are</add> the vastly over-crowded countries like China and India. </p>
        <p>SANGER: Yes --- <add>Where many are too weak from lack to fight to eat??</add>
            <del>we've been dreadfully confused on this problem of population.</del> China and
            India's tremendous birth rate are certainly no sign of <add>Natural</add> strength or
                <del>national virility</del>
            <add>Political honor</add>
            <del>You know Mrs. Patch</del> when I hear people quote from the Bible "Be fruitful and
            multiply" -- I want to remind them of another Biblical saying -- "Thou has multiplied
            the nation, and not increased the joy." That's from Isaiah in the 9th chapter, 3rd
            verse.</p>
        <p>PETCH: But, Mrs. Sanger <emph rend="underline">isn't</emph> there strength in numbers?
            And doesn't our national security depend on it?</p>
        <p>SANGER: If America's safety depended on numbers we would have <add>been</add>beaten at
            the start of both world wars. You know what a decisive factor the United States actually
            was in modern, technological warfare. It is the quality of
                    <del><unclear>brains</unclear></del>
            <add>brains?</add> that counts. In fact our national -- and international security
            depends on this! --- and by quality I mean man's intelligence and ingenuity and
            foresight --- but most of <add>/</add> all man's humanity. That is what will count in
            our fight to survive and achieve a stable world peace. We won the last war because we
            had a surplus of goods over and above the needs of our own daily living. We can win the
            peace because we have enough goods to keep <add>our own</add> people fed and clothed and
            housed. Happy, well-fed people <del>are not led by</del><add>do not listen to</add>
            warmongers. They would think it a poor bargain to give up their freedom to dictators who
            promise them bread if they <add>already</add>have bread - and freedom to eat it in!
            That's the best combination for peace. </p>
        <p><emph rend="underline">Wiesel</emph></p>
        <p>If an option of an uncanny of ? for the ? May I ask if you think we are ? one present
            prepetuation as affectively as we need. </p>
        <p><add>Sanger: No indeed.</add></p>
        <p>SANGER: Technically trained people are badly needed in many parts of the world. We keep
            saying that in the case of certain skills and professions, a nation will ahve to wait
            for a whole new crop of babies to grow up before the trained group are availible in
            large enough numbers. I'd like to see an International Placement Bureau -- a Labor Pool
            of skills and professions. Individuals from this pool could <add>choose to</add> be sent
            to any part of the world where they are needed.</p>
        <p>PETCH: But how could you start this Labor Pool of professions and skills?</p>
        <p>SANGER: Just think of all the highly trained men and women wasting away in the Displaced
            Persons Camps! It's criminal to waste people like that. If they could be made availible
            according to their skills, to the countries that need those techniques, it would be one
            way of solvign their problem.</p>
        <p>PETCH: <del>You know Mrs. Sanger, I've lived a great deal</del><add>I understand
                that</add> in Scandinavia -- <del>where</del> your idea has been attempted on a
            national scale. It's been very successful. Those countries are really a small scale
            model of what you hope to do on a world scale, aren't they?</p>
        <p>SANGER: Yes, so far only small countries with no imperialistic ambitions like the
            Scandinavian lands have attempted this planning of their people. <add>to their
                resources</add></p>
        <p>PETCH: And they certainly found that it made for happiness and plenty for all their
            citizens. Everyone had a fair share of food and jobs and homes. </p>
        <p>SANGER: When the great powers recognize the truth -- that it's the caliber of people and
            NOT the quantity of people that matters, they will begin planning their populations.
            When that day comes, no nation will have more people than it's resources can take care
            of satisfactorily. </p>
        <p><add>and that day will come.</add></p>
        <p>SANGER: There are courageous, farsighted people throughout the world who believe that the
            time has come for less waste in people, <del>Mr. Petch.</del> They are deeply concerned
            with the swarming millions of unproductive, defective human life that is multiplying
            with such uncontrolled velocity. You see once we <del>stop thinking</del> that
                <add>realizing brains, not</add>numbers mean strength we <emph rend="underline"
                >have</emph> to change our attitudes. In modern war and in modern peaceful society,
            it takes ability and skill and education to function. Numbers no longer mean strength in
            war or in peace!</p>
        <p>PETCH: <del>Where are your Conference delegates coming from Mrs. Sanger?</del></p>
        <p> And while you were helping to solve their problems the countries that employed them
            would be helped back on their feet. It's an extraordinarily interesting idea, Mrs.
            Sanger.</p>
        <p><del> Wursel: In closing Mrs. Sanger may I ask you how Jon ? so influenced in so an
                abstract idea so subject as population</del></p>
        <p><del>They have accepted Hilter's propaganda that only frowing natios are strong, and so
                they think that nations with a stable or a declining population must be "old" or on
                their way out.</del></p>
        <p><emph rend="underline">PETCH:</emph></p>
        <p><del>Yes--I'm afraid a great many of us believe that. But isn't there some truth in the
                idea of a growing nation?</del></p>
        <gap reason="torn"/>
        <p><del>began ? </del> what a tremendous job control of birth could do in effecting world
            peace. If hungry, despserate people explode into war, why not begin to balance the
            number of people born with the resources availablle to care for them? Then <del> all of
                us can enjoy the good things of this world</del> none of us need starve or do
            without. If medical science has given us the blessing of controlling death, it has been
            generous in also giving us the means of controlling birth. Now we can plan both the size
            of our families and the growth of our nations. And by planning we can produce the number
            of people that we can best take care of.</p>
        <p>I've seen what poverty and overcrowding did in the slums of New York when I worked in
            them as a nurse 30 years ago. <add> And I saw how active + numerous humans breath wealth
                and prosperity to a family</add> I have just expanded <add> The principle operating
                ?</add> those New York City slums. <del>Now I see</del>
            <add>to</add> the terrible world slums/ Like all slums they breed death and hunger and
            disease --- and finally war!</p>
        <p>PETCH: So your idea has grown from one slum in one city to the <del>whole</del>
            <add>one slum of the one</add> world.</p>



    </docBody>

</doc>
