<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2009/07/16 JS</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/03/10 EK cleanup</prepDate>

        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1930-09-01">
            <supplied resp="MSPP">1 Sept 1930</supplied>
        </docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>
                <supplied resp="MSPP">Presidential Address to Seventh International Birth Control
                    Conference</supplied>
            </titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp143728</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
            <bibl><title>LCM</title> L130:572</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>               
                  <resp/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>Margaret Sanger opened tbe Seventh International Birth Control Conference with this
            speech</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues" level3="in Netherlands"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="disputes within"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="goals and strategies"/>
        <index level1="conferences" level2="International Birth Control Conference"
            level3="1930 (7th)"/>
        <index level1="Netherlands, the" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="physicians" level2="birth control and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>President’s Opening Address</head>
        <p>Ladies and Gentlemen, Honored guests and Members of the Conference: -- </p>
        <p>I have the honor to welcome you to the <name type="conference">Seventh International
                Birth Control Conference</name>. It is indeed an honor and a privilege which I
            cherish and appreciate not only because of the attendance of so many distinguished
            guests who have come from vast distances to attend this Conference, but also because of
            the important place the idea of birth control is taking in the social program of all
            civilized peoples.</p>
        <p>When one considers the world wide problems of the population question, we seem in a way
            like a small group, a mere handful of people battling for so mighty a cause, But while
            you who come here because you are in the front ranks of the birth control army seem to
            be small in numbers we know that the millions of men and women in all countries are
            looking to you to unshackle them from the tyrannical laws of their own reproductivity.
            You have become the protagonists of the millions of poor, hopeless, enslaved souls
            caught in the trap of their own fecundity, and as such you voice their wrongs and battle
            for their emancipation.</p>
        <p>The last or <name type="conference"
                reg="Sixth International Neo-Malthusian and Birth Control Conference">Sixth
                International Conference</name> was held in <place reg="New York, NY">New York
                City</place> in March, 1925. Since that time we have lost through death three of our
            oldest workers, Dr. <person reg="Jacobs, Aletta">Aletta Jacobs</person>, Dr. <person
                reg="Rutgers, Johannes">Rutgers</person> and Dr. <person
                reg="Vickery, Alice Drysdale">Vickery</person>, the beloved mother of our <personRef
                reg="Drysdale, Charles Vickery">Honorary President</personRef>. These three noble
            souls carried high the ideals of this cause through those years when it severely tested
            courage and vision, and they never wavered but proved themselves tried and true. May
            their work live and may we carry their dreams into practical realization.</p>
        <p>In 1925 there were outside of <place reg="Netherlandsthe ">Holland</place> only four
            birth control clinics in the world, modeled mostly on the ideas I had obtained from my
            visit to <place reg="The Hague, Netherlands">the Hague</place> in 1915, where I took
            a course of contraception from Dr. Rutgers and outlined the organization of separate
            birth control clinics.</p>
        <p>Today we know of over 100 birth control clinics or centers where contraceptive
            information is being given by qualified members of the medical profession. We know of
            another fifty centers or departments of health or welfare work, where birth control
            advice is part of general health and welfare service, so that it is safe to say that
            there are today about 200 recognized centers where information on birth control is <emph
                rend="underline">officially recognized</emph> and imparted. Besides these we know of
            several thousand doctors who have begun to give advice in their private practice, and it
            seems predestined that with this start already made nothing can prevent its permeation
            to all corners of the earth, within the lifetime of those in this room.</p>
        <p>There may be some who wonder why we came to <place reg="Zurich, Switzerland"
                >Zurich</place> to hold this conference, and I’d like to explain why--
                <del>First</del>
            <add>Secondly</add>, because we knew of no organizations already here upon whose toes we
            might tread. <del>Secondly</del>
            <add>First</add>, because of the world wide reputation of the charms of
                <place>Switzerland</place> and its hospitality. Thirdly because of its geographical
            location which made it convenient for so many of our friends from
            <place>Germany</place>. We had no idea of or desire to invade the precincts of this
            delightful country, nor to <del>spread</del>
            <add>broadcast</add> our ideas <del>among</del>
            <add>to</add> the general population. We have already been justified in our selection,
            for we have met with great kindness and helpfulness on all sides, and I am proud to say
            that we have been honored tonight by the presence of such distinguished men,
            representing the <org>Zurich Department of Health</org> (<foreign rend="GER"
                >Gesundheitamt</foreign>), and the <org>Zurich Department of Social Welfare</org>
                (<foreign rend="GER">Wohlfahrtsamt</foreign>), as Councilor (<foreign rend="GER"
                >Stadtrat</foreign>) Dr. <person reg="Häberlin, Heinrich">Häberlin</person> and
            Councilor (<foreign rend="GER">Stadtrat</foreign>) Herr <person reg="Gschwend, Herr"
                >Gschwend</person>.</p>
        <p>
            <del>We had no idea or desire to invade the precincts of this delightful country,</del>
        </p>
        <p>The object of this Seventh International Conference is to discuss freely among the
            workers all questions relating to the methods and technique of contraception to present
            facts based upon past experience and to suggest plans and programs for research. We
            cannot know what we need unless we know what we already have. This is in essence to be a
            fact-finding conference, and we shall not be concerned with nor attempt to express our
            opinions on birth control in conjunction with politics, religion or morals. We take it
            as an accepted fact that the workers in this field are already convinced of its
            importance. Therefore we do not need to be further converted. I ask you therefore,
            during the sessions beginning tomorrow and ending Friday noon to leave aside all
            controversial issues except those based on the experience of medical and scientific
            study and fact. </p>
        <p>
            <add>In this way only [<unclear>we</unclear>] can take an accurate inventory of our work
                and be guided accordingly for progress in the future.</add>
        </p>
        <p>
            <add>Now again I extend to you a hearty and cordial welcome to this conference.</add>
        </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
