<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2012-04-02 AW Intitial Tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2012-04-04 CH Proofed Tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-08 EK clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1935-10-30">30 Oct 1935</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Statement Before Birth Control Campaign in
                East</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp143732</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress Microfilm</bibl>
            <bibl>LCM 130:587</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="India" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="overpopulation and"/>
        <index level1="family size"/>
        <index level1="family size" level2="class-based"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="efforts to reduce"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="economic benefits and risks of"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="maternal"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="infant"/>
            
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>STATEMENT BY MARGARET SANGER BEFORE HER BIRTH CONTROL CAMPAIGN IN
            THE EAST</head>
        <dateline>OCTOBER. 30th. 1935</dateline>
        <p>I have been invited by the <org>All India Women’s Conference</org> to
            address that great body when it meets in <place>Travancore,
                India</place> in December and to conduct a campaign for birth
            control throughout the Country.</p>
        <p>The first thing I must make clear is that I am not going to
                <place>India</place> in order to persuade everybody to have a
            small family. I want rather to convince them of the
            desirability--for themselves and posterity--of having families of
            the right size and right quality. We all agree that healthy parents
            of good stock, and with an income that will support several
            children, should have them; and if they have normal instincts will
            want to have them. Do not imagine that the practice of birth control
            is unknown in India. But there, as in the Countries of the Western
            World (as in <place>England</place> and <place
                reg="United States">America</place>), it is still
            highly concentrated among the economically most prosperous and the
            educationally best endowed classes. So in my campaign I shall not be
            introducing into India views and a practice that do not to some
            small extent exist there already: But I hope to produce a better
            distribution of birth control practices, that is to say to
            disseminate it among the social, economic and biological classes in
            which it is most urgently needed. It is said that birth control
            to-day is dysgenic that it is resulting in ever smaller
            contributions to posterity from biologically well endowed families,
            while contributions from those families whom posterity could most
            easily spare have hardly abated in size since the Victorian day. I
            shall try to persuade the people of India that the remedy for this
            dangerous situation is not less birth control--a futile endeavor to
            turn the clock back--but more birth control. The control over their
            numbers that is now being exercised by responsible, well educated
            persons throughout the world must be exercised also by those who are
            not so well endowed in nature or so favorably treated by economic
            circumstances.</p>
        <p>In my campaign I shall not presume to dictate to anybody in India
            what constitutes the proper income level for justifying each
            addition to the family. That is a matter that parents must and
            should decide for themselves. But there is nothing magical in an
            income; and I believe that every parent can be made to realise that
            an income which will just suffice to support x children will fail to
            support x plus 1 more. On the other hand, I shall make it clear that
            the estimate of how far an income can go must not be based simply on
            luxury. I know parents who regard an annual income of £5,000 as just
            sufficient for a one child family. That seems to me in its way as
            fantastic as the kind of sum suggested by government departments--I
            believe in your country it is now or shortly will be three shillings
            a week--as sufficing for the food, clothing, shelter and civilized
            amenities of a child of the working classes.</p>
        <p>A word about population problems. It is not my intention to tell the
            people of India that their great country is over populated in any
                <emph rend="underline">absolute</emph> sense. Nobody knows how
            large a population India could support if all her economic resources
            were properly developed and if the products of industry and
            agriculture were equitably distributed. But in a relative
            sense--relative that is to say to her actual resources--India in
            common with <place>Japan</place> and other countries of the East is
            indubitably over populated. The ultimate solution of this problem
            may perhaps be in an economic reorganization; but I believe birth
            control can make the most efficient contribution to a short-term
            solution. In any case, that is not the main basis of my campaign.
            Birth control may or may not offer a solution for population
            problems: What it certainly does is contribute to the health,
            happiness and mental poise of individual families.</p>
        <p>I shall show in my campaign that the Indian maternity and infant
            mortality rates are a direct consequence of the present birth rates;
            that if we want to lower the former we must lower the latter. I
            shall show too that the low expectation of life in India is a
            consequence of the high birth rate, and can be raised by bringing
            that rate down. Above all, it will be my purpose to convince the
            great Indian people that between the practice of birth control and
            their highest conception of ethics and religion there is no
            inconsistency whatever.</p>
        <p> Birth Control is one of the great liberating forces of mankind. Like
            the control of infection by asepsis, the control of pain by
            anaesthesia, the control of communicable diseases by the methods of
            preventive medicine, it is one step in mankind’s mastery over the
            blind forces of nature, a measure of his civilization and growth to
            maturity. It is in that aspect that I shall present birth control in
            my coming campaign in the East.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
