<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-02-06 JC encoding</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-02-06 CH proof tags &amp; enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1929-00-00"><supplied resp="MSPP">1929</supplied></docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>Birth Control</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp156569</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="book">Social Work Year Book Vol. 1</title>, New York: 1929, pp.
				38-40. </bibl>
			<bibl><title>Library of Congress Microfilm 76:243-244</title></bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name/>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>For an essay published in the 1933 volume, see <xref from="321976.xml">Birth
				Control"</xref> 1933.</p>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="history of"/>
		<index level1="birth control movement" level2="history of"/>
		<index level1="birth control movement" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="birth control movement" level2="goals and strategies"/>
		<index level1="birth control movement" level2="international"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<div>
			<head>BIRTH CONTROL</head>
			<p>The general aim of the birth control movement is to legitimatize the practice of
				contraception through scientific and hygienic methods, and to educate the adult
				public as to its advantages from the personal and social points of view.
				International in scope, the movement has been known under a number of names; in the
					<place reg="Great Britain">British Empire</place> as “neo-Malthusianism”; in
					<place>France</place> as “conscious generation”; and occasionally as “voluntary
				parenthood.” </p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<head type="sub">History and Present Status.</head>
			<p>In English-speaking countries the present movement derives from <person
					reg="Malthus, Thomas Robert">Malthus</person>. In the second edition of his
				famous <title type="book">Essay on Population</title>, published in 1903, the
				English clergyman first enunciated his law of the pressure of population upon the
				means of subsistence. The only solution he suggested for overpopulation was the
				practice of celibacy and late marriage. In 1826 Dr. <person reg="Knowlton, Charles"
					>Charles Knowlton</person>, a <place reg="Boston, MA">Boston</place> physician,
				was prosecuted for publishing a small book, <title type="book">The Fruits of
					Philosophy</title>, advocating mechanical and chemical methods of contraception.
				In 1876-1877 <person reg="Bradlaugh, Charles">Charles Bradlaugh</person> and
					Mrs.<person reg="Besant, Annie"> Annie Besant</person> were prosecuted and
				convicted for distributing that book among the working classes of Great Britain.
				Their conviction led to the foundation of the <org>Malthusian League</org> in 1878
				by <person reg="Drysdale, Charles Robert">Dr. Charles Drysdale</person> and his
				wife, <person reg="Vickery, Alice">Dr. Alice Vickery Drysdale</person>. A <org
					reg="Nieuw Mathusiaansche Bond">Dutch League</org> was founded in 1881. The
				neo-malthusians differed from Malthus in advocating contraception to prevent
				overpopulation and to reduce the birth rate. </p>
			<p>The period between 1914 and 1921 in the <place>United States</place> was one of
				militant agitation and widespread publicity, partly as a result of several
				convictions of persons active in the movement for challenging federal and state
				laws. In <place reg="New York, NY">New York City</place> in 1914, Mrs. Margaret
				Sanger began to advocate contraception on feministic and libertarian grounds,
				coining at that time the term “birth control.” The interest awakened in the whole
				question of contraception resulted in 1921 in the foundation of the <org>American
					Birth Control League</org> and of the <org>Voluntary Parenthood League</org>;
				also in the publication of a monthly periodical, the <title type="journal">Birth
					Control Review</title>, edited by Mrs. Sanger. The two organizations were
				subsequently combined under the name of the former. </p>
			<p>Activities of the second period of the American movement, from 1921 to 1925, included
				the organization of local leagues, the education of public opinion, and campaigns
				for the amendment of statutes which class the practice of contraception with
				obscenity and criminal abortion. During the third period, 1925 to the present,
				advocates of birth control have concentrated upon the establishment of clinics and
				research bureaus, and upon enlisting the interest and activities of physicians,
				biologists, biochemists, and social scientists generally. Results of these efforts
				are seen in the fact that no less than 55 clinics and bureaus are now operating
				legitimately in the United States (covering 23 cities and 13 states), dispensing
				contraceptive information to all persons legally permitted to receive it. In
					<place>New York</place> State it is given to married people for the cure or
				prevention of disease. In <place>California</place> there are 12 clinics; there is
				one each in <place reg="Baltimore, MD">Baltimore</place>, <place
					reg="Cincinnati, OH">Cincinnati</place>, <place reg="Cleveland, OH"
					>Cleveland</place>, <place reg="Denver, CO">Denver</place>, <place
					reg="Detroit, MI">Detroit</place>, <place reg="Newark, NJ">Newark</place>,
					<place reg="New Haven, CT">New Haven</place>, and <place reg="Philadelphia, PA"
					>Philadelphia</place>; there are six in <place reg="Chicago, IL"
				>Chicago</place>; and New York City has eight in hospitals and one operating
				independently. In addition, a branch for colored women has recently been established
				in the Harlem section of New York City by the Clinical Research Bureau. </p>
			<p>The year 1929 was marked by the establishment of 27 new clinics. The successful
				operation of such clinics and research bureaus, under medical direction, makes
				possible the scientific analysis of individual cases, and also statistical studies.
				Through the latter material is being developed for the replacement of untested
				theory with impartial analysis. Social agencies are beginning to cooperate with such
				clinics. Owing to the widespread change in public opinion, physicians are more
				willing to give advice in private practice. Over 10,000 of them have expressed
				willingness to do so.</p>
			<p>The birth control movement is exerting a noticeable influence upon eugenics and
				giving a new direction to programs for race-betterment; it has resulted in renewed
				consideration of the problem of the legal sterilization of the unfit; and has
				influenced programs for the control of the dependent, delinquent, and defective
				groups in society. It has been given consideration by many social agencies seeking
				to decrease maternal and infant mortality rates, particularly by the <org
					reg="National Committee on Maternal Health">Committee on Maternal Health</org>
				of New York City. Financial support of the birth control movement has been from
				independent and anonymous sources, with the exception of temporary support from the
					<org>Brush Foundation</org> of Cleveland. During 1929 a study of 10,000 cases
				was made by the <org>Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau</org>, and a study of
				fertility and sterility by the Committee on Maternal Health. </p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<head type="sub">Legislation, 1929.</head>
			<p>No laws on the subject were passed during the year. Bills to amend the laws which
				prohibit contraceptive instruction were defeated in New York and
					<place>Connecticut</place>. </p>
		</div>

		<div>
			<p><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
			</p>
		</div>

	</docBody>
</doc>
