<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Printed article ">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2003-07-01 SB</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2003-07-28 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2012-05-29 AW Correct Tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-10 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-12-11 CH proof tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-12-11 CH enter corrections</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1922-04-00">Apr 1922</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Woman's Power &amp; Birth Control</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp201364</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">The Kaizo</title> Apr. 1922, pp. 147-157.</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="BIB">Bible</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="abortion"/>
        <index level1="abortion" level2="health risks of"/>
        <index level1="abortion" level2="illegal"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="continence"/>
        <index level1="eugenics"/>
        <index level1="family size"/>
        <index level1="family size" level2="class-based"/>
        <index level1="famine"/>
        <index level1="&quot;feeble-minded&quot; persons" level2="allowed to reproduce"/>
        <index level1="heredity" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="infanticide"/>
        <index level1="marriage"/>
        <index level1="marriage age" level2="women"/>
        <index level1="mentally disabled and diseased"/>
        <index level1="mentally disabled and diseased" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="mentally disabled and diseased" level2="fertility of"/>
        <index level1="motherhood"/>
        <index level1="overpopulation"/>
        <index level1="overpopulation" level2="effects of"/>
        <index level1="physically disabled and diseased" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="population" level2="war and"/>
        <index level1="population growth" level2="regulation of"/>
        <index level1="population growth" level2="standard of living and"/>
        <index level1="poverty"/>
        <index level1="poverty" level2="family size and"/>
        <index level1="quackery"/>
        <index level1="sex" level2="marriage and"/>
        <index level1="venereal disease"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="employment of"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="freedom and rights of"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
        <index level1="working classes"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Woman's Power and Birth Control.</head>
        <byline>By Mrs. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret H. Sanger</person>.</byline>
        <p>It is not asserting too much to say that the gravest question the world faces at the
            present moment is the numbers and quality of its inhabitants. There are nations in which
            over-population is already chronic, and in which the surplus numbers are swept away from
            time to time by the cruel natural forces of nature--famine and pestilenes.
                <place>China</place>, <place reg="Soviet Union">Russia</place> and
                <place>India</place> show the workings of natural law when man leaves this most
            important question to chance. Other nations look forward with fear to the time when more
            space must be found for their teeming populations, and the result is wars and
            preparations for “expansion,” whilst others prepare to defend themselves against the
            aggressions of those with more rapidly expanding numbers. Until recently the
                <place>United States</place> was the greatest expansion ground for the world. Relief
            could be found there for the pressure of numbers in European countries. But America is
            shutting her gates, and the empty places of the world in both hemispheres are now
            rapidly filling up.</p>
        <p>Nor can we comfort ourselves with the reflection that the struggle for existence will
            serve to improve the race--that the strong, the capable and the intelligent will survive
            and that the weaklings and those of inferior mind and body will be eliminated. The
            struggle for existence does not have these results in human society. Artificial
            restraints of civilization and law prevent the struggle from being a fair trail of
            strength and endurance, such as it still may be among wild animals. The wealthy are
            sheltered behind their possessions, and the police of every country prevent the strong
            from snatching from the weak.</p>
        <p>Overpopulation means a continually increasing degradation of the poor. The poor man with
            a large family to support must accept any wage that is offered. His very need for more
            than his fellow work-man who is young and single, compels him to accept less--in the
            fear that he will get nothing. His family is underfed, underclothed, undereducated and
            not decently housed. His wife, worn out with excessive labour, is unfit for child
            bearing; yet continues to bear children. Some children die, some survive. For every
            chile that dies in the struggle, there are three of four who grow up stunted, and
            unfit.</p>
        <p> So it is in the case of famine and pestilence. Such visitations do not sweep through the
            community like a fire, carrying away the rotten members and leaving the sound untouched,
            with new room for expansion. They attack men, women and children, the best as well as
            the worst. Many they kill, and these are not always the weakest and the least desirable.
            But those they leave behind are in many cases a worse liability for the nation than
            those that were slain. A glance at the famine pictures of <place>Austria</place> or
            Russia tells what these nations have to cope with in the case of hundreds of thousands
            of human beings who have survived famine and pestilence, but who will all their lives be
            a burden rather than an asset to society.</p>
        <p>Nor is war any remedy. The pick of the men of the nation are taken for war, leaving the
            infirm and unfit to breed the new generation. With the results of the world-war before
            our eyes, who can claim that the result has been eugenic for <place>France</place>, for
                <place>Germany</place>, for Austria, for <place>England</place> or for any country
            that took part in it. From any and every point of view we find that men cannot trust to
            the blind forces of nature for the improvement of his race; but that if he desires
            improvement, he must use his intelligence and his will power and win it for himself.</p>
        <p>All these facts have been perfectly well known for generations. In the meantime, science
            has advanced and in almost every other field except that of the improvement of his own
            race, man has become the master of nature. He has discovered the laws of physics, of
            light and electricity. He has overcome the force of gravitation and made the air his
            highway. He has annihilated distance and made possible instantaneous communication with
            the ends of the world. He has even to a great extent conquered disease, and lengthened
            the lifetime of the average man of woman who survives infancy. But before the problem of
            overpopulation he has wrung his hands in helplessness, and the multiplication of the
            unfit goes on as though man were the subject, not the master of nature.</p>
        <p>What is the answer to the problem? Is civilization to be at the mercy of the terrible
            tendency of human beings to multiply beyond the power of human intelligence to provide
            for them-–beyond the possibility of the motherland to contain them? Must every nation
            look forward to exiling a proportion of its best inhabitants, if those who remain are to
            be fed? And must every nation be kept in dread lest the overflowing multitudes of
            another country descend upon its shores and force it to fight for its very existence?
            Must the human race grow less fit, as time goes on, rather that more perfect? Must more
            than half of the men, women and children on this globe of ours suffer throughout their
            whole lives because there is not room enough, not food enough, not opportunity enough to
            allow them their full development?</p>
        <p> The problem has not gone without attention. A new science–-the science of Eugenics-–is
            coming into being, and men and women who are deeply concerned over the large proportion
            in our population of feeble-minded and unfit have put forward propositions for dealing
            with the danger. These Eugenists have grasped part of the problem. They are calling
            public attention to the multiplication of the unfit. They have held international
            congresses, and have put forward various proposals for securing a better balance in the
            population. They would put a ban on the breeding of children by diseased and
            feeble-minded parents, and they rightly demand that society undertake the responsibility
            of caring for those of its members who are not capable of guiding their own lives. But
            they do face fairly the whole problem. Looking to the equality of population they leave
            out the factor of quantity. They seem to believe that by some form of government
            regulation, the multiplication of the fit could be encouraged, and that of the unfit
            prevent. They overlook the fact that to keep fit, there must be food, housing education
            and opportunity for each new comer, and that good stock cannot prevent deterioration and
            unfitness if the pressure be excessive.</p>
        <p>The way out will not be found through the making and enforcing of more laws and more
            government restrictions. The problem is not so insoluble as it appears to those
            scientists and statesmen who consider it from the point of view of men. The reason for
            the apparent impasse is that men have considered the problem a problem of their own–-one
            that they alone must solve. But reproduction is not primarily a man’s problem. It is the
            woman’s problem. The woman bears the child. It is her function to bring it into the
            world, to nourish and care for it, and to give it its start in life. It should also be
            her function to restrict the number of children to which she will give birth; to keep
            this number within the limits of her own strength and power, and within the limits set
            by the wages earned by her husband, the home in which they are able to dwell and food,
            clothing, education and nurture which are available for them.</p>
        <p> Women are not performing this duty. They are not able to perform it until they are given
            the liberty which is necessary before they can do it. They have been subjected so
            completely to the will of men that they scarcely realize their responsibility for the
            evils threatening the world through over-population. And yet it is true that women
            passionately desire the limitation of population. The spirit of woman rises up in revolt
            against the burden laid upon her of bearing children beyond her strength, children who
            are too numerous to allow her time for her own development, children who come into the
            world undesired and unwelcomed, a detriment to themselves, an oppression to the family
            and a menace to the nation.</p>
        <p>It was formerly a commonly held belief that the child belonged solely to the father. It
            was his “seed” and all that the mother contributed was the fertile soil in which this
            seed could grow and ripen until it was ready for birth. The law which gives the child
            into the sole power of the father reflects this old idea; and it partly due to this
            belief that the mother has been given so subordinate a position in the family. Modern
            science has proved that father and mother contribute equally to the inheritance of the
            child, and that the mother from her closer relation to the child both before and after
            birth exercises an influence over it far exceeding that of the father.</p>
        <p> This superior power of the mother over the child is easily realized when it is
            remembered that, although the father gives the fertilizing element which must unite with
            the ovum, or egg cell of the mother before a new life came into being, the mother
            carries the developing cell for nine months in her own body. During these months it is
            the blood of the mother that feeds the child. If the mother is over-worked, is out of
            health, or is infected with disease, all these conditions are bound to have their
            influence on the child. The inheritance on both sides might be excellent. Both sperm
            cell and ovum might be from good wholesome stock, from parents and grand-parents of
            sound and healthy bodies and intelligent minds. But if during the nine months of
            pregnancy, the woman is unable to give the child due nourishment, if her blood is
            poisoned from over-fatigue, from the worry that rests so heavily upon the expectant
            mother who knows that the coming infant with still the bread from her other children,
            who can expect a strong and healthy child? The breeder of animals would not allow his
            cows or his mares to be overworked and harassed when they were carrying the young. He
            would care too much for the welfare of both mother and progeny to risk the almost
            certainty of band results from such treatment. It would seem that men have never given
            to women the consideration that is given by every good farmer or horse owner to the
            prospective mothers of their calves and foals.</p>
        <p>While women have not realized their responsibility for the evils that afflict the world
            through over-population, it has never been their will that too many children should be
            born. Woman is the true eugenist, and it is not only her desire for her own life–a
            desire which has long seemed right and proper for men, but which is often denied to
            women–but also her passion of mother love that makes her cry out in rebellion against
            the bearing of child after child for whom there is no room and no opportunity.</p>
        <p>Always through the ages women have been in rebellion against too much child bearing. At
            various epochs this rebellion has been shown in infanticide–-infanticide which has been
            the net of the mother even more than the father.</p>
        <p>At other times abortion has been called into service to rid the woman of the undesired
            child. laws have been passed against both these practices, but they have never been
            abolished, and one wonders whether they have been greatly checked. Yet both these
            remedies for over-population are abhorrent to the women who have resorted to them; and
            it is only in desperation, because they seem the lesser of two great evils, that they
            have been adopted.</p>
        <p>There are conditions in which a woman should not bear children at all. These conditions
            may exist either in herself or in the man to whom she is married. Such conditions are
            present when either man of wife is suffering from such diseases as tuberculosis,
            syphilis, gonorrhea, cancer, epilepsy, insanity or any mental disorder, or is addicted
            to drunkenness or to some drug habit. While it is not believed that most of these
            diseases can be inherited, it is known that a tendency to disease can be handed down
            from parent to child. The increase in tuberculosis cases is attributed to the fat that
            the doctors keep alive to propagate their kind many men and women who formerly would
            have died before parenthood. They do not bequeath tuberculosis to their children
            directly, but the children probably inherit a greater liability to the disease than the
            children of normal parents.</p>
        <p>Syphilis can be inherited–-“<q who="BIB">unto the third and fourth generation</q>.” There
            is no prenatal force which is so murderous for infants as this dread form of venereal
            disease. The babies in any syphilitic ward of a children’s hospital for a heart-rending
            spectacle–-quite sufficient to convince any reasonable creature that breeding from a
            syphilitic stock is criminal as well as insanely foolish. As for the other diseased
            mentioned, and as regards also drunkenness and drug habits who can believe that parents
            so afflicted can produce and rear children who will be anything but a liability to the
            nation.</p>
        <p>Besides these diseases which ought to debar both parents from reproducing their stock,
            there are many conditions peculiar to the woman which ought to be taken into
            consideration before she enters upon pregnancy. She ought to be old enough for full
            development. She ought to be healthy and not suffering from recent illness or over
            fatigue. If she is affected with heart disease, kidney trouble or pelvic deformity, she
            risks her life if she bears a child, and no such risk should be imposed upon her without
            her knowledge and without her giving her free consent.</p>
        <p>It happens sometimes that a man and a woman, both apparently healthy and sane, have
            defective children. In cases like this, however much they may desire parenthood, they
            have no right to impose the burden of such defectives on society, or to risk the injury
            that such children may do to the race if they in their turn become parents of
            defectives. The descendants of a single feebleminded woman whose family has been
            carefully traced in <place>Massachusetts</place>, have been reckoned up into the
            hundreds with an expenditure of dollars by society on court trials, pirsons, and asylums
            for the army of criminals and defectives among them.</p>
        <p>Leaving aside these cases where some form of disease makes child-bearing unwise for the
            parents and anti-social for the nation, we still to consider the normal healthy woman,
            and to decide whether in her case child-bearing should be left to chance. There are
            again two points of view from which to judge the matter–-the point of view of society,
            and the point of view of the woman herself. Fortunately the decision from both points of
            view is usually in close agreement; because what is bad for the woman is usually bad for
            society; and society is only benefitted by the addition to its members of healthy, well
            nourished and well reared children.</p>
        <p>The bearing of children by very young mothers is not desirable. As soon as pregnancy
            begins, the mother’s own development has arrested. The child-mother is therefore stunted
            in growth both in mind and body. She remains a child and never attains to the level to
            which her innate powers and inherited possibilities would have tended. Every breeder of
            animals understands this natural law, and keeps his young heifers or mares from breeding
            until they are grown and developed and ready for the strain. It is commonly asserted
            that women mature earlier than men, and that in oriental countries they are ready for
            marriage at a much younger age than in the United States. But it should be remembered
            that maturity of a kind comes with arrested development for either boy or girl, and the
            longer girlhood and later maturity of the American boys and girls who are given longer
            education and freedom from responsibility shed considerable light on the forcing process
            which for so long has made women out of really immature girls.</p>
        <p>For the sake of the children, as well as for the sake of her own possibility of
            developing all that is in her, a girl should not become a mother before she is
            twenty-two years old. In America, girls are not fully ready for motherhood before they
            are twenty-five. The children of a woman has been given time to mature fully before she
            commences to reproduce will be better fitted for life and probably in every way better
            equipped than the children of very young girls. The mother will also have had the chance
            of developing to a higher level mentally and will therefore be better able to rear and
            train her children.</p>
        <p>No woman should bear children without adequate intervals for recuperation. It is a
            tremendous strain to which the female body is subjected when it forms out of its own
            material the little life to which it gives birth. Following the birth are the months
            during which the nourishment of the child must be provided by the mother. Many women
            begin another pregnancy before the nursing period is ended, or at any rate immediately
            on its conclusion. There has been no time to lay up any reserve of strength in the
            mother’s own body and this process, repeated time after time, makes a woman old long
            before her years, drains her of health and strength and all capacity for enjoyment and
            reduces her to the drudge who loses all her influence over her swarming brood of
            children. The large family of such necessarily incompetent mothers are more likely to be
            a burden to society than an asset, and it is out of such homes that we get our supply of
            criminals and prostitutes.</p>
        <p>So far we have considered only the health aspects. There remains the very important
            question of the economy status of the family into which the child is to be born.
            Over-population of a country is not at the base general or national question. It is the
            definite result of too many children in the family of Mr. and Mrs. A and too many in the
            family of Mr. and Mrs. B. It is the sum of these little “too manies” that make the
            problem for the statesmen who see that there is no longer room in a country for all the
            progeny of its people.</p>
        <p>There would be no such problem if each Mr. and Mrs. X had limited the number of their
            children to the few that they could afford to rear–to feed and clothe, to accommodate
            decently in the home of which they could pay the rent, and to educate to the point where
            the children would be able to make a good start in life for themselves. The number of
            children so reared would keep up the population of a country. If opportunities widened,
            if more wealth offered, if discovers or inventions made possible the support of greater
            populations, then enlarged opportunities would induce parents to take advantage of them.
            Mother-love and father-love can always be counted upon to be willing to undertake the
            labor of rearing children, if the burden is not greater than men or women ought to
            bear.</p>
        <p>It might seem that the father, as wage earner, would be the one most concerned with the
            economic problem. Many a man is crushed under the weight of his ever increasing family,
            and relier would be to him the greatest possible blessing. One has only to compare the
            young man, entering happily and buoyantly on married life, full of joy in living, of
            hope and belief in himself and in the opportunities that the world will offer him, with
            the same man after ten years, with a houseful of children, who have arrived far more
            rapidly than his waves have increased. Probably his wife has become an invalid–-worn out
            with the overmuch bearing of children and with the labor of caring for them. He is
            hampered by debts, and unable to meet the expenses of so large a family. Instead of
            moving into a larger house, now that he has a family of eight–-six children in ten years
            is a common occurrence–-he is obliged to reduce the expense for rent, and the pleasant
            little home that he could maintain until after the second child was born has been
            relinquished for a crowded and shabby dwelling in the tenement regions.</p>
        <p>In spite of all this hardship for the man, it is the woman upon whom the economic burden
            weighs most heavily. It is she who has to make a home out of the sordid tenement, and to
            find room for the living and sleeping of all the members of the family. It is she who
            has to make the scanty wages cover the ever-increasing needs of the family. It is she
            who first feels the pangs of hunger–even though she may all the time be carrying another
            new life under her hearth. The pregnant woman should be well fed, or both she and the
            infant will suffer. But the mother will not and cannot feed herself sufficiently while
            husband and children go hungry. The man’s hours of labor are probably protected by his
            union rules, or by the general custom of the trade. But the hours of labor of the mother
            with a large family of little children know no limit, and the frequent illnesses of
            children, brought up with the insufficient food and other hygienic deficiencies,
            lengthen out these hours of labor until the day hold no more.</p>
        <p>The economic problem is much wider than the individual family. It touches all the workers
            of the world. The servitude of labor in every nation is usually in direct proportion to
            the rate of increase of the population. In facing its own problems, labor has to some
            degree recognized the evil due to the competition of numbers; but it has never fully
            grasped the connection between the birth rate and the wage rate. It has never been
            willing to acknowledge that the only solution of its difficulties lies in the limitation
            of families, and that until this is done, and done by the workers themselves, other
            remedies for low wages, long hours, and oppressive conditions are palliatives. They may
            do considerable good, but the incoming horde of workers is ever threatening their
            stability and labor can never be secure in its victories, until it is safe from this
            ever-increasing competition from its own children.</p>
        <p>The theories of Socialists and the attacks upon capitalism have served to absorb the
            minds of the Labor leaders and to distract their attention from the basal cause of their
            poverty, as compared with the wealth that they produce; and they seem to have overlooked
            the fact that no matter what benefits they could secure by a change in the industrial
            system all such benefits would disappear, leaving scarcely a trace behind, if they had
            to share them with ever-increasing numbers.</p>
        <p>The trade unions, especially those of high skilled workers, recognize the relation
            between high waves and small numbers. They have steadily fought for the limitation of
            the number of apprentices, and for making conditions of entrance into their unions
            difficult. But these same men have apparently not recognized the general solidarity of
            labor, nor the fact that the uncontrolled entry into the in the ranks of labor of the
            younger generation makes ever more difficult the maintenance of the advantages they have
            secured for themselves. Even if their policy secures their own livelihood, it does
            nothing to open up opportunities for their children who must find places for themselves
            in the working world.</p>
        <p>As for “free” labor generally-–we have only look at the state of the world after the
            state of the close of the great war. Millions of the most perfect physically, the most
            capable and most intelligent of the young of all the belligerent countries were killed
            or entirely disabled during the titanic struggle. There was a feeling during the war
            that the world would short of workers, and that it would be necessary for those who
            remained to produce more per man than ever before. Yet within these three years
            unemployment was the most striking fact that faced the workers, and in the winter of
            1921-22, in America, the richest country if the world, and a country which had suffered
            nothing from the ravages of war, there were instnaces of more than a hundred men
            applying for a single job of unskilled labor, and other instance of men, highly skilled
            in some trade, who from no fault of their own were begging the opportunity to earn a
            little by shoveling snow in the city streets.</p>
        <p>It is not only men who are competing against each other, and making more difficult the
            struggle for each of them. large families mean child-labor, and the children become the
            means of forcing down the wages of their parents. With a family of two or three
            children, the self-respecting working man can often afford to continue their education
            the high school, and even sometimes sent them to college. When the children number six
            or eight, the eldest must necessarily go to work as soon as they can get their working
            papers, and sisters and brothers follow each other into the labor market at the earliest
            possible moment.</p>
        <p>The more children a woman has, and the greater the burden upon her at home, the greater
            is also the necessity for her to go out and earn something to take out the family
            income. She is needed at home. The children will suffer from neglect if she goes to
            work. But the family must eat, and the greater need takes precedence. If she is still of
            child bearing age–and it is the woman still bearing children, whose family, on account
            of the youth of the elder children, most needs the earning power of the mother. Her
            health will probably break under the strain. Such a consideration cannot deter her. She
            goes to work under the lash of absolute necessity.</p>
        <p>These competitors in the labor market–-the women and the children-–are unskilled and
            unorganized. They are obliged to take low wages, in most cases any wage that the
            employer may offer, and thus their competition brings down the general level of
            unskilled labor. So runs the vicious circle–large families forcing more workers into the
            labor market, and more workers causing lower wages, which again increase the number of
            workers, through the forcing of women and children into the labor market.</p>
        <p> It is hardly necessary to emphasize further the importance of the problem; it remains to
            find the solution of it. Modern civilization has outgrown the crude checks on population
            offered by the customs of infanticide or abortion. These methods are still in use. If,
            in most civilized countries, parents have ceased to drown or expose their superfluous
            children, there are easy methods of allowing them to die for want of proper care of
            feeding.</p>
        <p>Abortion is far more common than infanticide. It has been estimated that the number of
            abortions in the United States every year amounts to not less than one million. Every
            such operation is illegal, and, being illegal, is not undertaken by reputable and
            well-trained physicians. Women, desiring to rid themselves of unwanted children, are
            therefore driven to quacks and ignorant practitioners whose methods aggravate enormously
            the ill-effects and the danger of the operation. Abortion skillfully performed at an
            early stage of pregnancy is much less drain on the strength of the mother than the
            normal birth of the baby. But abortion as usually performed on the poor mother, by the
            ignorant and unsanitary practitioner, is not only almost equivalent in its demand on the
            patient to natural birth. But also carries with it innumerable dangers to health and
            even to life itself.</p>
        <p>In any case–apart from the question of its morality–-abortion is a wasteful procedure.
            From the moment conception takes place the mother begins to give of her life and
            strength to the coming infant. Every day that pregnancy continues means just so much
            more of a drain on the mother. Even the most skillful abortion requires time and rest in
            order that the patient may recover, and all this repsents sheer waste of time and life
            and strength. Abortion is condemned, because it is a destruction of human life already
            in existence and because it is a waste of the health and strength of the women
            submitting to it. The answer to the problem is not to be found either in infanticide or
            in abortion.</p>
        <p>The solution advocated through the birth control movement lies in the prevention of
            conception. Prevention carries with it none of the waste of infanticide and abortion.
            Nature provides in vast super-abundance the possibilities of new life. She gives the
            man, in his semen, countless million of living cells, each of which under fit
            circumstances could fertilize an ovum. She gives the women thousands of ova, the greater
            part of which must necessarily fail to develop into new human beings. the most prolific
            of men and women could use for reproduction only a tiny percentage of the cells with
            which nature has provided them.</p>
        <p>To claim that it is perfectly right to allow a thousand ova to go to waste naturally, but
            wrong to prevent designedly the fertilization of the one thousand and first, is a
            proposition too absurd for serious consideration. To avoid childbearing by preventing
            the coming together of the male and female reproductive elements is what is done
            continually by the unmarried and the widowed, and by faithful husbands and wives absent
            from each other. To carry this process further and prevent conception when married
            people are living together is the problem that science is now solving, and with the
            solution she is making man master of his own fate, as he is already the master of almost
            every other natural force.</p>
        <p> Until modern science made known the exact nature of the vitalizing seminal fluid and the
            ova of the female, there seemed only one way in which the prevention of conception could
            be carried out. That was by continence–strict limitations of sexual relations to the
            very few occasions when procreation of a child was desired. There are still many
            advocates of continence as the only really moral method of birth control. Such advocates
            are making a demand of human nature which is beyond the power of average man and woman
            living together in happy marriage. It is also making a demand which is positively
            immoral, if morality is tested by the good or bad effect of conduct on human
            welfare.</p>
        <p>Sexual relations between men and women are the basis of family life. The more happy the
            marriage and the closer the affection and sympathy between husband and wife, the more
            intolerable the strain of continence, enforced in order to avoid the bearing of too many
            children. The restraint which is necessary for such continence produces the most
            markedly evil effects on both the man and woman. The man probaably suffers from such
            continence most severely, and there are few men or normally strong sexual emotions who
            can stand it for any length of time without developing nervous or even mental disorders.
            Continence may be possible and consistent with health for a very few abnormal men, and a
            small proportion of women. But it offers no solution for the great problem of the
            too-large family, because it is a course of conduct utterly impossible to enforce, and
            highly detrimental to health and happiness if it could be consistently adhered to.</p>
        <p> Nor is it necessary to impose this hardship on married people in order that they may be
            enabled to control the number of their children. The only thing necessary is to prevent
            the coming together of the vitalising male principle and the ovum, and means for
            preventing this are not beyond the reach of intelligent human beings. As yet there has
            been little careful scientific research into the subject and it may be that the methods
            hitherto used will soon appear crude and clumsy. The object of the advocates of Birth
            Control is not so much to teach any particular method of preventing the conception of
            the undesired child, as to arouse interest in the subject of over-population. Birth is
            the woman’s problem, and she must be put in a position to solve it for herself. She must
            have the right to her own body, and the right to choose when she will bear a child. If
            this right be made absolutely hers, there will be an end to the bearing children for
            whom the world has no room and no opportunities, there will be an end to the bearing of
            diseased and defective children, for even the most inferior mother had too much
            mother-love to desire to bring into the world a child who will cause her grief instead
            of joy, and be to her the deepest humiliation that a human being can know instead of the
            crown of glory of true and happy maternity.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
