<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Printed article ">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2003/07/02 SB</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-03-07 CH clean regs</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-14 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1923-04"> Apr 1923</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>Hail! Not Farewell</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp201479</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="journal">The Birth Control Review</title> Apr. 1923, 84.</bibl>
			<bibl><title type="mf">Margaret Sanger Microfilm Edition, Smith College
					Collections</title> S70:998</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name/>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<index level1="England" level2="birth control in"/>
		<index level1="Drysdale family, MS on"/>
		<index level1="Malthusian League"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Hail! Not Farewell!</head>
		<p>Doctor <person reg="Drysdale, Charles V.">Charles V. Drysdale</person> and Mrs. <person
				reg="Drysdale, Bessie Ingham">Bessie Drysdale</person> have resigned their offices
			in the <org>New Generation League</org> of <place reg="London, England">London</place>.
			This means a great deal. It means first of all that for the first time in seventy years
			the Birth Control movement in <place>Great Britain</place> has been deprived of the
			Drysdale leadership. For approximately seventy years the great idea has been guarded,
			cultivated, tended with all the courage and bravery of unflinching devotion. It has been
			mainly due to the disinterested, the loyal devotion of the Drysdales that the flame of
			our cause has been kept alive and not allowed to die out–-a torch burning more brightly
			now than ever before. From the early 'Fifties, when <person reg="Drysdale, George"
				>George Drysdale</person> first published his epoch-making gospel of Birth Control,
				"<title type="book">The Elements of Social <supplied resp="MSPP"
				>Science</supplied></title>," throughout the Victorian era, through the tempestuous
			days of the Great War, down to these chaotic days when the whole world has been
			desperately driven to a realization of the fundamental need for conscious control of
			populations, it has been these brave self-sacrificing Drysdales who have kept alive the
			idea. It has been a noble tradition of the Drysdale family–-this quiet unceasing
			service, this loyalty to the idea.</p>

		<p>George Drysdale, the valiant author of the "<title type="book">Elements of Social
					<supplied resp="MSPP">Science</supplied></title>" was the greatest nineteenth
			century prophet of Birth Control. The founder of the <org reg="Malthusian League"
				>Neo-Malthusian (New Generation) league</org> was not George, but his brother
				<person reg="Drysdale, Charles R.">Charles R. Drysdale</person>, and the latter's
			wife, Dr. <person reg="Vickery, Alice">Alice Vickery</person>, pioneer of feminism and
			freedom, a woman of such unflinching and far-sighted vision that she remains today an
			example for all who seek the liberation of womankind and the human race. The League was
			organized as an outcome of the celebrated <person reg="Bradlaugh, Charles"
				>Bradlaugh</person>-<person reg="Besant, Annie">Besant</person> trial in 1877–-the
			parent of all similar leagues existing in the world today. The advocate of Birth Control
			in those hyper-respectable days was looked upon by shocked Victorian eyes as a monster
			of profligacy and wickedness, one who was interested solely in the degradation of women.
			For two physicians boldly and openly to champion such a cause was to entail great
			professional loss and even ostracism. The Drysdales did not hesitate. Today they would
			see the seed they so courageously planted and cultivated bearing healthy fruits and
			grown into a world movement.</p>

		<p>The retiring president of the New Generation League is the son of Dr. Charles Drysdale, a
			nephew of George Drysdale. He has nobly carried on the Drysdale tradition, as has his
			wife Bessie Drysdale. The latter has indeed worked so hard as administrative director of
			the movement in <place>England</place> at the sacrifice of her health, that a long rest
			is now imperative. When, after openly challenging the Birth Control law of the
				<place>United States</place>, I went to study the European movement the first people
			in England to open their arms to me were the Drysdales. It was indicative of their
			breadth of vision that while they themselves did not need to challenge the English laws,
			they realized at once the importance and the educational value of such a course of
			action in the United States. Staunch and uncompromising has been their conviction
			throughout their long years of service. They have ever made generous financial
			contribution to the cause. Seeking always to keep the movement on a scientific and
			dignified level, they have ever come to the defense of persons arrested for the cause of
			Birth Control, regardless of whether the victim was intellectually in agreement with
			their personal opinions, whether he was Socialist or Anarchist, Democrat or
			Catholic.</p>

		<p>The Drysdale school of thought stems directly from <person reg="Malthus, Thomas Robert"
				>Malthus</person> and the individualist <place reg="Manchester, England"
				>Manchester</place> school of economics. It is a sturdy, rational, self-respecting
			and unsentimental doctrine that they have promulgated. They are opposed to current
			convictions concerning the dictatorship of the proletariat and the ever increasing
			demands of labor. And so their retirement, at the moment labor begins to awaken to the
			necessity of the conscious control of human procreation, exemplifies the same fine
			selflessness, the desire not to act as a hindrance, a check on the progress of the
			movement. Honesty, intellectual integrity, firm conviction--these fine qualities are
			synonymous with the name of the Drysdales. And their retirement from active leadership
			is one of the most eloquent expressions of this integrity of spirit. The younger
			generation bows in reverence and respect to the passing of the old. Hail! but not
			farewell.</p>
		<byline>MARGARET SANGER.</byline>
	</docBody>
</doc>
