<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2009/07/21 LL</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1931-11-00">Nov. 1931</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Mrs. Sanger in Rebuttal</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp201696</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
                <title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title>, Nov. 1931. </bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S71:0242</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="HANFR">Hankins, Frank</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="Book Review" level2="response to a"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>MRS. SANGER IN REBUTTAL</head>
        <p>TO THE EDITOR:</p>
        <p>I have read Professor <person reg="Hankins, Frank">Hankin</person>’s review of the book,
                <title type="book">My Fight for Birth Control</title> with much interest. I am
            particularly interested to note that the very things he considers as weaknesses are
            spoken of by <person reg="Ellis, Havelock">Havelock Ellis</person> as being its strong
            points. I have not Ellis’ letter with me to quote from, or I could give the exact
            phrases, which would, I am sure, amuse you.</p>
        <p>I should like to have Professor Hankins point out to me the “<q who="HANFR">other
                persons</q>” to whom “<q who="HANFR">full credit</q>” should be given. This is
            certainly something that I should want to correct. As I am already preparing for the
            next edition, I can very easily do this, if Professor Hankins will indicate to me the
            person or persons whom I have left out.</p>
        <p>Furthermore, to my knowledge, Professor Hankins was not familiar with the facts of the
            earlier movement--at least I never heard of him until after 1922--and if he has
            knowledge which I have not of the movement preceding these years, I certainly would like
            to get it.</p>
        <p>If Professor Hankins reviewed or read this book with the idea that it is a history of the
            movement or an autobiography, he is mistaken. It is neither, nor was it intended to be
            more than reminiscences of the part that one person played in the movement. In no place
            did I say that thousands of persons awaited my arrival at the Grand Central on my return
            from <place>Europe</place>. On page 78, I said that thousands of persons awaited the
            arrival of the children of the strikers of <place reg="Lawrence, MA">Lawrence,
                Massachusetts</place>. I think that part should be read again and corrected. One can
            see how easily diverted a reviewer can be when he starts out with a “blind spot”
            somewhere in his sub-conscious. </p>
        <byline>MARGARET SANGER.<lb/><emph rend="Italics"><place reg="New York, NY">New York</place>
                City</emph></byline>
    </docBody>
</doc>
