<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Autograph Statement">
<mepHeader>
<prepDate>2004/06/30 CH</prepDate>
<prepDate>2014-03-07 CH cleaning regs</prepDate>
<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
<docDate value="1922-04-30">April 30, 1922</docDate>
<docTitle>
<titlePart>
<supplied resp="MSPP">Will China Accept the Principles of Birth Control?</supplied>
</titlePart>
</docTitle>
<idno>msp203744</idno>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl><title type="journal">China Times (Shanghai)</title>, Apr. 30, 1922 </bibl>
<bibl><title>MSM</title> S70:953</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
<respStmt>
<resp/>
<name/>
</respStmt>
</mepHeader>
<headNote resp="MSPP">This article was published as a facsimile of <person reg="Sanger, Margaret"
>Sanger</person>'s handwritten statement.<index level1="China" level2="birth control in"/><index
level1="China" level2="MS on"/></headNote>
<docBody>
<p>Will <place>China</place> accept the principles of Birth Control?</p>
<p>This is the question asked almost universally by people of the Western world.</p>
<p>The general belief is that she will not accept these principles not because the benefits of such
would not be obvious to her but because she is so entrenched in the age long habits of other
beliefs, contradictory to Birth Control, that it would take a psychological revolution to upset
them.</p>
<p>Their contention is to let China alone--let her work out her population problems by herself. But
we will <emph rend="underline">not</emph> let China alone. The Western Nations have long invaded her
shores and not always to China's benefit. Now we know that Birth Control has been practiced in the
Western countries much to those countries benefit. Is there any reason to believe the same benefit
would not be right for China?</p>
<p>I believe China will accept Birth Control, not perhaps at one swallow, but rapidly in the next
few years. Already there has been great interest in the question, especially among the younger
generation. It is in that generation China's destiny is to change and it will change, perhaps
dramatically. And Birth Control must <supplied>precede</supplied> any great permanent change in her
social systems, for birth control is first &amp; foremost a principle of freedom and social right,
and next a great very great indeed economic expedient.</p>
<byline>Margaret Sanger</byline>
</docBody>
</doc>
