<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published document">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2010/02/24 AC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/03/10 EK clean regs</prepDate>

        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1933-06">Standard Date</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>An Open Letter to Social Workers</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp210358</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Birth Control Review</title>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith
                Collection, Smith College</bibl>
            <bibl><title>MSM</title>S71:0443</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Connecticut"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Federal"/>
        <index level1="Birth Control Review, The"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>An Open Letter to Social Workers</head>
        <byline><emph rend="italics">From</emph> Margaret Sanger</byline>
        <p>In addressing this letter to the assembled delegates of the <org>National Conference of
                Social Work</org>, I do so with a feeling of kinship in a common purpose. Too often
            I find an Alice-in-Wonderland attitude prevailing–with poverty, disease and kindred
            evils all seen as through a looking-glass, as spectres without substance. To the social
            worker, however, these are grim realities, calling on every ounce of courage,
            resourcefulness and commonsense in their solution.</p>
        <p> You who have dedicated yourselves to the welfare of others–you who are working to build
            bridges for families to pass from dependency to self-support–know full well that a
            knowledge of birth control must form the keystone of that bridge. You are already aware
            of the futility of pouring untold millions into palliative measures that disregard the
            obvious fact that without birth control, no permanent adjustment is possible between the
            size of a family and the family income.</p>
        <p> A unique responsibility is today vested in the social workers of <place
                rend="United States">America</place>, as a result of the gigantic increases that
            have taken place in the cost of public and private charities. For you are the
            intermediaries between the diseased, the defectives, the delinquent, and the dependent,
            and the vast agencies charged with the administrative responsibility of spending
            billions of dollars from public and private funds to help these groups. It is upon your
            recommendations that organization policies are established; and such policies must be
            reconciled with constructive race-building. Upon your vision, upon your intelligence, in
            this crisis, rests the welfare not only of countless troubled, worried parents, but also
            of the children born in the midst of the greatest depression in history, on whom we
            depend to carry on the torch of civilization.</p>
        <p> I want to express my gratitude to the large and increasing number of individual social
            workers who are courageously bringing a knowledge of birth control to families crushed
            under the burden of feeding and clothing a constantly increasing family upon a
            stationary or diminishing wage. Through your efforts many mothers have been enabled to
            secure scientific information from dependable medical sources. Our common problem today
            is: How can we make it possible for every mother to obtain this help? How can we break
            the vicious circle of overlarge families, poverty, infant and maternal mortality, child
            labor, marital discord, prostitution, and other social cankers all linking up directly
            to the difficulty of obtaining information so essential to the health of these mothers?
            How can we stop the senseless perpetuation of these evils?</p>
        <p> Birth control clinics in every community are essential. These can be established under
            present State Laws, and can operate within certain limitations of the State Statutes. In
            24 states no legal restrictions exist, and contraceptive advice can be given mothers for
            economic and social reasons as well as for health reasons. There are 133 birth control
            centres legally operating throughout this country. The present Federal Laws, however,
                <name type="law" reg="United States Criminal Code, Sections 211, 245, 311, and 312"
                >Sections 211, 245, 311, and 312 of the Criminal Code</name>, class contraception
            with obscenity and abortion. They make it a criminal offense to send or receive from the
            U.S. mails or common carriers, information or supplies pertaining to contraception. They
            make no exceptions for physicians, hospitals or clinics, who are forced to violate the
            law in order to obtain necessary supplies from the manufacturers. Consequently, we have
            the spectacle of 133 legally operating birth control clinics that have become veritable
            “speak-easies” as far as the general public is concerned. It is difficult for the
            mothers in the communities where these clinics are operating almost surreptitiously, to
            know of their existence, and the consequence is that although a mother may live within a
            few hundred feet of a center, she is usually unaware of its existence. On leaving the
            maternity wards, or applying to maternity centres, or lying-in hospitals for such advice
            it is refused her. Only if she can pay the fee of a private physician can she obtain
            scientific individual instruction. For obviously, the physician who takes the personal
            responsibility of giving contraceptive advice in his private office, cannot involve the
            medical institutions with which he is connected in a subject classed by our Federal
            Statutes as illegal. He is compelled to protect himself and his institution in his
            public practice. It is here that the Federal Laws take their greatest toll in keeping in
            ignorance the most needy mothers who are dependent on hospitals, public dispensaries and
            clinics for their medical aid. It is class legislation, a sanction of knowledge for
            those who can afford to pay for it, and ignorance and misery for those who cannot.</p>
        <p>
            <org>The National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control</org> has sponsored
            legislation in <org reg="United States Congress">Congress</org> that would exempt
            physicians, medical colleges, hospitals and clinics from the provisions of the above
            Statutes, in order to enable every hospital to legally provide birth control information
            as part of its routine preventative health service. The amendment of the Federal Laws
            represents a “short cut” to bringing this needed relief to the greatest number in the
            shortest possible time. Hearings on our legislation have been held before Senate and
            House Committees. Medical, social and religious organizations with memberships
            approximating many millions of individuals, have endorsed these efforts to bring our
            Federal laws in line with decency and commonsense.</p>
        <p> Much remains to be done. You who are in touch with actual conditions are cognizant of
            the need. I am grateful to those among you who have had the courage to take an
            unqualified stand on this question, and who have thrown the weight of your influence
            into persuading the welfare agencies with which you are affiliated to openly endorse the
            work of our Committee. Your leadership is inspiring those who are more timid to do
            likewise. Each individual and group endorsement helps, and is urgently needed for our
            work during the next session of Congress.</p>
        <p> I am also looking to the social workers with their vast experience to help broaden the
            horizon on this important subject. Unfortunately, there are still many who, while
            reluctantly recognizing the need for contraceptive advice in cases of heart disease,
            cancer, tuberculosis, hereditary and transmissible diseases, and other health conditions
            where pregnancy is known to aggravate the disease, sometimes resulting in death,
            nevertheless do not always see the deeper social and ethical principles involved. There
            can be no justification for violating the right of every married woman to decide when
            and how often she shall undertake the physical and far-reaching responsibilities of
            motherhood. It is mediaeval and barbarous to treat parenthood as a punishment for
            shiftlessness or recklessness. On the contrary, the woman sufficiently
            socially-conscious to desire to take parenthood out of the sphere of accident, should be
            aided in obtaining scientific information that will enable her to space the births of
            children in consideration of her health, her husband’s earning capacity, and the future
            health, environmental and educational opportunities for her children. Unless there is
            intelligent direction of the movement, however, we will have continued attempts to
            legislate contraceptive advice into the same category as abortions. Only last week, in
            Connecticut, an incredible bill was introduced, making it necessary for a woman to
            secure the consent of two physicians, one of them recommended by the State Board of
            Health and residing in an adjacent town, before contraceptive advice could be
            prescribed. This is an instance of the type of shortsighted legislation passed by
            lawmakers and paid for by the people.</p>
        <p>In closing, may I again point out that yours is the responsibility and privilege of
            rendering an unequalled patriotic service to your country by taking a stand that will
            help to forward this constructive work. Birth control is here, it is being practiced, it
            has already done great good. It can relieve the economic distress of countless families.
            Like all great forces, however, it must be directed, it must be accessible to all
            classes, so that it may truly become a constructive force for the regeneration of the
            race. </p>


    </docBody>
</doc>
