<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
<mepHeader>
<prepDate>2003/06/30 SB</prepDate>
<prepDate>2004/07/27 CH</prepDate>
<prepDate>2014-03-05 CH clean regs</prepDate>
<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
<docDate value="1920-03-00">Mar 1920</docDate>
<docTitle>
<titlePart>Wasting our Human Resources</titlePart>
</docTitle>
<idno>msp210421</idno>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl><title type="journal">The Birth Control Review</title> Mar. 1920, 9-11</bibl>
<bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S70:837</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
<respStmt>
<resp/>
<name id="USC">United States Congress</name>
<name id="VEILA">Veiller, Lawrence</name>
<name id="MOOHA">Moore, Harry Hascall </name>
<name id="ALLNA">Allen, Nathan</name>
<name id="KINWI">King, Willford Isbell</name>
<name id="BORWI">Borah, William Edgar</name>
<name id="NEASC">Nearing, Scott</name>
</respStmt>
</mepHeader>
<headNote resp="MSPP">
<index level1="birth control" level2="socioeconomic benefits"/>
<index level1="heredity" level2="disability and disease and"/>
<index level1="jails and imprisonment"/>
<index level1="unfit (to reproduce)"/>
<index level1="occupational health"/>
<index level1="United States" level2="government" level3="birth control and"/>
<index level1="United States" level2="government" level3="public health programs"/>
<index level1="United States" level2="socioeconomic conditions in"/>
<index level1="venereal diseases"/>
<index level1="women" level2="health of"/>
<index level1="heredity" level2="criminality and"/>
</headNote>
<docBody>
<head>Wasting Our Human Resources</head>
<byline rend="italics">By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></byline>
<p>One person in a half million, perhaps, has some sort of comprehension of the terrific rate at
which we people of the <place>United States</place> are wasting our most precious resources. These
particular resources are not rich soils, forests, mineral deposits and the like--though we waste
those prodigally, too--but the lives of the people. So-called "natural resources" are of no use
until they have been developed by the genius and skill of human beings. It is in the strength,
genius and skill, of the people that the real wealth of a nation lies. These qualities reflect
themselves in health, happiness and longevity, as well as in ability to utilize natural resources,
and these human assets we waste even more riotously than we do the assets which have come to use
from the generous hands of Nature.</p>
<p>The sum total of this waster, expressed in dollars, runs into incalculable billions, and this
does not take into account the still more terrible sum of misery brought about by our present
callous and unreckoning policy.</p>
<p>This condition will continue unabated while we have unlimited human resources to draw upon. We
have wasted our ">atural wealth" like a nation of "drunken sailors" and are only now beginning to
make the first faint effort to conserve it for sound uses. We will go on destroying our human wealth
in the same fashion until we come to the realization that this wealth also has its limitations. We
shall then, in the natural caurse of things, make better and higher use of this wealth and become a
truly great people. But we will do this only when, through Birth Control, we have limited the supply
of human beings and have brought to their senses those who are content now to waste human lives like
chaff.</p>
<p>In <title type="book">National Vitality, Its Wastes and Conservation</title> (<person
reg="Fisher, Irving">Fisher</person>), which is <org reg="United States Senate">Senate</org>
Document No. 416 of the <org reg="United States Congress">Sixty-first Congress</org>, it is shown
that "<q who="USC">in the <place>United States</place> there are probably at all times about
3,000,000 persons seriously ill, and every day 1,700 unnecessary deaths.</q>" It does not take long
to discover that the loss of the productive time of these 3,000,000 sick persons, most of whom,
perhaps, are suffering from the diseases recognized as preventable, runs into the billions. And
other sums of national wealth, equally staggering, are lost through the unnecessary deaths.
Seventeen hundred deaths a day is more than one death each minute, and even computing each life as
worth only $1,700 to the country, it means that the United States is wasting, in this item alone,
nearly $3,000,000,000 a year. The conservation of these lives and the proper utilization of these
human resources would pay off our national debt within a few years. If we could also apply to the
national debt the cost of caring for the unnecessarily sick, the United States could very shortly
face the world without a cent of financial obligation.</p>
<p>Of the 1,500,000 who die in the United States each year, according to the report quoted above,
150,000, or one in ten, are consumptives. One in six of the persons constantly and seriously ill are
also suffering from tuberculosis. Of the 20,000,000 school children in the United States, one in ten
will die of tuberculosis if they continue to die at the present rate, according the <person>Lewis M.
Terman</person>, in a report of a medical survey of the <org reg="Oregon Public School System"
>Public School System of <place>Oregon</place></org>.</p>
<p>Yet the United States has never taken any serious measures to deal with the "white plague." There
are associations of individuals who have been trying for years to arouse both the people and the
government of states and nation to this peril, but the terrible toll-taking goes on and the
governments, which have both the power and the resources to grapple with the problem, still neglect
to attack it in an effective manner. Meanwhile, except for more or less palliative state and local
measures, the causes of tuberculosis are permitted to operate in full force. Save where labor unions
have forced a shorter day, the hours of work continue to be so long as to exhaust completely the
worker and expose his system to the attacks of the ever present scourge. The Fisher report calls
attention to this fact thus: "<q who="USC">The present working day, from a physioligical point of
view, is too long, and keeps the majority of men and women in a continual state of
overfatigue.</q>"</p>
<p>An example of the extent to which individuals are permitted for their private profit to waste the
vital resources of the nation through maintaining breeding places for tuberculosis and other
diseases is that to which attention is called by <person reg="Veiller, Lawrence">Lawrence
Veiller</person>, in <title type="book">Housing Reform</title>, issued by the <org>Charities
Publishing Company</org> of <place reg="New York, NY">New York</place> in 1911. Said he: "<q
who="VEILA">In the lower East Side of New York City dwell 500,000 people, most of them immigrants.
In 1910 there were over 10,000 tenements with 'air shafts,' furnishing neither sunlight nor fresh
air.</q>"</p>
<p>During the year ending June 30, 1914, for example, there were admitted to the United States
1,250,00 immigrants, most of whom were compelled to seek the company of other millions who had come
in other years, in communities where the housing conditions were often but little better than those
described. While such conditions exist, there is little hope for curtailing either the sickness rate
or the death rate from tuberculosis in the United States.</p>
<p>Neither can there be hope of curtailment while 2,500,000 children are permitted to give up their
strength in factories, or men are compelled to kill the tissues of their lungs in ill ventilated
factories or in the "dusty trades" where the protection afforded them is too often inadequate when
such protection is afforded at all.</p>
<p>Again, the tuberculosis toll cannot be reduced to its lowest level until women are educated in
the use of contraceptives. Pregnancy renders tuberculosis fatal at certain stages and always
aggravates it. Moreover, to continue to deny tubercular women the use of contraceptives means that
every year there is a fresh crop of children coming into the world predisposed to the disease.</p>
<p>While the Great War was in progress, the United States government took a most commendable step
toward educating the people as to the danger of venereal disease. It was only a beginning, however,
and if the tremendous waste of vital wealth is to be competently checked, direct and vigorous
efforts must be made by state and federal agencies to arrest this scourge. Thus far, nothing
appreciable has been done, except to patch up a few of the wrecks and send them forth, quite as
likely as not, to communicate their diseases to others. <title type="journal">Bulletin No.
8</title>, issued in June, 1915, from the office of the <org>Surgeon General of the United States
Army</org>, showed that one man in five of the class from which men were drawn for the army suffered
from syphilis. It was estimated by Fisher, in the report referred to, that there are 2,000,000
syphiletics in the United States. Most of these syphiletics are perfectly at liberty to infect
others, if they are in the stage of the disease at which it is communicable. And the heritage of
syphilis is the heritage of disease in manifold forms, ranging from insanity or total physical
disability to general ill health. To say nothing of its huge total of physical and mental suffering,
this disease alone represents financial loss to the nation of billions.</p>
<p>Tuberculosis is not the only disease that reaps a rich harvest from the 2,500,00 child laborers
of the United States and from the weakly descendants of such laborers. The wearing out of the
youthful body, the lack of recreation, the sapping of the basic forces of life, brings all manner of
diseases to these unfortunates and if they are not claimed by death, they bring another crop of
human weaklings who in their turn become victims.</p>
<p>One of the expedients which we must inevitably adopt, in order that the problem of disease and
its causes may be intelligently handled, is that of registering the sick. Physicians should be
required to report all cases of serious illness each day. Simple records should be kept by
departments of health. Thus, the health authorities would have at their disposition a mass of data
that would enable them to plan and execute effective campaigns for the elimination of disease. The
individual, seeking to improve his own health, could consult these records which would cover his
health history from birth.</p>
<p>According to <person reg="Richards, R. C.">R. C. Richards</person>, chairman of the <org>Central
Safety Commission</org>, and to the <title type="book">Final Report of the (Federal) Committee on
Industrial Relations</title>, filed in 1915, there are 35,000 killed each year in industrial
accidents and 700,000 injured. Again the cost in misery, maintenance of the injured and loss to the
nation reaches an appalling total. As <person reg="Moore, Harry Hascall">H. H. Moore</person> points
out in <title type="book">The Youth and The Nation</title>, "<q who="MOOHA">this means that every
day in the United States nearly 100 are killed in industry and nearly 2,000 are injured--that one
man is killed every fifteen minutes and one is injured every minute, twenty-four hours a day.</q>"
The explanation is lack of proper safeguards--a greed for private profit that is each minute of the
day robbing the nation of untold wealth.</p>
<p> A still more far-reaching cause of loss of vital wealth than any yet mentioned is the want of
the masses, with its terrible harvest of unhappiness, disease and crime. <person
reg="King, Willford Isbell">King</person>, in his <title type="book">Distribution of Wealth and
Income</title>, estimates that "<q who="KINWI">over 50 per cent. of the wealth of the United States
is owned by only two per cent. of the people.</q>" Other authorities place the percentage of wealth
owned by two per cent. of the people nearer to ninety per cent. <person reg="Towne, Ezra Thayer"
>Towne</person>, in <title type="book">Social Problems</title>, says that there are probably
10,000,000 persons in the United States living in poverty, while there are 5,000,000 dependent upon
some form of public relief. Senator <person reg="Borah, William Edgar">Borah</person>, who is a
Republican presidential possibility, and who spoke presumably from the best figures that could be
compiled from information in the <org reg="United States Census Bureau">Census Bureau</org>, said in
a speech in the United States senate, August 24, 1917, that seventy per cent. of the families in the
United States had an income of $1,000 a year or less and that a man supporting a family thus is an
"<q who="BORWI">industrial peon</q>."</p>
<p>When these conditions prevail, what must be the terrible harvest of disease, rime ,and weakened
family stock, to produce through generations, more and more disease and crime! This in itself is
sufficient to wipe out a nation, but for fear these unfortunates may limit their numbers, the
governments of the nation and of most of the states use all possible means to stop the spread of
Birth Control information, which would automatically check the multiplication of this hardship and
social loss.</p>
<p>Only two of the factors of national loss and racial weakness springing out of a system that piles
up huge fortunes on one hand and slums on the other, can be considered here. The census shows that
in 1910 there were 100,000 children before juvenile courts, of which 14,000, mostly boys, were sent
to so-called corrective institutions. It is well know that these boys are more than likely to go to
penitentiaries or jail later on, owing to the influences surrounding them in reform schools.</p>
<p>As shown by the <org>National Child Labor Committee</org> in <title type="book">Pamphlet
276</title>, the juvenile delinquency increased thirty-four per cent. in <place
reg="Berlin, Germany">Berlin</place> during the war. It is hardly likely that the youth of the
United States has shown a more favorable reaction, and the conditions as to juvenile delinquency are
probably much worse than they were in 1910.</p>
<p>In 1910 also there were 11,498 persons in jails, penitentiaries and similar institutions in the
United States--and most of these, as every student of sociology knows, come out stamped with
disgrace and educated in crime.</p>
<p>The United States has yet to solve the problem of dealing with criminals and it has not yet
learned either to stop creating them or to permit overburdened mothers to so limit their families
that they will not bring into the world children who are in danger of becoming criminals.</p>
<p>As early as 1890 there were in the United States 400,000 feeble minded persons, according to
<person reg="Goddard, Henry Herbert">Goddard</person>, in <title type="book">Feeble mindedness; Its
Causes and Consequence</title>. This, taking into consideration the difficulty of detecting certain
degrees of feeble mindedness, the tendency of families to conceal mental defects of their members,
and the haphazard way in which statistics as to feeble minded are gathered, is probably a very low
estimate, even for thirty years ago. Be that as t may, something of the appalling result of
permitting the perpetuation of mentally feeble strains is shown by two classical examples. When it
is remembered that most of the feeble minded are free, either all their lives or at some time in
their lives, to reproduce their kind, the situation takes on an ominousness the bespeaks prompt and
effective action.</p>
<p><person reg="Kallikak, Martin">Martin Kallikak</person>, Jr., a feeble minded man, married
<person reg="Zabeth, Rhonda">Rhoda Zabeth</person>, a normal woman, in 1803. They had ten children.
From these children have come not less than 470 descendants, and of the progeny of Martin Kallikak,
Jr., there were 143 feeble minded, 36 illegitimate children, 33 sexually immoral persons, mostly
prostitutes, 24 confirmed alcoholics, 3 epileptics, 82 who died in infancy, 3 proprietors of houses
of ill fame and 3 criminals. Birth Control would have been an inestimable blessing there, and even
more of a blessing to the Jukes family.</p>
<p>There were 1,200 descendants of the founder of the Jukes clan in 75 years. Of these, 130 were
professional paupers, who in all spent 2,300 years in poorhouses, 50 prostitutes, 7 murderers, 60
habitual thieves and 130 common criminals. One authority estimates that the loss of potential
usefulness, cost of prosecutions, expense of maintenance and so on, for this family amounts to
$1,300,000 in 75 years.</p>
<p>There are thousands of Kallikaks and Jukes at large in the United States to perpetuate their
kind. Social agencies, physicians and <org>departments of health</org> have much to answer for when
they fail to tell women of such families how to avoid having children. Unfortunately, however, they
encourage rather than discourage this multiplication of misery and social loss through the
reproduction of such defectives as these.</p>
<p>There are several million women in industry in the United States. There are other millions who
work quite as hard or harder in their homes. These women are potential mothers, when not already
actually mothers, as in usually the case. Most of them are over-fatigued each day; most of them,
perhaps, are already suffering from disease. They achieve little relief by their labors. As <person
reg="Nearing, Scott">Nearing</person> pointed out in <title type="book">Wages in the United
States</title> (1911), "<q who="NEASC">probably two-fifths or more of the women wage earners earn
less than $6 a week.</q>" Wages are higher now, but in most cases, the rising prices have
outstripped the increase.</p>
<p>"<q who="ALLNA">It is now generally believed to be in accordance with the laws of hereditary
descent</q>," says Dr. <person reg="Allen, Nathan">Nathan Allen</person> in the <title type="book"
>Law of Human Increase</title>, "<q who="ALLNA">that the mother, not the father, transmits the
vitality and stamina, the strength of the physical system to the child. It becomes, then, vastly
important that the mother herself have the right kind of constitution.</q>" The time is coming when
we shall look back with horror upon our present policy of permitting the mother stamina to be killed
by toil. We shall also wonder why we were blind enough to compel a mother incapable of transmitting
strength to her children to bring such children into the world.</p>
<p>Can the nation endure with these great factors of destruction and waste operating unchecked? It
cannot. It will die as other nations have died and give place to more vigorous peoples.</p>
<p>What is the remedy? Only this--to take our vast stock of human wealth in hand. We have wasted it
prodigally because we have had an unlimited supply. We have had more than we could use in the
highest way and to the best advantage. We have been content with quantity, rather than quality. Let
it be repeated that we shall continue this course until we resort to the limiting of our numbers--to
Birth Control. When our numbers are cut down, these human resources will appear to us in their true
light--as the most precious of all our possessions. We shall guard the health and the happiness of
each individual for the service that he can render to himself and to the whole of society. We shall
make the best possible use of our material. We shall conserve human vitality for constructive social
uses. We shall guard it more zealously than we now guard our gold.</p>
</docBody>
</doc>
