<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
<mepHeader>
<prepDate>2003/06/30 SB</prepDate>
<prepDate>2004/07/27 CH</prepDate>
<prepDate>2004/08/06 CH</prepDate>
<prepDate>2014-03-07 CH clean regs</prepDate>
<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
<docDate value="1920-04-00">Apr 1920</docDate>
<docTitle>
<titlePart>Preparing for the World Crisis</titlePart>
</docTitle>
<idno>msp211397</idno>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl><title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title>, Apr. 1920, 7-8</bibl>
<bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S70:840</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
<respStmt>
<resp/>
<name id="GILFR">Gillett, Frederick H.</name>
<name id="HAYAR">Hayday, Arthur </name>
</respStmt>
</mepHeader>
<headNote resp="MSPP">
<index level1="birth rate" level2="decline in"/>
<index level1="child welfare"/>
<index level1="Martens, R. C."/>
<index level1="New York City" level2="working classes in"/>
<index level1="population" level2="excess"/>
<index level1="population" level2="food supply and"/>
<index level1="population control" level2="public reaction to"/>
<index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
<index level1="working classes" level2="conditions of"/>
</headNote>
<docBody>
<head>Preparing for the World Crisis</head>
<byline rend="italics">By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></byline>
<p>For three months we have been suggesting through this magazine that women cease bearing children
for five years--that is, until the world, most of which is disorganized industrially and
financially, shall have had time to right itself in one way or another. The suggestion has received
wide publicity in the daily press, and most of that publicity has been favorable. It has been
discussed from platforms, as well as in private and in small gatherings. Some of the discussion from
the platform has been unfriendly to a degree, some of it pronouncedly antagonistic. Many letters and
verbal comments from thinking people who are aware of the actual trend of world affairs have
confirmed the opinion that a cessation of births for a period of a few years will not only save an
unimaginable amount of misery, and give society a chance to put its house in order, but that such a
step is a prime necessity in our present situation.</p>
<p>Everywhere in <place reg="United States">America</place> the talk of a financial panic is
growing. It may not come within a few months or within the year, as predicted by <person
reg="Martens, R. C.">R. C. Martens</person>, whose series of interviews have appeared in these
columns, but the very fact that it is expected and that it is feared on every side, means that it is
inevitable. And that means industrial paralysis, unemployment and want.</p>
<p>Within a few days after <title type="journal">THE BIRTH CONTROL REVIEW</title> published one of
the Martens interviews, predicting a shortage of farm products in the United States, the <org>United
States Department of Agricultures</org> issued a statement in which it made substantially the same
prediction for the coming year. The report, based upon information gathered throughout the country,
said that there was a serious risk of reduced food production. And this when Europe is starving and
America is constantly being called upon to send food, either as a gift or upon credit.</p>
<p>The financial crisis, which Speaker <person reg="Gillett, Frederick H.">Gillette</person> of the
national <org>house of representatives</org> says is to be "<q who="GILFR">the worst in
history</q>," and the altogether probable food shortage of next year, are enough in themselves to
make every thinking mother refrain from bringing more children into the world until the situation is
stabilized. But such conditions as those mentioned bring in their train others which are worse--the
paralysis of industry and hunger among the masses.</p>
<p>Meanwhile the United States is not taking proper care of the children already here. To say
nothing of the two or three million child laborers, the hundreds who are perpetually undernourished
and the vast amount of preventable disease that is at all times with us, new factors and situations
are coming to light. The <org>Association for Improving the Condition of the Poor</org>, in <place
reg="New York, NY">New York</place>, for instance, is making a drive for nearly a million dollars,
and promises nothing better than mild palliatives for a situation which it describes in
disheartening terms. This drive is typical of many now in progress. Mayor <person
reg="Hylan, John F.">Hylan</person> of New York City is trying to find the way out of an intolerable
housing situation by an agreement between real estate operators, contractors and labor. There is no
apparent prospect of success. Rents have doubled upon the average, and no landlord seems to care to
have children in a building that has all the modern comforts.</p>
<p>Milk continues at 18 cents a quart in New York and despite the constant agitation, the price
doesn't seem to be inclined to come down. The housewife's dollar continues to be worth about forty
cents or fifty cents, as compared with a few years ago, and high wages seem to rule only in spots.
Moreover, there is a shortage of public school teachers in New York owing to the salaries paid.
Twenty-two hundred more teachers are needed.</p>
<p>The conditions mentioned are prevalent to a greater or less degree throughout the country, and on
top of it all comes the report of the <org>United States Bureau of Education</org>, showing that
owing to the low salaries paid teachers. 18,279 schools have been closed and there are 41,900
schools being taught by teachers who are not satisfactory.</p>
<p rend="italics">The fact is that we are not caring properly for the children now here and the
conditions which are in prospect for the near future will make it impossible to give even such care
to children as they are now getting. The sensible mother will have no more until conditions are
better.</p>
<p>The Soundness of the plan to curtail births until world affairs are sufficiently stabilized to
give a better prospect of providing for children, is being attested by a number of facts, most of
which are being brought to light by persons who become panicky every time the birth rate shows signs
of going down. Speakers are beginning to clamor for more births in the United States, which is a
good indication that a considerable percentage of the mothers have decided to bring no more children
into being until the newcomers can be well cared for. <place>France</place>, officially and
unofficially, is making a tremendous campaign, with bonuses and whatnot for mothers, in a thus far
futile effort to induce women to usher children into the disordered world.</p>
<p><person reg="Hayday, Arthur">A. Hayday</person>, labor member of <org>Parliament</org>, in a
recent speech in the Commons, served notice upon his fellow Britons that if the English imperialists
who are demanding more babies should attempt to speak in districts inhabitated by workers, <emph
rend="italics">they would be mobbed by women and that "<q rend="italics" who="HAYAR">there is
growing in this country today a woman's movement which may be called a birth strike</q>." This
strike would continue, he said, until the mothers were surer of being able to provide for their
children.</emph></p>
<p>Those who demand of the middle class and the laboring class more and more children, are sending
up cries from all corners of the earth that women are not bearing enough children. No nation is
exempt--even <place>Germany</place> with its firmly grounded "birth politics," has a falling birth
rate like the rest.</p>
<p>All of this means that women are already beginning to act instinctively upon the principle
involved in the suggestion made in these columns. It is but a step to the application of the
principle upon a broader scale. The call to women to cease bearing children until conditions are
better is born of the bitter necessity of the times. It springs from conditions--not from a theory.
The propriety and the common sense of it is as obvious as that of ceasing to overload a vehicle
which is already breaking down under its burden. The plan is Birth Control applied to the world,
just as it is applied to families--a limitation of numbers in accordance with our ability to
provide.</p>
</docBody>
</doc>
