<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="(Published Article) ">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/06/1947 YG</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1947-06-30">30 June 1947</docDate>
        <docDate value="1947-07-01">01 July 1947</docDate>

        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Moratorium on Babies</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp213352</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Smith College</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm Smith College Collections</title> S77:49</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="NYDN">New York Daily News</name>
            <name id="NYT">New York Times</name>
            <name id="EI">Evening Independent</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Sanger's statements to the press on leaving for
            <place>England</place>were picked up by newspapers in both the <place>United
                States</place> and England. Sanger's handwritten statement was likely written on
            arriving in <place>London</place>. Other quotes, taken from newspapers have been added
            on. Additional quotes taken from "10 year Moratorium on Europe Babies Urged," NY Post,
            July 1, 1947 "American Birth Control Pioneer Stirs British Anger," Evening Independent,
            and "Mrs. Sanger's Plan Opposed by Britons," NY Times, July 14, 1947.</p>
        <index level1="Europe" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="and war"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="civilization and"/>
        <index level1="war" level2="overpopulation and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Moratorium on Babies</head>
        <p>My message to the parents of the children in starving countries is to declare a
            Moratorium on the birth rate for the next ten years. Why ten years? I am asked. Because
            it is going to take from six to ten years for the world to get settled again and the
            conditions of poverty misery hunger and strife which exist in the world today are not
            the conditions in which to have and rear happy and healthy children. </p>
        <p>Women in war torn countries write me that they are giving birth to death not to life. To
            bring children into these conditions is not kind nor fair to those already born and to
            those unborn. So again I say to hungry mothers and fathers-declare the Moratorium on the
            birth rate, with which we can make a better world.</p>
        <p><supplied rend="MSPP">The following quotes came from the New York Daily News.</supplied>
            <q who="NYDN">A 10-year moratorium on babies in the world’s hungry countries was urged
                yesterday by <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Mrs. Margaret Sanger Slee</person>,
                noted advocate of planned parenthood, as she left <place reg="LaGuardia Airport"
                    >LaGuardia Field</place> for a family planning conference in England.</q>Those
            countries should not have another child for a decade, <q who="NYDN">she said.</q>They
            should do all in their power to help keep women from having children for that
            period-until the food and economic situations are adjusted there.<q who="NYDN">She said
                her plan “definitely” includes England. </q>I think the adults who are living today
            could be moved into those countries where they need labor,<q who="NYDN">she
                continued.</q>Use the manpower that’s there today, and don’t bring any more children
            into the world to starve. <q who="NYDN">Somebody asked who would fight the wars, and
                    <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Mrs. Slee</person>replied,</q>At least there
            would be fewer people to be battered to death.<q who="NYDN">Mrs. Slee left on the
                American Overseas Flagship Eire. She said that while abroad she also will work on
                arrangements for an international population conference to be held in <place
                    reg="Oxford, England">Oxford</place>next year. This will deal with the problem
                of populations in relation to the food supplies and natural resources of countries.
                She said all overpopulated countries, including <place>India</place>,
                    <place>China</place>, and <place>Japan</place>, would be invited to send
                representatives.</q>In this country we have achieved a favorable balance of
            population and resources,<q who="NYDN">she stated.</q> This situation has contributed
            greatly to the raising of our national standard of living.</p>
        <p>But it will do us little good if in the end European and Asiatic countries, and some of
            our possessions, continue to overflow their boundaries, crowd their resources and breed
            themselves into new famines. Many of them will ultimately breed themselves into another
            war. For these reasons the whole world should be interested in intelligent limitations
            of populations.</p>
        <p><supplied rend="MSPP">The following quotes came from the New York Times.</supplied>
            <q who="NYT">Mrs.Sanger’s Plan Opposed by Britons</q>I suppose my ideas will upset all
            my friends, <q who="NYT">Mrs. Sanger said. </q>Unsound? Not a bit of it. There is pretty
            heavy overcrowding in <place reg="England">Britain</place>. Adults could be moved to
            other countries instead of having babies here while food is short.</p>
        <p><supplied rend="MSPP">The following quotes came from the Evening Independent.</supplied>
            <q who="EI">It all started when gray-haired little Mrs. Sanger stepped off a plane and
                told the press:</q>It’s pretty certain that the world won’t be able to produce
            enough food to support any more babies for at least 10 years.<q who="EI">So, she said,
                women should stop having babies for 10 years-- in Britain, especially. She wanted
                <org>the United Nations</org>to recommend baby quotas for all countries.</q></p>

        <p/>
    </docBody>
</doc>
