<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011-09-09 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2013-04-23 CH Proof tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2013-04-29 AW Correct tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-07-02 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1955-01-00">Jan 1955</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Happy Birthday</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp213736</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Around the World News of Population and Birth
                    Control</title> Jan. 1955, p. 1</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S72:915</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>The byline was a facsimile signature.</p>
        <index level1="International Planned Parenthood Federation"/>
        <index level1="Around the World News of Population and Birth Control"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>HAPPY BIRTHDAY</head>
        <p>Happy Birthday to our international bulletin and congratulations to the <person
                reg="Brush, Dorothy">editor</person>. The <title type="journal">News of Population
                and Birth Control</title> is now three years old. The Chinese would say that it is
            four--according to their reckoning, life is one year old the day it begins. However,
            what difference is a year or two when progress and growth lead this little monthly paper
            steadily forward as they have ever since its birth.</p>
        <p>The beauty and simplicity of the contents give you, the reader, a vision of both achieved
            and potential aid toward the good life of your planned parenthood ideas. You can see at
            a glance how these ideals are permeating far-flung cities and countries--wherever people
            are united in interest for a new, civilized world. When this paper began realize that
            only four countries had initiated the <org>International Planned Parenthood
                Federation</org>: <place>Great Britain</place>, <place reg="Netherlands"
                >Holland</place>, <place>Sweden</place>, and the <place>United States</place>.
            Within this short time, fifteen members now belong to it. Already the News is translated
            into German, Italian, Japanese and Spanish. Shortly, <org
                reg="Hong Kong Family Planning Association">Hong Kong</org> will publish a
            bi-lingual paper, re-printing some of our bulletin in Chinese.</p>
        <p>My wish for the New Year is that the paper will stay as it is and not increase in size.
            Jewels come in small packages! Reaching us ten months of the year like a fresh breeze on
            an April morning, these four pages of quickly read, closely packaged, well edited facts
            present us all with a world’s eye view of the latest news of population and birth
            control.</p>
        <p>Let us all increase and multiply its circulation in every country around the world!</p>
        <byline><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></byline>
    </docBody>
</doc>
