<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published document">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2012-06-08 AW Initial Tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-17 EK clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1955-10-29">29 Oct 1955</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Votes of Thanks</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp214433</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="proceedings">The Fifth International Conference on Planned
                    Parenthood, Report of Proceedings, <place>Tokyo, Japan</place>,
                    1955</title>(<place reg="London, England">London</place>: 1956)</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm: Smith College Collections,</title>
                S72:0958</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>This document appears at the end of the Report of Proceedings, after Lady <person
                reg="Rama Rau, Dhanvanthi">Dhanvanthi Rama Rau</person> and Mrs. <person
                reg="KatÅ, Shidzue Ishimoto">shidzue Kato</person>'s messages of thanks.</p>
        <index level1="conferences" level2="International Conference on Planned Parenthood"
            level3="1955 (5th)"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head rend="italics">VOTES OF THANKS</head>
        <byline>Margaret Sanger,<lb/>
            <emph rend="italics">President, <org>International Planned Parenthood
                Federation</org></emph></byline>
        <p>Our efficient, capable and charming <person reg="Rama Rau, Dhanvanthi">chairman</person>
            has left practically nothing for me to say. I had hoped that she would leave a few
            things out of her congratulations and expressions of thanks, but she covered all except
            the Press, and then Mrs. Kato took that. But there is one group no one has yet mentioned
            -- the photographers, who were here early and late with their bulbs flashing, and thanks
            to them we have all been appearing in the newspapers. </p>
        <p>There is one to whom I want to give special thanks -- Dr. <person reg="Koya, Yoshio"
                >Koya</person> -- who is really the one responsible for sifting through and bringing
            most of the scientists and medical delegates to this conference. He has done a superb
            job. I also want to thank the <person reg="Shimojo, Yasumaro">President</person> of the
                <org>Family Planning Federation of Japan</org> for the wonderful reception he gave
            us. That will remain as something quite unique in our memories, the dinner by the light
            of the moon in the beautiful gardens of the Korinkaku Mansion. I also want to say what a
            splendid job was done on the mimeographed papers in the translations from Japanese into
            English, as well as by the interpreters at the meetings. </p>
        <p>We have all enjoyed these days, and I hope that you will go back to your own homes with
            what you have gained from this pooling of experience and knowledge and the wonderful
            contributions from the scientists. I feel sure we shall make great progress after this
            harnessing of the work of the international planned parenthood movement. Thank you for
            coming and for giving such splendid support to this conference in <place>Japan</place>,
            which is going to mean a great deal to us in every country. Hail and farewell. </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
