<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/04/11 YG</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/04/16 CH proof tags</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1938-10-22">22 Oct 1938</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Interview with The Memphis Commerical Appeal</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp214911</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <title type="article">Birth Control Clinic Wins Sanger Praise</title>
        <title type="journal">Memphis Commercial Appeal</title>, Oct. 23, 1938.
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="MCA">The Memphis Commercial Appeal</name>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">This text is a summarizes comments <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger</person>made at the end of a
        speaking tour in <place>Memphis, Tennessee</place>. 
       
        <index level1="birth control" level2="in Tennessee"/>
        <index level1="birth control clinics and leagues"/>
        <index level1="birth control movement" level2="MS on"/>
    </headNote>

    <docBody>
        <div>
            <head>Interview with The Memphis Commercial Appeal</head>
        </div>

             <div>
            <p>Mrs. Margaret Sanger, nationally known birth control authority who has been here a
                week for a series of lectures, left Memphis last night, equipped with at least three
                convictions: </p>
            <p> 1. Memphis’ public health work is being carried on efficiently and advantageously. </p>
            <div><head type="sub">Clinic Is Progressing</head></div>
            <div><p>2. The birth control clinic set up and sponsored by the <org>Memphis Birth Control
                Committee</org> is progressing, doing excellent work in advising and aiding the many needy
                (and mostly young) mothers. </p>
            <p>3. Work of this clinic should be incorporated into activities of the public health
                clinic at <org>John Gaston Hospital</org>because it was established only as a proving ground
                to show the real need of a similar public clinic. The favor with which she was
                generally received in Memphis is indicative of success in this aim, although not
                necessarily in the near future. </p>
            <p>Mrs. Sanger spoke to numerous grous, some physicians
                and nurses only, some for the public at large. But on each occasion, Mrs. Sanger
                stressed last night before boarding her train for New York, she was cordially and
                very favorably received. </p></div>
            <div><head type="sub">Definite Gains Seen</head></div>
           <div> <p>“I was particularly impressed with the
                reception I had with every medical group. The best people of every community
                throughout my first trip to <place>Tennessee</place> were always present. No, I don’t expect any
                new idea to leap into execution, but we are definitely making progress. This is
                evidenced by the fact that while in Tennessee I spoke before 16 meetings. In Memphis
                alone my audiences totaled at least 2500.” </p>
            <p>Mrs. Sanger was guest of honor last night
                at the home of <person reg="Long, Elizabeth B.">Mrs. Jerome P. Long</person>of 1513 Linden. Returning to New York with her
                were <person reg="Blodgett, Marguerite">Mrs. Stephen Blodgett</person>, also of <place reg="New York, NY">New York</place>, and Mrs. Long. 
                She will go to <place reg="Tucson, AZ">Tucson, Ariz.</place>, soon. </p>
            <p>“This morning I visited our clinic,” she said. “There I saw three young
                mother, typical of the thousands we instruct yearly. One of them was the mother of
                nine children, with another coming along. She was the oldest. The other two,
                however, were girls in their 20s, both the mother of two or three. This is the type
                and age that need our help most.” </p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
