<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published interview">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-04-09 JK initial tag</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1938-11-12 ">12 Nov 1938</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Interview with International News
                    Service</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp214910</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">"U.S. Marriage Aid
                    Proposed"</title><title type="journal">San Francisco
                    Examiner</title>, Nov. 13, 1938.</bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="SFE">San Francisco Examiner</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>This is a summary of an interview <person
                reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger</person> gave in <place>New
                York</place> to the<title type="journal"> International News
                Service </title></p><index level1="population growth"
            level2="regulation of"/>
        <index level1="population growth" level2="standard of living and"
            /><index level1="birth control" level2="American opinion on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="in New York"/>
        <index level1="marriage"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>U.S. Marriage Aid Proposed</head>
        <head type="sub">Mrs. Margaret Sanger Urges Pensions, Subsidies</head>
        <dateline>
            <date value="/----/-11-12"/> Nov. 12, <place>New
            York</place></dateline>
        <q who="SFE">
            <p>Two radical proposals to check “human erosion” in the nation were
                urged upon the government tonight by Mrs. Margaret Sanger, birth
                control advocate, in an interview here.</p>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger recommended:</p>
            <p><list>
                    <item>1- Pensions for persons of child-bearing age with
                        transmissible or hereditary diseases who will agree to
                        sterilization, and: </item>
                    <item>2 - Subsidies for healthy young men and woman, skilled
                        artists, professionals and agriculturists who would
                        welcome children, to tide them over the trying early
                        years of married life until they can become
                        self-supporting.</item>
                </list></p></q>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Provisions Urged.</head>
            <p><q who="SFE">Pointing out that the <org
                        reg="Government of the United States of America">Federal
                        Government</org> would seen he asked to appropriate
                    $850.000,000 for improvement of the public health, Mrs.
                    Sanger said that no doubt much of this sum required of the
                    taxpayers would be sought to increase existing health and
                    welfare services for mothers and children.</q></p>
            <p><q who="SFE">So in addition to her other proposals she
                    recommended that</q> “the men and women who have the welfare
                of this country at heart” <q who="SFE"> urge their
                    representatives in <org reg="United States Congress"
                        >Congress</org> to see that provision is also made for
                    the Government to supply birth control information to
                    parents</q> “among that enormous group of 20,000,000
                individuals dependant upon some form of public aid.” </p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Constructive Relief.</head>
            <p>“Such a measure,” she said, “not only will give constructive,
                immediate relief to millions of families and prevent additional
                suffering, but would be he greatest forward step ever taken on a
                national scale to raise the level of intelligence of the
                nation’s population, and the quality of life.”</p>
            <p>
                <q who="SFE">Stressing the need for such government aid, Mrs.
                    Sanger said that of the 2,000,000 babies born in this
                    country in 1937, 1,100,000 were born to parents on relief or
                    with incomes of less than $18 a week.</q></p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Aid to Marriage</head>
            <q who="SFE">
                <p>Of her two proposals Mrs. Sanger said:</p></q>
            <p>"The cost of maintaining our derelict population is nothing
                compared to the loss of creative effort which might be utilized
                in other channels. Why should our benevolent Federal Government
                not make a constructive investment in the quality of our future
                citizenship by offering pensions to all those in the
                child-bearing aged with transmissible or hereditary diseases who
                will agree to sterilization?"</p>
            <p> "Here truly is a system of pensioning that would bring its own
                reward.</p>
            <p>“Couple with this another appropriation as an aid to marriage for
                those healthy, intelligent young men and women, skilled
                artisans, professionals, agriculturalists, who wish to marry and
                would welcome a family, if there were some provision to tide
                through possible emergencies in the first years until they could
                become entirely self-supporting.”</p>
        </div>

    </docBody>
</doc>
