<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2002-08-01 KH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2002-08-09 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2002-08-15 KH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2003/09/16 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/08/09 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/08/13 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/11/28 CH correct typos</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011-11-30 CH typos</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-01 CH</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1938-03-03">March 3, 1938</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Human Conservation And Birth Control</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp220126</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
                <title>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</title>
            </bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S71:0977</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="DARLE">Darwin, Leonard</name>
            <name id="SYDED">Sydenstricker, Edgar</name>
            <name id="POPPA">Popenoe, Paul</name>
            <name id="WILEL">Williams, Ellen Morton</name>
            <name id="HOOHE">Hoover, Herbert</name>
            <name id="PARTH">Parran, Thomas S. Jr.</name>
            <name id="MACHE">MacMurchy, Helen</name>
            <name id="WOORO">Woodbury, Robert Morse</name>
            <name id="INGDE">Inge, William Ralph</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <sourceNote>For duplicate versions see Library of Congress Microfilm 127:702 and <title>Margaret
            Sanger Microfilm</title> S71:996.</sourceNote>
    <headNote>
        <index level1="eugenics"/>
        <index level1="mental capacity"/>
        <index level1="eugenics" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="population control"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="class-based"/>
        <index level1="fertility rates"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="socio-economic benefits of"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="maternal"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="infant"/>
        <index level1="abortion"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits and risks"/>
        <index level1="client letters"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues"/>
        <index level1="sterilization" level2="methods and devices"/>
        <index level1="mentally disabled and diseased"/>
        <index level1="&quot;unfit&quot; to reproduce" level2="social burdens, as"/>
        <index level1="United States government" level2="public health programs"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="charitable relief in"/>
        <index level1="sterilization" level2="candidates for"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head rend="underline">Human Conservation And Birth Control</head>
        <byline>
            <person>Margaret Sanger</person>
        </byline>
        <div type="">
            <p>In almost all of the conferences dealing with human conservation, maternal health,
                infant and maternal mortality, or population and the falling birth rate,
                conservation of the race through birth control is avoided or ignored. Speakers skirt
                the subject, delicately, and while it is in every one's mind and is discussed in the
                ante-rooms, and in private, at such conferences, it is not brought out into the open
                and given the place it deserves at these gatherings. It is a pleaser, therefore, to
                have the subject assigned me at this meeting. It is time -- in fact the time is long
                overdue -- that we should be frank and honest; that we should face the facts in this
                country and ask where the present policy -- if there be a policy -- of race
                conservation is leading us, so that we may plan to stem the tide of production of
                the unfit and try to turn it in the right direction. </p>
            <p>In his address to the <org>International Congress of Eugenics</org>, 1932, <person
                    reg="Darwin, Leonard">Leonard Darwin</person> said: "<q who="DARLE">Racial
                    deterioration is, I fully believe, taking place amongst us in such a way as to
                    affect society as a whole; and if this be so, the cure should be as wide spread
                    as the disease.</q>"</p>
            <p>How can we define human conservation biologically? In olden times the race struggled
                toward a higher standard through the exercise of the law of the survival of the
                fittest. Only the strongest members of the race survived; it was a process of
                natural selection of those physically most fit. Inferior stocks were weeded out in
                the ruthless process; famine, pestilence and war assisting. Populations grew slowly
                under these checks, and intelligence was fostered as those not so physically strong
                had to learn how to protect themselves and develop arts and culture as well.</p>
            <p>Then came the time when this balance was upset. Humanitarians, among civilized
                nations began their work to conquer disease, prolong life, reduce infant mortality
                and generally improve living conditions. Social services later became a business and
                the conservation of human life -- <emph rend="underline">any</emph> life--a goal.
                There was no defined plan behind this program. It was motivated by sympathy and the
                desire to alleviate suffering. Laudable as was its purposes, emphasis was often not
                put on the proper objectives and the ultimate result has not tended to improve the
                race, but rather the reverse. Population increased rapidly, as natural checks were
                removed, but its quality of stamina, initiative and resistence did not increase
                proportionately. All over the world, where the subject is studies, we find
                biologists concerned over the fall in the level of intelligence, and the increase in
                the number of those of low I.Q. The figures of those men drafted for service in the
                World War in the <place reg="United States">United States</place>, showed a level of
                about 12 years, mentally, and that in a nation with exceptionally high standards of
                living, and almost nationwide compulsory education.</p>
            <p>All this is elementary and perhaps it is unnecessary to reiterate it, but we are here
                to deal with effects and hence, while searching for remedies for these effects,
                cannot ignore their causes. </p>
            <p>Although the multiplication of the unfit is a world problem, we are here concerned
                with its impact on this country primarily. </p>
            <p>Birth control, properly directed, is an implement of vast importance in conservation
                of the race: it is a basic need in any program of human betterment. But it has never
                been utilized in large scale planning and it is time to ask why. </p>
            <p> The growth of population in the United States has been tremendously rapid, due both
                to natural fertility and immigration. The birth rate is now decreasing, and the
                increase slowing down, so that alarmists are already deep in gloom over the prospect
                of a stationary population in the not very distant future, though the increase still
                goes on. No one seems unduly alarmed about the <emph rend="underline">quality</emph>
                of our population; the fears are all about decreasing quantity. We have millions of
                unemployed, many of them idle because they are unemployable except in boom times
                when almost any one can get a job. These people are providing a large proportion of
                the increase in both our social problems and our population today. At the recent
                conference on Better Care for Mothers and Babies, held in Washington, January 1938,
                the Surgeon General, Dr. <person reg="Parran, Thomas S., Jr.">Thomas
                Parran</person>, stated that "<q who="PARTH">approximately one million children are
                    born each year in families on relief or with an annual income of less than
                    $1,000.00.</q>" </p>
            <p>These findings are backed by the studies of Dr. <person reg="Stouffer, S. A.">S. A.
                    Stouffer</person> of the <org>University of Wisconsin</org>, in the <title
                    type="journal">Journal of the American Statistical Association</title>,
                September, 1934, showing that in 5,520 families on relief in <place
                    reg="Milwaukee, WI">Milwaukee</place>, the rate of confinements, taking place
                nine months or more after the families went on relief, exceeded the non-relief
                families by 43%. </p>
            <p>The late <person reg="Sydenstricker, Edgar">Edgar Sydenstricker</person> and <person
                    reg="Perrott, George St. John">G. St. J. Perrott</person> in another study of
                8,000 families in 8 American cities (<title type="journal">Milbank Mem.
                    Quart.</title> 12 April 1934) found that the birth rate had been highest during
                the depression in families without employment or with only part time work in 1932.
                The highest rate was in families who were poor in 1932 and continued poor in 1932.
                The rate was 66% higher than that of families in relatively comfortable
                circumstances. The birth rate of all those on relief was 54% higher than those not
                on relief. "<q who="SYDED">High fertility,</q>" says Sydenstricker and Perrott, "<q
                    who="SYDED">was associated with inability to succeed in the severe competition
                    for jobs, brought about by the depression."</q> The high birth rate, they found,
                was largely in families who "<q who="SYDED">could least afford, from any point of
                    view, to assume this responsibility.</q>"</p>
            <p><person reg="Paul Popenoe">Popenoe</person> &amp; <person
                    reg="Williams, Ellen Morton">Williams</person>, in an article, "<title>Fecundity
                    of Families Dependent on Public Charity</title>",(<title type="journal">American
                    Journal of Sociology</title> 40:214-220, September, 1934) found that in 504
                families who prior to the depression were dependent on charity in <place
                    reg="Los Angeles, CA">Los Angeles</place> County, California, the completed
                family averaged 5 children, of whom a third were born after the families became
                dependent. Over 80% of these families were being assisted by three or more social
                service welfare agencies."</p>
            <p>The authors in questioning the possibility that such families may be producing
                children of superior quality point out that one must be optimistic indeed, to
                believe in such a possibility, if one may judge from intelligence levels in
                comparable groups elsewhere, which have been found uniformly below par.</p>
            <p><org>The Charity Organization Society in New York</org> in testing 451 representative
                children under its care found the median I.Q. 86. That of 821 children in <place
                    reg="Indianapolis, IN">Indianapolis</place> was the same, while of 1,500 women
                admitted as charity obstetrical patients at <org>Johns Hopkins Hospital</org>,
                    <place reg="Baltimore, MD">Baltimore</place>, 39% o the whites and 70% of the
                negroes were found to have a mental age of 11 years or less. (Popenoe &amp; Williams
                p. 220)</p>
            <p>Prof. <person reg="Bossard, James H. S.">James H. S. Bossard</person>, of the
                Department of Sociology, <org>University of Pennsylvania</org>, was quoted in 1935
                    (<title type="journal">New York Times</title>--January 25, 1935) as citing
                figures to show that the birth rate of families on relief was about 60% above that
                of families no on relief. </p>
            <p>Any plan of human conservation would be supposed to build for human betterment--not
                to tear down; to encourage, not penalize those who are prudent and thrifty, while it
                encourages the reckless and improvident to breed. </p>
            <p>Relief, by its ver nature is not conservation. It may serve a destructive purpose,
                first by keeping alive the most unfit and encouraging them by federal, state and
                local aid, to multiply their kind. Second: Relief cannot do more than try to patch
                up a bad situation. It serves to prolong conditions of poverty and misery. It
                provides just enough to keep from actual starvation those who live, normally, almost
                submerged. </p>
            <p>But while keeping these people alive and fed it does something worse to them,
                mentally. It takes away the necessity that urges them forward in the endeavor to
                provide for themselves and their families. It destroys what little initiative they
                may have had before they went on relief. It supports the instincts of those who are
                always looking for the easy way, who love to follow the line of least resistance;
                the inefficient; the soft. It increases the unfit and decreases the fit. </p>
            <p>The State is now placing a burden on the fit. Heavy taxation makes them keep their
                numbers down, but the unfit are relieved from the burden; the machinery of the State
                takes care of them at the expense of those who work and try to save for their
                children and old age. </p>
            <p rend="underline">People no longer have pride in taking care of themselves and their
                families. They assume the responsibility of parenthood carelessly, knowing that some
                one else will carry the burden for them it is not necessary now for them to make
                good. The sympathy which operated to take care of them has kept their bodies alive
                and fed, but has atrophied their spirits, and in so doing has dealt a heavy blow to
                the nation, for it was its spirit that drove it forward. There is not one of us here
                who does not remember -- and not so many years ago -- when there was nothing the
                average American would not do to avoid taking charity. Those days are gone. He does
                not take charity now, he goes on relief, and feels no shame about it often because
                charity is camouflaged now under this new name.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head rend="underline" type="sub">The Burden.</head>
            <p>What efforts has this country made toward race conservation, and what agencies carry
                the load of the unfit?</p>
            <p><emph rend="underline">Physical</emph>. Dr. <person reg="Kingsbury, Johns Adams"
                    >Kingsbury</person> will give you the picture of the cost of trying to keep the
                nation in health. Over 165,000 doctors; almost 6,500 hospitals; all kinds of public
                health agencies; nurses, dentists and others at an estimated cost of about 3 3/4
                billions a year are part of the load. Dr. <person reg="Huntington, Ellsworth"
                    >Huntington</person> in "<title type="article">Tomorrow's Children</title>" (p.
                3) estimates that we spend 3 billion on education and possibly 2 billion on
                recreation for children, with another 2 billion on their health. </p>
            <p>Much of this load is borne by all the people in taxes for public schools and state
                universities; in contributions for up-keep of hospitals and health agencies; in
                donations to <org>Community Chests</org> for every kind of activity, health and
                recreational. No one would grudge this money if it brought results. But we are
                constantly appalled by reading of the increase in crime--a large proportion of it by
                young criminals--by the low physical an mental standards of so many of our people.
                And if we ask why so little progress is made we are told that it is because we don't
                spend enough money--we need billions more if the needs are to be properly met. </p>
            <p>In all this frantic struggle to get more money to take care of the hordes of the
                unfit, few voices have been heard asking why the people of this country should be
                asked to drag this increasingly heavy ball and chain forever; why something cannot
                be done to help these people keep themselves, thus relieving the burden on every
                one. Why spend so much money and effort on the effect, without going to the root of
                the matter and eliminating the cause? Why continue to put salve on a wound which
                never heals?</p>
            <p>The nation's most precious asset is its children--provided that they are born of
                parents who can give them a fair physical and mental inheritance and can provide
                them with at least decent comfort. </p>
            <p>At the <org>White House Conference on Child Health and Protection</org> in 1930,
                    <person reg="Hoover, Herbert">President Hoover</person> said, "<q who="HOOHE">If
                    we could have but one generation of properly born, trained, educated and healthy
                    children, a thousand other problems of government would vanish.</q>"</p>
            <p>Yet when these conferences are called together everything but birth control is
                weighed and considered--that topic is omitted. </p>
            <p>The <org reg="United States Children's Bureau">Children's Bureau</org> was created
                after the first White House Conference was called in 1912 by <person
                    reg="Roosevelt, Theodore">Theodore Roosevelt</person>. the Second Conference
                called by <person>Woodrow Wilson</person> in 1929 reviewed the same old problems,
                and said that many things ought to be done about them; but birth control was not
                mentioned. </p>
            <p>The Third Conference, called by Herbert Hoover in 1930, made the recommendation,
                through a sub-committee on obstetric training, that medical students should be
                taught the technique of contraception and medical indications therefore, but birth
                control was not discussed at the sessions.</p>
            <p>The latest <org>conference on Better Care for Mothers and Babies</org>, held under
                the auspices of the Children's Bureau in January, 1938, was addressed by the Surgeon
                General, Dr. Thomas Parran, who informed it that, "<q who="PARTH">One-third of the
                    population here is ill-fed, ill-housed, ill-clothed and ill-provided with
                    opportunity for life and health.</q>" He stressed the fact that the relationship
                between poverty and disease had long been known, and said that "<q who="PARTH"
                    >illness among persons on relief is 68% higher than among those in comfortable
                    circumstances; chronic illness 87% higher,</q>"--these figures probably being
                taken from the recent National Health Survey under the Division of Public
                Health.</p>
            <p>Dr. Parran then went on to consider the question of maternal mortality. "<q
                    who="PARTH">The 12,544 mothers who died as a result of conditions of pregnancy
                    and child-birth in 1935, do not represent the whole of the loss from
                    child-bearing. In the past it seems clear that we have underestimated the size
                    and scope of the problem, for there were more than 60,000 babies who died 2
                    weeks after birth; there were 77,119 recorded still-births. In other words,
                    there occur inthe country each year, more than 150,000 deaths -- 60% of which
                    are needlessly lost because of the mismanagement of the child-bearing
                    function.</q>" He went on, "<q who="PARTH">Approximately one million children
                    are born each year to families on relief or with an annual income of less than
                    $1,000.00. Here are found the highest death rates of mothers and infants; Here
                    the least, and the least good, medical care.</q>"</p>
            <p>Yet not a voice was raised to ask why this crime was permitted, why there mothers and
                babies were sacrificed; why no one gave these families any advice on
                contraception!</p>
            <p>What form of race conservation is this? Not that many American men were killed in the
                World War, but we mourn them unceasingly, because they were young and they were
                sacrificed. Night and day a sentry guards the tomb of the Unknown Soldier at <place
                    reg="Arlington, VA">Arlington</place>--the symbol of our sorrow for the
                holocaust of war. But who mourns these mothers, or tries to prevent the yearly
                repetition of their deaths by making it possible for them to have a breathing spell
                between the births of their children?</p>
            <p>In only one tabulated report on maternal mortality, by Dr. <person
                    reg="MacMurchy, Helen">Helen MacMurchy</person> of <place>Canada</place>, have I
                see <q who="MACHE">"Exhaustion after repeated pregnancies</q>", listed as a cause of
                death of the mother. </p>
            <p>But the nation loses more than the mothers. There are the babies. Figures on infant
                mortality in this country have been incomplete until the last few years, because all
                of the states had not come into the birth registration area. Still-birth
                registration is even now most unsatisfactory, and the <org>American Committee on
                    Maternal Welfare</org>, under Dr. <person reg="Adair, Fred">Fred Adair</person>,
                is endeavoring to have a uniform blank adopted for such registrations, for until
                this is done all vital statistics are skewed by this unknown factor. </p>
            <p>We do know, however, that infant mortality in the United States is inexcusably high
                and that some of its underlying causes should be attacked. In 1926,<person
                    reg="Woodbury, Robert Morse">Robert Morse Woodbury</person>, in "<title
                    type="book">Infant Mortality and Its Causes</title>", said,--"<q who="WOORO"
                    >Perhaps first in the underlying causes of these infant deaths--was lack of
                    health and physical vitality in the mother during pregnancy. Infants whose
                    mothers died within one year following confinement had a mortality rate 4 times
                    as high as that for other infants. Where the mother died one month after
                    confinement 6 in every 10 of the babies died before the end of the first year.
                    Infants whose mothers had tuberculosis had a mortality 2 1/2 times as high as
                    that among other infants.</q>"</p>
            <p>Woodbury's figures showed that lack of spacing of birth affected the death rate
                unfavorably; that the rate when births were at one year intervals was 146.7,
                dropping to 98.6 within two year intervals and to 86.5 when children were born three
                years apart. </p>
            <p>Low family income was another unfavorable factor. Where earnings were less than
                $450.00 a year, infant death rate was 166.9. When they rose to $1,250.00 and over,
                the rate dropped to 59.1, and where there was no income it shot up to 210.9. </p>
            <p>The larger families, where the family income per capita fell with each additional
                child, the death rate was heavy. Woodbury's figures show that where earnings were
                less than $50.00 per capita each year the infant death rate was 215.9. </p>
            <p>Each survey of maternal mortality lists induced abortion as one of the major causes
                of this loss of life to the nation. From 1/4 to 1/3 of the mothers died from this
                cause. Statistics show that they are usually young married women, who leave families
                of small children behind them. They induce abortion because they have reached the
                end of the rope. In many cases they cannot feed the children behind them. They
                induce abortion because they have reached the end of the rope. In many cases they
                cannot feed the children they have and another is something they cannot face.
                Government investigations of this problem are now in progress in <place>Great
                    Britain</place> and <place>New Zealand</place>. It is a growing evil all over
                the world. Repressive laws do not stamp it out. The trade flourishes because the
                poor, who should have the best contraceptive advice do not get it, and the cheap
                abortionist or midwife "helps them out" when an undesired pregnancy exists. There is
                money in it for the unscrupulous men, sometimes physicians, who either operate
                alone, at high prices for those who can afford to pay, or form an "abortion ring"
                such as was uncovered on the West Coast about a year ago, when one of its victims
                died.</p>
            <p>It is incredible that organized medicine does not know that these evils exist, (a
                canker inside the profession in spite of Hippocratic oaths) and do something about
                it; but no one stirs. It is encouraging, however, that more and more in these
                surveys of maternal death following abortion the point is stressed that had these
                women been given proper contraceptive information many of them need not have died,
                and recommendation made that such instruction be made available, so that in the
                future, lives may be saved. </p>
            <p>And so we go to the same weary round. The White House Conference of 1930 found that,
                out of 45 million children, 6 million were improperly nourished, 1 million had
                defective speech; 3 million impaired hearing, 1 million weak or damaged hearts;
                675,000 behavior problems; 450,000 mentally retarded; 382,000 tuberculous; 300,000
                crippled. It was recommended that something be done to alleviate these conditions.
                And sothey started to patch and tinker and repair the damage.</p>
            <p>But the same flood of defective children went on pouring out in the same old way. No
                one ever dreamed of stopping that leak. And another conference was held in 1938. Its
                Findings Committee, <q who="WHC30">"after reviewing the information placed before
                    it</q>", announced (its figures slightly at variance with the Surgeon General's
                who spoke at it that "<q who="PARTH">14,000 women die each year in this country from
                    causes connected with childbirth, leaving at least 35,000 children motherless;
                    more than 75,000 infants are still-born, and more than 69,000 die during the
                    first month of life.</q>" They say that the maternal mortality rate has not been
                appreciably reduced here in years; that the still-birth rate has remained unchanged
                and that from one-half to two-thirds of these maternal deaths are preventable. They
                go on to state that approximately 840,000 or more than one-third of al the births in
                the United States "<q who="PARTH">occur each year in families on relief or with
                    incomes (including home produce) of $750. a year.</q>" </p>
            <p>They then make recommendations. The nearest they dare get to birth control is to say
                that "<q who="UNK">preconceptional and premarital care will help to safeguard the
                    mother from possible later disaster.</q>"</p>
            <p>The usual recommendations of adequate pre- and postlated care; medical, dental and
                nursing care during pregnancy, and labor; periodic examination by a pediatrical
                hospitalization, etc., etc., were made. And then came the inevitable demand for
                larger funds, under the <name type="law">Social Security Act</name>, to finance
                these needs. </p>
            <p>Has it never occurred to our present charitable and relief agencies that they are
                really not relieving our social problems, but are aggravating them? What have our
                government agencies really done to conserve the best in human kind? In animal
                industry the poor stock is not allowed to breed; in gardens the weeds are kept down.
                The Government sends all kinds of literature through its numerous departments to
                inform farmers and livestock breeders as to how they can improve produce--by
                nurturing the good and eliminating the bad stock.</p>
            <p>But when it comes to human beings these same agencies prefer to patch and tinker
                rather than to prevent or eliminate. They are dominated by the fear of religious
                intolerance, with its dogmatic cruelty. It is this same intolerance (and let us be
                frank about it) that prevents all discussion at these National Conferences of the
                one thing which would help most in human conservation--birth control.</p>
            <p>You cannot build a good house without a strong foundation, and the foundations of
                this nation are being sapped. While alarmists are shaking their heads over the
                declining birth rate, we had in 1935 (Huntington--"<title type="book">Children of
                    Tomorrow</title>") 90,000 feeble-minded and epileptics in institutions alone,
                with 2 million, estimated, in the population. Few state laws forbid the marriage of
                such persons. There were 324,000 insane in institutions and 184,000 criminals,
                confined, but constantly paroled to commit more crimes. There were 650,000 persons
                committed to jail each year. The cost of all this is staggering; it runs into many
                billions annually. In addition there were about 5 million who failed to go above the
                4th grade in school and about 5 3/4 millions of that age in the United States. </p>
            <p>These are not reassuring figures, but if we do not really attack the problem
                intelligently, the totals will be worse in another generation. This is the size of
                the problem. What is being done about it? No government agency dares to suggest a
                nation-wide program of birth control, but such a program must ultimately be adopted
                or our national level of intelligence will continue to sink. </p>
            <p>Private enterprise and philanthropy have always blazed the trail in human
                conservation. It was a lay group that inaugurated the battle against tuberculosis
                and which has successfully fought that disease and greatly lowered its incidence. So
                with cancer. Lay groups raised funds for research in this field. Lay groups carried
                the burden of charity for years, until in 1932, the Government took it over and the
                    <emph rend="underline">relief</emph> program began. </p>
            <p>We are now facing a situation where more and more of our citizens are expecting and
                demanding that they and their children be taken care of indefinitely--possibly for
                life. This load is assuming such proportions that the nation will not be able to
                carry it unless the annual increment of relief babies is checked, and unless those
                not on relief but living on the bare subsistence level are given instruction. </p>
            <p>It may be said that they do not want such help, but my experience of years tell a
                different story. Over a million mothers have written to me begging for information
                on family limitation and their letters would convince any one -- except a religious
                fanatic, that here is a great and agonizing need that is not being filled. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head rend="underline" type="sub">Program</head>
            <p>What can we do about it? What plan will cover it? Only a national, coordinated
                service. We have now in this country about 384 birth control clinics for a
                population of millions of women of child bearing age. The majority of these are
                financed by lay committees; a few are run by state or local public health agencies;
                all are under medical direction. </p>
            <p>To say that this handful of centers is filling the need is ridiculous. They are a
                drop in an ocean. There should be thousands of clinics, easily accessible, with less
                rigid requirements and financed by the Government as part of its public health
                service. </p>
            <p>But even if every organized health center had such service it would still not be
                enough. The clinics almost invariably advise one method. This method entails a
                medical examination and technical knowledge. In rural areas such clinics often
                cannot be set up. Not only are no trained physicians available, but the women live
                too far away to be able to travel in for aid; so it must be taken to them, as
                obstetric service is taken to them by the frontier nurses in many states. </p>
            <p>Simple methods have been discovered, to fit the needs of these women; something which
                will not require a doctor's examination but which will not require a doctor's
                examination but which a nurse can advise under a doctor's prescription. Simple
                methods may not be 100% effective, but what therapy in any disease can claim that?
                Such methods will be better than nothing-- They will reduce the number of the
                unwanted and the unfit. </p>
            <p>All obstructive laws should be so clarified and recorded that nowhere in this country
                should there be a shadow of doubt as to the doctor's legal right to advise patients
                where pregnancy is contraindicated.</p>
            <p>Discovery of even simpler, effective methods entails research. Millions have been
                spent in research in other fields, but only a few thousands in this. Well directed
                liberally financed research is an essential part of this program. </p>
            <p>For those mothers--and there will always be such--who are too dull-witted, to
                careless or too inert to use even simple methods, under direction, sterilization is
                indicated. I shall not go into this field extensively, for it is covered by another
                paper on the program, but the last available figures from the <org>Human Betterment
                    Foundation</org> show that to date of January 1, 1937, only 25,403 persons had
                been sterilized in state institutions in the United States. Of these 10,674 were men
                and 14,729 women. Twenty-eight states have laws governing institutional inmates, but
                these figures include 42 cases operated on in New York before the law there was
                declared unconstitutional in 1918. Of the total number sterilized 11,484 or over 45%
                were in <place>California</place> institutions. There is no way of estimating the
                number of women sterilized in hospitals, where it is often routine procedure in
                cases where the mother-s life would be endangered by another pregnancy; nor can we
                estimate the number of men in our population who have had a voluntary vasectomy, for
                various reasons, though communications from individual physicians indicate that this
                number is increasing, particularly among professional men. </p>
            <p>Contrary to common belief it is not illegal in most states for a physician to
                sterilize a patient on request. In such cases written consent should be obtained
                from wife or husband as a safeguard for the doctor. </p>
            <p>Operation on the male may be an office procedure and is accompanied by little risk.
                Operation on the woman is a major surgical procedure in most cases, but perfection
                of the operation by the vaginal route, or by Xray in cases where an artificial
                menopause will not too greatly unbalance the woman's system, may obviate the risks
                to the mothers of the future. </p>
            <p>Again, however, we must stress the fact that in a national program for human
                conservation institutional and voluntary sterilization are not enough; they do not
                reach those elements at large in the population whose children are a menace to the
                national health and well-being. </p>
            <p>Reports in medical journals state that the indications laid down in the German law
                are being carefully observed. These are gongenital feeble-mindedness; schizophrenia,
                circular insanity; heredity epilepsy; hereditary chorea (Huntington's)' hereditary
                blindness or deafness; grave hereditary bodily deformity and chronic alcoholism. </p>
            <p>Surely everyone will agree that the children of parents so afflicted are no
                contribution to the nation for even if they do not inherit these defects they are
                children of parents so handicapped that life will give them little, owing to their
                necessarily bad environment. </p>
            <p>There are 1,700 special courts and 27 higher courts in <place>Germany</place> to
                review the cases certified for sterilization there. The rights of the individual
                could be equally well safeguarded here, but in no case should the rights of society,
                or which he or she is a member, be disregarded.</p>
            <p>Dean <person reg="Inge, William Ralph">Inge</person>--The Gloomy Dean--in his "<title
                    type="book">Gleanings from a Note Book</title>" has said: "<q who="INGWI">Don't
                    be a pioneer. It is the early Christian that is gotten by the lion. The safest
                    mountain paths are those trodden by mules and asses. Follow them.</q>"</p>
            <p>In their anxiety to follow this advice, many nations are throwing away their
                heritage; discarding the best to take care of the worst elements of society. If we
                have not intelligence to adopt the program outlined above because it is a step
                toward human conservation, let us adopt it in consideration for the mothers who have
                borne the crushing load of our neglect through the centuries. If we have no sympathy
                for the mothers, whose normal duty has been considered childbearing, regardless of
                physical or economic conditions, let us adopt it in pity for the children--those
                innocent sufferers born into a world they never made -- thrown out handicapped to
                struggle for subsistence in a society so organized that only the strong can get
                ahead--but eventually revenging themselves on this society by forming the social
                problem group which costs us billions annually. </p>
            <p>But let us thing straight and think fast, for the years are rolling by while we drift
                without a real or practical program for race conservation. </p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
