<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2012-03-26 AW</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2012-03-28 CH proofed tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-02 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1952-02-14">14 Feb 1952</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Address to the Sixth International Conference in Planned
                Parenthood</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp223999</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Sixth International Conference on Planned Parenthood, <title type="book">Report of
                    the Proceedings 14-21 February 1959</title> pp. 10-11</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S72:0983</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>Sanger gave this speech to open the <org
                reg="International Conference on Planned Parenthood, 6th">Sixth International
                Conference on Planned Parenthood</org> in <place>New Delhi, India</place>. Other
            speaks included Jawaharlal Nehru and Dhanvanthi Rama Rau.</p>
        <index level1="International Conference on Planned Parenthood, 6th (1959 India)"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="birth control movement in"/>
        <index level1="family planning, principles of"/>
        <index level1="reproductive responsibility"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>MRS. MARGARET SANGER</head>
        <head type="sub"><emph rend="italics">President, International Planned Parenthood
                Federation</emph></head>
        <p>Mr. <person reg="Jawaharlal, Nehru">Nehru</person>, Lady <person
                reg="Rama Rau, Dhanvanthi">Rama Rau</person>, Distinguished Friends and Governing
            Body, Ladies and Gentlemen, Friends and Co-workers:</p>
        <p>This is one of the greatest days of joy of my life to have traveled from <place
                reg="Arizona">Arizona</place> through <place reg="California"
                >California</place> and <place reg="Hawaii">Hawaii</place> and to come here to
                <place>India</place>, and to hear the greatest living statesman of the world today,
            Mr. Nehru, open this Conference. It is a day that I did not think would come quite so
            soon. I knew that eventually it had to come, and it must come from officials of various
            governments who have the intelligence to see its importance. I also want to congratulate
            the women of India, for when I was here in 1936 the <org>All India Women’s
                Conference</org> at that time held a meeting and passed a resolution asking the
            Municipalities, I think of <place reg="Bombay, India">Bombay</place> and other cities,
            that they should give contraceptive information to the women of the community and from
            that time up to this day you have made great strides. Lady Rama Rau has been a wonderful
            leader, a distinguished speaker, well known throughout many countries of the world, and
            she has really inspired a great many in this country and other countries. It is a
            wonderful thing to have the women of the country co-operate with the government, but
            better yet to have a government co-operate with the women. There are several things that
            I would like to say. I wish I could have time, or had time, to pay tribute to the vast
            number of pioneers who through their scholarly writings, addresses and thinking have
            left to us marvelous ideas. There really isn’t time to tell about them all, from the
            days of <person reg="Malthus, Thomas Robert">Malthus</person> to the present time, but in one
            way we do pay tribute to them because we are using and expressing their opinions, their
            writings and their thoughts in nearly every address that any of us makes. There are some
            basic principles that I should like to tell you about which concern the
                <org>International Planned Parenthood Federation</org> movement. The first is, that
            it has, as we see it, almost a duty and a responsibility to help married couples, or
            those about to be married, to acquire knowledge of contraception. It is also our aim to
            inspire research work, so that there will be simpler contraceptives for the more
            ignorant, simple-minded people who know little about anatomy or physiology. The second
            is, that we want to have such information advocated and guided by the medical
            profession. But I want to say, beware of many of those who have an MD behind their
            names! I do not think all of them are suitable to give the kind of information, the
            sympathy, the understanding to the shy, simple woman who comes to them, asking for
            information as to how to space her pregnancies, and how to take care of the children
            that she has already borne. One of our duties, of course, is to co-operate with the
            health and welfare departments of the country, and you in India have already done that,
            and it seems to me that a great educational campaign must go on and on to achieve the
            health necessary to bring children into the world: the health of the mother, the health
            of the father and the healthy atmosphere of the home. I was very happy to hear the
            address of the <person reg="Karmarkar, D.P.">Health Minister</person> here today, and
            for him I would like to just add a few of the principles of family planning that I think
            should be widespread in every country in the world. The first is that, with a Health
            Ministry alive and alert to the evils of venereal or other transmissible disease, no
            couple with a transmissible disease should be allowed to have children. Secondly, there
            are certain disorders -- tuberculosis, and heart and kidney disease -- which should be
            cured, or at least arrested, before a woman becomes pregnant. That also is part of the
                <org reg="India, Ministry of Health">Ministry of Health</org>’s duties. Then there
            is the interval of two or three years necessary to give the mother a chance to
            recuperate from the ordeal of childbirth and to give her time to prepare for the coming
            of the next. Then there is the everlasting economic state, especially of the father,
            whose earnings might possibly take care of two children, keep them in health and educate
            them, but which are quite inadequate to take care of ten or twelve. That is when they
            come to need outside help. Further, we must think of the children that are born with
            some ailment, some stigma from the past generation, and it seems to me that it is only
            wise to say to parents of such children: “Halt! Have no more!” Even though you do not
            feel that it is your own fault, there is something in the genes, something in the
            background, that may distribute itself to future children. I believe that there should
            be early marriage, but a postponement of children or pregnancies for at least two or
            three years. It is essential in these high pressure days that if the marriage is to be a
            happy one a young couple should get acquainted, should understand each other and should
            develop a social and cultural atmosphere in the home before they bring a baby or
            children into the world. These are all simple issues and responsibilities, but they are
            just as essential today as they were 20 or 30 years ago, when this movement first began,
            and it is on these principles that we have built our family planning and planned
            parenthood movement. In conclusion, I want to say that, even though these are all great
            responsibilities, there is one greater that should, I think, be in the minds of every
            married man and woman thinking of bringing a child into the world -- the responsibility
            of ushering a soul into this world to take its part in the mystery as a material being.
            I think if we could have about two or three generations where children are wanted and
            loved before they were conceived, I believe it would take only a few generations before
            we could really have faith in the possibility of peace on earth, goodwill to men,
            throughout the whole world.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
