<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2010/02/24 AC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-11 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1933-MM-DD">Standard Date</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Women and the Future</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp224705</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title>, S71:0630</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="enslavement of"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="freedom and rights of"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Women and the Future</head>
        <p>Women’s place in the creation of the structure of the future has never been more
            important than it is today.</p>
        <p> We witness the bankruptcy and the collapse of man’s attempt to conquer the universe and
            dominate it in his man-made -- one-sided womanless battle for supremacy.</p>
        <p> He has flung railroads and airlines across continents, conquered the sir, harnesses the
            endless torrents of water power. Through the lenses of his telescope he has explored
            distant universes; through the lenses of his microscope he has waged war against germ
            and microbe; girdled the globe in a fraction of a second with his radio broadcast.
            Everything has been done and accomplished in the effort and desire to <emph
                rend="underlined">Unite</emph> peoples and nations and to bring them closer
            together. Yet, we fond him goaded to a frenzy of power in exploitation and war.</p>
        <p> In all his ventures and accomplishments woman has been allowed to march beside him-- to
            serve his physical needs, competing with animals as pack horses or nurse maids for his
            offspring. He has succeeded in conquering everything but his own ignorance. I am not
            pleading for the substitution of a woman-made work for we have seen enough of
            exclusively masculine adventure, enough destruction, chaos and confusion. Rather do I
            look forward to a future created by a united harmonious endeavor of women and men
            working together as equals. Equals as creative entities. Woman’s bondage has been and
            still is based on the biological task of childbearing. Our ecclesiastical fathers have
            and still decree that there are only two states of responsible womanhood open to women
            -- virginity and motherhood. Sex in any manifestation is justified only in the bearing
            of a child.</p>
        <p> With such a mental attitude confusing a basic function of life with shame and sin, women
            cannot rise to her highest possibilities. For millions of mothers too poor, too weak,
            too inarticulate to demand their liberties because they are crushed under the double
            burden of poverty and childbearing, they can never have full potential or civil rights,
            never full opportunity for education, no freedom to enlarge their talents, or submerged
            abilities until the functions of child bearing becomes under control. Until that
            function of her being, the procreative power, is under her complete control woman can
            never hope to aspire to the heights of her own spiritual destiny.</p>
        <p> The Militarists of <place>Europe</place> and <place>Asia</place> are clamoring for an
            increased population to enlarge their armies. To these pleas women must refuse to
            listen. She must awaken to the responsibility which is hers . as a creative force in the
            remaking of a New World. She can become the conscious instrument to a World of
            Peace.</p>
        <p> Birth Control is the first sign of an awakening consciousness in womankind. It signals a
            new moral responsibility, a higher regard for human life, not only after birth but even
            before it has been conceived.</p>
        <p> It is through this consciousness of birth, the recognition of the importance of the
            quality of life itself, that women shall extricate humanity from the man-made muddle in
            which it finds itself grounded today. Instead of a world torn asunder in jealousies and
            bitterness created by irresponsible hordes in antagonism and despair--Woman consciously
            free could guide us into a future created by the all embracing love of peace on Earth --
            Good will toward Men over the entire face of the globe. </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
