<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "file:/S:/TRANSCRIPTIONS/XML%20Drafts/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
<mepHeader>
<prepDate>2002-0805 KH</prepDate>
<prepDate>2002-08-15 KH</prepDate>
<prepDate>2003/08/19 CH</prepDate>
<prepDate>2004/08/13 CH</prepDate>
<prepDate>2014-03-07 CH clean regs</prepDate>
<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
<docDate value="1929-03-00">Mar 1929</docDate>
<docTitle>
<titlePart>Will Birth Control Diminish It?</titlePart>
</docTitle>
<idno>msp226798</idno>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl><title type="journal">Eugenics</title>, Mar. 1929, 23</bibl>
<bibl><title>MSM</title> S71:0156</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
<respStmt>
<resp/>
<name/>
</respStmt>
</mepHeader>
<headNote><p>Sanger's article appeared next to an opposing article by Father <person
reg="McClorey, John A.">John A. McClorey</person>.</p>
<index level1="eugenics" level2="birth control and"/>
<index level1="mentally disabled and diseased"/><
/headNote>
<docBody>
<head>Will Birth Control Diminish It?</head>
<byline><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">MARGARET SANGER</person></byline>
<p>To say that birth control runs the risk of excluding from life geniuses as well as defectives is
to imply that chance is a better guide than intelligence. The total number of geniuses in the whole
of human history is much less than one thousand. The total number of defectives could never be
computed. The damage they have done to civilization cannot be counterbalanced by the benefits we
have derived from genius. The garden of humanity has been choked by the destructive forces of
uncontrolled and misdirected procreation. Small wonder that the potentialities hidden in the human
species have so seldom flowered in genius. Father McClorey may think it better to abandon the garden
to the weeds, naively confident that geniuses will make their appearances regardless of heredity and
environment. But no student of genetics, no one who has even superficially observed the achievements
of scientific horticulture and animal breeding, can consider seriously that the road to human
perfection can ever be attained by abandoning scientific control and reverting to a childish
reliance upon the blind fores of uncontrolled procreative instincts.</p>
<p>Little as we still know about genius, or about men and women of exceptional talents, we do know
that they do not come into this world with hereditary backgrounds of imbecility, or
feeble-mindedness.</p>
<p>The seed of genius is hidden deep in the race. It is the most sacred duty of every parent and
parent-to-be to recognize that he is the guardian of this seed, that he is, so to speak, the
ancestor of a future genius.</p>
</docBody>
</doc>
