<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2003/08/04 SR</prepDate>
		<prepDate>8/06/2003 CH Proofed Tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>05/09/2012 AW Corrected Tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-04-09 CH clean regs</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1924-12-00">Dec 1924</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>Editorial</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp226797</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title>, Dec. 1924, 339-40.</bibl>
			<bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S70:1056</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name/>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<index level1="England" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="England" level2="birth control in"/>
		<index level1="England" level2="clinics in"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="support for"/>
		
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Editorial</head>
		<p>To revisit <place reg="London, England">London</place>, after an absence of two years, is
			nothing less than an inspiration. From an intellectual and spiritual point of view,
			London to me seems almost like a fountain of youth. One's flagging enthusiasms are
			rejuvenated in the bracing air of intellectual freedom one breathes in there. London is
			still faithful to her age-old tradition of hospitality to new ideas. London enjoys,
			indeed revels in, free discussion. And so to go back to this fountain of eternal youth
			is necessary for a complete revitalization of interest and enthusiasm. I do not think
			this is a mere illusion on my part. English faith in the instrument of Birth Control is
			expressing itself in the splendid progress of the movement, exemplified in the fine
			organization known as the <org reg="Walworth Women's Welfare Centre">Walworth
				Center</org>. This splendid accomplishment has been achieved in no small degree
			owing to the fact that the doctors and authorities in charge of the Walworth Clinic are
			not hampered by obsolete and uncivilized statutes of the type that were written into our
			federal and state laws in the darkest ages of our history–-under the blighting reign of
			St. <person reg="Comstock, Anthony">Anthony Comstock</person>. At Walworth any woman or
			man may receive proper instruction upon application to the physicians in charge. No
			appointment in advance is necessary. The mother may drop into the clinic at any time
			convenient. She then awaits her turn for advice. Due to the fact that the instruction
			and ensuing benefits may be shared by all, the physicians in charge are not compelled to
			undertake a general health examination and to find a special or exceptional cause to
			undertake the instruction. For this reason, there is no invasion of personal freedom and
			reason, there is no invasion of personal freedom and the sense of parental
			responsibility is encouraged instead of discouraged. It is the mother herself, awakened
			to this need of self-mastery and self-reliance, who makes the decision. The Walworth
			Clinic, so splendidly organized and carried on, stands ready to serve these mothers and
			potential parents, to answer their needs, instead of dictating their personal and
			private behavior. The work is inspiring and suggests manifold possibilities for future
			development. Their activities not hindered by barbaric obsolete laws, the physicians at
			Walworth may instruct five women in the time that our physician needs to take care of
			one.</p>
		<p>The report of the work which was sent to me is illuminating. It will be reviewed at
			length in a later issue.</p>
		<p>The <org reg="Society for the Provision of Birth Control Clinics">English committee</org>
			are to be congratulated for their exceptional perseverance and courage in pushing
			through this work. For they have succeeded despite all sorts of discouragement and lack
			of funds. But with that characteristic and typically British ability to "carry on" most
			of the obstacles have been overcome and ultimate success is assured. The initial example
			having proved its value and its practical importance, other clinics are now in the
			course of being organized. For the success of the Walworth Center, the committee in
			charge is mainly responsible for its splendid management and organization. This
			committee consists of Mrs. <person reg="Fuller, Margaret">Fuller</person>, Hon. Mrs.
				<person reg="Murray, Evelyn Graham">Graham Murray</person>, Lord <person
				reg="Westley, Gerald">Gerald Westley</person> and our friend <person
				reg="Cox, Harold">Harold Cox</person>. Mr. <person reg="Sumner, John S."
				>Sumner</person> contributes the house, rates and taxes. A small fee is charged to
			each applicant. This fee, which makes possible the continuance of the work without
			doubling of expense, also increases the sense of responsibility of those who derive its
			benefits, since it is a notorious human trait that people never value advice that is
			gratuitously given.</p>
		<p>Perhaps the most inspiring event of the visit of our vice-president, Mrs. <person
				reg="Rublee, Juliet Barrett">Rublee</person>, and myself in London was to find men
			and women of the highest intellectual attainments in hearty agreement with our
			fundamental principles. The occasion of this discovery was a brilliant dinner party at
			the home of Mr. and Mrs. <person reg="Robbins, Amy Catherine">
				<person reg="Wells, H. G.">H. G. Wells</person></person> in Whitehall Court. Among
			the guests were <person reg="Shaw, George Bernard">George Bernard Shaw</person> and Mrs.
				<person reg="Payne-Townshend, Charlotte">Shaw</person>, the eminent Lord <person
				reg="Buckmaster, Stanley Owen">Buckmaster</person>, one of the most brilliant
			jurists of Great Britain; Sir <person reg="Arbuthnot-Lane, William">Arbuthnot
				Lane</person> and Lady <person reg="Briscoe, Charlotte Jane">Lane</person>; the
			great scientist and educator, Sir <person reg="Lankester, Edwin Ray">Edwin Ray
				Lankester</person>; Prof. <person reg="MacBride, Ernest William">E. W.
				MacBride</person>; the eminent novelist, <person reg="Bennett, Arnold">Arnold
				Bennett</person>; the dramatist and critic, St. <person reg="Ervine, John">John
				Ervine</person> and Mrs. <person reg="Ervine, Leonora Mary (Davis)">Ervine</person>;
			that rising figure of contemporary Irish literature, Mr. <person reg="Donavan, Robert"
				>Robert Donavan</person> and Mrs. <person>Donavan</person>, and Mr. <person
				reg="Salter, W. R.">W. R. Salter</person> of the <org>League of Nations</org>.</p>
		<p>To know that the fundamental importance of Birth Control as an instrument of human and
			social emancipation is recognized by such brilliant minds, as well as by the
			intellectual leaders in every field of British life, has indeed been inspiration for
			your delegates to return to the timorous and fear-ridden atmosphere with renewed
			enthusiasm and fresh courage, ready to "carry on" until our compatriots awaken from
			their slumber and are ready to go into battle with real problems of American
			society.</p>
		<byline>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">MARGARET SANGER</person>
		</byline>
	</docBody>
</doc>
