<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2003/06/26 RK</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/27 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/08/09 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007/08/28 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-07 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1919-07-00">Jul 1919</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>How Shall We Change The Law</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp226876</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title> July 1919, 8-9</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S70:824</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
            <name id="LINSA">Lindsey, Samuel McClure </name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits and risks of"/>
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="doctors-only bills"/>
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="State"/>
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Comstock Laws"/>
        <index level1="New York" level2="birth control in"/>
       <index level1="midwives" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="nurses" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="physicians" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="health of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>How Shall We Change The Law</head>
        <byline rend="italics">By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></byline>
        <p>Appalling situations revealed every day indicate all too plainly that in cases where a
            woman's disease is affected by pregnancy, the medical institutions and clinics of <place
                reg="New York, NY">New York</place> State are accomplishing nothing to relieve those
            diseased conditions. Where the disease is tuberculosis, syphilis or some other organic
            malady which is aggravated by pregnancy, women appeal in vain for instruction concerning
            contraceptives. Physicians are willing to perform abortions where they are pronounced
            necessary, but they refuse to direct the use of preventives which would make the
            abortions unnecessary. The almost invariable reply to the appeals of their women
            patients is: "<q who="UNK">I can't do it -- the law does not permit it."</q> Recent
            inquiries made of physicians leave no doubt as to the accuracy of this statement.
            Medical practitioners are heavily handicapped -- especially in institutional and public
            work -- by Section 1142 of the New York State law which prohibits anyone whatsoever from
            communicating to any person information concerning contraceptives.</p>
        <p>Recognizing this condition of affairs and the tremendous evils to individual women, to
            children and to the whole social body, various groups and organizations have attempted,
            in the past four or five years, to secure amendments to the law.</p>
        <p>Within the Birth Control movement there have been two distinct opinions as to what sort
            of an amendment should be urged. One opinion has favored what has been called the
            "unlimited bill". This measure would so amend the law as to permit anyone who chose to
            do so to impart information concerning contraceptives to anyone who wishes it. It would
            accomplish this end simply by striking the words "prevention of conception" out of <name
                type="law" reg="New York State Penal Code Section 1142">Section 1142</name>. The
            amendment favored by other Birth Control advocates would allow doctors, and possibly
            midwives and nurses, to instruct in the use of contraceptives.</p>
        <p>The time has now come to analyze both of these proposed plans and make up our minds
            finally and definitely which one we should support. In arriving at our conclusion we
            must consider both what kind of an amendment it is possible to obtain in the present
            state of the public mind, and, most of all, what is <emph rend="italics">best</emph> for
            those who are going to apply for the information, once it is made available.</p>
        <p>My interest in the proposed amendments is to see American womanhood freed from forced
            maternity. Which of these bills will best bring about that liberation? How shall this
            information be given in order that the woman who receives it may be sure of obtaining
            the results desired? Will this end be served by permitting every one to give the
            information, regardless of age or condition -- physical, mental or economic? Do we
            desire that everyone, regardless of scientific knowledge, experience or ability, shall
            have the right to advise as to the use of means of preventing conception?</p>
        <p>Personally, I object to the so-called "unlimited bill." My
            objection, however, is not the usual one, that it would increase immorality. I do not
            believe that a universal knowledge of contraceptives would lead to immorality. On the
            other hand, I do believe that when instruction in the use of contraceptives is given, it
            should be given by the kind of persons best suited by training and experience to give it
            scientifically and accurately. If everyone is permitted to impart information, those who
            receive it have no guaranty that it is correct or suitable to the individual's physical
            requirements. Incorrect, unscientific information may bring good results in some cases,
            but it is more likely to cause a vast amount of disappointment and anxiety in
            others.</p>
        <p>A bill which would authorize physicians, nurses and midwives to impart information would
            meet this need. These classes of persons are equipped with the physiological and other
            knowledge to make the results of contraceptives dependable.</p>
        <p>A second point in favor of the Doctor's and Nurse's bill is that it brings the applicant
            for contraceptives into direct touch with the person giving the information. This, of
            course, means direct instructions, and specific information suitable to the individual
            case. It means that the important factors of health, physiological structure,
            temperament and economic condition can be considered and their requirements accurately
            met. </p>
        <p>A third point that must not be overlooked is that under such a measure it would be
            possible to get statistics of cases handled, methods applied, and results obtained. Thus
            there will be no guesswork as to what methods are the most reliable for certain cases.
            Thus, too, will those who give instruction improve upon the present methods and develop
            new and superior ones. A system of disseminating information which depends largely upon
            neighbors, friends and kindly relatives is not likely to give the best results. Neither
            is it likely to improve present methods and develop more desirable ones. I do not
            believe it to be more advisable to have an amateur instructor in contraceptives than to
            rely upon an amateur dentist or surgeon.</p>
        <p>The Legislative Bureau of <org>Columbia University</org>, under the direction of <person
                reg="Lindsey, Samuel McClure">Samuel McClure Lindsey</person>, has drawn the
            following bill, which in a general way, covers the ground indicated:</p>
        <p>"<q who="LINSA">Sec. 1. Section 1145 of Chapter 88 of the laws of 1909, entitled 'An Act
                providing for the punishment of crime, constituting Chapter 40 of the Consolidated
                Laws,' is hereby amended to read as follows:</q></p>
        <p>"<q who="LINSA">1145 Physicians, instruments and <emph rend="italics">information</emph>.
                An article or instrument used or applied by physicians lawfully practicing, or by
                their direction or prescription, for the cure [or] prevention of disease, is not an
                article of indecent or immoral nature or use, within this article. The supplying of
                such articles to such physicians or by their direction or prescription is not an
                offense under this article. The giving by a physician or registered nurse lawfully
                practicing of information or advice in regard to, or the supplying by any person of
                any article or medicine for, the prevention of conception, is not a violation of any
                provision of this article.</q>"</p>
        <p>"<q who="LINSA">2. This Act shall take effect immediately.</q>"</p>
        <p>With the inclusion of midwives among those authorized to impart information, I believe
            that this proposed amendment would be the best possible at this time. It would permit
            those in institutional and private practice and those in public health work to give
            freely and without fear of prosecution the information which is so sorely needed. These
            are my personal opinions, based upon my experience as a nurse and in the Birth Control
            movement. I believe, however, that the more these measures are discussed, the more
            suggestions are put forward, the better the results achieved in the end. I would
            suggest, therefore, that those interested, write their views to <title type="journal"> THE BIRTH CONTROL
                REVIEW</title>.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
