<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
<mepHeader>
<prepDate>2003-12-17 ML</prepDate>
<prepDate>2014-03-10 CH clean regs</prepDate>
<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
<docDate value="1925-09-00">Sept 1925</docDate>
<docTitle>
<titlePart>The Incident At Williamstown</titlePart>
</docTitle>
<idno>msp226889</idno>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl><title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title>, Sept. 1925, 246-47.</bibl>
<bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Papers Project</title>S71:32</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
<respStmt>
<resp/>
<name id="CIPAN">Cippico, Antonio</name>
</respStmt>
</mepHeader>
<headNote resp="MSPP">
<index level1="xxxx"/>
</headNote>
<docBody>
<head>The Incident At Williamstown</head>
<byline>by <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></byline>
<p>We are rejoicing in the incident at <place reg="Williamstown, MA">Williamstown</place>. Great
good will come of it. We mean the clash between Count <person reg="Cippico, Antonio">Antonio
Cippico</person>, a typical representative of <person reg="Mussolini, Benito">Mussolini</person>'s
Fascist régime in <place>Italy</place> and our friend <person reg="East, Edward M.">Edward M.
East</person> of <org reg="Harvard University">Harvard</org>, on the question of Italy's
overpopulation. This duel of ideas took place at the <org>Institute of Politics</org>, an annual
gathering of eminent authorities on problems of international importance, a conference conservative,
academic, and in the opinion of the New York <title type="journal">Herald-Tribune</title>, somewhat
theoretical in its speculations. Its deliberations are reported in the daily press; but seldom do
they awaken any intense public interest. Now–-all thanks to Professor East–-that is changed. He has
transmuted public lethargy into burning interest. He has demonstrated how closely bound up with the
great question of international policy are the profoundly personal problems of contraception and
Birth Control. Not one of the distinguished authorities gathered last month at Williamstown can
return to his desk or post without feeling the influence of Professor East's stimulating and
life-giving ideas.</p>
<p>First let us trace the origin of the Williamstown duel. Senator Cippico, who is the spokesman and
the astute apologist of the Mussolini policies, bravely and blandly undertook to offer the world a
solution for Italy's ever-growing problem of over-population. The world in general, and the <place
reg="United States">United States</place> in particular, were invited by the Count to contribute
land, opportunity and prosperity to Italy's swarming, spawning surplus millions. We must open wide
our doors to emigrants from Southern Italy–to all those teeming millions deprived of a foothold in
their own country. These immigrants, the Count suggested, are to remain Italians in foreign climes,
while Americans, for instance, are advised to move on to make room for these alien hordes. The
alternative is more land, more colonies by conquest, for Italy's "<q who="CIPAN">explosive
expansion</q>." The threat of war, of "expansion" was thinly veiled in Count Cippico's address.
Mussolini's government desired to avoid the "<q who="CIPAN">cruel necessity of war</q>." In brief,
we were invited to take care of the hapless fruits of Italy's reckless and uncontrolled procreative
activity.</p>
<p>Professor East answered Count Cippico's extraordinary chauvinist threat–answered it promptly,
courageously, forcibly, and his voice has been heard not merely by the two hundred scientists,
economists and statesmen gathered at Williamstown, but by the world at large. It is of tremendous
educational value. The world, asserted Professor East in effect, asks Italy to set her house in
order. Instead of spawning children with reckless rapidity and haphazard irresponsibility, when
there is no opportunity for these unfortunates to create a life of usefulness or happiness, Italy
should encourage families to restrict their numbers in accordance with opportunity. This, as we all
know, is the only safe avenue to national peace, prosperity and the progress of civilization. It is
a truth, and a feasible policy of national ethics; applicable not only to overcrowded Italy, but to
all enlightened nations. It is the only alternative to war, pestilence and famine–those inevitable
convoys of overpopulation.</p>
<p>There was nothing in Professor East's vigorous, forceful and brilliantly expressed utterance to
which any student–even a freshman–of economics or history might take offense–nothing offensive,
nothing shocking, nothing impudent, nothing harsh nor crude nor impractical. It was, as Professor
East subsequently suggested in an interview, the counsel of a benevolent family physician who does
not want to see a great career ruined by foolhardy indiscretion. But to Count Cippico, a perfect
representative of Fascist psychology, this suggestion was one of "<q who="CIPAN">cool
impudence</q>." Let us here recall that the Fascist mind resents criticism and cannot forgive those
who puncture its own delusions of grandeur. In <place reg="Rome, Italy">Rome</place> liberal
newspapers which criticize the policies of Mussolini's sinister régime are instantly suppressed.
Foreign newspaper correspondents who try to cable the impartial truth have been expelled from Italy.
Senator Cippico met Professor East's counter-attack in much the same official Fascist manner. He
denounced the "<q who="CIPAN">infamous theories of <person reg="Malthus, Thomas Robert"
>Malthus</person></q>." He condemned advocates of Birth Control as "<q who="CIPAN">apostles of
infanticide</q>." His angry, out-of-date utterances suggest that he should have gone to <place
reg="Dayton, TN">Dayton, Tennessee</place>, instead of Williamstown; for to denounce the Malthusian
law of population is no less absurd than to legislate against evolution, and to speak of the "<q
who="CIPAN">infamous theories of Malthus</q>" is as ridiculous as to condemn the law of gravitation
as immoral and materialistic. Any college freshman could inform the illustrious and astute Count and
Senator that Rev. Thomas Malthus offered no infamous remedies for overpopulation, and that Birth
Control is not infanticide, but the only remedy for the practice of abortion and infanticide. Before
undertaking to offer solutions for the problem of Italy's overpopulation, the Fascist would do well
to take an elementary course in what was once known as "political economy." Before blaming the
misfortunes of his country upon <place>France</place>, <place>England</place> or America, he might
profitably investigate the sources of its own national ills.</p>
<p>But instead, like a schoolboy unused to the weapons of mature and impartial thought, discovering
in spite of himself that the balloon of his own pet delusions had been suddenly and skillfully
punctured, Count Cippico could resort only to angry words, and like a spoiled child had to be
appeased and quieted by those who were more interested in diplomatic politeness than in invigorating
and thus often stinging truths.</p>
<p>But great good has come of this amusing and educational incident. Professor East's brilliant
advocacy of Birth Control as the only sane, enlightened and peaceable avenue to international amity
and equilibrium aroused national interest and comment. All of the metropolitan dailies published
editorial comment, most of it sane, sober and hospitable to the idea of Birth Control. There were
also a number of fine letters, some in the press and others, almost three hundred of them, addressed
to Professor East. Notable among the letters is that of <person reg="Davis, Elmer">Elmer
Davis</person> in the <title type="journal"><place reg="New York, NY">New York</place>
Times</title>, a splendid exposition of fundamental Malthusian truths concerning overpopulation,
truths which no amount of bombastic denunciations can sweep away.</p>
<em rend="italics">We cannot too enthusiastically express our gratitude to Edward M. East for his
splendid, courageous and clear-cut advocacy of Birth Control at the Institute of Politics. His
splendid utterance have had the effect of transmuting our notorious American indifference to
international problems into a warm and vivid interest. Birth Control, as an implement of enlightened
national progress, thanks to his efforts, is making further headway into our national consciousness.
Professor East is doing valiant pioneer work in opening new avenues of thought; and we are confident
that all the distinguished authorities who listened to him at Williamstown will return to their
posts conscious of a new angle of approach to the great complex problems of international relations
they are seeking to solve. For the rest of us, let us give assurance to such a statesman and scholar
as Edward M. East, that we appreciate his unflinching championship of the truth, which has again
been brilliantly dramatized by this incident at Williamstown.</em>
</docBody>
</doc>
