<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Printed article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2003/07/02 SB</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-09 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1923-07-00">Jul 1923</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>The Responsibility of an Idea</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp226922</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">The Birth Control Review</title>, Jul. 1923, 171.</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S70:1007</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </mepHeader>
    <docBody>
        <head>The Responsibility of an Idea</head>
        <p>Remember this: there can be no progress in this old world of ours unless there is loyal
            allegiance to ideas. Men and women differ from one another, because the things they
            believe in are different. But sincerely to believe in an idea is to support it. Only
            when an idea is supported–-supported generously and whole-heartedly–-only when it is put
            into action can it make its mark on the world in general and on men and women in
            particular. Passive belief–-will-nilly, weak-kneed, faint-hearted acceptance of an idea
            is not enough. It is worse than cynicism; it is a harmful disease of the will. We must
            put our impulses into action. We must take sides. We must be battlers for Light and
            Liberty, or for the Powers of Darkness. Suppose that <person reg="Edison, Thomas Alva"
                >Edison</person> or <person reg="Westinghouse, George">Westinghouse</person> or
                <person reg="Ford, Henry">Henry Ford</person>, having conceived some idea that would
            advance civilization, had been content to sit back and indulge in day-dreams about it!
            Personally we may not wish to engage in the battle for an idea. But life becomes
            infinitely more exciting, more full of zest, of enjoyment, when we support, at least
            spiritually and morally, those who are actually on the battle front. The success of an
            idea, the triumph of a movement, depend, in the final analysis, on those who possess the
            courage of their convictions, a courage upstanding and direct enough to inspire them to
            stand behind their belief and to put it into action. The Birth Control movement in this
            country is constantly making friends. But the only way to assure us of your friendship
            and your adherence to the ideal of Birth Control is to express your belief in it openly,
            both in public and in private, and for each one to support the movement to the utmost of
            one's moral and financial ability. A dollar contributed to charities and philanthropies
            means a dollar spent to perpetuate these social efforts. Every penny contributed to
            Birth Control means a blow at the root of the social diseases which call into existence
            our organized charities and philanthropies. The campaigners for Birth Control are in the
            trenches in this war against poverty, mental defect, and maternal slavery. We are
            cheerfully willing to work, to fight, to sacrifice and to endure abuse and
            misunderstanding. But we need the support and allegiance of those who accept our ideals.
            If those who believe in Birth Control would support the movement generously and
            whole-heartedly the struggle would be of short duration. There is a serious
            responsibility resting on all those who accept an idea. If the mind has become
            illuminated and the principle is seen and accepted, action must follow. He who is
            convinced of new, dynamic truth must assume the spiritual responsibility for carrying
            the idea into action and for following it up to completion and success.</p>
        <byline><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">M.S.</person></byline>
    </docBody>
</doc>
