<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/07/07 NC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-21 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1940-03-11">11 Mar 1940</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Radio Message--Station WFAS</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp228178</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S72:0141</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Sanger delivered this address on staion <org reg="WFAS (New York)"
                >WFAS</org> in New York, NY at 2:00 P.M. in March of 1940.</p>
        <index level1="birth control"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="American opinion on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="war and"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Message from Mrs. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person> to be
            delivered over Station WFAS</head>
        <dateline><date value="1940-03-11">March 11, 1940 -- 2:00 P.M.</date></dateline>

        <p><emph rend="underline">Friends:</emph> It is a matter of much regret to me that I cannot
            participate personally in what I regard as a unique occasion, marking the recognition by
            an influential radio station that birth control so deeply concerns the welfare of our
            people that it merits wider discussion over the Forums of the Air, as well as in the
            Forums of the public press and lecture platform. All honor to Station
                W.F.A.S.!</p>
        <p>I welcome this opportunity, however, to express my thanks to the countless unseen
            friends, whose loyal and sustained support throughout the dark and difficult years, have
            made our present progress possible.</p>
        <p>Now that the recent <org>Gallup poll</org> has unmistakably pointed its prophetic finger
            towards the future--for in a democracy the will of the people must eventually come to
            pass--it is to be hoped and expected that conservative public health officials will be
            encouraged to move ahead more confidently. For 77% of American voters have now
            registered their opinion that birth control should be added to existing government
            health services! Motherhood may soon indeed become for ALL mothers a blessed privilege,
            rather than an unwelcome burden imposed by a relentless nature.</p>
        <p>In a war-torn world, we see the tragedies resulting from the fact that little or no
            consideration has ever been given to the quality of life; only to its quantity; and the
            quantity has been enormous, making life cheap indeed. In birth control we have the means
            of raising the quality of life itself; a basic element in any constructive program for
            “Race Building in a Democracy.”</p>


    </docBody>
</doc>
