<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Autograph Draft Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011-08-04 NC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011-08-23 CH Proofed</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011-09-15 EK indexed and mounted; corrections added</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011-09-16 CH/EK Proofed</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011-09-20 EK proofed corrections added</prepDate><prepDate>2014-07-10 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1952-09-00"><supplied resp="MSPP">Sept 1952</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Suggestions for an Experimental Birth Control
                    Clinic</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp230858</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S72:808</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>This handwritten draft was enclosed in a Sept. 1952 letter to <person
                reg="Bohn, Frank">Frank Bohn</person>, who wrote speeches for <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>, as
            material for two short speeches she would present in <place>Japan</place>. No published version has
            been found.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits and risks of"/>
        <index level1="birth control clinics and leagues"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="educational benefits of"/>       
        <index level1="birth control clinics and leagues" level2="marriage counseling at"/>
        <index level1="birth control clinics and leagues" level2="research benefits of"/> 
        <index level1="fertility rates"/>
        <index level1="sex education"/>
       <index level1="birth control" level2="definitions of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <p><add>I want to humbly</add> Suggest an Experimental Bc Clinic--or center not only to
            disseminate information on contraceptive methods but to be a human Research laboratory
            for Social &amp; Scientific Research. It should demonstrate the practicability of b.c.
            on health, moral, civic &amp; humane grounds. It should be a teaching center to which
            Medical Students can come for instruction &amp; technical knowledge. This center would
            be the laboratory or research institute for clinical &amp; laboratory aspects of all
            methods of contraception. It would become the center of studies in the field of human
            fertility. It could embrace the field of Infertility &amp; help those who want to have
            healthy strong children--</p>
        <p><del>It could extend its teaching to <add>the</add> counselling the married----</del></p>
        <p>Marriage Counselling could be a part of its work -- all phases of human fertility to be
            recorded. Marriage <unclear>guidance</unclear> is also a part of the <org
                reg="Margaret Sanger Research Bureau">Bureau</org>s field work where couples -- men
            &amp; women want guidance relative to each other &amp; the development of children. </p>
        <p>This department includes advice relative to mother-in laws--which in certain
            circumstances can be a “trouble spot” in the home, all these factors may be more evident
            in the Occidental world than in the Oriental. But we all grow out of the old habits into
            relatively new ones. </p>
        <p>There are several definite reasons to practice Bc-- But first let us know the meaning of
            the term -- as it was my own idea to call it that, “Bc, is the <emph rend="underline"
                >conscious control</emph> of the Birth Rate by means that <emph rend="underline"
                >Prevent</emph> conception.” There are three words which have meaning when people
            criticize the term Birth Control. The words are <emph rend="underline">Prevent,</emph>,
                <add>to</add>
            <emph rend="underline">control</emph>
            <add>&amp; to be</add>
            <emph rend="underline">conscious</emph>. To <emph rend="underline">prevent</emph>
            conception means to keep the male &amp; female eggs apart--when this is done there is
            no life started-- It is not different biologically or physically than remaining
            unmarried or practicing continence.</p>
        <p>To control means the intelligent ability to apply knowledge to your sex life--<emph
                rend="underline">control</emph> means to have children <emph rend="underline"
                >when</emph> you want them &amp; to have the number you desire to have-- It does not
            mean to <emph rend="underline">limit</emph> but to control. </p>
        <p>Conscious also means knowledge &amp; intelligence applied to your life not to be a victim
            of superstition &amp; chance.</p>
        <p>Children should be conceived in love &amp; wanted before they are conceived. The special
            reasons to use birth control are various. </p>
        <p>The first is to be sure the child will be healthy &amp; not carry traits to physical or
            mental to handicap its development &amp; progress in life. So,</p>
        <p>(1) Men &amp; women who have any transmittable disease should <emph rend="underline">not
                have</emph> children. </p>
        <p>(2) Parents who may show no physical</p>
        <p>(3) &amp; tB. kidney</p>
        <p>4-</p>
        <p>5-</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
