<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011-07-29 NC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-25 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1952-01-00"><supplied resp="MSPP">Jan 1952</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>New Years Greetings to the Women of Japan from Margaret Sanger</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp231041</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S77:0066</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="birth control" level2="in Japan"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>New Years Greetings to the women of Japan from Margaret Sanger</head>
        <p>Happy New Year to the women of <place>Japan</place>. May this year bring all women of the
            world into closer agreement to do all in our power to put a stop to all military
            aggression that may lead to another world war. </p>
        <p>When I first visited Japan in 1922 I realized how ignorant all western people were
            regarding the status, intelligence, education, and beauty and charm of the women of
            Japan. Everywhere I found hundreds of young women, journalists, writers, editors, as
            well as hundreds taking part in other professions.</p>
        <p>But the subject of birth control had not at that time seeped into the country. But as
            soon as it was understood the beautiful phrase “like the lightening”, the men as well as
            the women wanted to learn all about it and put it into practice. I called out to all
            women that we, as mothers, were at fault. We had produced explosive populations which
            would convert all peace pledges into scraps of paper. We have since that time seen this
            happen in <place>Europe</place>. Women must control births and lift motherhood to a
            plane of a voluntary, intelligent function, and thereby remake the world. When
            populations of all countries are thus controlled with women at the helm the world will
            be remade and it will exceed the dream of statesman, reformer and revolutionist.</p>
        <p>In October, 1955 we will meet in <place reg="Tokyo, Japan">Tokyo</place> to discuss the
            problems of population, not only of Japan, but of the world in general. My best wishes
            to you, one and all, until we meet again.</p>
        <p><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></p>


    </docBody>
</doc>
