<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Autograph Draft Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011-08-04 NC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011-08-23 CH Tagging proofed</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011-09-15 EK index terms added</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-26 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1952-11-00"><supplied resp="MSPP">Nov. 1952</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Midwives Annual</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp231042</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S72:0803</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="BIB">Bible, The</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>Sanger was in <place>Japan</place> from October 30 to November 9, 1952. No information
            has been found on if or where this article was published. Written on the letterhead of
            the <org>Prince Hotel</org> in <place reg="Tokyo, Japan">Tokyo</place>.</p>
        <index level1="child spacing"/>
        <index level1="midwives" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="midwives" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="nurses" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="nurses" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues" level3="physicians and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Midwives Annual</head>
        <p>Perhaps it can be said without question that the two Professions in the Modern World
            where there is the closest relationship between the professional &amp; laymen is the
            Midwives &amp; Nurse (practical) professions-- </p>
        <p>It is truly a great privilege to belong to either group. -- but a privilege only if the
            nurse or midwife’s heart is completely in the work. She must love people. She must love
            to care for them regardless of race, sex or creed. This caring for people &amp; caring
            to make them well &amp; healthy must be her religion if she is to be a success &amp; be
            happy in her job. It is not the same with a Doctor of Medicine -- He has the Scientific
            abstract -- objective approach toward his patient. Patients become cases in many
            illnesses. He shares his opinion his skills his treatments &amp; results with his fellow
            members of his profession. He is happy in a different way &amp; for a different reason
            than the Nurse or Midwife who may be helping him obtain his results. </p>
        <p>While the necessity “<q who="BIB">to earn ones bread by the sweat of the brow</q>” cab be
            100% true in nursing the sick -- it should never be forgotten that a long range view of
            the patients health by those attending care produce butter &amp; jam on the bread &amp;
            not bread alone. </p>
        <p>When during the early years of the beginning of our educational campaign on birth control
            it has the usual question on the lips of obstetricians &amp; gynecologists &amp;
            midwives ask -- where will we end in our practice if women practice birth control and
            cease to have children -- The answer is that women have not ceased having children --
            they have spaced their pregnancies through knowledge of contraceptives. They have born
            fewer but healthy babies during the years. Instead of a baby every 18 months or two
            years totaling six children in ten year. Sometimes seven or eight, with disease, of
            deficiency, debts -- hunger, nervous disorder of parents &amp; children.</p>
        <p>The parents have born two or three children spaced two &amp; a half to three years
            between, giving the mother an opportunity to recuperate from the ordeal of one birth a
            rest and a period to prepare her body &amp; nervous condition for the coming of the next
            wanted baby. A wanted baby has the feeling of security all its life. By wanted I mean
            wanted before conception not after birth. We all love &amp; want to keep alive the baby
            after we see it &amp; nurse it. </p>
        <p>While I was the <emph rend="underline">one person</emph> leading the Educational work
            throughout the English Speaking world who stood out strongly for Medical Control of the
            BC Clinic, I still believe it was the correct procedure even tho it was <unclear>many
                years</unclear></p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
