<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2002/10/23 CH</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-03-10 CH clean regs</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-08 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1921-11-18">18 Nov 1921</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Closing Remarks at First American Birth Control
					Conference</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp231277</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="book">Proceedings of the First American Birth Control
					Conference</title>, Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith
				College. </bibl>
			<bibl><title type="mf">Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Sophia Smith Collection</title>
				S67:916-18.</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name/>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>After a police raid broke up the November 13 closing session of the <org>First American
				Birth Control Conference</org>, <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger</person>
			rescheduled the meeting at <place reg="New York, NY">New York</place>'s <org>Park
				Theater</org> a few days later. After the keynote speech by <person
				reg="Cox, Harold">Harold Cox</person>, a discussion followed. Sanger closed the
			discussion and meeting with the following. For Sanger's other statements at this
			conference see "<xref from="229953.xml">Opening Remarks</xref>," and "<xref
				from="229952.xml">The Use of the Pessary</xref>," both on Nov. 11, 1921. For a
			transcript of the entire session see MSM S67:881.</p>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="methods and devices" level3="continence"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="morality of"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="opposition to"/>
		<index level1="women" level2="freedom and rights of"/>
		<index level1="marriage" level2="MS on"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<p>Friends. I feel that it is much more difficult to answer the questions of those who are
			neither with us nor against us, much harder than it is to have to answer the question of
			a thorough going opponent. None of those who have spoken tonight have been entirely
			against us. Most of them have agreed, or both of them have agreed with us on principle,
			but have disagreed with us on methods. If only we could have more discussion along this
			line, we would get somewhere.</p>
		<p>Now, the assumption of both the <person reg="Chase, William Shafe"><person
					reg="Jacobs, Theodore">last speakers</person></person> has been that there is
			some other method of birth control than the mechanical use of contraceptives. They infer
			that it would be higher and better to perhaps remain continent or to use what is some
			times termed self control, although those words were not used I presume that that is
			what they were trying to get at. Now, we want to say that we have no objection to any
			individuals using self control. (applause) We leave that entirely to your individual
			freedom. But what we do contend is this. That in the first place, the laws of these
			various states are so construed that unless a woman gives of herself to her husband, she
			does not have his support. (applause) A woman cannot attain to any kind of freedom when
			she is forced into pregnancy every year or year and a half. Women must have leisure.
			Leisure to think. She must have control over her own body. She must have time to evolve
			and to develop her own soul development. So must man. And certainly a man who finds that
			he is the father of a child every year or two soon finds that this home is not the home
			of his honeymoon dreams, and we find them running out to secure their entertainment in
			the evening elsewhere than by the fireside.</p>
		<p>Now, if we do believe in self-control, what do you mean by that? Do you mean absolute
			continence in marriage? Then why marry? If you believe in the marriage relationship only
			for the procreation of children, then that would mean such a union and relationship but
			once or twice perhaps in a life time.</p>
		<p>Now, I contend that that argument is perfectly absurd because it places man upon the same
			level as animals. In other words, you use the procreative act only for procreation, and
			I contend that there is another side, and another use of this relationship. (applause) I
			contend that it is just as sacred and just as beautiful for two people to express their
			love when they have no intention whatsoever of being parents. (applause) And I contend
			that they can go into that relationship with the same beauty and the same holiness with
			which they go into music or to prayer. I believe that it is the right understanding of
			our sexual power and of its creative energy that gives us spiritual illumination. I say
			that there is more than one use to make of it, and that is the higher use, the
			development of our soul development and soul growth.</p>
		<p>I find that there is practically no argument against birth control. I have gone far
			across this country, and almost around the world, and I have never yet met a real
			argument against birth control. (applause) And why? Because it is the one need of the
			people, because this subject belongs mainly to women. It is the first step that woman
			must take to have her real emancipation. It is the first step that we must take to free
			our children. It is the first, last and final step that we all are to take to have real
			human emancipation. (applause)</p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
