<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed document">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2012-06-18 AW Initial Tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-17 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1958-12-17">17 Dec 1958</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Statement for Proposed Souvenir</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp231341</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm: Smith College Series</title> S72:72</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="conferences" level2="International Conference on Planned Parenthood"
            level3="1958 (6th)"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="International Planned Parenthood Federation"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="descriptions of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>STATEMENT BY MARGARET SANGER for Proposed Souvenir of <org
                reg="International Planned Parenthood Federation">IPPF</org>
            <emph rend="underline">Sixth International Conference</emph></head>
        <p>Once again after five years, we, the International Planned Parenthood Federation meet for
            our international sessions in India. This <org
                reg="International Conference on Planned Parenthood, 6th">Sixth International
                Conference on Planned Parenthood</org> is our second Conference convened in
                <place>India</place>, as we held our <org
                reg="International Conference on
                Planned Parenthood, 3rd">Third
                International Conference</org> at <place reg="Bombay, India">Bombay</place> in
            1952.</p>
        <p>In the years since that Third Conference, India has achieved much and advanced far in
            educating Government Officials as well as the general public about the importance of
            family planning and birth control. It is with profound gratitude and pride that we of
            the IPPF congratulate all the people of India who have made this progress, and
            especially those leaders of the <org>Family Planning Association of India</org> who have
            been in the forefront of the program.</p>
        <p>It is a matter of much personal gratification to me that one of India’s <person
                reg="Unknown">leading business men</person> reported in a <place
                reg="Los Angeles, CA">Los Angeles, California</place>, Newspaper last autumn that,
                "<q who="UNK">As <person reg="Gandi, Mohandas">Mohandas Ghandi</person> was the
                leader before independence in India, <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret
                    Sanger</person> is the leader for India today, meaning that our Nation can
                progress faster if its people practice birth control as expounded by Mrs. Sanger for
                many years</q>.” Although this praise must be accepted for our cause rather than for
            me as an individual, it is good to find that progressive business men of India now are
            taking this position in favor of birth control, which I knew your scientists and doctors
            had taken for a long while. </p>
        <p>The full cooperation of the <org reg="India Government">Government of India</org> in the
            preparation of this Conference is a most welcome approval of the importance of our
            goals, as is the increasing place given to the planned parenthood services in the
            budgets of the Five Year Plans. </p>
        <p>My best wishes to all the friends and co-workers who have made this Sixth International
            Conference on Planned Parenthood possible. </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
