<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Autograph Draft Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011-09-09 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2013-04-23 CH Proof tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2013-04-29 AW Correct tags</prepDate><prepDate>2014-07-03 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1955-10-24">24 Oct 1955</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Greetings to the Fifth International Conference on
                    Planned Parenthood</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp232463</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S72:936</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Draft of a speech prepared for the Fifth International Conference on
            Planned Parenthood, held in Tokyo, Japan.</p><p>For Sanger's other speech at this
            meeting, see "<xref from="232462.xml">Planned Parenthood: A Cultural Civilization Will
                Bring World Peace</xref>," Oct. 24, 1955. For another version see <title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title>
            S72:938.</p>
        <index level1="International Conference on Planned Parenthood, 5th (1955 Tokyo)"/>
        <index level1="International Planned Parenthood Federation"/>
        <index level1="Family Planning Federation of Japan"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <p> On behalf of the officers of the <org reg="International Planned Parenthood Federation"
                >Int PPF</org> it is my pleasure to express our thanks to the addresses of welcome
            especially by the <person reg="Miki, Takeo">Minister of Welfare of the Government of
                    <place reg="Tokyo, Japan">Tokyo</place></person> Metropolis.</p>
        <p>It is also my privilege to thank the <org reg="Family Planning Federation of Japan">F.P.
                Fed of Japan</org> for inviting us to come to <place reg="Japan">this charming
                country</place> &amp; hold our <org type="Conference"
                reg="International Conference on Planned Parenthood, 5th (1955, Tokyo)">fifth Int
                Conference on BC</org> here in Tokyo. </p>
        <p>In my last years of experience I know a good deal about the organization of Conferences.
            I <supplied resp="MSPP">know</supplied> the importance of sweat &amp; tears, the
            headaches &amp; heartaches all of which combine to meld together strong bonds of minds
            &amp; hearts. These qualities have been evident for the past year by the Japanese
            Planning Committee. They have worked voluntarily, they each have had positions to hold
            during the regular eight hours &amp; conference work had to be done in after hours often
            late in the night.</p>
        <p>They have had no office, so secretary, little funds, a battered typewriter, and had to
            face all the primitive <supplied>expedients</supplied> where only faith, love &amp;
                <emph rend="underline">caring</emph> spurred on their endeavors. Today you are to
            see the results which this courageous group has organized &amp; presented on paper.</p>
        <p>It is now the same qualities of faith &amp; love &amp; caring on our part as delegates to
            bring this into realization.</p>
        <p>It is a special joy to me that I do not have to make any special address as there are
            Scientists of various categories to tell you what I would like to say, it will be told
            from <add>the</add> experience of experts and will be of historical importance for our
            future civilization--</p>
        <p>Again may I thank you who have come from far away lands some at great Sacrifice to pool
            their ideas &amp; experiences. This week is to be a record breaker of high standing for
            quality of clear thinking &amp; frank discussion-- My gratitude the warmth of my hear
            that you are here. </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
