<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/09/12 KG</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-01 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1955-10-24">24 Oct 1955</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Planned Parenthood: A Cultural Civilization Will Bring World
                Peace</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp232462</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="book">Fifth Report of the Proceedings of the International Conference
                    on Planned Parenthood</title>, (Tokyo, Japan, 1955), pp. 6-8.</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S72:0955</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="VOGWI">Vogt, William</name>
            <name id="BROHE">Broadly, Herbert</name>
            <name id="BLACP">Blacker, C. P.</name>
            <name id="CLEHA">Cleveland, Harlan</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>This was the opening speech for the <org
                reg="International Conference on Planned Parenthood, 5th">Fifth International
                Conference on Planned Parenthood</org>, held in <place>Tokyo, Japan</place>, on
            October 24-29, 1955. For earlier drafts, see <title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title>
            S72:940, S72:944, and S72:946.</p>
        <index level1="Asia" level2="overpopulation and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="international"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="population and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="war and"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="population growth and"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="population policies of"/>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="population policies of"/><index level1="overpopulation"/>
        <index level1="overpopulation" level2="effects of"/><index level1="overpopulation"
            level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="overpopulation" level2="threat to peace as"/>
        <index level1="peace" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="population control" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="population growth" level2="natural resources and"/>
        <index level1="population growth" level2="regulation of"/>
        <index level1="population growth" level2="standard of living and"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="speaking tours" level3="1955 (Japan)"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>PLANNED PARENTHOOD: A CULTURAL CIVILIZATION WILL BRING WORLD PEACE</head>
        <byline><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">MARGARET SANGER</person>, LL.D. (HON.) <lb/><emph
                rend="italics">Founder, <org>Margaret Sanger Research Bureau</org>, <place
                    reg="New York, NY">New York</place>;</emph>
            <lb/>
            <emph rend="italics">President, <org>International Planned Parenthood
                Federation</org></emph></byline>
        <p>May I express the warmth in my heart as I greet all of you, and as I return to the East.
            I first came to your lovely, green islands in 1922, thirty-three years ago. Then the
            question of population control as a necessity for world health and peace had no
            international forum and was fiercely beset by nationalist, expansionist aims. Now we are
            meeting for the Fifth International Conference with delegates from seventeen countries.
            It is surely significant that, in 1955, two great nations of the
                East--<place>Japan</place> and <place>India</place>--are the first countries of the
            world to place population control within the functions of the state.</p>
        <p>I feel again in this East, as I felt it in the earlier years, a surge of concern for the
            individual human being, a determination to raise the dignity of mankind. There are grave
            hazards in man’s path to happiness, health and peace. He needs wise leadership to guide
            in these troubled, anxious times.</p>
        <p>World crisis follows world crisis; great statesmen rush from one meeting to another
            across huge areas of the globe. National potentates make endless “friendly” visits. An
            incident in one remote outpost alerts half the world for action. Modern communication
            makes the world an agitated audience, swung now to hopeful optimism, alternating between
            hope and bitter resignation.</p>
        <p>This conference is concerned with a basic world problem--population-control through
            planned parenthood. <person reg="Malthus, Thomas Robert">Malthus</person> was correct,
            if premature, in his prophesy. His message was obscured by the great expansionist forces
            of the 19th century. The world is catching up with Malthus. Population pressures are
            enormous; they affect each country of the world economically and psychologically. The
            nature of this pressure is not commonly understood; the clash and tangle on a thousand
            fronts is often the result of action taken without previous definition of goals.</p>
        <p>Our experts here today will tell you that during the last 300 years global population has
            shot from five hundred million to two billion five hundred million! Every twenty-four
            hours there are 100,000 more people on this planet. <place>Western Europe</place> now
            adds annually about three million people; the <place reg="United States">US</place> adds
            about three million each year, and the Asian countries 10-20 million a year. Meanwhile,
            modern techniques cut the death-rate all over the world. Consider only that malaria
            control in <place>Ceylon</place> reduced the death-rate from 20.3 per thousand in 1946
            to 12.6 in 1949--no similar birth control during the same period.</p>
        <p>In 1952 the <title type="journal">United Nations Bulletin</title> of the <org
                reg="United Nations Food and Agriculture Organization">FAO</org> stated that in the
            immediate post-war period, the population of the world increased 12 to 14 per cent. In
            spite of our great technical progress, at least two-thirds of the world’s people at the
            present time cannot obtain enough calories to maintain normal standards of health and
            efficiency. Two-thirds of the world’s estimated 900 million children are underfed, while
            at the same time certain nations still call for more babies. It is estimated for the
            Asian countries that by 1956 the population will be 31 per cent greater than in the
            middle thirties, while food supply and agricultural output generally will be only 19 per
            cent greater. There is a demographic point of no return!</p>
        <p>This great lag between the present population and the actual results of our best
            scientific skill to supply it is the basic great threat to the world--not the alarms,
            the ideologies, the conflicting national aims which meet the surface eye and ear. If
            birth-rates are not sensibly balanced with death-rates in the individual countries there
            can be no fundamental planning for the separate countries no at the global level. This
            is not being done in most countries: the means employed to meet our problems are largely
            palliative. Confusion, anxiety, stop-gap measures--and even starvation--are the
            results.</p>
        <p>Was this population problem discussed during the recent meeting “at the summit”? Were
            these world leaders accompanied by demographic experts? Did such experts have equal
            weight with the foreign-policy expert, the historian, the domestic adviser? They did
            not, and it means--to get at the heart of it--that these leaders were really ducking the
            main issue, the basic issue inextricably bound to each of the problems discussed on the
            surface level.</p>
        <p>Various agencies of the <org>United Nations</org> are concerned with aspects of this
            problem, and we must call upon them for greater help. In a sense, however, the UN is
            held in a great vice. Their reports and studies often give way to religious and
            nationalist traditions which constantly obscure fundamental facts of health, welfare and
            peace. They often state many of the facts, but they feel it impossible to equate them to
            the obvious solution, population control. Population control is necessary if the
            separate countries are to make firmly knit units within comprehensive global
            planning.</p>
        <p>Thousands of good-will organizations in the world are giving lavishly of time and money.
            Which ones dare speak out boldly on the population problem? In all there is a great
            outpouring of generosity and kindly acts, but as <person reg="Vogt, William">Dr. William
                Vogt</person> points out: “<q who="VOGWI">...token operations seem to salve our
                consciences. They have the very serious defect of making it possible for many
                people, even our leaders, to act as though they were coping with reality; in truth
                they are going through motions that conceal a rapidly declining position.</q>”</p>
        <p>The wide, wild swing of the pendulum between hope and fear that forms a pattern of world
            anxiety must be checked by simultaneous struggles inall fields of human relations. the
            greatest of these anxiety forces lies in population pressure. We must demonstrate this
            truth again and again, slowly, constantly, so the world will accept and recognize it. It
            is the prime purpose of this conference to sound and re-sound this threat to the peace
            of the world.</p>
        <p>The Deputy Director-General of FAO (<person reg="Broadly, Herbert">Sir Herbert
                Broadly</person>) has written : “<q who="BROHE">Where birth-rates continue to
                advance, as is the case in many countries--and not only in the underdeveloped
                countries--where death-rates and human mortality are being halved ... we cannot just
                sit back and let Nature take its course. If we do, Nature’s course will be a very
                desperate one. It is only through international action that wise solutions can be
                achieved.” Many of you have spoken bravely and eloquently on world forums--and will
                speak on this world forum.</q>"</p>
        <p>Now I would like to turn to an aspect of the problem that is always, and increasingly
            dear to my heart--the individual, the single man or woman. The chanting chorus of his
            rising hopes and then his anxious despair is the cruellest sound in any land.</p>
        <p>When there is a great fire, a serious accident, an epidemic, the local mobilization of
            human effort is an astonishing thing. The innate goodness, the concern, and the
            abilities of the human mind and body are put to immediate, positive use, to prevent this
            ever happening again.</p>
        <p>Yet, each day there are born--in all countries--human defectives; mentally and physically
            lost children, children who cannot be loved or cared for. Such births bring no dramatic
            mobilization of the public resources. True, separate beings feel the grief of such, and
            we make colossal efforts to house, feed, and care for them in thousands of
                institutions--<emph rend="italics">after</emph> they are born. Just as we resort to
            superficial action on a global scale, so level man engages in a maze of surface action:
            charity-calls, community-chest drives, and ever-increasing taxation. The fundamental
            problem is left untouched--namely, that the child should not have been born, knowingly
            born to congenitally diseased or unwilling parents. Each of these births unleashes a
            train of difficulties which are now faced only on a confused, surface level.</p>
        <p>There is an enormous amount of common sense in the heart of men and women. We must trust
            this innate goodness; we must appeal to it in the simplest, clearest way. We must give
            more and more practical help to individuals or parents. The average parent responds to
            the human side of planned parenthood--a wanted child in a stable home. The individual
            can most easily see it in terms his own family: the health of the mother, the happiness
            of the household, the true harmonious growth of the family unit. He can be shown that
            such family units make a health nation; that public-health planning is a joint problem
            for him and for his society. We can help him break through many psychological barriers
            if we never lose sight of the heart of this separate man.</p>
        <p><person reg="Blacker, C. P.">Dr. C.P. Blacker</person>, speaking to the <org
                reg="International Conference on Planned Parenthood, 3rd">Third International
                Conference</org> at <place reg="Bombay, India">Bombay</place>, said: “<q who="BLACP"
                >There exists, I believe, and unassessably large matrix of goodness in the world
                which, though largely unnoticed and unrecorded, is yet responsible for the
                refinement of morals and the spread of human ideals. These forces, unlike the
                excursions and alarms which history records, but like the processes of physiological
                healing, are almost wholly silent. Yet they provide the essential motive power
                behind social progress.</q>”</p>
        <p>This paradox--and the gulf between the simple, known needs of man and woman and the
            general social confusion--is dramatic in each country. In the <place>United
                States</place> we boast of our five to six hundred planned parenthood clinics, of
            our studies of fertility and infertility. Yet, the sad fact remains that millions of
            mothers cannot come to our clinics nor do they have knowledge of our research projects.
            We must use other means to reach these families. Economists have said that half the
            world’s population is experiencing a “<q who="CLEHA">revolution of expectations</q>”.
            Individual man is often submerged in areas where material progress hardly touches
            him--when he is close to hunger amid the plenty.</p>
        <p>Perhaps it is the East which will resolve this paradox. Your ancient cultures are rooted
            in knowledge and achievement. This is clear even now during the turbulent movements of
            recent years when the triumphs of the industrial West have rolled across the ancient
            East. Japan and India have looked squarely at the population problem before them, and
            each has drawn the necessary conclusions. Planned parenthood has to be a part of
            national planning if there is to be any hope of a peaceful society. You have had the
            courage to act!</p>
        <p>Reports of family planning activity come from all over the East to the offices of the
            IPPF: from Japan, <place>Hong Kong</place>, <place>Formosa</place>,
                <place>Thailand</place>, <place>Malaya</place>, the great movements in India, from
                <place>Pakistan</place>. The experiments of <person reg="Koya, Yoshio">Dr. Yoshio
                Koya</person> here in Japan, the work of countless others, is a tribute to your
            people and to your nation. In 1954 the Japanese birth-rate was below 20 per thousand and
            the death rate below 9--the lowest levels of fertility and mortality ever achieved by an
            Asian nation. Certainly the picture is clouded by the problem of abortion, but education
            and your intelligence will swing the balance to planned control before conception rather
            than the ancient destruction of the foetus.</p>
        <p>Each country must work within its own natural framework; problems will be countless and
            pressing; the important thing is that you have the courage--and the wisdom--to act.
            Again, may I express the great warmth in my heart as I stand before you today. The work
            of this conference must go forward on many fronts. With basic goals defined, all these
            fronts must share the battle. If we never lose sight of the inarticulate masses the
            struggle will come out all right. This knowledge of--and communication with--the average
            man and woman is the real forward tide of history. Let us push it, let us guide it, and
            the glory will be world-wide.</p>
        <p>PRESENTATION TO FAMILY PLANNING FEDERATION OF JAPAN</p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger presented to the <org>Family Planning Federation of Japan</org> a statue,
            “Mother and Child,” made by <person reg="Golden, Charles">Charles Golden</person>, a
            well-known artist from <place reg="Tucson, AZ">Tucson, Arizona</place> (Mrs. Sanger’s
            home-town), in appreciation of all the work which the Japanese Federation had put into
            the preparation of the Fifth International Conference on Planned Parenthood.</p>
        <p/>
    </docBody>
</doc>
