<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011-08-04 NC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011-09-15 EK index terms added</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2013-04-30 CH proof and enter tags</prepDate><prepDate>2014-07-03 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1954-12-06">6 Dec 1954</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Message to the 2nd All India Conference on Family Planning</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp232717</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S77:071</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">Sanger sent this message to Lady <person reg="Rama Rau, Dhanvanthi">Rama
            Rau</person> to express her regrets on being unable to attend the <org
            reg="All India Conference on Family Planning, Second">conference</org>. <index
            level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues" level3="in India"/>
        <index level1="conferences" level2="All India Conference on Family Planning" level3="1954"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="international conferences on"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="birth control movement in"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>MESSAGE TO THE 2nd. ALL INDIA CONFERENCE ON FAMILY PLANNING</head>
        <p>To Lady Rama Rau and Friends of the Family Planning Association of India</p>
        <p>Kindly convey to the delegates and co-workers of the <org
                reg="Family Planning Association of India">F.P.A. of India</org> my compliments and
            congratulations for the splendid accomplishments of the past two years.</p>
        <p>I regret that I can not be with you for your second national meeting to congratulate in
            person the accomplishments as a result of hard work and consecrated devotion.</p>
        <p>What <place>India</place> has accomplished relative to family planning centers and the
            spread of this educational reform has been a great surprise and inspiration to many of
            us who have labored through the years. What has taken us twenty years to accomplish,
            India has done in two years. Yours is the first <org reg="Government of India"
                >Government</org> to have contributed to the spread of this work, and now with
            reports from some of your scientists in the scientific laboratories they are on their
            way to develop simple cheap contraceptives, which is indeed much to be desired. And
            again my congratulations and hearty best wishes for the continued success of your work
            and the worldwide inspiration that your Family Planning Association of India has give to
            us all. </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
