<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011-08-05 NC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2012-03-28 CH proofed tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-04 EK clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1954-04-18">18 Apr 1954</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Address Before the <org reg="Japan Family Planning Federation">Japan Family Planning Association</org></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp232986</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Magaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S72:0897</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger</person> gave this address at
            the first meeting of the <org>Japan Family Planning Federation</org>
            in <place>Tokyo, Japan</place>.</p>
        <p>Sanger wrote words and numbers summarizing the paragraphs in the left
            margin. These have been transcribed at the end of the paragraph.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="in Japan"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="in India"/>"
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>ADDRESS BEFORE THE FIRST INAUGURAL MEETING OF THE NATIONAL FAMILY
            PLANNNING ASSOCIATION</head>
        <byline>Mrs. Margaret Sanger</byline>
        <dateline><date value="1954-04-18">April 18, 1954</date></dateline>
        <p>Today as President of the <org>International Planned Parenthood
                Federation</org>, I bring you cordial congratulatory greetings.
            You have done a fine splendid thing in organizing the various groups
            in your country into a National Association assembled here today,
            the <org><emph rend="underline">Japan Family Planning
                    Federation</emph></org>. </p>
        <p>The International Planned Parenthood Federation consists of nine
            national organizations. All of these have voted for and welcomed
            into the World Organization your <emph rend="underline">Japanese
                Family Planning</emph> group as a full member of the Federation.
            This World group have also in <place reg="Stockholm, Sweden"
                >Stockholm</place> last August at its <org
                reg="International Conference on Planned Parenthood, Fourth (Stockholm)"
                >4th International Congress</org> elected unanimously Mrs.
                <person reg="Kato, Shidzue Ishimoto"><emph rend="underline"
                    >Shidzue Kato</emph></person> as one of the two
            Vice-Presidents of this <org
                reg="International Planned Parenthood Federation, Far East Region"
                >Western Region</org> consisting of
                <place>Singapore</place>,<place>Hong Kong</place>,
                <place>Malaya</place>, Western <place>Australia</place> and
                <place>Japan</place>. It is a pleasure to us all that Mrs. Kato
            has accepted this position as <emph rend="underline"
                >vice-president</emph>. <add>1</add></p>
        <p>It is also my pleasure to accept for the International World
            Organization the kind invitation rendered by the President of the
            Japan Family Planning Association, Mr. <person
                reg="Shimojo, Yasmaro">Yasmaro Shimojo</person> to hold the next
            Conference here in this lovely city in 1955. I am here in person as
            President to accept it with gratitude and respectful thanks.
                <add>2</add></p>
        <p>Now that the two functions of my office as President have been
            expressed, I want to say how happy I am to find that your
            government, through its <org
                reg="Japan Ministry of Health, Labour, and Welfare, Department of Public Health and Welfare"
                >departments of <emph rend="underline">Public Health and
                    Welfare</emph></org> is expanding its <emph rend="underline"
                >interest into fields and areas and villages through its trained
                medical personnel, its nurses and midwives</emph>. This is the
            most wide-spread practical method of instructing poor, busy,
            hard-working mothers and fathers as to the importance of Birth
            Control. This will certainly be the most direct way to lower the
            birth rate among parents and in families where already there are
            more children than can be properly provided for and educated.
                <add>Health &amp; Welfare</add></p>
        <p>The birth rate in Japan must be brought down to the level of the
            death rate to avoid the increasing numbers in your country. With 87
            million people today, many in homes over-crowded, with little
            privacy, and food on a very low caloric level, it seems to me that
            all devoted parents must decide to limit the number of children to
            those now alive and no more. <add>&amp; avoid the 100 million
                expected in 10 years.</add></p>
        <p>There is only one other nation trying to reach the masses in the same
            practical method as Japan’s Health and Welfare Departments and that
            is <place>India</place>. While Japan has only a little over a
            million new babies a year, India has over 5 million. But the
            intelligent Prime Minister Mr. <person reg="Nehru, Jawaharlal"
                >Nehru</person> and his advisers have realized the danger of
            this increasing numbers. So they have included Birth Control
            education and practice in the Five Year Plan and backed up this
            project by allocating the $1,300,000 in American dollars or 46,800
            man yen. Not too much, but a start so that medical and welfare
            workers can go to the villages and instruct parents and give the
            supplies necessary to achieve a lower birth rate in India.
                <add>India</add></p>
        <p>The greatest difficulty today in all countries in regard to the
            practice of Birth Control is the expense and inconvenience of the
            methods. While we know the present methods of diaphram pessary and
            jelly are safe and give excellent results, we must get a simpler and
            cheaper method if we are to reach into the submerged over-crowded
            homes in every country. There are now several scientific projects
            going on in the <place>United States</place>, <place>England</place>
            and India which will, we think, within another year, be given as a
            method for greater use. <add>Methods</add></p>
        <p>We are inviting Japan’s Health and Welfare Departments to join us in
            this scientific project. But people must be patient because the
            conscientious scientists and doctors labor carefully and long in the
            interest of the people before giving out pills or drugs until they
            are satisfied that these will be harmless and satisfactory.
                <add>Scientific Project</add></p>
        <p>I want, in conclusion, to thank the Japan Family Planning Association
            for their courtesies and kindness to me. I want also to pay my
            tribute in person and for the International Planned Parenthood
            Federation to those valiant pioneers in this country who have so
            faithfully carried the torch through those hard years of wars to the
            present time. </p>
        <p>Our thanks to Senator Shidzue Kato who since 1922 has never ceased her
            interest and lifted her voice in the cause of Planned Parenthood;
            Dr. <person reg="Kan, Majima">Majima</person> who came to <place
                reg="Zurich, Switzerland">Zurich</place> in 1930, alone and with
            that adventurous inquiring spirit, came to the first contraceptive
            conference in Europe to be informed in the practical methods of
            contraceptive techniques. Then the <person reg="Amano, Kageyasu"
                    ><person reg="Amano, Fumiko Y.">Amanos</person></person>,
            both doctors, who also have traveled to learn the facts not only of
            the practice but the theories of experts, and today, the publishing
            of The <title type="journal">Planned Parenthood Journal Quarterly</title> is the
            finest publication printed in both English and Japanese. Their
            influence is truly international and their sacrifices too many.
            Besides the above mentioned, there are many others too numerous to
            mention but Dr. <person reg="Abe, Iso">Abe</person> and Dr. <person
                reg="Nagai, Hisomu">Nagai</person> cannot be left out in paying
            tribute to pioneers in this country. <add>Pioneers</add></p>
        <p>Finally from the individual we emerge to the group and now with the
            brilliant leadership of Dr. <person reg="Koya, Yoshio"
            >Koya</person>, as Director of the <org
                reg="Japan Institute of Public Health">Institute of Public
                Health</org>, and Mr. <person reg="Kusaba, Takamaru"
                >Kusaba</person>, Minister of Public Health and Welfare, we can
            at last feel that the work of the pioneers is not an isolated
            sacrifice, but of transmissable or contagious disease. Birth control
            will continue to be and should be a vital function in the promotion
            of health and welfare. It is not only a health and economic
            expedient. It is a great Social Principle and that principle
            interlocked with the progress and culture of a nation and with the
            advance of civilization.</p>
        <p>I thank you for your welcome and your patience in listening to
            me.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
