<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Handwritten document">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011-07-29 NC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-08 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1950-00-00"><supplied resp="MSPP">1950</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Permit to Visit Japan</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp233507</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S72:0613</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="MACDO">MacArthur, Douglas</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>First and last page may be missing.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="in Japan"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>

        <p>Ever since the end of the war with <place>Japan</place>--There have been <del>requests
                &amp;</del> invitations from several organizations in Japan requesting me to come to
            Japan &amp; help set up an adequate organization on teaching &amp; technique of
            contraception to enable the poorest parents in that country to space pregnancies &amp;
            control the size of the family. One of the most prominent women in Japan Mrs. <person
                reg="Kato, Shidzue Ishimoto">Shizue Kato</person> a long time friend in <place
                reg="Tokyo, Japan">Tokyo</place> made a special request <del>&amp; I according</del>
            and at no cost to the Occupating Authorities I was to be her guest.</p>
        <p>Previous to my application for a permit Gen <person reg="MacArthur, Douglas">Mc
                Arthur</person> on July 6, 1949 had announced that the subject of birth control or
            the pros or cons of the subject did not fall within the prescribed scope of the
            Occupation” He announced a “<q who="MACDO">hands off policy</q>” as he rightly
            considered it to be a subject for the Japanese people themselves to decide according to
            this sane &amp; right policy (Democratic)</p>
        <p>I sent an application on Aug 30 1949 to the <del>Military</del>
            <org>Pacific Military Permit Branch</org> in <place reg="Washington DC">Wsh
            DC</place>. Received a reply Aug 30 that my request could not have favorable
            consideration On Sept 10th I wrote again requesting that my application be given further
            consideration because of the health factors involved in the large number of abortions
            now practiced by the desperate women in Japan--</p>
        <p>A further reconsideration was suggested after 2 months. On Nov 22 a reply came that the
                <org>Theatre Headquarters</org> of Tokyo -- <del>Gen</del> had on Nov 21st informed
            Wash DC that my request could not be favorably consider. It does not seem fair or
            Democratic policy to allow the <org reg="Tokyo American Catholic Women's Club">American
                Catholic Womens Club</org> of <add>the</add> Tokyo area -- a small unimportant
            foreign group of women who had protested against references to BC in a book
                <title>Japanese Natural Resources</title> by Prof <person reg="Ackerman, Ed">Ed
                Ackerman</person> of the <org reg="University of Chicago">Univ of <place
                    reg="Chicago, IL">Chicago</place></org></p>
        <p>Over 2500 copies of this book had been halted in destination of reference to BC
            eliminated according to a <supplied resp="MSPP">statement</supplied> by Col <person
                reg="Schenck, Hubert Gregory">Schenck</person></p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
