<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011-07-21 NC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/02/11 CH corrected date</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-11-12 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1938-02-21"><supplied resp="MSPP">21 Feb 1938</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Tucson Speech on Population</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp234396</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Smith College Series</title> S72:0137</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Sanger gave this speech in <place reg="Tucson, AZ">Tucson,
                Arizona</place>, likely on February 21, 1938. For a related speech see <xref
                from="236531.xml">"Pressure of Population as a Cause of War," 1938</xref>. For an
            earlier draft version see S71:1056.</p>
        <index level1="peace" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="war" level2="causes of"/>
        <index level1="population" level2="war and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="international"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <p>Many of you must feel like I do each morning as I read the daily paper, and ask
            yourselves, “Will we ever again have Peace in <place>Europe</place> or the World?”</p>
        <p>As we have witnessed during the past few years nation after nation become subdued and
            humiliated, controlled and dominated, by aggressor nations while friendly nations of the
            democracies stand by helpless and afraid.</p>
        <p>What has happened that these conditions exist and can continue to exist? My own answer to
            this question is that the men and women now living who took part in the World War have
            lost faith in the promises of the democracies. We are all bewildered, confused and
            skeptical.</p>
        <p>The one consolation for this position is that people are at last seriously trying to find
            out the cause of wars and if this can be discovered we can look hopefully to an end of
            wars. </p>
        <p>There is one fundamental cause of present wars. The pressure of population in a given
            country to its means of existence. <place>Germany</place> and <place>Italy</place> and
                <place>Japan</place> are overcrowded countries. They need room for expansion. They
            need more land for food. They need tillable productive land. They need natural resources
            with iron, oil, minerals and other necessities for manufacturing and they need markets
            in which they can sell and exchange their goods for food which they cannot grow but must
            purchase to exist. </p>
        <p>Briefly, this is one of the chief causes of the present conflict in Europe and
                <place>Asia</place> today. Population problems are various and increasingly complex.
            But unless statesmen tackle and solve these problems they will continue to increase
            beyond solution. </p>
        <p>Germany and Italy are calling for colonies and more land while at the same time they
            offer prizes to their people to bring more children into the already overcrowded country
            to increase their numbers. </p>
        <p>“Our babies are starving. Give us more babies,” is the absurd cry of the militaristic
            nations. </p>
        <p>There has been a general belief in this and other countries that a large population is
            the sign of prosperity and advanced civilization. Because of this opinion we are told
            that small families will mean extinction of the race. </p>
        <p>Never has there been greater need of careful accurate thinking than today concerning this
            question of population, the birth rate and birth control. </p>
        <p>We are witnessing today in Europe and Asia a condition of war and expansion for
            territory, colonies and markets which means that the population of Italy, Germany and
            Japan have outgrown the territory upon which their numbers can subsist.</p>
        <p>There are three conditions in which nations find themselves when its populations gets
            beyond its capacity to support itself -</p>
        <p><emph rend="underline">1st</emph> They can colonize like <place>England</place>,
                <place>France</place> and other countries did in the early 18th century before new
            countries were crowded. </p>
        <p><emph rend="underline">2nd</emph> They can lower their standards of living, like
                <place>India</place>, <place>China</place> and Islands like <place>Puerto
                Rico</place>. </p>
        <p><emph rend="underline">3rd</emph> They can control their birth rate like the <place
                reg="Scandinavia">Scandinavian countries</place> and adjust their increasing numbers
            to their ability to feed, clothe and educate their population. These small nations,
                <place>Sweden</place>, <place>Norway</place> and <place>Denmark</place> do not
            colonize, do not own land outside their own border, yet have a high civilization, with
            health and educational facilities which have become models for the rest of the world.
            These are peaceful nations whose people prefer culture, intelligence and peace to
            disorder.</p>
        <p>The almost universal custom in discussing population decrease is to deplore a decreasing
            birth rate. This is a sad commentary on sound thinking. </p>
        <p>There may be fewer children born in a family or city or country while the numbers as a
            whole <add>may</add> increase. This is caused by a decreasing death rate and longer
            lives of more people. In other words, to keep those babies now born alive, to keep the
            mothers alive and healthy, to give the father a chance and opportunity to keep his head
            above water and <add>to</add> provide for his family means not only a growing
            population, but a healthier and happier people who will want Peace and Education and
            Happiness. </p>
        <p>If each nation will keep its birth rate under control, fears and needs for wars will
            become extinct relics of a barbarous age. </p>
        <p>You have here in Tucson a <org reg="Tucson Mothers Health Clinic">Birth Control
                Clinic</org> where mothers may go for safe harmless information as to the way to
            space the babies and avoid conditions of pregnancy. Every child has the right to be
            wanted and every mother has the right to safeguard her health and life to enjoy
            motherhood and live to see them grow into manhood and womanhood. </p>
        <p>No subject is closer to the hearts of men and women, especially parents, than that of
            Peace. Just what can be done by us to see that Peace in the world can be maintained, not
            only for ourselves but for our children, should be the greatest question before us
            today. </p>
        <p>Since the end of the World War twenty years ago there has been applied various known
            theories of the political and social sciences to keep peace in Europe, but all have
            failed. Wars may not be caused by any particular one factor, but no one can deny that
            too many people crowded into territory too small for maintenance either leads to a
            depleted inert condition of the people, such as in Puerto Rico under our own forty year
            rule--or in China and India. </p>


    </docBody>
</doc>
