<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2002-08-08 KH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2002-08-09 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2003/08/14 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/03/11 CH Entered corrections suggested by Andy Carloff.</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-11 CH Clean errors and regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1929-04-16">16 Apr 1929</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>
                <supplied resp="MSPP">Ford Hall Forum Address</supplied>
            </titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp234418</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, <title>Margaret Sanger
                    Microfilm</title>, S71:157</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <sourceNote/>
    <headNote>
        <p>Sanger prepared this speech for <place reg="Boston, MA">Boston</place>'s <org>Ford Hall
                Forum on Free Speech</org>, but because public discussion of birth control was
            banned in that town, Sanger stood on the stage with a gag over her mouth while <person
                reg="Schlesinger, Arthur M., Sr.">Arthur M. Schlesinger</person> read her speech.
            For other versions, see LCM 129:484 and 487.</p>
        <index level1="censorship"/>
        <index level1="free speech and free press"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head rend="underline">
            <add>Censorship</add>
        </head>
        <p>To inflict silence upon a woman is indeed a drastic punishment. But there are certain
            advantages to be derived from it nevertheless. Some people are so busy talking that they
            do no thinking. Silence inflicts thoughts upon us. It makes us ponder over what we have
            lost--and what we have gained. Words are after all only the small change of thought.</p>
        <p>If we have convictions, and cannot express them in words, then let us act them out, let
            us live them! Free speech is a fine thing, it should be fought for and defended.</p>
        <p>If my voice is silenced by the hypocritical powers of reaction, in Boston, so much the
            worse for me, but so much the better for you for this act of suppression is to test the
            courage of your convictions, if you desire for free speech.</p>
        <p>It becomes your cue to speak, to act, to demonstrate the valor of your thought.</p>
        <p>Sometimes I think we all talk too much. We read too much. We listen too much. But we act
            too little. We live too little. The authorities of Boston may gag me, they do not want
            you to hear the truth about Birth Control. But they cannot gag the truth. We do not need
            words. We do not need to talk, because the truth speaks for itself. Use your eyes, use
            your ears, use your intelligence and you can find out for yourself all that I could tell
            you. You all know that I have been gagged. I have been suppressed. I have been arrested
            numerous times. I have been hauled off to jail. Yet every time, more people have
            listened to me, more have protested, more have lifted their own voices. Here have
            responded with courage and bravery.</p>
        <p>As a pioneer fighting for a Cause I believe in free speech. As a propagandist I see
            immense advantages in being gagged. It silences me, but it makes millions of others talk
            and think the cause in which I live.</p>
        <byline><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>.</byline>
    </docBody>
</doc>
