<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed draft article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2009/07/30 LL</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/11/30 PS DELETED THIS ONE. IT WAS FOUND TO BE A DRAFT OF 236054.</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1932-03-22">22 Mar. 1932</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>World Population Increase and War</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp235041</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Smith Collection, Smith College.</bibl>
            <bibl><title>MSM</title>, S71:404.</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>     
            For other versions see LCM 48:256B, <title>MSP</title> S71:370, 374, and 384.</p>
        <index level1="Italy" level2="overpopulation and"/><index level1="overpopulation"
            level2="effects of"/><index level1="overpopulation" level2="emmigration and"/><index
            level1="overpopulation" level2="MS on"/><index level1="population growth"
            level2="natural resources and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <p>In the past there have been many and diverse causes of War, but the economic factors and
            the pressure of population on the resources of <del>the</del></p>
        <add>a</add> country are pre-eminently at the root of our modern wars.
        <p><del>Just as</del><add>It is an acknowledged fact that</add> the big battalions of babies
                    <del>make</del><add>have made</add> the working man's life a constant battle to
                keep his productive or labor powers up to <add>the need of</add> his reproductive
                    powers<del>, so has</del>. <add>We also know that</add> the revolution in modern
                industry <add>has</add> made the necessity for man power of less value than the ox
                or the dray horse.</p>
            <p>The tragic difference is that the reproduction of the ox or dray horse is controlled
                and its numbers predicated on potential needs. While the man with only his labor
                power to sell, proceeds to multiply and increase his numbers regardless of his own
                ability to provide for his offspring or regardless of the social opr economic needs
                of <del>men power</del>
                <add>the labor that he has to sell.</add></p>
            <p>There are two or three essential and fundamental factors to recognize at the
                beginning of any plan for National or International Peace.</p>
            <p>1. Normal marriage leads to offspring.</p>
            <p>2. The normal couple can produce during the child-bearing years from ten to twelve
                children.</p>
            <p>3. Unless death through disease, famines or other misfortune, takes off a large
                number of these children yearly, no social order known today can provide and
                maintain <add>the multiplication &amp; increase of</add>such vast numbers in so
                short a period.</p>
            <p><del>Just as an</del>
                <add>An</add> acre of land is limited to the number of plants it can occupy<del>,
                        <gap extent="two words"/> a man's labor power limited to the number of
                    children he can decently provide for.</del></p>
            <p>5. <del>That the</del> The social factors, or returns to the State from slums and
                over-crowded territories <del>dwindle</del> decrease rather than increase our racial
                wealth.</p>
            <add><p>Populations have been kept down in the past by keeping the death rate almost
                    equal to the birth rate. The survival rate was very low but it allowed for a
                    healthy, fit population and enabled it to compete in the struggle for existence.
                    Today we have changed all this.We can not allow disease, floods, pestilences and
                    famines to spread over a civilized land. The consequence is that we have greatly
                    lowered our death rate while we have at the same time increased the longevity of
                    adult men and women.</p>
                <p>Both of these good factors have been obtained mainly through the lowering of our
                    birth rate. Those Nations who fight against this civilized means of applying
                    science to the control of population, become the danger spots in World
                    Peace.</p></add>
            <p>With these facts in mind, we know that the quality of a population making up a State
                is an <add>equally</add> important factor in its progress. A population on any given
                territory must produce its own food or get food from other areas. Not only food but
                the necessary means of maintenance which today means oil, iron, fuel and natural
                resources. If a Nation can not maintain its population, <del>it leads</del>
                <add>the first effort</add> to the only way out <del>-</del>
                <add>is through emigration.</add></p>
            <p><add>But</add> when other countries close their gates against migrants, they are then
                forced to remain at home. <del>They then have one of three problems <add>to
                        face</add>.</del><add>There are then but three remaining solutions to their
                    problem.</add></p>
            <p>1. Reduce the birth rate.</p>
            <p>2. Lower the standards of living.</p>
            <p>Expand into other territory by force of Arms and declare War.</p>
            <p>Japan has recently given us an excellent example of <del>this</del><add>the</add>
                fact <add>of overpopulation</add>. She has a population of approximately 60,000,000
                according to the census of 1928. She has <add>about</add> 150,000 square miles of
                territory. Only one-sixth of this area is cultivable which brings her density of
                population up to 993 persons a square mile - the highest in the world. She has an
                enormously high birth rate of 34.8 and a death rate of 19.2 - the second highest
                natural increase <del>than</del>
                <add>of</add> any country <add>today</add>
                <del>in the world</del>. <del>From</del>
                <add>Besides this she has an increase of</add> 800,000 to 900,000 infants a
                year.</p>
            <p>Japan has not the resources to feed <del>her</del>
                <add>this growing</add> population. <del>Japan</del>
                <add>She</add> has</p> not been allowed free access to other lands as
                <add>other</add> European <add>[ILLEGIBLE]</add>. The world has closed its doors against her surplus population. Japan has not the natural resources of iron and coal to
            become a manufacturing or industrial nation which could be exchanged for food. Her silk
            industry can not provide sufficiently for her needs. Her standards of living were fairly
            high. <del>Her population is</del>
            <add>Japan's population is highly intelligent &amp; largely literate, which like Germany
                in 1914 must have an outlet as well as a return on her [ILLEGIBILE] for educational
                facilities.</add><p/>
            <p>She had three ways to settle the problem.</p>
            <p>1. To lower her standards of living and increase her death rate.</p>
            <p>2. Decrease the birth rate to a very low figure as quickly as possible to check the
                increase of numbers.</p>
            <p>3. To acquire new territories where she <del>could</del>
                <add>can</add> have ready access to fuel and mineral resources in order to create
                industries and provide for the needs of her present and future population.</p>
            <p>We know now which of the above Japan chose to do. She had little or no choice <del>in the way out in 1932</del> <add>after she allowed conditions to drift until 1932</add>.</p>
            <p/>
            <p/>
            <p/>
            <p/>
            <place>Italy</place> has 119,670 square miles of territory. Italy’s population, 1930,
            was nearly 41,000,000. Italy’s density 540 per square mile. <place>Germany</place>’s
            density 347 per square mile in 1914. 1921 Italy’s population was 38,756,000. 1927
            Italy’s population was 40,548,000. Italy’s birth rate 1920= 30.4. Italy’s birth rate
            1927=26.4. 400,500,000 new babies to provide for. From 1902-1913, over 90,000 Italians
            emigrated into the <place reg="United States of America">U.S.A.</place> each year. In
            1920, over 1,610,00 born Italians. Over 25% of Italy is natural increase was coming into
            the U.S.A. Since 1928, not more than 1,000 Italians were admitted into their country.
            Italy has no other outlet for her increasing population. <place>France</place> received
            in 1926 over 600,000 Italians, but here, too, gates are closed.</p>
        <p>Italy’s problem is acute. Her tillable land is scarce. She cannot support her numbers
            today. Her standards of living are already very close to the subsistence level, and
            cannot safely be lowered. Her fuel, coal, petroleum and iron ore are scarce. Her water
            power may be developed but not with any degree of industrial efficiency.</p>
        <p>She could build up her textile industry but the cheap labor of <place>China</place>,
                <place>Japan</place> and <place>India</place> can be relied upon to outclass her as
            a competitor.</p>
        <p>It is clearly evident that as Italy has neither the agricultural nor industrial resources
            to provide for her present growth and increasing population, that before the next five
            years we can expect the usual result when a population explodes--<emph rend="underline"
                >WAR</emph>.</p>
        <p>It is just possible that <place>South America</place> may save the situation--but the
            conditions in South America are not sufficiently developed to profitably use additional
            hundred of thousands unskilled and common laborers, each year. Not only are not the
            agricultural faculties not developed but also the transportation faculties in South
            America are not developed for this task.</p>
        <p>It is a point in fact to remember that in the past there was collossal ignorance in
            official and Parliamentary circles concerning the results of high birth rates. No nation
            deliberately brought this condition about, but today this is all changed and any
            Dictator or group of dictators who deliberately lay down laws urging or forcing the rise
            of a birth rate in a country already on the verge of explosion, should be made
            accountable to a World Court, for the consequences.</p>
        <p>Japan has 148,000 square miles.</p>
        <p>Japan has 65,000,000 people.</p>
        <p>Japan has a density of 400 square miles.</p>
        <p>Japan’s increasing 700,800,000 each year. The gates of the world closed against her
            except South America.</p>
        <p>Like Italy she has little fuel or iron ore for her industries. Unlike Italy her
            population is largely educated. Her illiteracy rate is very low--2 1/2%.</p>
        <p>1. She has but two ways open to her, lower her standard of living.</p>
        <p>2. Acquire new territory where she can have ready access to coal, iron and mineral
            resources, through which industry may be built up to help provide the needs for a
            rapidly growing population.</p>
        <p><place reg="Manchuria, China">Manchuria</place> has these possessions. She has the
            railway facilities to make production available.</p>
        <p>Japan has cast aside all the outer glittering tinsils of Man-Made Diplomacy. She has
            followed the dynamic urge of the Survival of the Fit, and Might makes Right. What are we
            going to do about it?</p>
        <p>The open spaces of <place>Australia</place>, <place>Canada</place>, South America, and
            the United States are the subject of bitter controversy throughout the world.
            Overpopulated countries with their spawning, teeming, illiterate millions challenge the
            right of low birth rate, high-standard countries to keep them out. <person
                reg="Keynes, John Maynard">John Maynard Keynes</person> predicted that the question
            of birth control as a key to the population problem will cause more bitterness of
            controversy than any.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
