<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Unpublished Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2013/11/13 JK encoded</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-08-21 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1930-02-20">20 Feb 1930</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>The Next Step in Birth Control</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp235609</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College </bibl>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers Microfilm, Smith College Collections S71:178</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Sanger gave this speech at the opening dinner of the <org>Western State
                Conference on Birth Control and Population</org> at <org>Baltimore Hotel</org> in
                <place>Los Angeles</place>. For notes on her other speech at this conference, see
                <xref from="240447.xml"> "Legal Obstacles to Racial Progress,"</xref> Feb. 23, 1930. </p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Federal"/>
        <index level1="Western State Conference on Birth Control and Population"/>
        <index level1="National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="State"/>
        <index level1="American Birth Control League"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>The Next Step.</head>

        <p>The first step towards Birth Control legislation in the <place>United States</place> was
            taken in 1914 when <name type="law" reg="United States Criminal Code, Section 211"
                >Section 211 of the Penal Code</name> was challenged by me. In this section of the
            Federal law contraceptive and instruction is classed with abortions, lewdness,
                <unclear>pornography</unclear> and obscenity. I felt this classification to be not
            only dangerous to the well being of the race, but an insult to the intelligent womanhood
            of the present generation, whose ideals and standards of family life were held in high
            esteem because of the practice of birth control. </p>
        <p>After two years of campaigning to arouse the consciousness of the public the case was
            dismissed in 1916 without coming to trial. At this time the subject was little known and
            most of us believed it to be a matter of free speech. After studying in <place
                reg="Netherlands">Holland</place>, <place>England</place>, <place>France</place> and
                <place>Spain</place> I was convinced that the basis of principle of contraception
            was more technical than that implied in a free speech campaign. I saw in the clinics of
            Holland the important of the knowledge of physiology and anatomy on the part of the
            instructor if good results were to be obtained. Consequently we must depend upon the
            medical profession to instruct and inform the women who were to be benefitted by the
            laws we desired to amend.</p>
        <p>When the Federal indictments against me were dismissed I turned my attention to the State
            laws and found various restrictions in over twenty three of the 48 states. In 25 states
            there was no restriction whatever, while in nine states there are complete restrictions
            as to writing or publishing notices or advertisements as to the means to prevent
            conception. There are not more than ten states in the Union in which he physician is
            exempt from the laws. </p>
        <p>The Federal law Section 211 makes it a crime to send any paper, book, letter, written or
            printed through the United States Mails. It also includes articles and drugs from being
            transported through the U.S. Mails or common carriers.</p>
        <p>The Federal law not only prohibits books or pamphlets containing information to prevent
            conception, but it makes it a crime, punishable by five years or $5,000 fine to tell
            anyone where, or by whom such information may be given. In other words the Federal law
            makes it a crime for me to write to anyone in <place>California </place>and give the
            address of any doctor or clinic of which there are over seven already, legally operating
            under the laws of the State of California!! (Preposterous truly.) The same law prohibits
            the sending of our clinical reports to doctors or to exchange records, reports, data or
            scientific facts regarding the studies already made on the technique and methods of
            contraception. It prohibits the entrance from <place>Europe</place> of articles, or
            books or appliances most necessary to advance the scientific work of our clinics.</p>
        <p>The Federal laws Section 211, 245, 305 must be amended to allow medical and scientific
            books, records and articles to be sent through the mails to and from the physicians and
            include necessary provisions for the patients as well as that of druggist importers and
            manufacturer. </p>
        <p>The State laws are being attended to by the <org>American Birth Control League</org> but
            the amendment to the Federal law must be secured by a general protest of enlightened and
            intelligent citizens throughout the country. I have the honor to be Chairman of the <org
                reg="National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control">National Birth
                Control Federal Committee</org> and I invite you to participate in this National
            campaign and to help emancipate the mothers of America from the enslavement of
            overburdened, undesired and enforced maternity. </p>


    </docBody>
</doc>
