<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011-07-20 NC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03=24 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1944-07-19">19 Jul 1944</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>How to Avoid Post War Divorce</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236035</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S72:0405</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Sanger gave the following radio talk on station <org
                reg="WMCA (New York)">WMCA</org> on July 19, 1944 at 9:00 AM. For an earlier draft
            version see LCM 116:666B.</p>
        <index level1="war" level2="marriage and"/>
        <index level1="divorce" level2="in U.S."/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>How to Avoid Post War Divorces</head>
        <byline>Radio Script<lb/> Margaret Sanger<lb/> Station WMCA</byline>
        <dateline><date value="1944-07-19">Wednesday, July 19, 1944</date>
            <lb/>9:00-9:15 AM</dateline>
        <p>Announcer: <q who="UNK">Good morning. Can anything be done to head off the wave of
                divorce that many expect will sweep this country when peace returns? That is one of
                the questions of the hour and during her absence to attend the <org
                    reg="Republican Party Convention">Chicago Convention</org>, <person
                    reg="Hughes, Alice">Alice Hughes</person> has arranged to have the subject of
                post war divorces discussed by one of the most famous, one of the most widely known
                women of our day. . . Mrs. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>.
                Mrs. Sanger, whose work in the cause of better family health and happier home
                relationships has made her name known throughout the civilized world, is the
                Honorary Chairman of the <org>Planned Parenthood Federation of America</org>,
                lecturer and author of numerous books and magazine articles. With her own sons
                serving as physicians with the <org reg="United States Army">Army</org> and <org
                    reg="United States Navy">Navy</org>, Mrs. Sanger is devoting much of her
                interest to the cause of sound marriage counselling for servicemen and their wives.
                She speaks from a lifetime of experience in the field of human relations. Mrs.
                Sanger.</q></p>
        <p>Sanger: Good morning. <add>Friends</add> do you know that some experts are <add>now</add>
            saying that seven out of every ten of our wartime marriages are headed for trouble?
            Seems like rather a lot, doesn't it, until you remember the way our divorce rate <emph
                rend="underline">soared</emph> after the last war and realize that this war has seen
            an even greater number of hasty war marriages. The pity of unhappy, ruined marriages is
            that with a little scientific advice and the use of common sense so many of them could
            be saved.</p>
        <p>Riding in on the train yesterday from my home <del>in <place reg="Fishkill, NY"
                    >Fishkill</place></del>
            <add>up the Hudson</add> I happened to sit next to a young girl whose war marriage could
            easily be one of those doomed to a tragic finish. She held her sturdy little year old
            son on her lap and soon after I admired him and offered to hold him, she told me the
            whole story. Although she was extremely young, her's had not been one of those spur of
            the moment affairs. She and her husband had planned to be married as far back as their
            high school days and they had had six months together before he was shipped overseas.
            That's a better start than many of them get. They hadn't wanted to have a baby until he
            came back, but the baby had come along <add>just the same</add> and now the wife.. who
            was realy just a girl.. was feeling trapped and <emph rend="underline"
            >rebellious</emph>. She loved her baby <add>of course</add>, and well she might, because
            he was a beautiful child, but she was beginning to feel very bitter toward her husband
            because she said that she could tell from his letters that he was actually enjoying the
                <add>excitement of</add> war! Already he had been to <place>Iceland</place>,
                <place>England</place>, <place>Africa</place>, and <place>Italy</place>! Oh, she was
            willing to admit there were plenty of hardships connected with it... but what had <emph
                rend="underline">she</emph> been doing all this long while? Just staying home day
            after day minding the baby! "<q who="UNK">When he gets home</q>," she told me, "<q
                who="UNK">he can just sit with the baby for a while and she what it's like. I'm
                going out and have some fun!</q>"</p>
        <p>I could see her point of view... what woman couldn't. You don't have to be a <emph
                rend="underline">war bride</emph> to feel trapped... many a house-wife gets that
            feeling just watching her husband go off to the office every morning while she stays
            home facing the same meals, dishes, and children. How many divorces have their
            beginnings in just this very feeling of imprisoned futility. As I talked with the girl I
            never wished more that there could be a simple set of rules to hand out on ways to
            protect a marriage, and keep it fresh and warm and interesting. <add>While</add> there
            are no such simple rules, <del>of course, hub</del> there <emph rend="underline"
                >are</emph> some basic truths which everyone should know. More than that, there are
            now some scientific treatments which have proven as successful in curing <emph
                rend="underline">marriage</emph> casualties, as our new medical treatments have been
            in saving <emph rend="underline">battle</emph> casualties.</p>
        <p>Announcer: <q who="UNK">I'll be back in a moment but now a word from <person
                    reg="Cornwall, Bill A.">Bill A. Cornwall</person>.</q></p>
        <p>Sanger: In treating <emph rend="underline">marriage</emph> casualties scientifically, it
            has been found that one of the most effective cures is a completely frank discussion of
                <emph rend="underline">all</emph> factors involved, with a person who is prepared to
            offer <emph rend="underline">factual advice</emph> and not just kind words and nebulous
                <emph rend="underline">nothings</emph>. My little friend on the train, for instance,
            who was building up such a fine resentment toward her husband, because he was having an
            exciting time, while she was stuck at home, needed someone to point out that the very
            fact that he <emph rend="underline">was</emph> enjoying the war, <add>(</add>in spite of
            the horror and hardship<add>)</add> showed that he would come home a more <emph
                rend="underline">interesting</emph>, <emph rend="underline">entertaining</emph>
            companion <emph rend="underline">than he had ever</emph> been before. It meant that he
            was getting something from his new experiences, adding to his knowledge, enriching his
            philosophy. Instead of resenting it, that young wife should have been trying to keep
            pace with him... she should have been broadening her own horizons, acquiring new
            knowledge and accomplishments if possible, so that <add>on his return</add> he too would
            find her a more stimulating <add>&amp; entertaining</add> companion</p>
        <p>It is so important that wives whose husbands have been gone for long periods in camps or
            overseas, <emph rend="underline">realize</emph> that they <emph rend="underline"
                >will</emph> come home changed in many ways. They must not expect them to settle
            back into the same old patterns and routines. They must be ready to change with them if
            their marriage is to grow and <del>flourish</del>
            <add>strengthen</add>.</p>
        <p>A second important safeguard for wartime marriages is that there be no misunderstood
            emotional barriers between you. Because so many of these marriages have been hasty
            affairs, keyed to an intensely dramatic pitch, there have been limitless opportunities
            for emotional <emph rend="underline">maladjustments</emph> and <emph rend="underline"
                >misunderstandings</emph>. It is <add>just</add> in this field that expert marriage
            counselling can accomplish so much. Fortunately the day is <emph rend="underline"
                >fast</emph>
            <emph rend="underline">passing</emph> when parents will <emph rend="underline"
                >permit</emph> their children to take the most important step of their lives with
            little or no knowledge of what this new relationship implies. How much misery and
            anguish could be avoided if our young people could be taught that marriage and the
            creation of a family <emph rend="underline">is</emph> the most essential, the most
            beautiful and <add>really</add> the most <emph rend="underline">satisfying experience of
                their lives</emph> and be instructed accordingly.</p>
        <p>Right now the <org>Red Cross</org>, <org reg="United Service Organization">USO</org>,
                <org reg="Young Men's Christian Association">YMCA</org>, and <org
                reg="Young Women's Christian Association">YWCA</org> are giving increased attention
            to <del>sound</del>
            <add>selective</add> marriage counselling and more and more ministers and private
            physicians are making it a point to discus the marriage relationship fully and clearly
            so young people may give their marriage a foundation of knowledge and truth, and plan
            their families with love and intelligence.</p>
        <p>Here in <place reg="New York, NY">New York</place> the <org
                reg="Planned Parenthood Federation of America">Planned Parenthood</org> centers can
            provide information on family planning and refer inquiries to experienced marriage
            counselors with whom <emph rend="underline">any</emph> marriage problem may be
            discussed. Here young couples may learn from physicians how to have their children <emph
                rend="underline">when</emph> the parents are well and able to provide for a new
            child. One of the growing services of planned parenthood is <del>for</del>
            <add>to help</add> couples who earnestly want a child but find they cannot have one. New
            medical treatments are now proving successful in almost two out of every three cases of
            childlessness including many cases which would have been considered hopeless even a few
            years ago.</p>
        <p>Of course marriage counselling and family planning alone cannot solve our post war
            divorce problem. Many wartime marriages have been made by couples who are quite unsuited
            for life partnership. But many of the <emph rend="underline">shaky ones can</emph> be
            saved if they are given the knowledge they so desperately need. It has long be possible
            to call in experts on central heating, the care and feeding of spaniels, and how to grow
            vegetable gardens. Thank fortune, we are at last entering an era when trained
            counsellors are available to help our young people with the most essential and complex
            problems of all; the problem of happpy, successful marriages, and healthy, well planned
            families. War brides and their husbands should avail themselves of these services not
            only for their own security and happiness, <emph rend="underline">but</emph> for the
            sake of <del>our wonderful war babies</del>
            <add>those darling youngsters</add>, many of whom may otherwise <emph rend="underline"
                >become</emph> the <emph rend="underline">victims</emph> of broken homes.</p>
        <p>Announcer: Thank you, Mrs. Sanger. This morning in place of <person reg="Hughes, Alice"
                >Alice Hughes</person>, who will return on ______ you have heard Mrs. Margaret
            Sanger, author, lecturer and Honorary Chairman of the Planned Parenthood Federation of
            America, which together with the <org>New York State Federation for Planned
                Parenthood</org> and the <org>Planned Parenthood Committee of Greater New
            York</org>, made this broadcast possible. For copies of Mrs. Sanger's talk or further
            information regarding planned parenthood and marriage counselling, address Mrs. Sanger
            at the Federation's offices, 501 Madison Avenue, New York 22, N.Y.</p>


    </docBody>
</doc>
