<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed draft speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2004/08/01 MPL</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/08/06 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007/06/25 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/03/11 CH Entered corrections suggested by Andy Carloff.</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011-11-30 CH typos</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-01 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-09 EK entered proofreading corrections</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-02-22 CH added references to other 1916 speeches in the headnote.</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1916-04-00">
            <supplied resp="MSPP">Apr.- May 1916</supplied>
        </docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Birth Control</supplied> (Chicago Address to
                Women)</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236132</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title>S70:759</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="EMERA"> Emerson, Ralph Waldo</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>During her <place>United States</place> tour, <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret
                Sanger</person> spoke three times in <place reg="Chicago, IL">Chicago</place>,
            giving a speech called "<title type="article">Birth Control</title>," at the <org>West
                Side Auditorium</org> on April 25 and May 7, and at the <org>Little Theater of
                Chicago</org> on Apr. 30. She was scheduled to appear before the Chicago Woman's
            Club on Apr. 11, but the event was canceled because Sanger was perceived as too
            controversial. For a newspaper report of Sanger's April 25 speech, see "<xref
                from="321958.xml">Birth Control</xref>."</p>
        <p>Sanger made many handwritten changes to the document which may have been the base text
            for several of her appearances. In an effort to offer the most complete version
            possible, the editors have opted to include all the text, even those paragraphs she may
            have omitted for some of appearances.</p><p>For other speeches given on that tour, see
                "<xref from="128002.xml">Woman and Birth Control</xref>," "<xref from="101859.xml"
                >Birth Control and Society</xref>," Apr.-June, 1916, and "<xref from="128003.xml"
                >Condemnation is Misunderstanding</xref>," Apr.-Jun. 1916.</p>
        
        <index level1="abortion" level2="health risks of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="class-based"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits and risks of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="natural law and"
        <index level1="birth control methods" level2="douche"/>
        <index level1="birth control methods" level2="efficacy of"/>
        <index level1="birth control methods" level2="safe period"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="socio-economic benefits of"/>
        <index level1="censorship"/>
        <index level1="Christianity"/>
        <index level1="men" level2="sexuality and"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="infant"/>
        <index level1="physicians" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="physicians" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="sex education"/> 
        <index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="freedom and rights of"/>
         <index level1="working classes"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head rend="underline">Chicago Address to Women.</head>
        <p>We are regimented by conventions. Habits and customs control us. We are ever afraid of
            the untried, of the unknown. Instead of making of life a wide expanse of social
            development we allow ourselves to be herded into narrow tracks through fear of
            conventions. We are the victims of habit, not only of action but of thought. Our parents
            thought so and so; and we think so and so. The world expects us to do so and so, and so
            and so we do.</p>
        <p>The earth is a globe, it revolves around the sun, it rotates on its axis: its inhabitants
            have learned <emph rend="underline">this</emph> much in spite of opposition. And the
            whole HISTORY of Civilization is the history of the STRUGGLE between those obeying the
            OLD laws and those establishing the NEW.</p>
        <p>
            <add rend="underline">And</add> Every age adopts that which was considered UTOPIAN in
            the last and wonders how its forefathers could have been so blind, backward, stupid,
                <add>for</add> Progress infuses itself into everything and woe to him who would
            impede its course. </p>
        <p><person reg="Bruno, Giordano">Bruno</person> was burned to death because he chose to
            teach the Italian people scientific truths about religion in the Italian language
            instead of using the dead languages which had been employed to cloak the REAL EMPTINESS
            of its dogmas.</p>
        <p><person rend="underline">Socrates</person> was poisoned because he dared to combat the
            SUPERSTITIONS of his people. Not long after his death, the citizens of <place
                reg="Athens, Greece">Athens</place>, his countrymen, recognized the INJUSTICE of his
            sentence, and executed <emph rend="underline">his</emph> accuser. Socrates thereby
            became a demi-god.</p>
        <p><person>Jesus Christ</person> was crucified because he attempted to SUPERCEDE the ritual
            of <person>Moses</person>. As time rolled on the opinions of men CHANGED until
            Christianity became an established dogma which it meant DEATH to dispute. Though he who
            does dispute it may be imprisoned, slandered and persecuted, if he has courage in his
            belief future ages may exalt HIM to a divinity and PERSECUTE others in his name as he
            was persecuted in the name of his predecessor. SUCH is the HOMAGE of the world.</p>
        <p>Now we realize that Christianity <del>came but to LAY</del>
            <add>has come &amp; has lain</add> CHAINS on the human mind, and <del>to</del>
            <add>has</add> imposed upon mankind the weary struggle to RECOVER the freedoms it had
            obtained.</p>
        <p><add>Christianity turned the hands of Civilization back 1000 years it turned them back
                2000 years for woman and</add> Today we find ourselves engaged in a relentless
            struggle with the SAME POWERS OF OPPRESSION which wrought from us the liberties our
            forefathers obtained <emph rend="underline">for</emph> and gave to us for
            preservation.</p>
        <p>Today we are engaged in a GREAT STRUGGLE FOR WOMAN'S LIBERTY,! for the freedom of HER OWN
            BODY, for her RELEASE from the domination and control, of CHURCH AND STATE.</p>
        <p>Birth Control is the first step toward the goal of <del>her</del><add>this</add> freedom.
            She can never gain political, social or spiritual freedom so long as her body remains
            THE SLAVE OF IGNORANCE. No woman <add>can</add>call herself free who cannot choose the
            time to be a mother or not as she sees fit. And women of today REBEL against spending
            the whole of their adult lives in bringing children into the world. Out of this
            rebellion, out of this impulse, out of this desire <add>for voluntary motherhood</add>
            has risen the Birth Control movement in the United States.</p>
        <p> I believe that this is the <del><emph rend="underline">first</emph> great movement since
                the Civil War,<add>most revolutionary movement of the day</add> and THE MOST
                IMPORTANT ISSUE of the Twentieth Century. Its advocates <add>too</add> have been
                SLANDERED, PERSECUTED, JAILED because they have voiced THE CRY OF WORKING WOMAN for
                    <del>their</del>
                <add>her</add> BODILY FREEDOM.</del>
        </p>
        <p>In nearly every country in the world today the great mass of educated and wealthy women
            PRACTICE SOME METHOD OF BIRTH CONTROL, though in the same countries the WORKING WOMEN
            are kept in ignorance of this knowledge.</p>
        <p>It is said by physicians and others who work among the working women, that as soon as she
            rises out of the lowest stages of ignorance and poverty her FIRST STEP is to seek
            information of some practical means to <del>limit her family</del>
            <add>control the size of her family</add>.</p>
        <p>Everywhere she seeks for knowledge on the subject very seldom can she find it, because
            the medical profession refuses to give it to her and others with whom she comes in daily
            contact are as ignorant as herself of the subject.</p>
        <p>The consequence is she must accept <add>any</add> stray bits of information wholly
            UNRELIABLE and UNINFORMED. The result is that quacks and abortionists thrive on her
                <emph rend="underline">innocence</emph> and ignorance is perpetuated.</p>

        <p>In my opinion the proper authorities to give <add>special &amp; scientific</add> advice
            on Birth Control are the DOCTORS and NURSES <add>&amp; midwives-</add>. No other class
            of men or women are so AWARE of the NEED of this knowledge among the working people as
            they. YET THEY HAVE REMAINED SILENT! The time has come when they MUST TAKE THEIR STAND
            in their progressive movement. For though the subject is largely <emph rend="underline"
                >social</emph> and <emph rend="underline">economic</emph> yet it is in the main
                <emph rend="underline">physical</emph> and <emph rend="underline">medical</emph>,
            and the object of those advancing the cause is to open the doors of the medical
            profession, who in turn will force open the doors of the laboratories, where our
            chemists will give the women of the twentieth century reliable and scientific means of
            contraception hitherto unknown.</p>
        <p> A meeting of this kind is somewhat new, but undeniably important. It may be
            DISAPPOINTING to some of you to hear that I am NOT going to give you information to
            prevent conception in this meeting. <add>I take for granted that every woman in this
                audience -- is serious minded &amp; wishes to learn some thing about the sacred
                truths of her body sex functions. It is not the best place to give knowledge.</add>
        </p>
        <p>You have a LAW in <place reg="Illinois">this State</place> which FORBIDS your getting
            this information <add>about abortions</add>. <del>from me NOW</del> but it does <emph
                rend="underline">ALLOW</emph> your PHYSICIAN to instruct you <add>in prevention of
                conception</add>. </p>
        <p>I do not intend to VIOLATE this LAW, nor to IMPOSE any legal defense of my cause upon
            your consideration, <emph rend="underline">UNLESS YOU WOMEN OF CHICAGO desire me to do
                so</emph>.! I do intend however to give you special information concerning your
            bodies which Every <add>adult</add>Women Should Know and which it is well within
                <del>your RIGHTS</del> for you to hear. <add>my<gap reason="illegible"/> rights to
                tell you</add>. </p>
        <p>The FIRST subject which we shall take up is:</p>

        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub"><emph rend="underline">HOW CONCEPTION TAKES PLACE</emph>.!</head>
            <p>It is important that every adult man and woman should know and clearly understand
                what CONCEPTION means and how <add>it</add> occurs.</p>
            <p>WHEN ONCE THIS IS THOROUGHLY KNOWN IT WILL BE IMPOSSIBLE TO <emph rend="underline"
                    >CONFUSE</emph> BIRTH CONTROL WITH ABORTION as the <add>ignorant</add> opponents
                of this movement are so fond of doing.</p>
            <p>I regret that I shall have time only to go very briefly into the subject to give you
                a general idea of what actually occurs.</p>
            <p>In every woman's <add>body there are two</add> ovaries <add>and within them</add>
                there are embedded millions of ovules or eggs. They are present in every female at
                birth, and as</p>
            <p><gap extent="one page" reason="missing"/>fertilized ovum any attempt at removing it
                or preventing its development or further growth is called ABORTION. <add>B.C. is not
                    abortion!</add></p>
            <p>That there is almost no other country in the world where so many abortions occur as
                in the <place>United States</place> is a fact worthy of consideration and interest.
                That the laws in these same United States are the most rigid and the penalty the
                heaviest for any action toward abolishing abortion (by prevention of conception) of
                any country is also worthy of interest.</p>
            <p>Abortion is the most common as well as one of the most SERIOUS disturbances of
                pregnancy yet it is said that ONE out of EVERY FIVE pregnancies terminate abruptly
                in abortion.</p>
            <p>It is roughly estimated that at least <emph rend="underline">250,000</emph> abortions
                occur in the United States EACH YEAR while <emph rend="underline">50,000</emph>
                women die from their effects.</p>
            <p><del>There</del>
                <add>One of the most tragic facts today </add>
                <del>no doubt</del>is that <add>our</add> women are apt to look upon an abortion as
                of little consequence and to treat it <del>accordingly</del>
                <add>lightly</add>. An abortion should be regarded as IMPORTANT <add>serious</add> a
                matter as a confinement and REQUIRES AS MUCH ATTENTION as the birth of a child at
                full term.</p>
            <p>It is only the women of wealth who can afford to give an abortion the proper care and
                treatment both at the same time and afterwards. Consequently THESE WOMEN seldom
                suffer any serious consequences from its occurrence.</p>
            <p>It is the WORKING WOMEN, whose means are limited <add>cheapest men incompetent</add>
                and who must continue AT WORK before they have recovered from the effects of an
                abortion, who are the GREAT ARMY OF SUFFERERS and it is from among THESE WOMEN that
                the DEATHS due to abortions usually ensue.</p>
            <p>If women had the knowledge to prevent conception there would be almost NO NECESSITY
                for abortion.!! It is because abortions occuring so frequently among the working
                women today -- the suffering, illness and death resulting from the carelessness of
                their performance, -- that has urged me to make ANY SACRIFICE and direct my efforts
                to make it possible for these women to obtain: CLEAN, HARMLESS KNOWLEDGE OF THE
                MEANS TO PREVENT CONCEPTION and thereby PREVENT ABORTIONS and <emph rend="underline"
                    >the NECESSITY FOR THEM</emph>!</p>
            <p>During my nursing experience in <place reg="New York, NY">New York</place> I came in
                contact with some of the midwives and had occasion to view their appliances which
                they use in their profession. I was HORRIFIED at the filthy condition of the
                scissors, forceps, brushes, etc. their kit contained.</p>
            <p>IS IT ANY WONDER THAT DEATHS OF THE POORER WOMEN MOUNT SO HIGH?</p>
            <p>The more I see of women who have had abortions and the more I see of the RESULTS of
                abortions, the more convinced I am of their INJURIOUS effect on women and the
                stronger do I urge the knowledge of the prevention of conception.</p>
            <p>The results of abortion are usually of far more serious effect on the woman's health
                than a full term child birth. There is the possibility of the womb not returning to
                its natural size but remaining large and heavy and tending to fall away from its
                proper position in the body.</p>
            <p>Then one abortion so often leaves the uterus in a condition to conceive very easily
                again, and unless prevention is strictly followed another pregnancy will SURELY
                occur. Frequent abortions have a tendency to establish sterility or barrenness in
                the woman as well as result in pelvic ailments.</p>
            <p>There are many cases of women suffering from tuberculosis, kidney disease, heart
                disease, pelvic deformities, etc. to whom pregnancy stimulates the disease and often
                means death, so that the physician must perform an abortion in order that her health
                and life may be preserved. THERE IS NO LAW AGAINST THE PHYSICIAN'S DOING THIS, yet
                our laws <add>must state</add>
                <del>make</del> it a CRIME for that physician to inform that same woman how to
                prevent conception and thereby prevent abortion and its tragic suffering.</p>
            <p><emph rend="underline"> KNOWLEDGE TO PREVENT CONCEPTION IS THE ONLY CURE FOR
                    ABORTION.</emph></p>
            <p>May the women of this country rise up and demand the REPEAL of the laws which force
                such abhorrent conditions upon them <add>&amp; demand this knowledge to prevent
                    abortion.</add></p>
            <p>Naturally one of the first questions asked by all concerned is:</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub"><emph rend="underline">ARE PREVENTIVE MEASURES CERTAIN?</emph></head>
            <p>It is always difficult to say that ANYTHING is CERTAIN in its result. A surgeon would
                not succeed with the most serious operation was he not most particular to take every
                precaution and insist that all directions be faithfully carried out.</p>
            <p>IT IS THE SAME WITH PREVENTION. There is EVERY REASON to believe that if the
                directions are carefully followed in preventive methods some means are quite
                certain.</p>
            <p>The educated women have been practicing methods of prevention for nearly a
                half-century and have found them certain and safe. Of course -- if a woman is TOO
                INDOLENT or TOO INDIFFERENT to <add>(douche)</add>to take precautions and to give
                herself certain attentions in cleanliness and hygiene, then NOTHING can be certain,
                but I have found most women desirous and anxious <emph rend="underline">for
                    knowledge</emph>, no matter what inconvenience it implied.</p>
            <p><del>One</del>
                <add>Another</add> of the questions so often asked by women who are fearful to use
                preventatives is:</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">
                <emph rend="underline">ARE PREVENTIVE METHODS INJURIOUS TO HEALTH?</emph></head>
            <p>A <person reg="Unknown">very prominent authority</person> claims that there is far
                more injury to a woman's health <emph rend="underline">to live in CONSTANT
                    FEAR</emph> of pregnancy than the use of all the preventive measures in the
                world. It is further claimed by some physicians that some preventive is absolutely
                necessary and even helpful to a nervously weak woman in helping her to regain her
                health. But much depends upon THE KIND of method used.</p>
            <p>Strong solutions of anti-septics for the douche are one of the many injurious
                methods. When they are ABOVE THEIR PROPER STRENGTH they are liable to injure the
                delicate membranes of the parts. The same solutions in weaker proportions <add><emph
                        rend="underline">bichloride tablets in bag. salt</emph></add>act as a
                cleanser and are seldom injurious. <add>but as</add> Every woman is susceptible to a
                greater or lesser degree to all drugs, <del>and</del>
                <add>it is best</add> if possible a physician should advise the use of them.</p>
            <p>There are also certain mechanical methods <add>buttons etc wishbone pessaries</add>
                employed by some women which might give rise to an irritation and cause disease, but
                the temporary use of the same would be quite harmless.</p>
            <p>In employing any preventive measure there is almost NO DANGER TO THE MAN'S HEALTH at
                all. Even the habit of coitus-interruptus which is so commonly practiced everywhere
                is not considered as dangerous to his health as was formerly thought, but on the
                other hand is considered by many prominent authorities as injurious to the woman's
                nervous system. In fact it is considered the cause of many nervous disturbances in
                women. <add>(explain)</add></p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">DO PREVENTIVE METHODS LEAD TO STERILITY?</head>
            <p>This question is often asked by women early in marriage, who desire to use preventive
                methods for a period, until it becomes economically possible to care for a
                    <del>child</del>
                <add>family</add>. It is feared that the use of preventives will cause sterility,
                and when a child is desired the woman will be unable to conceive.</p>
            <p><add>Physicians agree that</add> There is no ground for this fear. It has been shown
                by hundreds of cases where parents have lost a child, that though they had practiced
                prevention for four, five, or even ten years, conception has taken place when
                desired. Personally, I know a patient who gave birth to a child after 20 years' use
                of preventives.</p>
            <p>As mentioned before, strong solutions should be especially avoided in this respect.
                But it is well to get the advice of your family physician and bring these questions
                before him. <add>It all depends upon the proper method used.</add></p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">IS THERE A SAFE PERIOD?</head>
            <p>There are some women who believe there is a safe period in the month when CONCEPTION
                    <del>does</del>
                <add>can</add> NOT take place. That if intercourse does not occur from four days
                before menstruation until a week after it has ceased, in the time remaining
                conception will not occur.</p>
            <p>There are many women who have found this to be true in their own experience, but most
                medical authorities DENY its infallibility, and personally I have known of more
                abortions resulting from this method that those with whom it has been successful. IT
                IS NOT WISE TO TRUST TO IT.</p>
            <p>There are also many women, and a few men, who claim that intercourse is intended only
                for procreation, and that it should not take place unless a child is desired. In
                this way no preventives are necessary.</p>
            <p>I must admit I that held this view for years, and I have a <del>lingering regard
                    for</del>
                <add>interest in</add> it still. I believe the sexual act involves a CREATIVE ENERGY
                which can be directed into channels for creative work and self-expression.</p>
            <p>I lay special stress on CREATIVE WORK, which in my estimation draws on different
                forces in the body than mechanical, physical or routine labor.</p>
            <p>But I know, too, that the sexual life of man differs greatly in nature and the course
                of its development from the sexual activity of woman, and also that the MAJORITY of
                men and women today are doing VERY LITTLE creative work, which leaves almost the
                only outlet for their creative energy through the sexual act.</p>
            <p>The consequence is, all modern life FORCES a sexual outlet through intercourse, and
                IT IS ONLY THE FEW EXCEPTIONS who are able to live up to this theory, even if it is
                accepted.</p>
            <p>When once we throw down the bars of Puritanical bigotry and look upon sex and its
                expression apart from procreation as a fundamental basis of all life, we shall come
                to realize that all the repressive measures employed by legislatures and laws cannot
                solve our sex problem. Let us rather BEAUTIFY them and direct their flow into
                creative channels for the benefit of society, and look upon sex as <person
                    reg="Emerson, Ralph Waldo">Emerson</person> did when he said: "<q who="EMERA"
                    >Work your passions into poetry</q>".</p>
            <p>A new world awaits humanity when women shall raise the standard of sex and raise man
                to its level, of <emph rend="underline">beauty</emph> and <emph rend="underline"
                    >significance</emph> and <emph rend="underline">recognize</emph> and <emph
                    rend="underline">accept</emph> and <emph rend="underline">understand</emph> it,
                instead of suppressing and denying <del>it</del>
                <add>&amp; debasing it</add>.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">WHEN SHOULD WOMEN AVOID HAVING CHILDREN?</head>
            <p>It is well for a woman not to give birth to a child:</p>
            <p>1. Before she is AT LEAST <emph rend="underline">twenty-two</emph> years of age;
                better twenty-five if possible.</p>
            <p>2. From TWO to THREE years after the birth of the LAST child, in order to properly
                nurse and care for the last child and to allow the mother to renew her strength for
                the next.</p>
            <p>3. Whenever a woman or man suffers from diseases such as tuberculosis, gonorrhea,
                syphilis, cancer, epilepsy, pelvic deformities, insanity, drunkenness, and mental
                diseases. </p>
            <p>4. When parents, though healthy themselves, find that their children are physically
                or mentally defective.</p>
            <p>5. Whenever the conditions of life and the uncertainty of livelihood do not give the
                prospect of bringing up children decently and of giving them a better chance than
                the parents have had. </p>
            <p> AND FOR WORKING WOMEN <add>She should not have a large family</add></p>
            <p>6. So long as society remains indifferent to the needs of the worker's children. </p>
            <p> 7. So long as <del>child slaves still</del><add>her children must</add> toil in
                mills and factories.</p>
            <p>8. So long as a system of society exists in which children must compete in the labor
                market with their fathers for their daily bread.</p>
            <p>9. Let us remember that so long as the mothers of the race must breed <emph
                    rend="underline">in ignorance</emph>, they shall continue to fill insane
                asylums, penitentiaries, jails and almshouses with their offspring and provide the
                trenches of the world with their flesh and blood that has already <emph
                    rend="underline">reddened every battlefield in history.</emph><add>other
                    page</add><gap extent="one page" reason="missing"/></p>
            <p>Some of those who take their stand against Birth Control do so by the thought that we
                have no right to destroy potential life.</p>
            <p>A little study of human and animal physiology would convince them that every celibate
                male and female as well as married men insistently and inevitably waste MYRIADS of
                germ cells which had the potentiality of fusion with an ovum and consequently
                produced a child had the opportunity been given them.<add> If it's a crime to
                    prevent creation then its a crime to refuse to marry a man--</add></p>
            <p>For the supposed sake of one or two of these myriad sperms <add>cells</add> which
                must NATURALLY and INEVITABLY die <add>any way</add> they
                    <del>encourage</del><add>insist upon</add> the production of babies in rapid
                succession, which are weakened by their proximity which might otherwise have been
                sturdy and healthy, had they been conceived further apart from each other.</p>
            <p>Such people, while awake to the claims of the unborn and even the unconceived,
                continue to be BLIND to the claims of the woman's health and will force a woman to
                BEAR and BRING FORTH a child ANNUALLY. When each child following so rapidly its
                predecessor saps and exhausts the vital strength which is available for the making
                of the offspring which lowers the vitality of each child and EVENTUALLY MURDERS THE
                WOMAN who bears them.</p>
            <p>Dr. <person reg="Ploetz, Alfred">Ploetz</person> found that the death rate of the
                FIRST BORN infants is 220 a thousand.</p>
            <p>The death rate of the SEVENTH is 330 a thousand. While that of the TWELFTH is 600 a
                thousand. So that when "Nature has its way" and twelve children come to sap a
                woman's vitality so little strength has she left that nearly 60 percent of these
                later ones die.</p>
            <p>WE FIND THAT EVEN <emph rend="underline">NATURE</emph> TENDS TOWARD BIRTH
                CONTROL!!</p>
            <p>But what a hideous waste of vitality! What a hideous orgy of agony. For mothers to
                produce in anguish, DEATH-DOOMED and SUFFERING INFANTS.</p>
            <p>To those who protest that we have no right to interfere with THE COURSE OF NATURE one
                must point out that the whole of CIVILIZATION, <emph rend="underline">EVERYTHING
                    THAT SEPARATES MAN FROM ANIMALS</emph>, is an INTERFERENCE with what people
                commonly call NATURE.</p>
            <p>Railroads, boats, bridges, walking upright, living in houses, <add>shaving</add>,
                wearing clothes, cooking and talking all in the beginning were AGAINST Nature. We
                have come to realize that all civilization means the CONTROL and DIRECTION of
                Nature.</p>
            <p>Actions differ in their relative positions in the scale of things. ONLY THOSE ACTIONS
                ARE WORTHY WHICH LEAD THE RACE ONWARD TO A HIGHER AND FULLER COMPLETION AND TO THE
                PERFECTING OF ITS POWERS, <del>which</del> steer the race into the main current of
                that stream of life and <del>vitality</del> which courses through us and impels us
                forward.</p>
            <p>We <add>who advocate Birth Control</add> are trying to raise the STANDARD and
                HEIGHTEN the sacredness of human life, promote the well-being and happiness of
                    <del>the hopeless</del>
                <add>humanity</add>
                <del>and</del>
                <add>we are</add> trying to <add>intelligently</add> solve some of the MOST
                DIFFICULT AND URGENT PROBLEMS of our times.</p>
            <p>We recognize the importance of <del>everything that</del>
                <add>safeguarding</add>the DIGNITY of <del>the individual woman</del>,
                    <add>motherhood,</add> and we want to raise <del>her</del>
                <add>it</add> from the DEGRADATION OF SERVILITY and SEX SLAVERY to a
                <del>high</del>, <add>far higher,</add> and GLORIFIED <add>privilege</add>
                <del>womanhood</del>.</p>
            <p><add>For we believe that</add> It is the SACRED DUTY of all who dare to hand on the
                terrific gift of LIFE to hand it on in a vessel as fit and perfect as it can be
                fashioned, so that the body may be the STRONGEST and MOST BEAUTIFUL <add>INSTRUMENT
                    possible, in the service of the Soul we summon to play its part in the mystery
                    of material being</add>.</p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
