<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed draft article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2007/08/31 EK</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007/09/04 CH Corrections-list</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2009/07/22 CH Proof</prepDate><prepDate>2014-03-10 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1930-00-00 ">
            <unclear>1930</unclear>
        </docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Powerful Forces at Work</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236140</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College.</bibl>
            <bibl>
                <title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm Edition</title> S71:216. </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="population" level2="food supply and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Powerful forces at work.</head>
        <div type="section">
            <p>1. Marriage leads to offspring.</p>
            <p>2. The average healthy pair can produce and raise to the age of
                maturity more than two children.</p>
            <p>3. That when they continue to multiply the next generation will
                be more numerous than the first.</p>
            <p>4. That an acre of land is limited to the number of plants it can
                occupy.</p>
            <p>5. That the returns from crowded territory dwindle rather than
                increase.</p>
            <p>A population inhabiting any limited area must do one of two
                things: control its increase or get its food from wider areas.
                To control its number is to reduce the death rate and reduce the
                birth rate.</p>
            <p>There is a limit to the quantity of food that can be grown on a
                given acre of land--a limited space in which plants can spread
                their roots in the soil--their leaves in the air, and sunlight
                that the returns from the land are also limited. These facts
                have been demonstrated over and over again at various
                agricultural experimental stations.</p>
            <p>This fact explains the history of migration of peoples struggling
                for land and markets.</p>
            <p>It can draw its sustenance from wider areas by migrating to those
                areas or by selling to the inhabitants of other areas the
                finished product of its indoor industries--in other words in
                exchange for food and raw materials.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head rend="underline">
                <org reg="Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau">Clinic</org>
            </head>
            <p>37% sent by friends><lb/> 32% “ ” social organizations<lb/>
                <org reg="American Birth Control League">League</org><lb/> 37%
                sent by friends<lb/> 51% wives foreign born<lb/> 54% husbands “
                ”<lb/></p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
