<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="(Published article) ">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/04/04 VS initial tagging</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="(1929-10-00) ">Oct, 1929</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>The Next Step</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236174</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Birth Control Review</title> pp. 278-279</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="KEIAR">Keith, Arthur</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">Margaret Sanger speaks frankly of the United States Penal Codes, urging
        Americans to use co-ordination and co-operation to succeed in this endeavor. Printed in the
        Birth Control Review, October 1929, pages 278-289. <index level1="birth control"
            level2="distribution of information about"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="opposition to"/>
        <index level1="Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau"/>
        <index level1="Birth Control Review, The"/>
        <index level1="National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control"/>
        <index level1="physicians" level2="birth control and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>The Next Step</head>
        <byline>The <name reg="United States Penal Code">Penal Laws</name> of the <place>United
                States</place>, which obstruct and prohibit Birth Control, must be amended by the
            united effort of intelligent Americans.</byline>
        <div>
            <p> “<q who="KEIAR">The greatest experiment in race building the world has ever
                seen</q>” – this is the great human drama now unfolding in these United States,
                according to Sir <person reg="Keith, Arthur">Arthur Keith</person>,
                    <place>England</place>’s leading anthropologist. Are we going to play a leading
                role in this great racial drama? Are we going to push through to victory? Or are we
                going to sit back content to remain passive spectators of a play which threatens to
                turn into a national tragedy? There can be one answer only: we must act,
                courageously, promptly and in unison. If we refuse, we brand ourselves as lacking
                not only intelligence, but also courage.</p>
            <p> What is the next imperative step confronting us? I can answer this question in two
                words: co-ordination and co-operation. Let me explain why.</p>
            <p> Birth Control does not mean mere contraception. It has two aspects: positive and
                negative. It aims to place in the hands of every potential mother in America the
                power to say yes or no – to decide for herself if and when and how, she shall
                fulfill the function of motherhood. Birth Control will enable a woman to act as a
                free, self-directed, autonomous personality. It will liberate motherhood. For,
                remember, without free mothers we can never produce free and strong children.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Co-ordination and Co-operation Needed</head>
            <p> But this <title>Magna Carta</title> for womankind cannot become operative without
                co-ordination and co-operation. Last May we scored a great victory in <place
                    reg="New York, NY">New York City</place> in vindicating the right of the
                    <org>Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau</org> to function without the
                interference of obstructionists. That right is possible in other states – in
                    <place>California</place>, for instance. But due to obsolete statuses written
                into our Federal Penal Code by prudent fanatics, unified action on the part of all
                intelligent and farseeing groups in the United States has been impossible. Therefore
                I say that the first step toward the co-ordination and co-operation of our forces,
                acting as a nation-wide unit can be effected by the removal of the obstacles
                enacted, under the sinister influence of the late <person reg="Comstock, Anthony"
                    >Anthony Comstock</person>, into the Federal Penal Code.</p>
            <p> The Federal law not only excludes books or pamphlets containing contraceptive
                information, but it makes it a crime punishable by five years imprisonment or $5,000
                fine, to tell anyone where, or by whom, such information may be given. In other
                words the Federal law makes it a crime for me to write to anyone in California and
                give the address of any doctor or clinic, of which there are over seven legally
                operating under the law of the State of California. Preposterous truly.... The same
                law prohibits the sending of clinical reports to doctors or the interchange of
                records, data or scientific facts regarding the studies made in various localities
                on the technique and methods of contraception. It prohibits the entrance from
                    <place>Europe</place> of articles or books or appliances most necessary to
                advance the scientific work of the clinics, and of contraceptive research in the
                United States.</p>
            <p> The Federal laws (Sections <name reg="Section 334 of the United States Penal Code"
                    >334</name>, <name reg="Section 396 of the United States Penal Code">396</name>,
                    <name reg="Section 511 of the United States Penal Code">511</name>, <name
                    reg="Section 512 of the United States Penal Code">512</name>) must be amended,
                to allow medical and scientific books, records and articles to be sent through the
                mails to and from the physicians, and to include the necessary provisions for the
                patients, as well as for druggists, importers and manufacturers.</p>
            <p> The amendment to the Federal law must be secured by a general protest of enlightened
                and intelligent citizens throughout the country. I have the honor to be the Chairman
                of the <org reg="National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control"
                    >Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control</org> (46 West 15th Street,
                New York City) and we invite readers of the <title type="journal">Review</title> to
                participate in this national campaign.</p>
            <p> Here I have only briefly indicated the network of obstructions and obstacles which
                have been created by these Federal statutes. They stand as a veritable barbed wire
                entanglement which we must clear before the American nation can carry to successful
                fulfillment the greatest experiment in race building this world has ever
                witnessed.</p>
            <p> To join in this national campaign is to align oneself with the forces of
                intelligence. This is the most profoundly patriotic act now possible for American
                citizens. It means to play an active part in a great human drama. Here is an
                opportunity to be embraced joyfully, reverentially, religiously. To present a united
                front – valiant, indefatigable and undefeatable, against the powers of prejudice,
                prurience and stupidity – to gain strength by our very solidity, and to march
                joyfully into the future! There is an increased sense of living, more thrills in
                fighting, than the passive critic ever feels. Support the Federal Committee and
                discover this for yourself!</p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
