<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Draft Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011-07-29 NC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2-014-03-25 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1952-09-30">30 Sept 1952</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Notes for Japan Address</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236154</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S72:0687</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="birth control" level2="in Japan"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <dateline><date value="1952-09-30">September 30, 1952</date></dateline>
        <p>The principal thought in addressing the Japanese people seems to me that they will want
            to know how successful is the birth control movement progressing in other countries.
            What are the results of the practice? Has it made for happier families, for smaller
            families, for a lower birth rate? What is the opposition? How can they overcome it? The
            suggestions should come of what they should do to avoid our errors. I would like to not
            only suggest a national program of the culture and art along with the science of home
            building, but I would like to call on the authorities of public health and make them
            responsible to the people for the increase of disease and poverty, for the institutions
            for morons and insane population, and then call on the <org
                reg="World Health Organization">W.H.O.</org> and <org reg="United Nations"
                >U.N.</org> to resist the pressure of religious groups. To arouse the women of
                <place>Japan</place> to demand better methods of contraception than abortion, to
            formulate groups of research for simple methods of contraception, so that a cultural
            society can take its place in leadership of the world, instead of an expanding military
            or industrial society, which will only lead to destruction and chaos. </p>


    </docBody>
</doc>
