<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Autograph draft speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-05-07 JK initial tag</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1952-10-09">09 Oct 1952</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>
                <supplied resp="MSPP">Notes on Research Progress</supplied>
            </titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236160</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S72:718</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>These draft speech notes, written on the letterhead of the Biltmore
            Hotel, were likely written on Oct. 9, when <person
                reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger</person> stopped there en route to
            Japan. No final version has been found. These notes appear to be
            incomplete. </p>
        <index level1="motherhood"/>
        <index level1="planned parenthood"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="infant"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="maternal"/>
        <index level1="population" level2="war and"/>
        <index level1="population control" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="birth rate"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>


        <p>Today the far sighted, seriously Patriotic leaders in all countries
            where people are allowed the freedom to think -- these people are
            concerned with the increase of population &amp; the problems arising
            from too fast an increase -- its spacing in a family for the
            mother’s health -- for the father’s income &amp; the standards of
            education &amp; culture to be maintained. The same should</p>
        <p> appear</p>
        <p>arroused action for mothers &amp; children were our concern their
            health -- reduced, death rates</p>
        <p>Every mother -- population pressure was in 1922 not considered of
            immediate concern or problems. Then the Japanese population was 60
            million. There has been a war. Millions killed, injured, made
            useless -- yet population 1951, 84 million</p>
        <p>Research</p>
        <p>better health</p>
        <p> Today there are problems of our dream come true -- scientists have
            been working on a method to minimize a woman against pregnancy just
            as medical science has discovered measures to minimize men &amp;
            women against --</p>
        <p> Research Progress</p>
        <p>One of the most potent barriers to the advancement of our movment --
            B.C. or <org>Planned Parenthood</org> was the lack of simple, cheap,
            safe, harmless contraceptives -- the only methods to help women were
            such that to be 100% safe the woman needed physician’s knowledge of
            anatomy to help her -- the instruction was as important as having
            glasses properly fitted for the eyes --</p>
        <p>The methods used in <place>Europe</place> &amp; <place
                reg="United States">USA</place> have been under the supervising
            of medical practitioners. The so called diaphragm closing off the
            cervix from the possibility of the entrance of the sperm. This is
            sound procedure and the hundreds of thousands of women in <place
                reg="New York">NY</place> have used this method for years
            successfully. 150000 women in the <org
                reg="Margaret Sanger Research Bureau">MS Bureau</org> --
            abortions have been reduced -- examinations has helped women to</p>
        <p>to a community &amp; to a country -- a slow increase of the birth
            rate to assure every child have -- health, food, education, play
            grounds -- schools &amp; proper teaching, arts -- sciences and a
            place in the world for every child -- to progress -- to advance --
            to belong -- to help remake a new civilization of peace through the
            attainments of cultural arts &amp; sciences.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
