<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2009/07/06 CH 2010/03/10 AC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2013-11-25 CH integrate 236179 and make corrections</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-08-21 CH Clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1935-03-14">14 Mar 1935</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Birth Control the Concern of
                Youth</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236180</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Papers Microfilm, Smith College Collection</title>
                S71:0716</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
            <name id="YMCA">Young Men's Christian Association</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>Sanger gave this address in <place reg="Boston, MA">Boston</place> at a <org reg="Greater Boston Youth Conference>Youth Conference</org>.
            The version below includes portions of an incomplete draft (MSM S71:716) and a press
            release (MSM S71:714). For press coverage that includes quotes, see "<title
                type="article">Home, Family Under Scrutiny in Confernece</title>," <title
                type="journal">Boston Evening Transcript</title>, Mar. 14, 1935. </p>
        <index level1="Comstock, Anthony"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Comstock act"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Federal"/>
        <index level1="obscenity"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="youth and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="opposition to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="medical community and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>BIRTH CONTROL THE CONCERN OF YOUTH</head>
        <head type="sub"><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person> addresses the Youth Conferenece</head>
        <p><supplied resp="MSPP">From the draft:</supplied></p>
        <p> There is no group more deeply concerned with birth control and all it can do for good
            and for ill than your generation, the men and women in their twenties, who will shape
            tomorrow’s world. I suppose you are a bit tired of hearing of your responsibility, and
            of how you will have to get the country out of the mess it is in. I suppose you often
            want to shout back at us: “<q who="UNK">Why did you tangle it all up? Why didn’t you
                manage better?</q>”</p>
        <p>We <emph rend="underline">should</emph> have managed better, and it is up to us to do
            what we can to set things straight before we have to turn the whole affair over to you
            young people. It may make you less impatient with us to remember that we too have had to
            untangle confusion bequethed to us by the generation that went before. We have been
            busy, up to our ears in work, trying to rectify mistakes not entirely of our own
            making.</p>
        <p>A mistake that has worked incalculable harm, and that I have spent the best years of my
            life trying to straighten out, was made by <person reg="Comstock, Anthony">Anthony
                Comstock</person> in 1873, when the laws were passed prohibiting the sending of
            obscene literature through the mails. The overzealous Comstock made the tragic mistake
            of classing contraception with obscenity, and the result has been confusion worse
            confounded.</p>
        <p>As you perhaps know, the Committee of which I am the president, the <org>National
                Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control</org>, is seeking the amendment
            of these Federal laws. The amendments, ( <name type="law">Senate Bill 600</name> and
                <name type="law">House Bill 5600</name>)now before <org
                reg="United States Congress">Congress</org> would make it possible for doctors,
            hospitals and licensed clinics to secure contraceptive information.</p>
        <p> <person reg="Clarke, James Freeman">Someone</person> has said that the difference between a statesman and a politician is that the
            statesman thinks of the next generation and the politician thinks of the next election.
            By that definition I wonder how many statesmen we can claim to have in this country, in
            our present condition of relief and unemployment and misery, only to increase the
            population which increases poverty, unemployment and misery.</p>
        <p> Everyone knows that we are piling up enormous debts for future generations to pay. But
            it is not only financial or money debts that I am referring to–such debts may be easily
            cancelled–but it will not be so simple for future generations to wipe out of existence
            the debt of inferior racial qualities that we are passing down to them, or to wipe our a
            population with millions of morons and defectives which we are handing down for our
            children’s children to manage.</p>
        <p> You and your children will have to deal with these debts, with the results of the petty
            acts of politicians. You must put pressure on our lawmakers to legislate for the future,
            which belongs to you.</p>
        <p> Some sort of birth control is being practiced today, and will continue to be practiced.
            For birth control is here to stay. But which is better, you have a right to ask your
            elders, your parents, your teachers and you congressmen: Bootleg, uncertain and often
            harmful methods, promoted by commercial firms for profit, or scientific, harmless,
            efficient methods prescribed by physicians for the best interest of you and your
            children?</p>
        <p> The political problems of today are the unsolved social and economic questions of
            yesterday. We are trying to face them. The social and economic needs of today will be
            the political problems of tomorrow. These are for you to face.</p>
        <p>
            <list>
                <item>Ten Truths about Birth Control</item>
                <item>1. Birth controllers are divided into two groups, the largest group are those
                    who want knowledge for themselves; another, though smaller group, is those civic
                    minded people who wish to see birth control used, for health and economic
                    reasons by those who need it.</item>
                <item>2. Only a very small percentage of people who practice birth control are
                    perfectly satisfied with present day methods.</item>
                <item>3. Research and the development of better methods are retarded by existing
                    restrictive laws.</item>
                <item>4. These laws, which have been on the Federal Statute books since 1873, still
                    class prevention of conception with abortion and obscenity.</item>
                <item> 5. Neither physicians, hospitals, nor medical books are exempt under this
                    law, and violations provide a penalty of five thousand dollars fine or five
                    years in prison or both. </item>
                <item>6. The law, however, is unenforceable because there are thousands of articles
                    and drugs, that prevent conception and which may, at the same time, be used for
                    the prevention of disease.</item>
                <item>7. This situation has given rise to bootleg manufacture and distribution of
                    contraceptives and has placed the matter in the hands of commercial firms
                    operating for profit rather than of physicians working for the public good. </item>
                <item>8. If the <name type="law" reg="United States Criminal Code">Criminal Code</name> were amended, scientific
                    birth control instruction could be included in the public health program of the
                        <org reg="United States Government">Federal Government</org>, and
                    physicians, hospitals and clinics could secure supplies legally and give
                    information.</item>
                <item>9. The knowledge of how to control the coming of children is necessary for
                    happy marraige.</item>
                <item>10. The youth of <place reg="United States">America</place> should demand this knowledge.</item>
            </list></p>
        <p><supplied resp="MSPP">From the press release:</supplied></p>
        <p> As a result of the Comstock laws, birth control instead of being recognized for what it
            really is, a fine, constructive thing, necessary for health and happiness, has been
            besmirched and driven underground. Here is medical information, which should be
            prescribed by physicians. Leading medical supply houses should be putting their best
            talent to work in order that we might have ever better and ever less expensive
            contraceptive supplies. Instead, up to the present time, birth control supplies are a
            bootleg product, and their manufacture and sale does not come under the regulation of
            any government agency.</p>
        <p>What concern is all this of Youth? As the just married, or about--to--be--married couples
            of today, as the mothers and fathers of the future, I think that you, more than any
            other group should understand the present situation. Many young people would marry
            today, and have all the joys that should rightly come to young people--the start in
            life, the companionship, the chance to make of marriage a fine and constructive
            force--if they could feel certain that they could postpone founding a family without
            harm to themselves or to their future children. Many a girl would follow her natural
            inclination and marry, if she did not fear the coming of childbearing and baby tending
            before she was ready for them. The early months and years of marriage should be a time
            of adjustment between a young man and woman. They should learn to know each other first
            as comrades and human beings before assuming the role of parents. </p>
        <p>Many outstanding organizations of and for young people have taken a stand on birth
            control. The <org reg="Young Men's Christian Association">Y.M.C.A.</org> at its biennial
            convention last May, adopted a resolution in favor of “<q who="YMCA">social legislation
                such as measures which will provide that the dissemination of birth control
                information shall be placed under authorized medical direction.</q>” Many local
                <org>Junior Leagues</org> have endorsed birth control and the Junior League magazine
            has run several articles on the subject. The <org>National
                Conference of Allied Youth</org>, sponsored by <org reg="Boy Scouts of America"
                >Boy Scouts</org>, <org reg="Girl Scouts of America">Girl Scouts</org>, <org>Camp
                Fire Girls</org>, YMCA and <org reg="Young Women's Christian Association"
            >YWCA</org>, and other youth organizations, faced the issues squarely at its Youth Today
            dinner last fall. Should young couples have children when they had no assurance of the
            child’s future, they queried? Why is it not possible to obtain birth control information
            safely and legally and decently?</p>
        <p> Among the many letters that come to me, I received one the other day from a young man
            who wrote: “<q who="UNK">I am thinking of getting married, and am not in a position to
                have children. I know there are dozens of preparations on the market, supposed to be
                alright. The question I am asking you is what is the safest and the best way to
                prevent children until I am able to care for them. I asked my doctor about this, and
                he went into a tirade about the fall of <place>Greece</place> and
                    <place reg="Rome, Italy">Rome</place>, and gave me a lot of generalities which told me
                nothing.</q>”</p>
        <p>You have a right to ask of us, the older generation, about these things. And it is our
            duty to give you, not a lot of generalities about Greece and Rome, but the scientific
            and helpful truth.” </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
