<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed draft speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-08-19 KH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-08-20 proof tape</prepDate>
        <docAuthor><person>Margaret Sanger</person></docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1929-00-00">1929</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">The Population Problem</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236184</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Sophia Smith Collection</title>#S71:195</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Sanger likely gave this speech at the beginning of 1929. For another
            draft version of this speech see Margarent Sanger Microfilm S71:192 </p><index
            level1="Asia" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Asia" level2="overpopulation and"/>
        <index level1="Australia"/><index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to" level3="in remote places"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to" level3="international"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="American opinion on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="and marriage"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="international"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"
            level3="negative consequences of"/><index level1="birth control"
            level2="socio-economic benefits of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="suppression of"/><index level1="China"
            level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="China" level2="birth rate in"/>
        <index level1="China" level2="overpopulation and"/>
        <index level1="China" level2="population policies of"/><index level1="Europe" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="Europe" level2="overpopulation and"/>
        <index level1="Europe" level2="travel in"/>
        <index level1="Europe" level2="women in"/><index level1="Germany"/>
        <index level1="Germany" level2="birth control in"/><index level1="immigration"
            level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="immigration" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="immigration" level2="U.S. policy"/>
        <index level1="India"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="birth control clinics and leagues in"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="birth control movement in"/><index level1="India"
            level2="overpopulation and"/>
        <index level1="mentally disabled and diseased"/>
        <index level1="mentally disabled and diseased" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="mentally disabled and diseased" level2="fertility of"/>/> </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <p><add>A number of</add><del>The</del> intelligent thinkers in <place>Europe</place>, many
            of with whom I <del>had</del><add>have</add> conversed, believe that the empty spaces on
            the globe are becoming rare; that populations are so increasing in every country that
            governments are at a loss to know how to deal with the problems arising therefrom; that
            Europe is today faced with a problem of having more men than bread, and this problem has
            become acute, because of the attitude of <place>United States</place>,
                <place>Austrailia</place> and <place>Canada</place>
            <add>as experienced</add> in their recent immigration legislation. It is now recognized
            that each <add>European</add> country needs its own available food supply. Each country
            is guarding its own labor market, fearing unrest, unemployment and revolution. Soon
                <emph rend="underline">every</emph> nation will reserve its potential resources for
            its own people, and already most of the European countries have overdrawn on their
            margin of self-sufficiency. <place>Germany</place>, <place>Italy</place>
            <place>Poland</place> and all the <place reg="Central Europe">central European
                countries</place> should be encouraged to limit their population to their natural
            resources, <hi>but they</hi>are all dreaming of
                <del>colonization</del><add>colonies</add>, for colonization over seas was the
            solution of overpopulated Europe since the conquest of the <place reg="Atlantic Ocean"
                >Atlantic</place>. There is no doubt that this has made civilization almost
            world-wide, and yet, there are doubts that this solution was of permanent value, for we
            now see that economic greed caused nations to overlook fundamental principles, and the
            future potentialities of <del>peoples</del><del>nations</del> have been sacrificed for
                <add>personal</add> immediate gain. Colonial expansion is still the dream of those
            militarists who clamor for big battalions of babies, and we see from the past that
            colonization has aroused a hatred of peaceful nations against the white race, and every
            where in <place>Asia</place> is the growing determination to free themselves from
                <del>their</del><add>the</add> political dominations <add>of the white race.</add>
            It <del>has</del><add>had</add> long been hoped by some of us <add>,</add> that <add>at
                sometime</add> a sound international population program might be advanced. We
                <del>have</del>
            <add>had</add> seen that a broad <del>broader</del> bird's eye view of the problem was
            necessary if it was to fit international and modern conditions. It <del>was</del>
            <add>is</add> quite natural that the militarist should look upon the subject only with a
            view of armies; the demographer with the number of births, deaths, marriages in a given
            city, country over a given period. The anthropologist <hi>is concerned</hi> with the
            division into race <add>,</add> within a population, especially in respect to their
            adaptability and the effect of social selection and colonization <add>;</add> while the
            economist, biologist and statistician - each an expert in his own line - was bound
                <add>view the sufficient</add> to propose measures according to the limits of his
            inquiries; consequently, formidable errors were bound to arise when it came to practical
            issues. It was with this in mind that I went to Europe <del>for</del><add>two years ago
                with</add> the object of bringing together scientists from various countries of
            different departments to correlate their views, experiments and programs, and to
            establish, if possible, a permanent organization for further studies and research along
            population lines. <del>This</del><add>A</add>
            <org reg="International Union for the Scientific Investigation of Population Problems"
                >Population Union</org> has now been launched and it is hoped that there will be a
            recognition through their studies <add>,</add> of the fact <add>,</add> that there can
            be no solution to the population problem without
                <del>the</del><add>recognization</add><del>of</del> the human factors which make
            this problem. I refer to the parents who produce populations - and especially the
            mothers who bear and rear the children. Immigration legislation in the United States has
            caused much bitterness in Europe, for there is current a feeling that
                <del>various</del><add>these</add>
            <del>nations</del><add>countries</add> have expended through generations much of <emph
                rend="underline">their</emph> most valuable human material<add>,</add> in order to
            furnish America with ready-made workmen - skilled in the arts and crafts - thereby
            impoverishing herself of valuable stocks, with the obvious results of creating a rival,
            today more powerful than all of Europe combined. America, on the other hand, considers
            that <emph rend="underline">she</emph> has been overstocked with undesirable elements;
            that her dream of the melting-pot of assimilating the various races, colors, grades of
            mentalities through education <del>by</del><add>to</add> an American type of
            intelligence, has not succeeded. She now regrets her mistake, and has established a
            rigid system of immigration barriers for her own national and racial protections; and
            one can assume charge - even five years after entry - are liable to deportation at any
            time. <add>Why not apply these same restrictions to a reproductive policy?</add> In no
            other immigration country is the restrictive policy carried out so far as in U.S.A. This
            rigid policy of the <org reg="United States Government">U.S. Government</org> is the
            result of its short-sightedness in the past, for while this government never openly
            encouraged immigration, she took up a neautral attitude toward the question until <emph
                rend="underline">1914></emph>. She was much like the parents who - not really
            knowing what shall happen if their family continues to grow - nevertheless<add>,</add>
            do nothing to prevent it. She now has had to adopt a negative, selective quota
                <add>policy</add> where she might have in the past adopted a postive, selective
            quota, and this country would today have been in a position to deal intelligently with
            some of the intricate problems that she is today unable to face. <add>14 year <emph
                    rend="underline">intelligence</emph></add>. Our immigration laws have
                <add>nevertheless</add> made the European countries think. <add>They</add>
            <add>have</add> especially been responsible for speeding up <add>the</add> Birth Control
                <add>Movement.</add> Particularly is this true in countries like
                <place>England</place> and Germany. <add>8 years-6 million</add>
            <add>1928-1936 it is 126 millions</add>
            <del>This morning's press gave an estimate that the population of this country is <emph
                    rend="underline"> now 120 millions.</emph></del> In the glory of increasing
            populations we must recognize that numbers are not the only thing to consider.
            Individuals are not mere statistical units who are <add>merely</add> born, marry and
            die, and while these functions cannot be entirely ignored, there is, howevere, a
            personal value depending upon the quality of the material with which they are endowed
            through inheritance. This is of infinitely greater value to society and to the progress
            of the race than mere statistical numbers. The greatest assets of a nation are
                the<del>se</del> human values and resources upon which the conservation and
            utliziation of its future depend, for it is to these innate values, to the quality of
            posterity, that attenion must now be directed, if civilization is to endure. Science is
            now bordering on the infinite and the most powerful brain seems feeble in front of the
            tasks which are glimpsed. If one is to judge by the predicament of the world situation,
            we are right to assume that there is not an individual born nor a group whose
            intelligence is up to the tasks that the international situation demands. It seems
            almost as if the kind of knowledge required exceeds out <add>mental</add> capacity
                <del>for understanding</del><add>to cope with it.</add> It is to the <emph
                rend="underline">science</emph> of population that we must now look for future
            guidance. It must point the way for <add>a</add> population <del>legislation</del>
            <add>policy &amp; plan</add> which in this country in particular could soon deliver
            society from more than half of its terrific burdens. It could soon help us to eliminate
            the possibility of increasing dysgenic stock, such as those with inherited or
            transmissible diseases. It could soon lessen the burden or philanthropic needs <del>are
                fast</del><add>have</add> grow<del>ing</del><add>n</add> beyond the <del>cultural
                needs of this generation</del><add>individual ability to carry them.</add> Sane
            legislation would indirectly direct reproduction with a sense of adaption toward future
            conditions by raising the mean level of brain power <add> raising the general average of
                intelligence of our population</add>, for the importance of numbers - mere
            statistical units like that of muscular brute force, belongs to the past rather than to
            the future. The needs of manual labor <add>are already supplied by machines</add> in the
            future will be greatly reduced by the progress off chemistry, physics and the possession
            of unlimited source of heat and force at a minimum of expenditure. On the other hand, we
            shall need brains highly resistant to work and capable of a degree of instruction which
            surpasses that of the most intelligent skilled artisan today. Vaster memories must be
            forged, shaper insight must be gained, and with the discovery of the laws of inheritance
            man can choose whether we shall evolve to the expression of highest within us, or if we
            shall revert to the state of barbarian. It is for man to decide. With all the knowledge
            that we today possess, it is obvious that it is a crime <del>for</del><add>against</add>
            generations to come, it is a crime against out civilization to encourage the
            reproduction of mediocre, diseased or inferior types of groups. Such offspring can only
            be a burden to the future and retard the progress of the present generation. It has
            become clear that the population of the earth is fast arriving at its possible maximum;
            that its density is badly distributed; that redistribution of space can only be
            rectified by displacements; and that Birth Control in overpopulated countries is the
            first and surest method whereby the balance may be peacefully restored.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
