<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Autograph draft document">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2012-04-04 AW Initial Tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2012-04-13 CH Proofed Tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2012-05-15 CH Proofed Tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2012-05-16 AW Corrected Tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-10 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="0000-00-00">N. d.</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Notes on the History of Marriage</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236365</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S73:0084</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="ELLHA">Ellis, Havelock</name>
            <name id="LAT">Latin</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>Pages 1-6 and last page(s) of this rough draft are missing.</p>
        <p>In the notes below, Sanger summarizes Havelock Ellis' 1925 <title type="book">Studies in
                the Psychology of Sex</title>, Volume XI, <title type="book">Sex in Relation to
                Society</title>, Chapter X, <title type="article">Marriage</title> pp. 362-420.</p>
        <p>No final version has been found.</p>
        <index level1="Christianity" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="marriage"/>
        <index level1="marriage" level2="history of"/>
        <index level1="Roman Empire"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <gap extent="6 pages"/>
        <p>valuation of the new shoots, which are springing up in Society today toward the Marriage
            system is to consider the history of marriage.</p>
        <p>Page (395) <person reg="Ellis, Havelock">Ellis</person>--on Woman's status in Rome--</p>
        <p>In the <add>later</add> days of <place>Roman Empire</place>
            <q>women had acquired an independent position <add>nearly</add> equal to their husbands
                while the patriarchal authority over them was almost nominal</q>.</p>
        <p>In Roman law there was no legal forms of marriage--it was considered a fact not a legal
            form, and living together a year constituted a marriage &amp; regarded just as <q
                who="ELLHA">complete &amp; legal as if it had been inaugurated by the <supplied
                    resp="MSPP"><foreign lang="LAT">Confarreatio</foreign></supplied></q>. It was
            considered a private agreement in which <q who="ELLHA">man &amp; woman approached each
                other on a footing of equality</q>. The wife controlled full rights of her property
            &amp; divorce was also a private transaction to which both husband &amp; wife were
            entitled without the interruption of courts. Ellis says “<q who="ELLHA">it is
                interesting to note this enlightened conception of marriage prevailing in the
                greatest &amp; most masterful Empire which has ever dominated the world.</q>”</p>
        <p>After the face of the Roman Empire the Roman law remained as a standard for new
            developing nations, but its become influenced by &amp; with Christianity which gradually
            &amp; subteley <q who="ELLHA">revealed a growing ascetic feeling hostile to the dignity
                of the married woman &amp; the freedom of marriage &amp; divorce.</q> With this was
            introduced the Jewish Marriage system (barbaric) which gave to the husband rights in
            marriage &amp; divorce but denied them to the wife.</p>
        <p>The German ideas regarding marriage were even more primitive &amp; barbaric than that of
            the Jews and <q who="ELLHA">involved the wife as a husband’s chattel &amp; marriage as a
                purchase</q>, all these influences clashed but the result was that the fifteen
            hundred years which followed the conquest of Christianity represent <q who="ELLHA">the
                most degraded condition to which the marriage system has ever been known to fall for
                so long a period during the whole course of human history</q>.</p>
        <p>Sale marriage was the usual form &amp; the ring was a form of the bride price or a
            "arrha" which was money in this contract is the symbol of it. </p>
        <p>(Harvards vol I p.p. 278-281, 386)</p>
        <p> At first the ring was a sign of the brides purchase, but later it <q who="ELLHA"
                >acquired the significance of subjection to the bridegroom</q> &amp; was later
            emphasized by other ceremonies. Some forms of <place>England</place> &amp;
                <place reg="York, England">York</place> marriages direct the bride <q who="ELLHA">to fall at the feet of
                the husband &amp; kiss his right foot</q> at the delivery of the ring.</p>
        <p>(L. Gautier) <supplied resp="MSPP">or ring--</supplied></p>
        <p> The influence of the <org reg="Roman Catholic Church">Catholic Church</org> over marriage has been handed <supplied
                resp="MSPP">over</supplied> to us for the tenth century. Earlier than the sixth
            Century there was no special religious service.</p>
        <p><q who="ELLHA">The <org>Christian Church</org> at first accepted the forms of marriage
                already existing in these countries in which it found itself</q>, it demanded that
            it <q who="ELLHA">should be hallowed by priestly benediction</q> the same as was
            demanded for all other civil contracts. <q who="ELLHA">But marriage was recognized by
                the Church even in the absence of such benediction</q>.</p>
        <p><q who="ELLHA">A special marriage service developed slowly</q>. At first the first part
            of the nuptials was performed outside the Church door &amp; was followed by the bride
            mass of the occasion during the tenth century &amp; gradually at the twelfth century the
            priest directed the ceremony inside the Church &amp; in the 13 Century the priest
                <del>directed</del>
            <add>officiated</add> the whole <supplied resp="MSPP">ceremony</supplied>. Up to this
            time <q who="ELLHA">marriage had been a purely private business transaction</q>--a
            thousand years <del>after</del> of Christianity through the slow growth of custom Church
            marriage was <supplied resp="MSPP">established</supplied>. Today the public method of
            marriage is based on the marriage form of the twelfth century.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
