<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Autograph draft document">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2012-04-25 AW Initial Tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-10 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="0000-00-00">n.d.</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Quality of Our Population</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236433</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Sophia Smith Collection, Margaret Sanger Papers</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S73:0154</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>No final version was found.</p>
        <index level1="child spacing"/>
        <index level1="child welfare"/>
        <index level1="poverty"/>
        <index level1="poverty" level2="family size and"/>
        <index level1="working classes" level2="MS on"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <p>We hear a great deal today about preserving institutions of democracy, liberty to future
            generations, but these institutions will take care of themselves if the people have the
            ability to use &amp; appreciate them. It is not the <add>loss of</add> institutions or
            traditions that I fear--but the kind of people we are breeding to form <del>the
                next</del> future generations. This is the real question of today &amp; tomorrow. To
                <del>base</del> infer that the quality of our <del>people</del> population depends
            upon the birth rate of college graduates is tinsel thinking. There are deeper &amp;
            sounder qualities <add>of democracy</add> ingrained in the <place>Arizona</place>
            country than in thousands of college graduates. There is potential qualities of sound
            thinking ingrained &amp; bred in artisans &amp; <unclear resp="MSPP">medians</unclear>
            which is a necessary corner stone of any civilization a selective birth rate will soon
            be in order.</p>
        <p>An exciting controversial experiment for a scientific group to present to the world is to
            draft, a set of qualities necessary for the human vessel to contain--man--during the
            next hundred years--what shall those qualities be? Should each nation pool its desires
            &amp; ideals? We should doubtless find out. </p>
        <p>The Int Pop union might exert its imagination a little &amp; recent statements set up an
            alarm that old men &amp; women are to inherit this earth--well what of it? As we are
            neither old or young we may be allowed to set forth unprejudiced opinions.</p>
        <p>In Oct 1846. <add><org>Irish Relief Works</org></add> 114,000 persons employed on Relief
            Works.</p>
        <p>In Nov. 285,000. In Dec 440,000</p>
        <p>‘’ Jan 1847 it grew to 570,000.</p>
        <p>‘’ Feb ‘’ ‘’ ‘’ 708,000.</p>
        <p>‘’ March ‘’ ‘’ ‘’ 735,000</p>
        <p>heads of families or about four millions of persons living on payment obtained out of the
            taxation of other people, which they got for little more than idling away their time, on
            works that were not absolutely necessary to be done at all”</p>
        <p>At the same time, the essential works of the world could not get done, it was difficult
            to get a coat patched, or a pair of shoes mended &amp; whenever relief works were
            established the necessary agricultural work was being neglected. Farmers could not get
            their fields tilled. Relief works were too “attractive.”</p>
        <p> In <place>France</place> 1886--<person reg="Bernard, M.">M. Bernard</person> deputy
            proposed to the <org reg="France Chamber of Deputies">French Chamber</org> that the
            state should educate the seventh child of all parents--who had seven living
            children--but limited the sum to be spent upon this ridiculous idea to ℒ16.000 ($80,000)
            annually. It was shown it would take a million sterling or 10 million dollars a year to
            carry out this idea in all cases. After a long debate an act was passed limiting
            assistance to the families of the poor. ℒ40 a year ($200)--Malthusian editors commit to
            the effect that parents with more than three children when they could not educate &amp;
            provide for should have been “deprived of some privilege” since it is often these poor
            large families that the greatest amount of poverty, misery, sickness &amp; death is
            found.</p>
        <p> This act will tend to irate the poorest classes of France to plunge themselves yet
            deeper into poverty. <gap extent="one word" reason="illegible"/>--desperation.”</p>
        <p> He’ll agree that the set goal for the next three years is to concentrate &amp; direct
            all our efforts &amp; resources toward getting B.C. a fact of country, state, &amp;
            natural public health work.</p>
        <p>But While that is an unexpected goal--&amp; <gap extent="three words" reason="illegible"
            /> for there are millions of mothers &amp; fathers too who will not come under public
            health care &amp; whose sacrifice, independence &amp; cues view responsibly for their
            children entitles them to the same consideration given to private persons who do not
            desire to become a public charge. </p>
        <p>These two groups comprise millions of our population &amp; from their increase or
            controlled birth rates shall emerge the problems or complexities of generations yet to
            come.</p>
        <p>The B.C. movement might decide to tackle both groups--dividing its interests according to
            its support general public health. --</p>
        <p> For millions--</p>
        <p> private clinics (extra <gap extent="one word" reason="illegible"/>) for their small pay,
            self <gap extent="one word" reason="illegible"/> independent parents who prefer to pay
            as they go-- </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
