<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Autograph draft speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2010/03/31 AC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-11 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1935-00-00">1935</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>The Truth about Birth Control</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236440</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title>, S71:0809</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"/>
    <index level1="abortion"/>
    <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="MS on"/>
    <index level1="birth control"/>
    <index level1="birth control" level2="definitions of"/>
    <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="safe period"/>
    <index level1="Post Office (U.S.)"/>
    <docBody>
        <head>The Truth about Bc</head>
        <p>No subject that has so large</p>
        <p>No other subject of Social &amp; Natural importance.</p>
        <p><person reg="Darwin, Charles">Darwin</person></p>
        <p><list>
                <item>1- BC is Not Abortion. Control. prevent. Conscious.</item>
                <item>2. Fed &amp; State laws still class BC with abortion Medical Colleges,
                    Universities Depts of <gap reason="illegible" extent="one word"/>. genetics
                    &amp; zoology. Sec 211, 245.312.</item>
                <item>3. After 62 years these laws are still in Statue books!!! Unchallenged (&amp;
                    Unchanged) Drs in <org reg="United States Senate">Senate</org>. Women as
                    representatives laws still remain.</item>
                <item>4 In spite of these laws 5000 fine. 5 years prison. 162 birth Control Clinics
                    “Speak easies “are operating legally in the various States!! Speak easies,
                    bootleg their supplies.</item>
                <item>5. In spite of laws– commercial forms advertise their contraception products
                    Salesmen &amp; Saleswomen peddle there products to ignorant &amp; innocent women
                    from door to door. These have “increased &amp; multiplied” over 100%. No checks,
                    no control no investigation as <gap reason="illegible" extent="one word"/>
                    quality or Effacaciousness. If you know what to ask for you are able to get it
                        <emph rend="underline">at the price</emph>. </item>
                <item>6. Hospitals, Clinics public health agencies &amp; institution <gap
                        reason="illegible" extent=""/> to obtain these products in violation of Fed
                    laws. Consequently poorest women are unable to obtain material or information
                    &amp; must have babies or abortions.</item>
                <item>7. <person reg="Farley, James A.">P. Farley</person> is not a <emph
                        rend="underline">Doctor</emph> He is not a <add>Federal</add> Judge. Yet he
                    has decreed that one kind of BC information is legal. Any book or pamphlet or
                    newspapers carrying advertisments of these books or pamphlet written with
                    “Ecclastical approval” Those with Scientific or Medical approval are not exempt.
                    except as boot leg products. </item>
                <item>8. Farley’s bill to tighten up the law on all other information which does not
                    have “Ecclesciastical Approval”</item>
                <item>9. The books <del>allowed</del> exempt from the <org
                        reg="United States Postal Service">US Mails</org> on those giving
                    information as to the so called “Safe Period” Calenders are displayed &amp;
                    dates worked out <emph rend="underline">Meticulously</emph>. Congratulate the
                        <org reg="Roman Catholic Church">R. C. Church</org> in the faith they have
                    placed in the <add>morals of</add> youth of the world, in scattering this book
                    about so promiscuosly for Sale</item>
                <item>10/ There is no Safe Period definitely Safe for all women</item>
                <item>11/ That period where conception does not take place is <del>likely</del> to
                    be the period where sex union should not take place. Sex tide is low all contact
                    should be avoided. flattened her curve of sex desire, causing indifference &amp;
                    frigidity</item>
                <item>12/ Present methods are most relied upon chemical &amp; Mechanical. <list>
                        <item>97% Safe.</item>
                        <item>3% should hit did not technical failures.</item>
                        <item>15% human failures</item>
                    </list>
                </item>
                <item>13/ Contraception recommended by persons qualified to instruct &amp; adjusted
                    to individual requirements are conducive to better health in the woman better
                    care of children &amp; lessening infant mortality when children are spaced. Less
                    nervous tension <gap reason="illegible" extent="one word"/> husbands &amp;
                    wives. Fewer divorces in homes where sex fears and neurosis cause a maladjusted
                    marriage. Less infant &amp; Material mortality. fewer abortions. More children
                    born into the home when parents are able to plan for their arrival &amp;
                    welfare. </item>
            </list></p>


    </docBody>
</doc>
