<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith
    College</title></bibl>
<doc type="Typed draft speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2010/03/24 AC</prepDate><prepDate>2014-03-11 CH clean regs and other errors</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1934-01-00">Jan 1934</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Yesterday, Today, and Tomorrow</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236439</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title>S71:0655</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="race suicide"/>
        <index level1="birth control"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <p>FRIENDS:</p>
        <p>Standing here before you tonight, my mind is filled with the differences between
            YESTERDAY, TODAY– and To-MORROW!</p>
        <p> YESTERDAY, TODAY, TOMORROW! These three words stand as symbols for all the changes and
            all the progress we have made.</p>
        <p> Y E S T E R D A Y</p>
        <p>YESTERDAY:</p>
        <p>To me YESTERDAY stands for the reign of SPOOKS–the rule of FEAR, SUPERSTITIONS and the
            POWERS of DARKNESS.</p>
        <p> Just twenty years ago, our great OFFENSIVE for BIRTH CONTROL BEGAN. It was OFFENSIVE
                <add>, indeed it was!</add>–Offensive to the Conspiracy of Silence concerning the
            most important of all human functions. For me YESTERDAY stands for the great
                <add>smoky</add> battle against those SPOOKS. YESTERDAY every one said to me:</p>
        <p> “You <emph rend="underline">cant</emph> say that... You <emph rend="underline"
                >cant</emph> print that... You <emph rend="underline">cant</emph> tell them that...
            you <emph rend="underline">cant</emph> teach them that! You’ll be arrested... you’ll be
            indicted... You’ll be thrown into prison!”</p>
        <p> YESTERDAY meant patrol wagons, indictments, police courts, prison bars. But that was the
            only way to fight the SPOOKS–to drag them out into the <add>pitiless</add> glare of
            publicity and discussion and to <del>examine</del>
            <add>analyze</add> them <del>with</del>
            <add>under</add> the <emph rend="underline">penetrating</emph> light of
            intelligence.</p>
        <p> YESTERDAY we were <emph rend="underline">denounced</emph> from the pulpit, <emph
                rend="underline">jeeered</emph> at in the press, <emph rend="underline"
                >hustled</emph> to jail by the police. Our press was suppressed, our meetings <emph
                rend="underline">broken</emph> up, our clinics <emph rend="underline"
                >raided</emph>. BIRTH CONTROL, they said, meant Race Suicide. Birth Control was the
            instrument of the devil, destroyer of the home, the morals of youth, and the future of
            the Nation. BIRTH CONTROL would produce Sterility, Physical Degeneration, and the Morals
            of the YOUNG!</p>
        <p> YESTER DAY <add><emph rend="underline">UNDAUNTED</emph></add> we ploughed the field; we
            sowed the seeds of a new intelligence. <add>TO DAY we are gathering the harvest!</add>
            <del>TO-DAY</del> TO-DAY this Conference convinces me that those YESTERDAYS <del>can
                never return</del>. <add>are of the past FOREVER!</add> The SPOOKS of Darkness, of
            Fear, of Superstition and Ignorance can never return to obstruct our progress into the
            DAWN of TO-MORROW.</p>
        <p>
            <emph rend="underline">But we can not rest with TO-DAY.</emph> We must move ONWARD.
            Unless <del>at the same</del> time they <del>are</del>
            <add>be</add> preparations for the creation of a better world TO-MORROW, all attempts to
            solve the social problems which press upon the consciousness of the world to-day are
                <emph rend="underline">futile</emph>. You can pour out <emph rend="underline"
                >millions</emph> and <emph rend="underline">BILLIONS</emph> in an unending Niagara
            to feed the hungry and to give work to the idle and it will be wasted, unless–I repeat
            UNLESS–in so doing you are awakening the innate intelligence of <del><gap
                    reason="obliterated"/> the People</del>
            <add>all AMERICAN CITIZENS</add> to direct their own destinies and to create a LIFE MORE
            ABUNDANT for themselves.</p>
        <p> LIFE MORE ABUNDANT can never come until the nation–the whole nation–is awakened to the
                <emph rend="underline">primary</emph>, <emph rend="underline">fundamental</emph>
            and <emph rend="underline">elemental</emph> importance of GOOD BREEDING <add>through
                CONTROL</add>. The wealth of this country–of all <add>any</add> country–can not be
            measured in Dollars, nor in Gold. It can only be estimated in the quality of individuals
            who make it up.</p>
        <p> TO-MORROW, therefore, Our Legislators must decide. ARE the <place reg="United States">UNITED STATES OF AMERICA</place> to
            go on tacitly <add>encouraging</add>
            <del>and</del> by <del>mainting</del> obstructing <add>perpetuating ARCHAIC laws</add>
            laws on the statute books the BREEDING OF the DEFECTIVE, the DELINQUENT and the
            CRIMINAL? <add>COMPUTE THE COST TO THE NATION</add> this WORK must be carried on in
            every section of the Country that in each Community the problem is more pressing that
            ever before.</p>
        <p> ALL citizens and taxpayers are asked to meet the expenses of relief, to feed the hungry,
                <add>to clothe the poverty-stricken,</add> to <del>employ the</del> give work to the
            unemployed. That is TO-DAY’S Problem. But let us not forget that the solution of TODAY’S
            PROBLEMS may involve us in greater complication’s TO-MORROW.</p>
        <p>
            <add>EVEn if</add> the obstacles confronting us <emph rend="underline">today</emph> are
            so menacing, so threatening, so pressing, be<del>cause</del> even if Emergency Measures
            seem so imperative, VISION MUST NOT PERISH. The BLINDNESS of <emph rend="underline"
                >Yesterday</emph> has resulted in the CHAOS of TODAY<add>.</add> BUt the VERY
            CONFUSION OF TODAY should make us more keenly conscious than ever of our DUTY to
            ToMORROW, <del>makes a we wish</del> to The respect and gratitude of the Children of
            To-Morrow and the day after To-morrow we <add>can earn to=day</add> only by
            demonstrating for future historians that despite the World Tragedy into which we have
            been <del>precipitated</del>
            <add>HURLED</add> by the Stubborn and Wanton Ignorance of <emph rend="underline"
                >Yesterday</emph>, <del>we have held</del>
            <gap/> despite the stumbling of our feet along the steep and rocky battlefield, we
                <add>have</add> managed to hold aloft the tattered banner of intelligence–have
            indeed carried forward still brightly burning the <add>SACRED</add> TORCH OF LIFE.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
