<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Autograph speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-02-13 JC transcribe and encoding</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person>Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1935-00-00"><supplied resp="MSPP">1935</supplied></docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Population Control and Economic Recovery Speech
					Notes</supplied></titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp236471</idno>
		<sourceDesc>

			<bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</title> S
				71:799</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name/>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>For earlier drafts, see Margaret Sanger Microfilm Edition, S71:794, S71:785, and
			S71:789</p>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="and public health"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="class-based"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="economic benefits and risks"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"/>
		<index level1="birth rate"/>
		<index level1="birth rate" level2="decline in"/>
		<index level1="birth rate" level2="increase in"/>
		<index level1="birth rate" level2="differential"/>
		<index level1="population size" level2="and birth control"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<p>No force in the world so great--</p>
		<p>There is no subject that has so large a practical significance.</p>
		<p>Bc is the keynote of a new social awakening</p>
		<p>It is the conscious <emph rend="undlerline">control</emph> of the birth rate <emph
				rend="underline">prevent</emph></p>
		<p>Prevent not destroy-- not interfere (celibacy)</p>
		<p>Control not limit-- furnace automobile traffic currency</p>
		<p>Conscious control, intentional, deliberate. Choice not chance, reckless abandon</p>
		<p>positive attitude, not negative</p>
		<p><person reg="Shaw, George Bernard">G B Shaw</person>-- revolutionary idea of the century</p>
		<p><person reg="Wells, H.G.">HG Wells</person> most momentous fact of modern life</p>
		<p><person reg="Inge, Dean">Dean Inge</person>-- It is here to stay, a great force for good or bad</p>
		<p>History supports the fact that there are three ways to control population</p>
		<p>1 Increase death rate</p>
		<p>2 Emmigration</p>
		<p>3 decrease of the birth rate</p>
		<p>1) Death rate controlled thru disease, famine, pestilence, crimes, floods &amp; war</p>
		<p>2) Emmigration has been in operation</p>
		<p>now for the third and last alternative <gap reason="faulty-reproduction"
				extent="one word"/> are demigods, war thirsty militants, Medieval Dogmatists of the
			<org reg="Roman Catholic Church">R C</org> Hierarchy refuse to accept it</p>
		<p>decrease the birth rate thru successful Bc</p>
		<p>Bc is not a theory, it is being practiced among the well to do and intelligent</p>
		<p><gap reason="faulty reproduction" extent="one work"/> say some of our opponents that's
			just the problem: Bc is practiced by the intelligent for"selfish" reasons</p>
		<p>Of course it's practiced by the intelligent. Why not? For any knowledge of ??? which will
			embrace the beauty health &amp; happiness of life will always be most readily accepted
			by the intelligent of all classes.</p>
		<p>That's been the natural place for the practice of Bc to <emph rend="underline">Begin</emph></p>
		<p>But it needs not <emph rend="underline">end there</emph>!!</p>
		<p>To say that it is practiced for selfish motives is not true. The desire for Bc ??? on the
			part of all parents comes from a higher and much more ??? cause than that.</p>
		<p>It comes from an increased respect for the sanctity of life &amp; and increased regard
			&amp; responsibility for the welfare of our children.</p>
		<p>Such parents are inspired by the hope that having fewer children in time they can educate
			&amp; properly prepare to take a place in our complex struggle for existence that may
			escape the grinding poverty &amp; economic hardships they ??? have evidenced thru the
			accident of birth.</p>
		<p>Two groups-- low birth rate &amp; small families</p>
		<p>high birth rate &amp; large families, group</p>
		<p><emph rend="underline">low birth rate</emph></p>
		<p>few children</p>
		<p>planned pregnancy</p>
		<p>health</p>
		<p>culture, music</p>
		<p>schools, colleges</p>
		<p>civic interest</p>
		<p>Best positions in society</p>
		<p>Individual problems</p>
		<p><emph rend="underline">high birth rate</emph></p>
		<p>ignorance</p>
		<p>slums</p>
		<p>???</p>
		<p>maternal mortality</p>
		<p>deaths from abortions</p>
		<p>delinquency</p>
		<p>dependancy</p>
		<p>child labor</p>
		<p>unemployable</p>
		<p>social problems</p>
		<p>15% of our population intellectual</p>
		<p>85%= 45% subnormal</p>
		<p>m3ntally 15% feebleminded</p>
		<p>juvenile 25% mediocre</p>
		<p>under 14 years</p>
		<p>Is <place reg="United States">America</place> safe for Democracy?</p>
		<p>Difference between a Statesman &amp; Politician ??? of the next generation-- Politician
			the next Election</p>
		<p>4/ By that definition how many Statesmen can we claim to have in our present relief &amp;
			unemployment chaos?</p>
		<p>Let us rid our mind that the vast extent of unemployment is only <add>a</add> transient
			or temporary condition.</p>
		<p>The recent announcement by the <org>National Emergency Council</org> that the number of unemployed
			in December was 10,000,000 while another announcement by the <org reg="Federal Reserve">Federal Reserve Board</org>
			stated that industrial production rose to 90% of the 1923-25 average. In other words: we
			are almost back to what is considered normal production. Well what good is it to boast
			of industrial recovery when there continues to be a vast army of millions who remain
			unemployed. It is obvious that the problem which confronts this nation is much more
			complicated than <emph rend="underline">turning out our</emph> set of politicians or
				<emph rend="underline">bringing</emph> in another!!</p>
		<p>5/ One Of the present difficulties in this nation is the stubborness of men in power who
			refuse to face facts. One of the most pertinent facts of modern life is that the growth,
			increase &amp; development of mechanical applicances in production is a significant
			factor in the present problems of unemployment.</p>
		<p>There has been for the past decade &amp; will continue to be less need for manual or
			human labor power in the production of the necessities of life. What is to become of
			these millions whose labor is not needed? What is to become of the millions of their
			children, many of whom are born of parents who have neither the physical nor mental
			equipment to support themsleves or their children.</p>
		<p>The birth rate among the unemployed is increasing 48% higher than in the families of the
			employed. From reports of the <org reg="Federal Emergency Relief Administration">Fed Relief Administration</org></p>
		<p>6/ There are <gap reason="faulty-reproduction" extent="three to four words"/> relief
			&amp; that those families having 6 or more children were having the largest proportion
			of hardships that goes with unemployment distress.</p>
		<p>And that those officials in charge of relief are directly &amp; indirectly responsible by
			encouraging an increase of the birth rate in these families. They refuse to direct them
			to birth control clinics &amp; offer ??? by the way of quicker relief if the woman can
			report a condition of pregnancy!!</p>
		<p>Slogan: "Your Children are <emph rend="underline">Starving</emph>? <emph rend="underline"
				>Produce</emph> more Children!!"</p>
		<p>Organized labor: unemployment continues</p>
		<p>Produce more unemployables</p>
		<p>Suggestion-- Open the doors of the insane asylums and let the inmates take the reins on
			government!!</p>
		<p>Everyone knows that we are piling up huge debts for future generations to pay. It is
			quite ??? too that future generations ??? <place>Europe</place>-- will <emph rend="underline"
				>refuse</emph> to pay them. But while financial or monetary debts may be easily
			cancelled-- but there</p>
		<p>7/ are other debts that will not be so easy to wipe out-- I refer to the debt of
				<add>our</add> inferior quality of life that we are passing down to them. It will
			not be easy to destroy the population of morons &amp; defectives we are handing down for
			our children's children to manage.</p>
		<p>What are we doing with them today. What is to become of their increasing numbers? What
			nation will take the morons, imbecils &amp; defectives off the hands of another nation?
			They are not wanted even for war. No nation ??? them and even the Roman Catholic
			Hierarchy who clamor for their increase (in refusing to allow for their decrease) has
			not provided for the care &amp; upkeep of its own defective population. These and many
			more have already become ??? liabilities upon the normal &amp; intelligent population.
			Get the stream from the source. ??? on unchecked population may not be pressing upon the
			means of subsistence as Malthus, a hundred years ago, declared it could &amp; might do.
			But our population is certainly presing upon our Relief Funds which is the means of
			subsistence to nearly 11,000,000 unemployed. </p>
		<p>Population is pressing upon our Relief funds: upon the other ??? job: upon our Social
			Structure: upon our <add>natural</add> individuality: upon our natural independence:
			population is pressing its demands for a permanent dole: for age old pensions: for
			higher state and federal taxes: population is pressing upon every cultural &amp;
			Educational advantage our social structure has created the existence of which is
			threatened by the increasing hordes fearful of hunger &amp; want.</p>
		<p>If twenty years ago the Bc movement had had the support of organized labor &amp; those
			religions &amp; social agencies whose mission it is to eradicate our ??? miseries &amp;
			help solve our social problems. It is safe to say we would have had a slower growth of
			population: a balancing of our differential birth rate: a lessening of the defective
			&amp; unfit proportion of our population: through sterilization and contraception.</p>
		<p>The creation of a Population Bureau in State &amp; Federal Departments to classify
				<add>diagnose</add> analyze &amp; survey our human resources:</p>
		<p>We would have followed through a policy adopted by the Fed govt on emmigration &amp;
			adapted it to our birth rate.</p>
		<p>Read <name type="law" reg="Immigration Act of 1924">Act 1924</name> Immigration</p>
		<p>??? Japan &amp; Italy</p>
		<p>I agree with Shaw</p>
		<p>Read two letters</p>
		<p>7 reasons for Bc</p>
		<p>3 methods</p>
		<p>Federal &amp; State laws</p>
		<p><add>3 means</add></p>
		<p>Dis. Hospitals &amp; Clinics</p>
		<p>Children to be conceived in love</p>
		<p>Born</p>
		<p>Given heritage of sound bodies &amp; minds</p>
		<p>Value of bodies holy temples</p>
		<p>Sir <add>Arthur</add> Keith Anthropology</p>
		<p>Unfolding in America</p>

		<p/>
	</docBody>
</doc>
