<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Autograph draft article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2012-04-25 AW Initial Tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-08 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="0000-00-00">N.d.</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Early History of Birth Control in England and the
                    United States</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236446</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S73:0067</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>This document was most likely written sometime during the end of the 1930's, when Sanger
            set out to amend Section 211 of the United States criminal code.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="history of"/>
        <index level1="child spacing"/>
        <index level1="Comstock, Anthony"/>
        <index level1="family size" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="infant"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="maternal"/>
        <index level1="poverty" level2="family size and"/>
        <index level1="United States Congress"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <p>It is interesting to recall the Early history of the bc Movement &amp; to see the
            relation the Movement in both <place>England</place> &amp; <place reg="United States"
                >U.S.</place> have had to each other all along.</p>
        <p>The <person reg="Besant, Annie">Besant</person> &amp; <person reg="Bradlaugh, Charles"
                >Bradlaugh</person> trial centered around the little pamphlet Dr. <person
                reg="Knowlton, Charles">Charles Knowlton</person> had written forty years before
            that trial.</p>
        <p>It contained all the then known methods of contraception (there has not been much
            improvement since in that knowledge) &amp; was a very big step forward in the practical
            means of controlling the size of the family as advocated by <person
                reg="Malthus, Thomas Robert">Malthus</person> nearly fifty years before Knowlton
            wrote the <title type="book">Fruits of Philosophy</title>. </p>
        <p>Just about the time <place>Great Britain</place> was discussing the pros &amp; cons of
            the Besant and Bradlaugh case. </p>
        <p><org>The Purity Society</org> was there organizing itself for the <add>avowed</add>
            purpose of rescuing children from the influence of sex literature. <person
                reg="Comstock, Anthony">Anthony Comstock</person> was the principle spokesman for
            the Society &amp; he made his comments &amp; laws on the plea that children were being
            contaminated by the flood of <add>obscene</add> literature coming to this country from
                <place>England</place> &amp; <place>France</place>. It was a most telling plea--a
            most noble purpose to stop it at all costs.</p>
        <p>Consequently when Comstock went to <org reg="United States Congress">Congress</org> to
            present his bill on obscenity, it was rushed through on the last day amid great hurry
            &amp; confusion. There it has remained unchallenged to the present time.</p>
        <p>It is said that the following year a petition sent to Congress containing 60,000
            signatures requested its repeal--but nothing ever came of that. Since that law was
            passed in 1876 over <emph rend="underline">one million</emph> mothers have passed out
                <add>of life</add> from causes due to pregnancy, while 15 million children under one
            year of age have been sacrificed <add>of life</add> thru poverty &amp; neglect.</p>
        <p>Parents who could bring up two or three healthy children, educate them &amp; make them
            decent citizens in the community are forced (through lack of knowledge of contraception)
            to bring to birth eight, nine, or ten children.</p>
        <p>It is from these we have infant mortality, child labor, delinquent &amp; juvenile
            problems for the courts, slums, ignorance, unemployment &amp; the various other
            disturbing conditions of our modern life which costs the lively sum of twelve billions
            of dollars a year &amp; we're still going strong!</p>
        <p>Is there any wonder we have so great a differential birth rate?</p>
        <p>How can the intelligent, conscientious &amp; responsible parents in the country do more
            than maintain themselves &amp; their limited family of 1 or 2 children in decency, where
            the burdens of the unfit, the reckless &amp; prolific fall heavily upon their backs.</p>
        <p> The birth rate of the intelligent conscientious educated classes of Society will adjust
            itself when the birth rate of the diseased (physically &amp; mentally) is cut down--when
            mothers have a chance to space their children consistently with health &amp; earning
            power.</p>
        <p>You can do two definite things to help Senators &amp; Representatives woo &amp; <unclear
                resp="MSPP">win</unclear> these finance us--</p>
        <p>Help us to amend <title type="law">Sec 211</title>--by two letters. Write to your
            Congressmen--Senator &amp; your representative, tell him simply what you believe--He’s
            impressed by the force &amp; power of the women’s movement but he believes <emph
                rend="underline">what men say</emph>.</p>
        <p>Sir <person reg="Keith, Arthur">Arthur Keith</person>, England’s distinct anthropologist
            says of America it’s the greatest experiment in race building the world has ever seen
            spiritual unfoldment--instruments of create</p>
        <gap reason="missing" extent="page(s)"/>
    </docBody>
</doc>
