<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Autograph draft speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014/12/05 SC encode</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-12-19 CH proof tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-22 CH enter tag corrections</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1924/01/10">10 Jan 1924</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Speech to the Second Meeting of the American Birth Control
					League notes</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp236407</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
			<bibl>
				<title type="mf">Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Smith College Collections</title>
				S70:1060 </bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="TWAMAR">Twain, Mark</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>Sanger likely used these speech notes when she made the opening address at the Second
			Annual Meeting of the <org>American Birth Control League</org>, held in <place
				reg="New York, NY">New York</place>. Other speakers included <person
				reg="Ackermann, Frances B.">Frances B. Ackermann</person>, <person
				reg="Kennedy, Anne">Anne Kennedy</person>, and <person reg="Porritt, Annie Goodrich"
				>Annie Goodrich Porritt</person></p>
		<index level1="American Birth Control League"/>
		<index level1="birth control movement" level2="history of"/> 
	</headNote>
	<docBody>

		<p>I wonder how many of you here tonight realize just how much <unclear resp="MSPP"
				>significant</unclear> this gathering is <del>means</del>. How many of you realize
			that this meetingof intelligent representative citize4ns brought together by an interest
			in birth <del>means</del>
			<add>control</add> represent the year of struggle and effort. Ten years! </p>
		<p> Ten years of battling against ignorance and prejudice. A ten year fight for the right to
			get people to talk and to think about the greatest problems that confront the human
			race.</p>
		<p>For there are few subjects which leave so large a practical segregation and at the same
			time cut so deeply into the foundation of social evolution as birth control There are
			few other questions of Equal obscurity and yet none perhaps which can show so unequalled
			a leap in our Social Vista as birth control has done in so brief a period of time </p>
		<p>The fundamental reason for such interest are two. That civilization is confronted with
			two serious problems. 1 That of the pressure of population upon the food supply. 2 That
			of reconsidering Humanitarian with race improvement. </p>
		<p>Many of us realize that birth control is the key to their birth.</p>
		<p>Mark Twain said: "<q who="TWAMA">everybody talks about the weather but no one ever seems
				to do anything about it</q>"-</p>
		<p>Well- The american B.C League is doing something about these problems.</p>
		<p>We believe that words, theories, sentiment, sympathy are all very well in but we have got
			to have intelligent thinking put into intelligent action.</p>
		<p>If the programs for birth control is to grow, to expand, if it is even to hold the ground
			it has gained through untold sacrifice and seemingly hopeless effort, we must have
			cooperation courageous cooperation of individual and organizations who accept the truth
			of birth control but do nothing about it. We need more English Courage in <place
				reg="United States">America</place>. </p>
		<p>We need the build of intellectual courage such as <person reg="Inge, William Ralph">Dean
				Inge</person>, <person reg="Shaw, Bernard">Bernard Shaw</person>, <person
				reg="Keynes, John Maynard">John Maynard Keynes</person>, <person
				reg="Dawson, Bertand">Lord Dawson</person> the Kings physician, leave a private
			conviction publically expressed. </p>
		<p>These men have the courage to express their private convictions, publically.</p>
		<p>Nor have they lost in the estimation of the British public by doing so-</p>
		<p>The ABCL is calling for the cooperation of the medical <supplied resp="MSPP"
				>professionals</supplied> for scientific research, for investigative and unbiased
			study.</p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
