<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/05/24 CE</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-26 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1936-03-29">29 Mar 1936</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Birth Control International Centres Tour in India 1935-1936</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236495</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">The Senator</title>, Mar. 29, 1936, pp. 4-7.</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S71:0829</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="MEGJO">Megaw, Sir Jonn</name>
            <name id="RUSAL">Russell, Colonel Alexander J.H.</name>
            <name id="AIMC">All India Medical Conference</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
        <index level1="Asia" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to" level3="in remote places"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="birth control movement in"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues" level3="in India"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="efforts to reduce"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="infant"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="maternal"/>
        <index level1="population" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="speaking tours" level3="1935-1936 (India)"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Birth Control International Centres Tour in India 1935-1936</head>
        <byline>By Mrs. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></byline>
        <dateline>March 29, 1936.</dateline>
        <div type="section">
            <p>After ten weeks in <place>India</place>
                <place>Ceylon</place>, <place>Burma</place> and <place>Malaya</place> we are now
                speeding on our way to <place>China</place>.</p>
            <p>In the short interval of leisure on this China-bound ship, I want to give the friends
                who have helped with the tour in India a brief account of the outstanding events of
                the ten crowded weeks <person reg="How-Martyn, Edith">Mrs. How-Martyn</person>,
                    <person reg="Phillips, Anna Jane">Miss. Phillips</person>, and I spent in India
                and my visit to Malaya and Burma.</p>
            <p>There was little time to record for our friends at home our impressions as we
                traveled through India. There was so much to do. We wanted to devote every hour to
                the tasks most vital to the birth control movement.</p>
            <p>Every where there was an eagerness to hear about birth control. All the dubious and
                dismal prognostications as to religious objections of Hindus and Mohammedans have
                proven false in my experience. As in other countries the opposition came from the
                Roman Catholics and in India this weak opposition was expressed by foreign born
                priests and a few Eurasians.</p>
            <p>The masses in India as in other countries desire means to limit the size of the
                family. The problem there as elsewhere is how to supply the demand and to direct the
                practical application of birth control into the classes where it is most urgently
                needed.</p>
            <p>I entirely agree with <person reg="Megaw, Jonn">Sir Jonn Megaw</person>’s recent
                suggestion that a plan is wanted for India and that “<q who="MEGJO">contrary to the
                    usual belief, educated Indians were willing and even eager to consider any means
                    of dealing with the evil of over-population; the chief prejudice was encountered
                    among Europeans who wrongly imagined that Indians were antagonistic to any
                    suggestions to reform their ancient customs</q>.”</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">FACTS AND FIGURES</head>
            <p>The Indian Census report of 1931 showed an increase of 34 million people in 10 years.
                    <person reg="Russell, Alexander J. H.">Colonel Russell</person>, the Commissioner
                for Public Health in India, states in his last report for the year 1933 that since
                1931 there has been an increase of nearly 20 millions and that the total population
                of India is not less than 370 million people.</p>
            <p>\“<q who="RUSAL">There seems little doubt</q>” he says, “<q who="RUSAL">that by 1941
                    when the next census is taken, the population of India will considerably exceed
                    400 millions and later adds that the problem of numbers in India “a question of
                    which will shortly force itself upon the attention of every man and woman in
                    this country, it is to be hoped that it will receive adequate notice before
                    disaster befalls</q>.”</p>
            <p>\“<q who="RUSAL">Each year in India 1 and 3/4 million babies die below one year of
                    age and half the children born are dead before 5 years of age. The high maternal
                    death rate costs the lives of 2,000,000 girls and women every year</q>.</p>
            <p>These facts are in no way minimized by the increasing efforts in the form of infant
                welfare work which scarcely touch the fringe of the problem. Indeed by saving infant
                lives the problems of older children are greatly increased especially where there is
                already insufficient food and where the earning power of the parents is inadequate
                to provide for those already born and desperately struggling for existence. Such
                societies and organizations, eager to save infants from early death, must prepare
                themselves to carry those infants through the ages of childhood and possibly on to
                the age where they can be self supporting. Birth control instruction to these
                mothers would be a godsend. Its application to this class of defendants would
                establish in the country a basis for sound social and humanitarian works, producing
                good results almost immediately. Without birth control instruction these well
                meaning but, planless efforts become not only dysgenic but chaotic. This class of
                defendants is likely to become financially insupportable and unmanageable unless the
                intention is to steer a straight course for a Communistic society.</p>
            <p>While it is difficult, even impossible, at this stage of the tour to gauge accurately
                the results of the work, I can say from the letters, interviews, questions and
                favourable publicity as well as from the large number of invitations to speak, that
                Indian public opinion is favorable to the acceptance of the idea of contraception
                and eager and anxious to learn of reliable methods. Future action will depend upon
                medical and official direction and the availability of supplies.</p>
            <p>Much work is necessary, especially in the towns and villages, and should go hand in
                hand with maternal and infant welfare activities.</p>
            <p>To give a diary summary of the tour would be too lengthy. Some idea of the work
                accomplished can be gained from the following bare facts:</p>
            <p>Miss Phillips and I traveled over 10,000 miles, including 21 nights spent on spacious
                but jumpy railway trains. Three weeks out of the 10 weks were spent in actual travel
                on trains. I visited 18 cities and towns and addressed 64 meetings. Besides these
                formal meetings I had conferences with scores of government and city officials,
                mayors, governors, magistrates -- scientists, health directors, heads of hospitals
                and other public and private institutions, and with dozens of men and women who are
                leaders of public opinion in India, including <person reg="Nehru, Jaharwalal"
                    >Jaharwalal Nehru</person>, <person reg="Gandhi, Mohandas K.">Mahatma
                    Gandhi</person>, <person reg="Tagore, Rabindranath">Rabindranath
                Tagore</person>, Mrs. <person reg="Naidu, Sarojini">Sarojini Naidu</person>, the
                <person reg="Gaekwad, Sayajirao">Maharaja</person> and <person
                    reg="Gaekwad, Chimnabai">Maharani</person> of Baroda, the <person
                    reg="Visvesvarayya, Mokshagundam">Dewan of Mysore</person> and the <person
                    reg="Bai, Sethu Lakshmi">Maharani of Travancore</person>. Miss Phillips and I
                were state guests in four cities.</p>
            <p>Mrs. How-Martyn travelled about 6,500 miles, speant 12 nights on railroad trains and
                occupied 12 days out of her time in India travelling. She visited 16 cities, towns
                and villages and addressed 41 meetings. The total number of our meetings was 105 and
                included 32 with medical organizations. At each of the medical meetings addressed I
                showed the biological films prepared in <place reg="New York, NY">New
                    York</place>. They aroused much interest among the doctors and raised the
                subject from the field of propaganda into the realm of science.</p>
            <p>While Mrs. How-Martyn and I met in <place reg="Bombay, India">Bombay</place> and
                again in <place reg="Madras, India">Madras</place> and <place reg="Rangoon, Burma"
                    >Rangoon</place>, we did not travel a single mile together in India so that the
                total mileage covered was 16,500 miles. There was no overlapping of duplication of
                efforts. While Mrs. How-Martyn and <person reg="Palmer, Eileen">Mrs. Palmer</person>
                went to various cities together, Miss
                    Phillips and I went elsewhere.</p>
            <p>While there were many more requests for us to address medical and social groups in
                various places we feel that we have covered the most important and influential parts
                of India by our work.</p>
            <p>Village work must be taken up by those who can speak the vernacular. Our meetings
                necessarily had to be directed to an English speaking public.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">PRESENT ACTIVITIES IN INDIA</head>
            <p>While there is yet no national organization working solely for birth control some
                provincial and local groups are building up the nucleus for a national movement.</p>
            <p>First and foremost is the work done by <person reg="Pillay, A. P.">Dr. A.P.
                    Pillay</person> in Bombay in starting his <org>Eugenic Clinic</org>, in founding
                the <org>Journal of Marriage Hygiene</org> and following that up by organising the
                new <org>Society for the Study and Promotion of Family Hygiene</org> which came into
                being on December, 1, 1935. This centre in Bonbay is the outstanding place where
                information on birth control can be obtained in India. The magazine, although
                prohibited from entering the <place>United States</place>, is considered the finest
                on the subject at present in circulation in the world. It goes to all other
                countries and is building up a fine circulation wherever it is known. Financial
                assistance is urgently needed and unless it comes soon it will be difficult for Dr.
                Pillay to keep afloat on his own resources which he has generously used to launch
                his magazine.</p>
            <p>The <org>Madras Neo-Malthusian League</org>, founded by Sir <person
                    reg="Ramesan, Vepa">Vepa Ramesam</person> in 1928, carries on educational birth
                control work in Madras where there is bitter Roman Catholic opposition. This League
                has on its board many distinguished personalities including two Maharajas a high
                court judge, an editor the principal of the <org>National Academy</org> in <place
                    reg="Triplicane, India">Triplicane</place>, and several prominent attorneys.</p>
            <p>A 16 page magazine is issued and it is possible that this League will form the
                nucleus of a large network of centres covering the South of India. Already contacts
                have been made through interest our meetings have aroused and Sir Vepa, a retired
                Judge of no small vision, has immediately availed himself of every opportunity to
                tie up this new interest with the organized group for future activity.</p>
            <p>At <place reg="Calicut, India">Calicut</place>, on the southwest coast, the local
                organization is known as the <org>Birth Control Information Centre</org>, with
                    Dr.<person reg="Sundaram, Manjeri"> Manjeri Sundaram</person> as its medical
                director. This centre has fine future possibilities. It has real interest and
                enthusiasm behind it. It serves not only as an educational centre for the general
                public but with the establishment of a clinic will become a valuable asset to the
                Indian movement.</p>
            <p>Besides these major centres, <place reg="Calcutta, India">Calcutta</place>, <place
                    reg="Poona, India">Poona</place>, <place reg="Mysore City, India">Mysore
                    City</place> and <place reg="Bangalore, India">Bangalore</place> have clinics
                which are working along, perhaps with not the same rapididty, but with great promise
                of future development.</p>
            <p>During my tour I left fifty gynaeplaques, along with supplies, in places where
                information will be given out. Each of these centres, I am promised will form a
                centre for the dissemination of birth control information.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">CONFERENCES AND MEETINGS</head>
            <p>Since many national conferences are held about the time of Christmas and New Year, we
                could attend only the most important. Naturally the most important was the <org
                    reg="All India Women's Conference">All India Women’s Conference</org> at <place
                    reg="Trivandrum, India"> Trivandrun</place>, <place reg="Travancore, India"
                    >Travancore</place>, to which I had been invited as a speaker. Following my
                address and a general discussion of the subject, the conference passed a resolution
                in favor of establishing birth control clinics by a vote of 24 to 85 over bitter
                Roman Catholic opposition. All but one of the women who opposed the resolution were
                unmarried and the majority were western-born.</p>
            <p>We were both invited to attend the first <org>All India Obstetric and Gynacological
                    Congress</org>, opened in Madras by His Excellency <person
                    reg="Erskine, John Francis Ashley">Lord Erskine</person> and presided over by
                Dr. <person reg="Scudder, Ida">Ida Scudder</person>. I gave an address and showed
                the biological film at an open session of the Congress.</p>
            <p>At the <org>All India Medical Conference</org>, where Mrs. How-Martyn spoke, the
                following resolution was passed with no dissentions. “<q who="AIMC">This Conference
                    recommends that instruction in Conception Control Methods should form part of
                    the curriculum in Medical Colleges and Schools</q>.” Mrs. How-Martyn also spoke
                at the annual meeting of the <org>Tinnevelly Medical Association</org> where there
                was general agreement that contraception technique should be included in the medical
                curriculum.</p>
            <p>Both of us were invited to address the <org reg="Bombay Municipal Corporation">Bombay
                    Corporation</org> on “What Municipalities in the West have been doing to promote
                Birth Control.” The Mayor, Mr. <person reg="Nariman, Khurshed Framji">K. F.
                    Nariman</person>, was in the chair. About three weeks later the Corporation,
                after a heated debate, on the motion of Mr. <person reg="Masani, Minocher Rustam">M.
                    R. Masani</person>, carried by a majority of one vote a resolution to refer to a
                committee the question of given instruction in methods of birth control in municipal
                hospitals.</p>
            <p>I was invited and accepted the invitation to preside over the first <org>All India
                    Population Conference</org>, held at <place reg="Lucknow, India"
                >Lucknow</place>. However, when the date of the conference was changed owing to the
                    <person reg="George V (England)">King</person>’s death, it was impossible for
                me to go. In my message to the conference I urged that its members apply modern
                methods of science to the greatest problem facing India -- population, its growth,
                quality and distribution.</p>
            <p>What may almost be termed nation-wide meetings were achieved when I broadcast from
                Bombay and <place reg="Hyderabad, India">Hyderabad</place> Interest in the two
                lecture was shown by the many letters received which expressed appreciation of the
                broadcast.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">PRESS</head>
            <p>Special mention should be made of the Press. Never at any time have I seen more space
                in newspapers and magazines devoted to a discussion of birth control than during the
                past two months in India. In interviews, reports of speeches and special articles
                the public has been given a clear idea of what birth control stands for and what
                birth control can do for India.</p>
            <p>The <org>Bombay Chronicle</org> offered a prize for the best essay on birth control.
                The response was far beyond expectations and hundreds of essays poured in. The prize
                winning ones were published in full.</p>
            <p>Grateful acknowledgments are made to those good friends who contributed toward the
                success of this tour. Special thanks are due to: Mr. <person
                    reg="Kaufman, Alvin Ratz">Kaufman</person> of <place>Canada</place>, whose
                generous donation toward the expenses made it possible for both Mrs. How-Martyn and
                Mrs. Palmer to go to India: to Mrs. <person
                    reg="Elmhirst, Dorothy Payne Whitney Straight">Elmhirst</person>; to Mrs.
                    <person reg="Rublee, Juliet Barrett">J. B. Rublee</person>; to Mrs. <person
                    reg="Bass, Edith Harland Bird">Robert P. Bass</person> whose contribution made
                possible the purchase of the medical films and of medical supplies; and also to an
                    <person reg="Unknown">anonymous American contributor</person> who supplied
                the 50 gynaeplaques for India and the same number for China. Without
                these films and supplies and necessary funds to pay the cost of customs duties,
                shipping, postal and other incidental charges we could never have accomplished as
                much work as we did in the limited time.</p>
            <p>But I want to give a final message of thanks to the members of the All India Women’s
                Conference whose invitation to address them brought me to India where my vision has
                been given a new understanding of the problems confronting India and the Orient.</p>
            <p>I have attended many meetings of women in my lifetime but I am sure that the
                conferences in Trivandrum will remain an outstanding inspiration in my life. I feel
                that this group of women has a great future before it in guiding the policy of a
                newly awakened nation and that its influence, direct and indirect, is greater than
                is generally realized. I found among these women an outspoken directness of opinion,
                a native fearlessness in facing issues as they are, and most important, the will and
                courage to face the consequences when principles are at stake.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">MALAYA</head>
            <p>The welcome to Malaya at <place reg="Penang, Malaya">Penang</place> was a most
                enthusiastic one. We had no previous contacts on the island and few in all Malaya so
                that this was entirely new territory. Miss Phillips went on a few days before I did.
                Consequently I was immediately greeted by the <person reg="Brodie, W. Hugh"
                    >director</person> of <org reg="Penang Municipal Health Work">Municipal Health
                    Work</org> who had arranged a meeting with the Penang branch of the <org
                    reg="British Medical Society, Penang Branch">British Medical Society</org>. We
                had been warned that interest in meetings in Penang was slight so that I, as well as
                the health director, were surprised when every prominent physician on the island,
                Chinese as well as British, attended the meeting. The film was shown.</p>
            <p>The <person reg="Evans, Leonard Wynne">chief medical officer</person> of Penang then
                arranged another meeting for the following day with the nurses of the <org
                    reg="Penang General Hospital">General Hospital</org> and of the <org
                    reg="Penang Maternity Hospital">Maternity Hospital</org>. Again I showed the
                film and gave a practical demonstration. The <person reg="Unknown">Lady Medical
                    Officer</person> of the Island then invited me to visit one of the largest
                Maternal Welfare Centres. there I gave a talk and demonstration which was
                interpreted into Chinese Malayan and Tamil. That night I gave a radio address and
                the following day spoke before the <org>Penang Rotary Club</org> at a luncheon
                meeting.</p>
            <p>There were also many interviews with individual doctors and nurses, all of whom,
                although interested in the birth control movement, had never before had any contact
                with it. Press notices were also good, and columns, even after my departure, were
                devoted to a discussion of the subject.</p>
            <p>In a hurried morning in <place>Singapore</place> I had two lectures one for the
                medical association, the other at the <org
                    reg="Malaysian Young Men's Christian Association">Young Women’s Christian
                    Association</org>. There were so many invitations to visit cities and towns in
                Malaya that I considered staying there for another week but a wire from <place>Hong
                    Kong</place> told me that arrangements had been made for my reception there and
                I had to continue my journey according to schedule. What has been done in India is a
                drop in the bucket and any programme for the spread of international birth control
                should consider a five year plan of annual follow-up for India.</p>
            <p>With sincere regard to all our friends and thanks for their helpfulness,
                encouragement and hospitality.</p>
            <p>Most Cordially</p>
            <p>(signed) Margaret Sangar.</p>
            <p>By kind courtsey of</p>
            <p>Mr. <person reg="Sharma, P. S.">P. S. Sharma</person> B.A.B.L. Advocate</p>
            <p>Editor <title type="journal">Birth Control Bulletin</title>.</p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
