<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Autograph draft speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2002-08-12 KH encode</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2009-07-22 LL advanced endocde</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2009-07-22 CH proof tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2009-07-27 LL enter corrections</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-02-09 CH doc file list;re-enter doc.</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1929-11-12">12 Nov 1929</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Middle Western States Confernece on Birth Control
					Address Notes</supplied></titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp236566</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</bibl>
			<bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S71:183</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name/>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>This is a draft outline for Sanger's address to the <org>Middle Western States Conference
				on Birth Control</org>, sponsored by the <org>National Committee for Federal
				Legislation on Birth Control</org> and held in Columbus, OH. The audience was
			expected to be composed of doctors, scientists, and lawyers.</p>
		<index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Federal"/>
		<index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Postal Codes"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<dateline><place reg="Columbus, OH">Columbus</place></dateline>
		<div type="section">
			<p> We are here today to discuss plans to effect the Amendment of a <name
					reg="United States Penal Code, Section 211">Federal law--Sec. 211</name>, passed
				by <org reg="United States Congress">Congress</org>
				<add><person reg="Comstock, Anthony">Comstock</person></add> just 56 years ago.</p>
			<p>This law prohibits the sending thru the U.S. Mail of books, pamphlets, articles,
				records, charts, medical, scientific or data of any kind relative to <add>the</add>
				prevention of conception.</p>
			<p> There is no exception to the law, no exception to scientific or educational or
				medical literature no exception to Physicians or <add>to</add> any group whose
				usefulness to society might be advanced by such information.></p>
			<p> It is said that the bill has rushed thru Congress on the last day of its session
				[amid] great confusion &amp; hurry--few congressmen knew the significance of the
				bill they had voted on.</p>
			<p> 66,000 signatures were sent to Congress in protest of the bill immediately after but
				nothing came of it &amp; the citizens of this country have had to put up with
				bootleg information to limit the size of the family or resign themselves to the
				inheritable. <add>Here we began the first steps to effect the differential birth
					rate. </add> It is estimated that since the passage of this law over
					<add>1,</add>150,000 mothers have died in <place reg="United States"
					>U.S.A.</place> from causes due to pregnancy &amp; 15 million infants under one
				year of age have passed out of this life 90% of them due to poverty &amp;
				neglect.</p>
			<p> From 1876 to 1914 there was no concentrated effort on the part of any group to
				arouse public sentiment to change the law. It was a long period of arrests &amp;
				shameful persecutions on the part of the <org
					reg="New York Society for the Suppression of Vice">Comstock Society</org>.</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub"><add>(<emph rend="underline">Dead Hand of the Past</emph>)</add></head>
			<p> When I came upon the horizon in 1914 I had seen such misery &amp; unhappiness among
				the overburdened mothers of the poor during my nursing work in <place
					reg="New York, NY">NYC</place> that I was convinced that our heavy toll of
				mothers lives--our maternal mortality could be lessened if sick &amp; ailing &amp;
				poverty burdened mothers, Tb &amp; heart &amp; kidney could be protected from child
				bearing. </p>
			<p> I was convinced that our infant <supplied resp="MSPP">mortality</supplied> could be
				greatly reduced if our mothers were protected to space out babies-- <org
					reg="United States Children's Bureau">Children’s Bureau</org> of <place
					reg="Washington, DC">Wash DC</place>
				<add>Where there is one</add> interval of 3 years between births of babies there is
				a better chance of living than where only 1 year It also shows us that <supplied
					resp="MSPP">Deaths</supplied> of 2nd children less 100 per m<lb/>7<lb/>over 350
				“ ” “ ” 12 “ ” 600 per m. 60% of 12 <supplied resp="MSPP">children</supplied>
				die.</p>
			<p> I felt that the legislation &amp; pallative efforts to lessen infant mortality were
				not enough, child labor laws were not enough. Child labor laws were not enough. If
				we are to make the world safe for childhood safe for future generations, safe for
				civilization then we must stop at its source the unending stream of death doomed
				infants thru birth control.</p>
			<p> Background in 1914--<add>face of federal law↓ against me.</add></p>
			<p>Free Speech &amp; free press.</p>
			<p><place reg="Netherlands">Holland</place>--Clinics--USA 25, 1929</p>
			<p>7 conditions where BC. should be practiced.</p>
			<p>Federal law impedes progress.</p>
			<p>Fed Committee. 4 Regions.</p>
			<p>Congressmen to be convinced.</p>
			<p>1000 women to bring happiness to 120 million.</p>
			<p>Sir <person reg="Keith, Arthur">Arthur Keith</person>. <place>England</place>s
				anthropologist </p>
		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
