<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Autograph draft speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2013/12/11 JK encoded</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-09-10 CH clean up</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-29 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1931-11-07">
			<supplied resp="MSPP">07 Nov 1931</supplied>
		</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">The Arithmatics of the Problem of Population</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp236575</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</bibl>
			<bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Smith College Collections</title> S71:236</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name/>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>Sanger drafted these notes in <place reg="Houston, TX">Houston</place>, likely for her
			Nov. 7 appearance there. For another version of this speech, see <xref from="236598.xml"
				>"The Problem of Population" Nov. 1932 </xref></p>
		<index level1="New York City" level2="sex education in"/>
		<index level1="overpopulation" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="population control" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="population growth"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<p>The arithmetics of the problem of Population has too long been ignored. The almost
			universal custom of assuming in all discussions of population problems that the birth
			rate by itself is the indication of the increase or decrease of the population one reads
			editorials &amp; articles &amp; hears lectures make this error over &amp; over again
			that the decline of the birth rate means a decrease in population.</p>
		<p> It must come from our <gap extent="one word" reason="illegible"/> school day dislike of
			arithmetics. You would not make the same mistake if you <add><unclear resp="MSPP"
					>in</unclear></add> were calculating your income from investments found that a
			decline in the rate of interest had been accompanied by more than an equivalent in the
			increase in the amount of capital. Every one depending on income knows that it depends
			not only on the rate of the dividend, but also upon the amount of capital on which the
			dividend is paid.</p>
		<p> So the same arithmetics &amp; consideration must be applied to population statistics.
			For the growth of population depends not only on births, but on the excess of births
			over deaths. And the important point to remember is that a birth rate by itself can not
			possibly give any indication of the rapidity with which a population is growing unless
			we know the volume to which the rate is applied. </p>
		<p>An excellent illustration of this fact may be given from the figures representing the
			growth in the population of <place reg="New York, NY">N.Y.City</place> During the first
			20 years of the 19 Century N.Y.C. nearly doubled its population. The rate of <add>actual
				increase</add> increase being 92% or 73,000. In the first 20 years of the present
			century with a lowered rate of 63% the actual increase was 2,183,000. </p>
		<p>To deplore the falling birth rate without knowing the volume to which the rate is applied
			is like a man boasting of his riches because he gets 50% interest--on what his whole
			capital being $100. While another man complains of his poverty because <del>his</del> he
			can only get a dividend of 5% on a capital of 50,000 or a million. </p>
		<p>The meat of the above in a nutshell is: Where the population is increasing the <emph
				rend="underline">rate of increase tends to decline</emph>. In USA <del>from</del>
			<add>in</add> 1800 the rate of increase was 36%. In 1920 it fell to 15% while the actual
			numbers increased from <del>5,308</del>
			<add>2,400,000</add> to <del>105,711</del>
			<add>13,740,000</add>.</p>
		<p> There is no need to argue that our population problem is complicated by the immigration
			from other countries. We accept that point, but the case in point &amp; the law applies
			equally to other countries like <place>England</place> &amp; <place>France</place> where
			the growth of population is due entirely to her natural increase.</p>
		<p> No country can continue to stand a doubling of its population every 50 years as ours has
			done in the past. Take the case of a babys growth. When born it weighs 7 lbs normally it
			doubles its weight in the first 5 or 6 months But should it continue to double its
			weight every succeeding 5 months By the time it was five years old it would weigh nearly
			13 tons. Ten months later it would weigh nearly 50 tons! The same law of growth applied
			to the child governs the growth of every <gap extent="rest of document" reason="missing"
			/></p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
