<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2004/02/23 ML</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2009/07/14 LL</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2009/07/21 CH corrected docType</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-10 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1930-10-28">Oct. 28, 1930</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Huxley Luncheon Address</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236528</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</title>
                S71:0215</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p> Sanger organized a luncheon in honor of <person reg="Huxley, Julian">Julian
                Huxley</person>, sponsered by the <org>National Committee on Federal Legislation for
                Birth Control</org>, in <place reg="New York, NY">New York City</place>--other
            speakers were <person reg="Reiland, Karl">Karl Reiland</person> and Julian Huxley.</p>
        <index level1="conferences" level2="World Population Conference" level3="1927"/>
        <index level1="Huxley, Julian"/>
        <index level1="Huxley Family"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head/>
        <dateline>
            <date value="YYYY-MM-DD "/>
            <place/>
        </dateline>


        <p>I wonder if all of you here today realize just how proud <del>all of us</del> should feel
            that Julian Huxley is with us and cooperating with our Birth Control movement. The very
            name of Huxley means freedom and courage and fighting for unpopular causes. It is the
            very trademark of free-thinking and liberty of action. Julian Huxley's grandfather
                <person reg="Huxley, Thomas Henry" rend="underline">Thomas Henry Huxley</person>,
            was the <gap reason="deleted" extent="four characters"/> founder of our liberated
            outlook today. I well remember how generously Mr. Huxley helped me in the organization
            of the <org reg="World Population Conference, 1st">World Population Conference</org> in
                <place reg="Geneva, Switzerland">Geneva</place>. He gave unstintedly his advice and
            his time. Day after day he attended council meetings, and contributed to the conference
            that touch of personal interest that lifted it out of the purely academic and technical
            field into once of vital personal interest. Without the tireless interest of Julian
            Huxley it could not have achieved so marked a success.</p>
        <p>At the risk of being unpleasantly personal, but in the hope that this may save Mr.<gap
                reason="deleted" extent="three to four characters"/> Huxley <add>from</add>certain
            annoying questions. I shall seek to answer the queries that may be formulating in some
            of your heads. <title type="book">Who's Who</title> tells me that Julian Sorell Huxley
            is the grandson of the immortal <person reg="Husley, Thomas Henry">Thomas Henry
                Huxley</person>, the pioneer of free thinking and free speech in the nineteenth
            century; the son of <person reg="Huxley, Leonard">Leonard Huxley</person>, and <person
                reg="Arnold, Julia Francis">Julia Francis Arnold</person>, who was I think the
            sister of Mrs. <person reg="Ward, Mary Agusta
">Humphry Ward</person>. He is also the
            elder brother of <person reg="Huxley, Aldous">Aldous Huxley</person>, who is the most
            brilliant and penetrating novelist of the younger generation in <place>England</place>.
            Somewhere in Mr. Huxley's pedigree looms the important figure of <person
                reg="Arnold, Matthew">Matthew Arnold</person>. So you see that he brings to the
            Birth Control movement the most distinguished intellectual background England can boast.
            I forgot to mention that Julian Huxley is the collaborator with <person
                reg="Wells, H. G.">H. G. Wells</person> and his son <person
                reg="Wells, George Phillip">George</person> in that fascinating book of popular
            science now being published under the title of "<title type="book">The Science of
                Life</title>." In his late twenties, I have been informed, he taught biology in the
                <org>Rice Institute</org> in <place reg="Houston, TX">Houston Texas</place>, so he
            knows our country and our problems.</p>
        <p>Mr. Huxley's generous cooperation, far more valuable to B.C. than a vast amount of money,
            reminds me that English scientists of the best type are courageous and generous enough
            to lend their prestige and support to all liberating though unpopular causes. Until
            lately, American men of science have tended to lean backwards in their conservativism. I
            welcoming Julian Huxley let us hope that his example may serve as an inspiration to
            American thinkers and scholars who have held themselves aloof-- on their high horses--
            from our pressing social and sexual problems.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
