<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011-08-03 NC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2001/11/14 CH enter corrections</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-26 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1952-10-00">Oct 1952</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Birth Control Research on the March</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236511</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S72:0713</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="LAT">Latin</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>For a draft version see <title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title>
            S72:0707.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="pill"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="herbal"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head><add>Birth Control Research on the March</add></head>
        <byline>by <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></byline>
        <dateline><date value="1952-10-00"><add>Oct--1952</add></date></dateline>
        <p>All workers interested in the study of human fertility and its control will be encouraged
            to know that at last there are research possibilities that a simple, cheap, harmless,
            effective contraceptive will soon be obtainable for the masses of all countries.</p>
        <p>The following two recent studies have been publicized–one in the <place>United
                States</place> and one in <place>London, England</place>. Both of these experiments
            are, by no means, completed but I give them here to encourage those workers in the field
            of Birth Control and <org reg="Planned Parenthood Federation of America">Planned
                Parenthood</org> with the hope that within the not too distant future, both the tea
            from the weed and the pill will be available. Then the lovers and workers for World
            Peace and Happiness may look to a future where children will be born and cared for
            because the parents want them and can provide for them, who will become citizens of
            their country and the New World. </p>
        <div>
            <head type="sub" rend="underline">RESEARCH TODAY</head>
            <p>Recently a popular American magazine <title type="journal">LOOK</title> had an
                article written by <person reg="White, William H.">William H. White</person>, a
                staff writer, which electrified and amazed its readers. The article’s title was
                    “<title type="article">Birth Control by a Pill</title>,” which states there
                would soon be available a contraceptive to be taken by mouth–a pill which is simple,
                low cast and harmless.</p>
            <p>This so-called Pill is the result of intensive research in this field of biochemists.
                There are several chemicals known to the biochemist which have been tried on animals
                in their food and proved to be successful in preventing conception. Many of these
                have been used by men and women and results have reached the stage where research
                papers and reports are being prepared for publication in Scientific Journals.</p>
            <p>The requirements of the perfect “Pill” must undergo careful and painstaking scrutiny
                from various scientists in biology, biochemistry, as well as physical and
                psychiatric experts.</p>
            <p>The first requirement is that it must be absolutely proven to be harmless to the
                person who uses it and will not cause disease or bodily harm with repeated use.</p>
            <p>Second, it must control fertility, not limit or sterilize (a real Birth Control). Its
                effect must be temporary and entirely used at the discretion of the couple.</p>
            <p>Third, it must not impair potency or the ability to perform the sexual act.</p>
            <p>Fourth, it must be inexpensive so as to be used in all families for those in crowded
                tenements or slums, as well as for those whose intelligence is too retarded to use
                successfully the present methods of contraception (the diaphragm and jelly
                method).</p>
            <p>With the discovery of this chemical contraceptive Pill, sexual activity can be
                separated effectively from Reproduction; consequently, having children will be by
                choice and not by accident. A child will be wanted and born in love and
                consideration by the parents. A voluntary and deliberate act.</p>
            <p>The intricate details of this scientific study are too numerous to evaluate by any
                but the scientific student with years of experience behind him. There have been
                studies of experiments of immunization from pregnancy in <place reg="Soviet Union"
                    >Russia</place> in 1935 called Spermatoxin. A report stated that 20,000 women
                had been inoculated by male sperm and had been immune from pregnancy for two
                years.</p>
            <p>I went to Russia to study this experiment in 1936, but found the study had been
                discontinued for the Policy of an increasing birth rate. The formula given to me by
                two of the scientists who had worked in the Clinic was tried out on animals in the
                laboratory of one of our large universities (<org reg="University of Pennsylvania"
                    >Pennsylvania University</org> in <place reg="Philadelphia, PA"
                    >Philadelphia</place>) with no positive results. Nevertheless, these recently
                discussed chemicals are said to do the same thing–immunize temporarily the woman
                against conception. </p>
            <p>There are many agents including vitamins, hormones, Enzymes, and Special Chemicals
                with power to control fertility. But, Research has only begun but it is On The March
                and a pool of scientific knowledge and experience will chart a course of further
                study. It is these valuable Research advances which make it necessary for Free
                Nations to prepare its people to make proper use of such knowledge when it becomes
                available for public needs.</p>
            <p>It is, therefore, I suggest that the leaders in <place>Japan</place> who work
                coincides with these studies take council with leaders in other countries. Pool your
                experiences with ours. Set up Research and teaching centers–join the <org
                    reg="International Planned Parenthood Federation">World Planned Parenthood
                    Organization</org> which we hope will emerge from the <org
                    reg="International Conference on Birth Control, 3rd">Conference</org> in
                    <place>Bombay, India</place> to be held there November 24th to December 2nd. The
                world has been waiting for the Birth Control Pill. Now let us prepare our course to
                receive and use it for the benefit of the family, the Nation and the World.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub" rend="underline">RESEARCH DISCOVERIES IN 1952</head>
            <p><emph rend="underline">LONDON</emph> – A recent report from London from Professor
                    <person reg="Gudkin, John">John Gudkin</person>, <org>London University</org>
                Physiologist, has found a new liquid type of contraceptive taken as a tea–tastes
                like sherry wine and renders women sterile for several days but does not effect
                their general health nor prevent their future child-bearing capacity.</p>
            <p>The tea is made from a weed called Gromwell, a cousin of the forget-me-not flower so
                common in English gardens and to all garden lovers. Its official name is (<foreign
                    lang="LAT">lithosphermun officinale</foreign>). Dr. Gudkin began experiments
                with this weed three years ago with mice. The experiment was 100% perfect.</p>
            <p>With Dr. Gudkin was Dr. <person reg="Wiesner, Berthold P.">B. P. Wiesner</person>, a
                specialist in human fertility. Also helping are other experts–one Dr. <person
                    reg="Gilmore, John">John Gilmore</person>, Director of the Botanical Gardens of
                    <org>Cambridge University</org>. These experts are now encouraging people to
                grow Gromwell in their gardens and women are experimenting under their direction.
                The discovery came from a study of the <org>Shoshone Indian tribe</org> in
                    <place>Nevada</place>, U.S.A. This tribe practiced Birth Control with one
                variety of the weed most successfully. These experts plan to have a large scale
                human experiment next spring to adjust the dosage, also to prepare its potency for
                male and female fertility.</p>
            <p>These men believe that people should have children when they want them and to be
                helped to prevent those they do not want and to be made fertile for those children
                they desire to have.</p>
            <p>They also state that this weed might be the simple means of controlling World
                Population and lead eventually to World Peace. </p>
        </div>


    </docBody>
</doc>
