<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed draft article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2009/07/29 LL</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-10 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1931-11-14">14 Nov. 1931</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>The Need for Birth Control in America</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236598</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Birth Control: Facts and Responsibilities</title>, ed. <person
                    reg="Meyer, Adolf">Adolf Meyer</person>, M.D. (<place reg="Baltimore, MD    "
                    >Baltimore</place>: <org>Williams and Wilkins Co.</org>, 1925), 11-49</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S71:0321</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="SWIAL">Swinburne, Algernon Charles</name>
            <name id="FRYJA">Fry, James</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="population" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="population growth" level2="regulation of"/>
        <index level1="population growth" level2="natural resources and"/>
        <index level1="population growth" level2="quality of life and"/>
        <index level1="birth rate"/>
        <index level1="death rate"/>
        <index level1="working classes" level2="revolution and"/>
        <index level1="working classes" level2="living conditions of"/>
        <index level1="eugenics" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="England" level2="birth rate in"/>
        <index level1="feeble-minded persons" level2="fertility and birth rate of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <p> The problem of population should be considered from the point of view of its influence
            on the well-being of mankind.</p>
        <p>It is a problem from which man cannot escape. It affects the health and happiness of
            every adult man and woman and consequently individual families; it affects the
            prosperity and social progress of Nations, it affects the peace of the world.</p>
        <p>Every gardener knows that if seeds are sown too thickly, the resulting plants will be
            poor in quality.</p>
        <p>Every breeder knows that if healthy stock is to be had matings must be spaced.</p>
        <p>So with the production of human beings, unless successive births are adequately spaced
            and the total number in each family restricted to the available means of maintenance
            there will necessarily be a low standard of health and happiness, both for parents and
            offspring.</p>
        <p>These consequences can<del>not</del>
            <add>no longer</add> be evaded by substituting the benevolence of the State for the
            responsibility of the parent; <del>for</del>
            <add>it has been is</add> the provision of <add>social &amp;</add> welfare agencies to
                <del>women and children</del>
            <add>which</add> allows and encourages the multiplication of dependents on the State,
            thereby taxing the healthy and self sustaining members with the result that the
            self-supporting, productive, independent, creative groups relatively decline.</p>
        <p>Under no system of Society is it possible to allow the population of a country to expand
            more rapidly than the means of subsistence without the resultant affects of poverty,
            misery, disease and other unhappy conditions where low standards exist. In new countries
            an increasing population can often provide for itself an increased volume of
            subsistence, for men have brains and hands as well as mouths to feed. By hard labor, by
            application of scientific methods of production by fertilization and irrigation,
            maintenance has been increased ten fold (as in <place>Japan</place>,
                <place>France</place> and <place>Italy</place>). But ultimately the capacity of man
            to produce maintenance for himself depends on the plentifulness or the quantity of the
            materials that the earth supplies.</p>
        <p>When these begin to grow scarce in any country, the inhabitants must seek new territories
            or new markets. [Elaborate written in margin] Thus begins the phenomena of immigration
            as well as that of colonial expansion. National rivalries for markets and land resulting
            in militarism and wars.</p>
        <p>It is a common practice of assuming that the birth-rate by itself indicates the increase
            or decrease of a population. The assumption is so common that it might almost be
            described as universal. Certainly the majority of people in reading an official report
            of a declining birth-rate immediately conclude that the population of that country in
            declining--(This shows our dislike of arithmetic). Any business man calculating his
            income from investments would never think it was declining if a reduction in the rate of
            interest was accompanied by an equivalent increase in his capital. Every shareholder
            knows that his income depends not <emph rend="underline">only</emph> on the <emph
                rend="underline">rate</emph> of the dividend but also on the <emph rend="underline"
                >amount</emph> of capital on which the dividend is paid.</p>
        <p>Exactly the same arithmetic applies to population. The birthrate in itself does not
            control the population growth. It does not indicate the rapidity of growth unless we
            know the volume to which the rate is applied. A good illustration may be given from the
            figures representing the growth of population of <place reg="New York, NY">New York
                City</place>--which during the first twenty years of the 19th century nearly doubled
            its population, the actual rate of increase being very high 92%. In the first twenty
            years of the present century the rate of increase was 63% (still very high). These are
            the rates but what of the increase? The enormous rate of 92% gave an actual increase of
            73,000. The reduced rate of 63% in an equal period of time gave an increase of 2, 183,
            000. In other words you cannot argue from the rates alone without knowing to what volume
            the rates of percentage are applied. 50% is a high rate of interest--alone, but 50% on
            $100, 000 =50,000<lb/> [$100,000*50=50,000.00]<lb/> [While 5% on
            1,000,000*.05=50,000.00]</p>
        <p>In other words, where a population is increasing the rate of increase tends to
            decline--and should decline. No creature grows as rapidly as it did during the first
            months after its birth. 7 pounds a baby increases its weight a half pound a day for the
            first few weeks of its life--then a quarter of a pound--and finally a few ounces--until
            its full growth is attained. Had it kept its first increase on a half pound a day--it
            would have weighed 910 on its fifth birthday. <lb/>[365/2=182 1/2] <lb/>[182*5=910]</p>
        <p>A similar illustration can be taken from plant life--such as the tulip or daffodil--which
            first bursts from the ground and doubles its height visibly within a few days when it
            ceases to grow but blooms, flowers--serves its purpose before it declines. These
            illustrations are given to show that it is impossible for any growing thing to continue
            indefinitely to grow at a constant rate. As the volume expands, the rate of growth must
            decline. This principle applies to every growing thing. Everything has its natural
            volume of growth when it serves its usefulness.</p>
        <p>The population of <place reg="United States">U.S.A</place>. during the first 50 years of
            the 19th century increased four fold. Had this increase continued and been maintained we
            would now have had a population approximately equal to that spread over the entire
            globe.</p>
        <p><place>England</place>--a country which balances her population by sending out more
            settlers than she receives--yet she has doubled her population in the first fifty years
            of the 19th century. It doubled again in the sixty years ending with 1911.--while her
            birth-rate was 10.9 lower than it had been for a century. People began to express alarm
            at the decline in birth-rate!!</p>
        <p>There are two facts to remember in the question of population.</p>
        <p>1st.--The arithmetical possibilities of indefinite multiplication of species, plants,
            tribes of nations.</p>
        <p>2nd.--The physical obstacles to that multiplication namely--area and resources of the
            globe.</p>
        <p>While there is an automatic check by nature on the growth of a plant, a tulip or a
            child--there is no such natural check in the case of the multiplication of plants or
            tribes. Given suitable soil, one plant could scatter its seed over the face of the
            earth--the limiting factors are other plants crowding and interfering with each others
            means of subsistence, and the limitation of the size of the globe.</p>
        <p>The same principle applies to people. A normal couple can produce ten or twelve children
            while each child can raise a family of similar size--and that family again can multiply
            its numbers. While the first couple lives it can witness the astounding number of nearly
            two hundred birth originating from its own loins.</p>
        <p>There is no limit to the power of human beings to multiply themselves indefinitely if
            they could find room to live--and means to live by, but that is the rub. Every race is
            sooner or later brought up against the fact that the means of subsistence does not
            multiply as rapidly as its population and is not sufficient for unlimited numbers. It
            may invade the territories of other tribes, or improve the cultivation of its own soil
            or exchange the products of its work people for the food produced by workers in other
            countries.</p>
        <p>But sooner or later the final limitations of space will clash with the arithmetical
            possibilities of multiplication and the rate of expansion will have to decline. How can
            this be accomplished? Two ways only--decreasing the number of births--or increasing the
            number of deaths.</p>
        <p>This alternative applies to every living thing. It can be observed that the lower types
            breed fast and die soon--the higher types breed slowly and live long. The codfish lays
            millions of eggs--the majority of which never mature--the elephant breeds slowly and
            lives longer than any other animal. Among the different races of human beings there is a
            similar contrast.</p>
        <p>These races which maintain a high birth-rate (resulting from religions compulsions or
            animal carelessness) are subject to a correspondingly high deathrate.</p>
        <p>The death rate of infants is especially high in such countries as <place>India</place>
            and <place>China</place> where the birth-rate is enormous.</p>
        <p>In China where the population presses intensely upon the means of subsistence--whenever
            there is a serious crop failure--the consequences are terrific--millions of people are
            swept away in famines. In China 1/4 of the children born die before their first year.
            The high birth-rates and high death rates of both India and China are both due to the
            same cause--early marriage and ignorance or failure to control births.</p>
        <p>If you compare the figures of Indian birth and death rates with those of England and
                <place>Wales</place> for the years from 1910 to 1921 you will see the difference in
            the high survival rates in the latter. If the birth and death rates of India could be
            brought down to the English rates, there would be an increase of births over deaths, but
            also three or four million useless births and three or four million useless deaths would
            have been avoided.</p>
        <p>Such wastage of human life must diminish the general vigor of the country and the effort
            that might have been devoted to rearing healthy children is spent in giving birth to
            children who die within a few months and in burying or burning the bodies of tens of
            thousands of child mothers killed by pregnancy or by parturition.</p>
        <p>Summary of arithmetic of the problem: <lb/>1.--Rate of growth living things must decline.
            <lb/>2.--Nature’s laws in plants control growth of size. <lb/>3.--Populations growth
            depends upon reducing birth rates or increasing death rates. <lb/>4.--A reduction of
            these requires forethought, consideration, responsibility, regulation of conduct
            accordingly.</p>
        <p>ECONOMICS “<q who="SWIAL">Glory to man in the highest, for man is the master of
                things.</q>” <person reg="Swinburne, Algernon Charles">Swinburne</person> “<title
                type="book">Industrialized not Civilized</title>”</p>
        <p>Man differs from animals in his ability to increase his own food supply--animals can eat
            only the food they find on the soil or the weaker animals they can catch, but man tills
            the ground, plants seeds and provides food for himself or for the animals he proposes to
            eat.</p>
        <p>He also makes the ground more fertile, improvises tools and machinery to increase food
            production and develops shipping and transportation so that valuable products can be
            sent to and from group to group.</p>
        <p>Primitive man’s energies are devoted to the pursuit of food. Industrialized man is able
            to give his time and mind to other things: building homes, design and manufacture
            clothing, painting, music, singing, constructing roads, bridges, railways, steamships.
            He conquers the air and the sea. He develops his mastery over matter, sends his voices
            by wire and now by air--hundreds of miles away.</p>
        <p>Still there are limitations to his power--for he cannot escape from the fact that he is a
            product of the earth and all that he eats, wears and uses comes from the earth which,
            after all, is limited in size and its resources exhaustible.</p>
        <p>The prospect of exhaustion may seem remote to some people and they point to the vast
            areas of unpeopled land in <place>Australia</place>, <place>Canada</place> and <place
                reg="Argentina">Argentine</place> and to the still unexplored resources of mineral
            wealth in many parts of the world and claim that there is room for the indefinite
            expansion of the human race. This claim cannot be seriously maintained. However great
            the natural resources are, it is certain that they are <emph rend="underline"
                >limited</emph>.</p>
        <p>That man should live is not sufficient; it is important that he should live well--that we
            shall reason upon the purpose of life and protest against dogmas, ignorance,
            superstition and fear. These are the forces which have enslaved the human race. Man asks
            more of the earth than merely to be kept alive. He wants land to play upon and to enjoy
            its beauties.</p>
        <div type="section">
            <head>
                <emph rend="underline">Workers Conditions</emph>
            </head>
            <p>We rightly look upon the nineteenth century as a period of humanitarianism. Such
                conditions existed during the second half of the eighteenth century owing to the
                dislocation of social life caused by the development of industrial invention that
                humanitarianism was urgently needed.</p>
            <p>The old-fashioned, simple, rough but fairly wholesome rural industry under the
                domestic roof was destroyed. Machinery in towns brought the workers to it. They
                huddled together under conditions which had not been made for them, and while they
                prospered and multiplied for a time, their prosperity was not civilization.</p>
            <p>Until the first half of the nineteenth century scarcely any public money was spent on
                sanitation.</p>
            <p>The laboring population of <place>Great Britain</place> lived in almost unspeakable
                filth and disease. Small rural districts were--because of industrial expansion--made
                urban over night. The workers were huddled into huts, summer-houses and sheds never
                intended as dwellings. <add>never erected for shelter</add> In sections with thirty
                to forty miles of streets and hundreds of miles of byways--yet only a few miles were
                sewered. Dustbins were unknown, slops and refuse were thrown from the windows into
                the streets and all sorts of refuse accumulated in mountain-high, foul-smelling
                heaps. The task of scavenging Bethel Green with its 133 miles of houses was left to
                    “<q who="UNK">13 decrepid old men.</q>” It took ninety days or three months to
                go the rounds of a single parish! Disease and epidemics flourished.</p>
            <p>In all parts of England, Wales, <place>Scotland</place> and <place>Ireland</place>
                similar conditions prevailed.</p>
            <p>People living under these conditions seemed indifferent to them; they were reckless,
                intemperate, improvident; eating dainties one day and little or nothing the next;
                multiplying as rapidly as nature allowed and leaving to death and disease the task
                of preventing any excessive rise in the population.</p>
            <p>So we find that while the birth rate was rising, the death rate was rising too. While
                the race remained vigorous owing to the struggle of the fit against the
                unfit--nevertheless, it was conceded that the people were not physically the equals
                of the generation of thirty years earlier. There was general deterioration among
                certain classes, especially the weavers; still their numbers grew.</p>
            <p>Though the English people suffered severely from death and disease, their numbers
                increased more rapidly from 1911 to 1821 than at any other time. The English workmen
                were noted throughout Europe for their “savage industry”, for the conditions of old
                English rural life had built up a powerful stock which could not be destroyed by
                migration to towns or by the revolution in industrialism. The population increased
                two-fold, but criminality increased five-fold--not only in towns but in
                    <add>the</add> country as well. The workmen on the farm was no longer a
                companion of his employer--domiciled with his family and an equal in the community.
                He was now a “laborer”--a citizen rather than a domestic, but a citizen without
                friends, ignorant, intemperate and improvident.</p>
            <p>The nineteenth century--however--began the task of cleansing and improving the
                conditions of life under which lived the creators of the new industrial age.</p>
            <p>The streets were being paved; the filth cleared away; sewers were being built; the
                police system was being reformed; pure water and general lighting was given and
                sanitary conditions of dwellings received attention. The need was so obvious that
                reform in these matters could meet with little opposition.</p>
            <p>The next move was concerned with the conditions under which the laboring classes
                worked--or what was termed factory legislation. This began in a small and feeble way
                in the middle of the nineteenth century. The enriched middle classes felt no strong
                impulse to take an active interest in this regard. They saw that ignorance and
                degradation of the unorganized workers were working together for middle class
                supremacy. The workers must be left free--they claimed, even though that freedom
                meant to work themselves sick or freedom to starve to death. It was not the
                employing classes who influenced legislation, but the aristocracy who supported it
                and brought about considerable changes. But the greatest reforms governing the
                conditions of the workers--of women and children as well as of men--were brought
                about by the workers themselves through their unions and organizations. The era of
                factory legislation is still emphasizing its demands with very little opposition,
                but also with a full realization that improvement of the conditions of life is not
                enough.</p>
            <p>The improvement of the conditions of living, added to the improvement of the
                conditions of working--had to be reinforced by an effort to improve the conditions
                under which the workers are born and bred.</p>
            <p>This effort began about fifty years ago in England through the nationalization of
                education, but during the past ten years a far greater extension has been made and a
                certain provision for the child’s needs--medical attention and
                supervision--attention to cleanliness, dental work, proper meals were necessary, and
                general inspection into the causes of children’s problems, protecting the children
                too young to work and regarding the care and oversight of infants even back to the
                moment of birth. Finally an effort was and is still being made to provide conditions
                of <add>a</add> healthy life for the child, even before birth.</p>
            <p>We must remember that this movement for the improvement of environment is still in
                active progress among us.</p>
            <p>It is not ancient; it is modern history and is likely to spread as to impose upon the
                medical profession the duty of preventing disease and the preservation of
                health.</p>
            <p>The movement was exclusively concerned with the conditions of life, but not with the
                improvement of the quality of human life at all.</p>
            <p>To better the conditions under which life is lived, to take care of the soil, letting
                the seed take care of itself was the attitude of social reformers. We know today
                that both the soil and the seed do matter. The finest seeds may be starved, the more
                easily, often the finer it is--and every ill-adapted external condition is a kind of
                starvation. We should not relax our interest in safeguarding the conditions of life,
                but also we should recognize some of the penalties imposed upon civilization when
                our aims are exclusively bent on this task.</p>
            <p>In improving conditions, we pile heavy burdens upon ourselves. we make the task of
                life easier for the unfit as well as for the fit--to pass their inheritance on to
                future generations. The unfit are made able to compete with the fit at a heavy cost
                to the latter. These would doubtless have succumbed to their environment had nature
                had her way.</p>
            <p>We cannot raise the level of civilization by improving external conditions alone. The
                fact of experience shows that the results of such efforts have in no degree
                corresponded to the efforts made or expectations of those who initiated them.</p>
            <p>Notwithstanding our assumed moral and material progress and notwithstanding our
                enormous annual expenditure amounting to eight or nine billions a year in
                amelioration, we still have a vast army of persons quartered upon us unable to
                support themselves, showing an increase in numbers rather than a decrease.</p>
            <p>The vast expenditures--25 millions--spent in 1926, providing homes for the insane, is
                already not sufficient and an increasing appropriation will be asked for within the
                next few years.</p>
            <p>The muddled methods of social reform have been most marked in all that concerns the
                beginning of life, for that is where we have been most at fault.</p>
            <p>Shall motherhood be subordinated to “morals” or “morals” to motherhood?</p>
            <p>Why not place the claims of humanity on an independent basis?</p>
            <p>We know that maternal mortality in this country is vastly higher than that in other
                countries less equipped socially and financially to reduce it than we are. Why is
                this so? It cannot be due to lack of expenditure or to lack of costly and elaborate
                machinery. No, it is certainly not.</p>
            <p>It is due to the concentration of activities on the conditions, the environment of
                life, to the neglect of the betterment of life itself.</p>
            <p>It is the renewal of the spirit within that is needed--a real regeneration of
                life.</p>
            <p>It is known from authoritative sources that two feeble-minded persons have not been
                known to bring to birth a normal child. It is also found by <person
                    reg="Tredgold, A. F.">Tredgold</person> that 82% of the feeble-minded are found
                to have had a bad nervous inheritance. In <place reg="Vineland, NJ">Vineland, New
                    Jersey</place>, it was found that a large proportion of feeble-minded cases was
                handed on from three generations. In one family of 319 persons, 119 were known to be
                feeble-minded, 42 known to be normal. The families of the feebleminded are large.
                Some women have eight or nine feeble-minded children by different husbands, not
                counting several other children who died in infancy.</p>
            <p>Feeblemindedness is inherited. The feeble-minded are innately fertile and multiply
                faster than the normal. They have no forethought and no self-restraint. They are no
                capable of resisting their own impulses or the solicitations of others. They are not
                able to understand the motives which guide the conduct of normal people. They have
                no morals--consequently no moral standards to live up to. They cannot resist
                temptation. They have one third more children than the normal family--and sometimes
                more.</p>
            <p>The infant mortality among these children is high. One authority (<person
                    reg="Eichholz, Alfred">Eicholz</person>) states that 60% of the children of
                feeble-minded parents die in infancy.</p>
            <p>The social disorder and heavy expense which accompanies this, etc.</p>
            <p>The feeble-minded women give birth to illegitimate children. They come and go to the
                work houses, state farms and other institutions--leaving their babies where they can
                be cared for and returning shortly to give birth to the next.</p>
            <p>There is a recognized tendency of the abnormal to be attracted to the
                abnormal--feebleminded or mentally defective. This is a perpetual danger to Society
                and an ever increasing depreciation of the quality of the race.</p>
            <p>“<q who="FRYJA">The beneficence of one generation becomes the burden and the injury
                    of all succeeding ones.</q>”</p>
            <p>Vastly more effective than ten million dollars to charity would be one million to
                Birth Control and it would relieve the race of those qualities which today undermine
                our finest inheritance.</p>
            <p>This expenditure would be charity in the highest sense. It would be charity according
                to knowledge, charity applied to the right spot, and not allowed to run to waste or
                worse--to turn to poison.</p>
            <p>Feeblemindedness, prostitution, criminality are associated closely. One investigator
                claims that only four or five percent of the parents of criminals were sound, and
                from 50% to 90% of the criminals come from bad stock.</p>
            <p>Keen business men of today who so carefully scrutinize the stock markets for secure
                &amp; solid investments that their children &amp; children’s children may enjoy
                their wealth &amp; be protected from want &amp; other social inconveniences. Yet in
                their generosity they give huge sums to charity &amp; to other palliative efforts
                without expecting any investment or demanding that their money earn any equivalent
                interest in human welfare. The very sums given today in charity increases the
                possibility of demanding double that sum within five years for increasing needs of
                charities which without the first sums <add>these needs</add> could not have
                increased. </p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
