<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2009/08/03 LL</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-10 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1932-02-00">Feb 1932</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Legislation: Confused and Tangled</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236599</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
                <title type="journal">Church and Society</title>, Feb 1932, 3-4. </bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S71:0402</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>For other versions see MSP C16:0329; 048:0167B. For earlier drafts of this article see
            MSP S71:0362, 0354.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation"
            level3="Postal Code and Regulations"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="State"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>LEGISLATION: CONFUSED AND TANGLED</head>
        <byline>By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></byline>
        <p>For nearly sixty years, the federal laws on obscenity have held sway over our literature,
            art, science and medicine. These laws control the use of the U.S. Mails and all
            common-carriers including express companies. The Federal obscenity laws class prevention
            of conception and abortion with pornography, filth and indecency. Facts or knowledge
            concerning either of these two medical subjects do not belong there.</p>
        <p>First, let me emphasize that the prevention of conception is <emph rend="italics"
                >not</emph> abortion. It is not classed as indecent in other countries. It is not
            classed as indecent in many of our own states. A study of our state laws reveals
            this.</p>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">
                <emph rend="italics">Federal Laws</emph>
            </head>
            <p>The Federal law, <name type="law" reg="United States Criminal Code, Section 211">Section
                    211</name> of the Penal Code was passed by <org reg="United States Congress"
                    >Congress</org> in 1873 at the end and on the last day and during the last hours
                of a hectic, hurried, confused session of Congress. The instigator of that law,
                    <person reg="Comstock, Anthony">Anthony Comstock</person>, was as ignorant as he
                was fanatical. His idea was that everything relating to sex was obscene.</p>
            <p>The Federal laws make no exceptions in their prohibitions for literature of a
                scientific character. Nor have they made an exception for the physician in his
                regular practice, or for hospitals or clinics, or for patients of these hospitals or
                clinics, or for the general and proper distribution of medical supplies. These laws
                have been the means of suppressing properly authorized scientific literature on the
                subject of contraception because no publisher will jeopardize his freedom or risk
                his reputation in publishing books when there is a law against their
                circulation.</p>
            <p>These laws interfere with the importation of articles and of the results of research
                which is undertaken in other countries. Such data and such results of laboratory
                research would be of great assistance to the medical profession of this country in
                the proper functioning of their profession.</p>
            <p>They make it an offense subject to a penalty of five years in prison and $5,000 find
                for anyone to send through the U.S. Mails even the <emph rend="italics"
                    >address</emph> of a physician, hospital, or birth control clinic stating <emph
                    rend="italics">where</emph> contraceptive information may be obtained--this
                despite the fact that there are already laws in many states enabling physicians to
                give oral advice to patients in their regular practice, and there are in this
                country today over 80 legally operating birth control clinics distributed over 12
                states. These birth control clinics are medically established and medically
                directed, and have been organized solely for the purpose of giving contraceptive
                information by the medical profession.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">
                <emph rend="italics">State Laws</emph>
            </head>
            <p>The laws in the 48 states, while not so arbitrary, are nevertheless confusing, and
                many conflict with the Federal laws.</p>
            <p>1. Twenty-five states have obscenity laws which fortunately have <emph rend="italics"
                    >not</emph> classed prevention of conception with abortion. Here physicians and
                medical centers, hospitals, welfare agencies could legally establish birth control
                clinics and instruct mothers in safe methods of contraception for economic and
                social reasons as well as for health. These states are<lb/>
                <place reg="AL">Alabama</place>, <place reg="AK">Arkansas</place>, <place reg="DE"
                    >Delaware</place>, <place reg="FL">Florida</place>, <place reg="GA"
                    >Georgia</place>, <place reg="IL">Illinois</place>, <place reg="KY"
                    >Kentucky</place>, <place reg="MD">Maryland</place>, <place reg="NE"
                    >Nebraska</place>, <place reg="NH">New Hampshire</place>, <place reg="NM">New
                    Mexico</place>, <place reg="NC">North Carolina</place>, <place reg="ND">North
                    Dakota</place>, <place reg="OK">Oklahoma</place>, <place reg="OR"
                >Oregon</place>, <place reg="RI">Rhode Island</place>, <place reg="SC">South
                    Carolina</place>, <place reg="SD">South Dakota</place>, <place reg="TN"
                    >Tennessee</place>, <place reg="TX">Texas</place>, <place reg="UT">Utah</place>,
                    <place reg="VT">Vermont</place>, <place reg="VA">Virginia</place>, <place
                    reg="WV">West Virginia</place> and <place reg="WI">Wisconsin</place>.</p>
            <p>Many of the other states while including the term prevention of conception in the
                obscenity laws make some exceptions as to medical colleges, medical literature or
                medical practice. These states are<lb/>
                <place reg="CO">Colorado</place>, <place reg="IN">Indiana</place>, <place reg="IA"
                    >Iowa</place>, <place reg="OH">Ohio</place> and <place reg="WY"
                >Wyoming</place>.</p>
            <p>Nevertheless, the Federal law would make it a crime for doctors or anyone else to
                send through the U.S. Mails such books or publications specifically exempt under the
                laws in these five states.</p>
            <p>2. Eight other states prohibit the publishing of any notice or advertisement or
                distribution of information or material to prevent conception. Oral information not
                prohibited. These are<lb/>
                <place reg="AZ">Arizona</place>, <place reg="CA">California</place>, <place reg="ID"
                    >Idaho</place>, <place reg="LA">Louisiana</place>, <place reg="MA"
                    >Massachusetts</place>, <place reg="MT">Montana</place>, <place reg="NV"
                    >Nevada</place> and <place reg="WA">Washington</place>.</p>
            <p>3. Three states allow teaching of contraception in chartered medical colleges and
                publication of medical books, (but they do not mention practitioners of medicine).
                These are<lb/>
                <place reg="KS">Kansas</place>, <place reg="MO">Missouri</place> and <place reg="PA"
                    >Pennsylvania</place>.</p>
            <p>4. <place reg="NY">New York</place> and <place reg="MN">Minnesota</place> allow
                physicians to give information and prescriptions for supplies “<q who="UNK">for the
                    cure and prevention of disease</q>.”</p>
            <p>5. <place reg="NJ">New Jersey</place> grants exemption to physicians who find a “<q
                    who="UNK">just caus</q>e” for advising and instructing patients.</p>
            <p>6. <place reg="ME">Maine</place> and <place reg="MI">Michigan</place> are two states
                prohibiting the publication and distribution of <emph rend="italics"
                    >information</emph> (not material) relating to prevention of conception.</p>
            <p>7. <place reg="MS">Mississippi</place> prohibits the publication of information or
                the giving of oral information relating to prevention of conception.</p>
            <p>8. Lastly and uniquely, the one state of <place reg="CT">Connecticut</place> makes
                itself ridiculous by prohibiting the <emph rend="italics">use</emph> of any article
                which prevents conception.</p>
            <p>Hanging over all these tangled and confused laws is the Federal statue, Section 211
                of the Penal Code, which forbids the use of the mails to the doctors in those
                respective states where they are legally allowed to give advice in public or private
                practice.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, under the present laws, it is a crime for me to send a mother situated
                in any of these states the address of any clinic lawfully operating in that state,
                even though such an individual may be poverty stricken or diseased, and even though
                she may have a right under that state law to have this information for her health
                and for her family happiness.</p>
            <p>Over two generations have passed since the time that law was enacted. Women have
                gained suffrage; colleges and universities now teach scientific, biological facts of
                life to students; social hygiene is part of our educational program; yet, nothing
                has been done by the medical profession, the clergy, women’s clubs, etc., to take a
                dignified stand on cleaning up these archaic laws. <emph rend="italics">It was as a
                    challenge to these laws that the Birth Control movement arose and it is to amend
                    these laws that the <org>National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth
                        Control</org> was organized.</emph></p>
            <p>There is nothing to be gained by keeping on the statute books laws that are known to
                be inimicable to personal health, family happiness and racial development. These
                laws have already done untold harm. It is time that we replaced them by social
                legislation befitting the twentieth century.</p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
