<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed draft article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2012-04-16 AW Initial Tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2012-05-15 CH Proofed Tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2012-05-16 AW Corrected Tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-24 EK clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1923-00-00"><supplied resp="MSPP"
            >1923</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Notes on Eugenics and Birth
                    Control</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236585</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Smith College Collection</title>, S73:0091</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="DRYCH">Drysdale, Charles V.</name>
            <name id="CUROP">Current Opinion</name>
            <name id="MARFR">Marvin, Francis Sydney</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>This untitled draft has paraphrases and uncredited quotes from at
            least three other sources: <person reg="Drysdale, Charles Vickery"
                >Charles Vickery Drysdale</person>, "<title type="article">A
                Guiding Principle for Eugenic Reform</title>," <title
                type="journal" rend="italics">Eugenics Review</title>, July
            1922, 103-114; "<title type="article">Hostility to Birth Control As
                an Expression of Primitive Superstition</title>," <title
                type="journal" rend="italics">Current Opinion</title>, Jan
            1917, 40-41; and <person reg="Marvin, Francis Sydney">Francis Sydney
                Marvin</person>, <title type="book" rend="italics">Progress
                and History</title>, (New York: 1916). No final version has been found.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="and sexuality"/>       
        <index level1="birth control" level2="morality of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="upper classes and"/>
        <index level1="Catholic Church" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="marriage"/>
        <index level1="poverty" level2="family size and"/>
        <index level1="sexuality"/>
        <index level1="race suicide"/>
        
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <p><q who="DRYCH">We must consider the needs and happiness of
                humanity</q> and <q who="DRYCH">until the mass of humanity is
                able to command a reasonable level of comfort, that is a
                sufficiency of the necessaries and comforts of existence</q>,
            the great need is to hold our population at a stand still until we
                <q who="DRYCH">are able to increase the efficiency of the
                productive arts so as to provide this sufficiency</q>.</p>
        <p><q who="DRYCH">Sentimental humanitarianism has constantly interfered
                with natural selection. The “slave morality” which <person
                    reg="Nietzsche, Friedrich">Nietzsche</person> so eloquently
                denounces has been invoked in favor of the preservation and
                propagation of the unfit; poverty, sickness, humility have been
                exalted</q>, first by theology and later by social-democratic
            legislation, a marked contradiction between social convention and
            private conviction. Well-to-do classes practice Birth Control but
            condemn it for the poor. <emph rend="underline">The <org>Roman
                    Catholic Church</org> condemns it as a public practice,
                while the prelates of the Church themselves practice it
                religiously.</emph></p>
        <p>The law makers read the laws and pass sentences upon those who would
            pass information on to poor, desperate mothers to help them--while
            they themselves, boast of one or two children well spaced for the
            convenience of the mother’s health.</p>
        <p>Again there are those who shout out against the practice of Birth
            Control, proclaiming it against the laws of nature, while they
            recommend in its stead the practice of self control, ignoring the
            fact that “self control” or the denial of sex expression in a normal
            adult man and woman is far more of an effort and much more against
            the laws of nature than the use of knowledge of Birth Control can
            be.</p>
        <p>If they themselves happen to have only a small family, the impression
            is given that it is accidental or is attained by abstention from
            sexual relations, but in private conversation the contrary is
            accepted as a mutually understood fact.</p>
        <p>Again those who object to Birth Control on the “race suicide” grounds
            claim the race will die out, that it is dying out and throw out
            abuses upon the heads of those married couples who are trying hard
            to decently keep out of debt, while trying also to bring up their
            family as decent citizens. While the concern of this group of
            persons seems to be that the race shall increase, they dare not
            insist that men and women marry without love, even for the sake of
            the race. Neither do they dare to recommend illegitimate children.
            While the practice of polygamy--one of the surest methods of
            increasing our population, would be abhorrent to them.</p>
        <p>In fact after a little consideration they are willing to compromise
            and agree that the sickly and diseased and poverty stricken should
            not have offspring and the healthy might limit their number, if it
            is done through self control. There are two uses to be made of the
            sex act: generation and regeneration, or reproduction and love.</p>
        <p>So far as the ways of nature can be understood by us, it is both our
            right and our duty, as intelligent beings, to control these for our
            own uses and our own good. This includes both the regulation of the
            number of children and the methods of regulation.</p>
        <p> The means seems to be the object of attack by our opponents.</p>
        <p> No person can, with clear self-consciousness, choose to be born in
            disease, poverty and ignorance for the glory of the State or of God
            or of the species.</p>
        <p>
            <q who="CUROP">No self conscious human being can regard his sexual
                life as a means for the ends of others. For by the very fact of
                his being self conscious, this function, otherwise merely
                physiological, has become deeply personal and intimately his
                own. While for Nature and the animal kingdom the sex relation is
                only a means, for man and woman it is the first and most
                important part of the end. This attitude of men and women toward
                marriage is one the most distinct mark of a higher
                civilization</q>.</p>
        <p> We call it prostitution when one sacrifices personal choice and love
            in the sexual relation, for monetary gain; why should it be less
            prostitution when the end is the propogation of the species.</p>
        <p> Among the personal relations none is more replete with significance
            than the sex relation, and none makes a richer contribution to the
            content of life.</p>
        <p><q who="CUROP">Marriage must be regarded as an end and not merely as
                a means. Marriage should represent a choice unencumbered by
                extraneous obligation (as far as possible) while within the
                limits of health and safety we are justified in employing all
                the resources of knowledge to render marriage fertile or
                infertile as those individuals in question may see fit.</q></p>
        <p><q who="CUROP">The control of natural forces for human ends is now
                generally accepted as a mark of an enlightened humanity.</q></p>
        <p><q who="CUROP">We no longer allow women to suffer child-birth
                agonies without the use of anesthetics--we no longer leave the
                syphilitic to suffer because they have been “immoral”.</q></p>
        <p><q who="CUROP">We have discarded these views and we must also accept
                birth control as a right in itself.</q></p>
        <p><q who="MARFR">To a certain extent, we are each of us in touch with
                myriads of men past and present. We participate in a world
                    <del>love</del>, and by so doing are advanced in the scale
                of spiritual worth and dignity as members of the human race. It
                is not that we must agree in ideals with each other, but the
                quest for an ideal is a necessary factor for the ennobling form
                of experience whereby we become conscious co-workers and
                co-helpers in the age long, world wide striving after the
                good.</q></p>
        <p> Let us make a human experiment for one generation only. This will at
            least give us an intelligent surmise of what can be done through the
            application of Birth Control. We can then discard it or extend it.
        </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
