<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Autograph draft speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2010/03/24 AC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-11 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1934-01-00">Jan 1934</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Birth Control National Economy</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236581</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith
                College</title></bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title>, S73:0024</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="eugenics" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="physicaly disabled and diseased" level2="birth control and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <p>There are some basic truths which should form the corner stone of any <gap
                reason="illegible" extent="one word"/>plan for National Economic Recovery
            Security.</p>
        <p> These are first.</p>
        <p>
            <list>
                <item>A. That the physically unfit usually beget the physically unfit</item>
                <item> B. That the mentally unfit usually beget the mentally unfit</item>
                <item>C. That mental defectives, whether low or high grade usually beget mental
                    defectives That we shall never permanently improve the general standard of life
                    until we greatly lessen the population of physically &amp; mentally unfit to the
                    general population</item>
            </list>
        </p>
        <p>Birth Control is not <add>primarily</add> a movement to help the educated well to do
            parents control the size of the family–They know this already</p>
        <p> It is a movement designed &amp; organized to make available to the poorest &amp; most
            afflicted of our population scientific information to regulate the size of the
            family.</p>
        <p> It is in my estimation the greatest &amp; most important (effective) instrument which
            scientific thought has yet devised for raising the mass population to a higher level of
            life </p>
        <p> I wish that our present sentimentalists would realize that the birth of every defective
            or every potential defective child adds to the weight which lowers the standard of
            living &amp; general intelligence throughout the country</p>
        <p> The stream of children tainted with <add>phys mental</add> diseases still flows
            unchecked. The cost of institutional <gap reason="illegible" extent="one word"/>
            <add>care</add> is already gigantic. All ↑public institui↓ are full &amp; overflowing
            with constant demands for larger quarters &amp; facilities to maintain these
                <add>ever</add> increasing hordes.</p>
        <p> The burden on future generations is already collesal &amp; if it continues <gap
                reason="illegible" extent="one word"/> fair to destroy our civilization for they
            already sap the resources of this present generation.</p>
        <p> What shall we do about it?</p>
        <p>Politicians are influenced in their actions by <del>dogmas</del>
            <add>fears.</add> Psuedo theorists prefer to blame the [word erased]. The capitalists
            the economic system the unequal distribution of wealth rather than face the facts &amp;
            put the blame squarely on those who <add>through their own <gap reason="illegible"
                    extent="one word"/></add> create slums, inefficiency, deterioration.</p>
        <p>The problems created by the rapid &amp; perilous increase of populations. Everyone with
            internal vision knows the truth of this statement. The nation that can not &amp; will
            not control its population has is a danger spot in the world. It should be cut off from
            those nations furthering international peace &amp; international co operation.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
