<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/05/24 CE</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-18 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1942/12/08">8 Dec 1942</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Birth Control, Brittanica Year Book, 1942</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236628</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Smith College</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title>, S72:0368</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>For an earlier draft, see LCM 129:0094; for identical versions, see LCM
            129:098B and 129:101.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues" level3="in Europe"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues" level3="in US"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Connecticut"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Massachusetts"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="legalization of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="medical community and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="efficacy of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="diaphragm"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="sponge"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="international"/>
        <index level1="Catholic Church"/>
        <index level1="England" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Europe" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="family planning"/>
        <index level1="Germany" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Germany" level2="population policies"/>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="population policies"/>
        <index level1="population" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="Southern States"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="government" level3="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="government" level3="public health programs"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="population of"/>
        <index level1="working classes" level2="birth control and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head><emph>BIRTH CONTROL</emph><head type="sub"><emph>BRITTANICA YEAR BOOK,
                1942</emph></head></head>
        <div type="section">
            <p>The <org>Birth Control Federation of America, Inc</org>. by vote of its members at
                the Annual Meeting in January 1942, changed its name to <org>Planned Parenthood
                    Federation of America</org>, Inc., as more indicative of its aims and purposes.
                Work during the year was concentrated on: (1) inclusion of pregnancy spacing in more
                State Health Departments; (2) stimulation of adequate teaching of contraception in
                medical schools and wider distribution to physicians, of a condensed authoritative
                text by <person reg="Dickinson, Robert Latou">Robert L. Dickinson</person>, on
                techniques of conception control; (3) raising funds for research, and (4) continuing
                public education.</p>
            <p><emph><person reg="Pierce, Claude C.">Claude C. Pierce</person>, M.D</emph>. who
                retired as former Director of Region 1 of the <org
                    reg="United States Public Health Service">U.S. Public Health Service</org>,
                became Medical Director fo the Federation, <person reg="Upham, John H. J.">John H.J.
                    Upham</person>, M.D., former President of the <org>American Medical
                    Association</org>, was elected Chairman of the Board, and <person
                    reg="Eastman, Nicholson J.">Nicholson J. Eastman</person>, M.D., head of the
                Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, <org>Johns Hopkins Medical School</org>,
                became Chairman of the <org>National Medical Council on Birth Control</org>.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">Public Health.</head>
            <p>(1)Three more states were assisted in initiation pregnancy spacing in their Health
                Departments, bring the total to six.</p>
            <p><emph>Clinical Service</emph>. On December 1, 1942, there was 782 services in the
                    <place>United States</place>; 216 in hospitals; 256 in public health quarters;
                310 extra mural; and 336 of the total supported in whole or part by public
                funds.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <p>(2) <head type="sub">Medical Education</head>. Copies of a new edition of Dr.
                Dickinson’s <title>Techniques of Conception Control</title>” were sent, on request,
                to 45,000 physicians and medical schools. Returns on a questionnaire sent to 34,000
                of those receiving the pamphlet, showed that the doctors greatest interest was in
                technique. A syllabus for teaching contraception in medical schoold was drawn up, to
                be sent for their consideration to heads of these institutions.</p>
            <p><emph>Medical Endorsements</emph>. The <org><place>Florida</place> State Medical
                    Association</org>, the <org><place>Tennessee</place> State Medical Society</org>
                and the <org><place>West Virginia</place> State Medical Association</org>, all
                passed resolutions approving child-spacing, or Planned Parenthood, as part of public
                health activities and medical practice.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">Research and Investigations.</head>
            <p>(3) The Federation raised funds for research in various aspects of human fertility,
                to be conducted under the guidance of the <org>National Committee on Maternal
                    Health</org>. These studies are long range projects; results will be announced
                at their termination. There is still urgent need for research in simpler effective
                contraceptive methods. Among the <emph>independent clinical studies</emph> on simple
                forms of contraception, were those of <person reg="Stein, Irving R.">Irving R.
                    Stein</person>, et al (a) in <place reg="Chicago, IL">Chicago</place>, <person
                    reg="Beebe, Gilbert W.">Beebe</person> and <person reg="Overton, John"
                    >Overton</person>, (b) in <place reg="Nashville, TN">Nashville</place>, Beebe
                (c) in a rural area in <place>West Virginia</place>, and Beebe and <person
                    reg="Geisler, Murray">Geisler</person> (d) in a rural area of
                    <place>Kentucky</place>. All of these studies showed a varying reduction in
                fertility among the cases advised. <emph>Clinic Reports</emph> show diaphragm and
                jelly the choice of doctors in private practice; in public health clinics foam
                powder and sponge seemed to give adequate protection when regularly used. the
                non-use of a method, occasionally, was the human factor which faced doctors in all
                branches of preventive medicine.</p>
            <p>The <org reg="American Medical Association Council on Chemistry and Pharmacy">Council
                    on Chemistry and Pharmacy</org> of the American Medical Association appointed a
                Committee on contraceptives to study drugs used in this field and to report on
                contraceptive preparations, and the Medical Sub-Committee of the <org>Family
                    Planning Association of <place>Great Britain</place></org> appointed a special
                As-Hoc Committee to conduct a clinical investigation of the efficiency of certain
                chemical contraceptives.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">Public Education.</head>
            <p>(4)A marked increase in magazines and newspaper articles stimulated public interest,
                in planned Parenthood and especially in the question of having babies in wartime.
                    <emph>Negro Program</emph>. A two-year Negro child-spacing demonstration project
                was successfully carried out under the most difficult conditions to provide proof
                that under public health direction the benefits of planned parenthood can reach and
                will receive acceptance by even the poorest and most illiterate groups. Negro
                leaders in the fields of medicine, education and social welfare gave active support
                to a national educational campaign.</p>
            <p><emph>Legal Decisions, U.S</emph>. The <org>Supreme Court of Errors</org>, of
                    <place>Connecticut</place>, by a vote of 3 to 2, on the Tileston case in June,
                ruled that the State law on contraception was constitutional and that under it no
                doctor could advise the use of contraceptives even in cases where the life of a
                patient was threatened by pregnancy. In November, the <org
                    reg="United States Supreme Court">U.S. Supreme Court</org> agreed to accept the
                Tileston case for review. In <place>Massachusetts</place>, all efforts of the
                opposition to keep the question off the ballot having failed, the people voted in a
                referendum as to wehther physicians in that state could legally advice patients on
                contraceptives, when life or health were threatened by pregnancy. The question lost,
                due to ambiguity in its wording on the ballot, and to a campaign of
                misrepresentation, led officially by the <org>Roman Catholic Church</org>, which
                distorted and confused the issue.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">Population</head>
            <p>The countries abroad involved in World War II, as active participants, or under Nazi
                domination, had lowered birth rates in 1942, but the United States, whose marriage
                rate for 1941 was the highest on record, reported that its birth rates, leveled off
                during ten years of depression, had risen to 22.9 per 1000 population in September
                1942, due to war marriages and better economic conditions.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">Foreign</head>
            <p>In Great Britain birth control clinics remained open and an increase in the number of
                patients was reported. Conscription of women for war work led to a demand for
                contraceptive by many who could not carry on in th country’s war effort if they
                became pregnant. <org reg="United Kingdome, Ministry of Health">Medical Officers of
                    Health</org> were reported as cooperating, in many countries by referring cases
                to clinics for advice. Elsewhere in <place>Europe</place> no information filtered
                through, beyond and authentic report from <place>Germany</place> that contraceptives
                were among the few articles still advertised for sale in a number of large cities.
                Germany, <place>Italy</place>, and <place>Japan</place> were all pressing
                frantically for higher birth rates. this policy, accompanied by suppression of birth
                control information did not bring the desired results.</p>
        </div>
        <note>(a) Stein, Irving R. <person>Cohen, Melvin R</person>. and <person>Nielsen,
                Rita</person>. <title type="article">Jelly alone as Contraceptive Method</title>.
                <title type="journal">Human Fertility</title> 7:33-41, April 1942.</note>
        <note>(b) Beebe, Gilbert W. and Overton, John. <title type="article">The Contraceptive
                Service of the Department of Health, City of Nashville</title>. <title
                type="journal">Journal of the American Medical Association</title>. 118:1045-1049,
            March 28, 1942.</note>
        <note>(c) Beebe, G.W. <title type="book">Contraception and Fertility in the Souther
                Appalachian</title>. <place reg="Baltimore, MD">Baltimore</place>, <org>Williams and
                Wilkins</org>, 1942.</note>
        <note>(d) Beebe, G.W. and Geisler, Murray. <title type="article">Control of Contraception in
                a Selected Rural Sample</title> -- <title type="journal">Human Biology</title>
            14:1-20, February 1942.</note>
    </docBody>
</doc>
