<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2010/04/28 AC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-11 CH clean regs and other errors</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1938-11-14">14 Nov 1938</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied>Birth Control, 1938</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236625</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl> Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S71:1044</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp>
                <name id="NRCCPP">National Resources Committee, Committee on Population
                    Problems</name>
            </resp>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="venereal disease"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="government" level3="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="physicians" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="North Carolina" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="New York City" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="India"/>
        <index level1="Germany" level2="birth control in"/><index level1="Europe"
            level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="England" level2="birth rate in"/>
        <index level1="England" level2="population policies"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Comstock act"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="international conferences on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Federal"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="State"/>
        <index level1="birth control"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <div type="section">
            <p>During 1938 there has been a consistent trend in national population policies abroad
                to decry the decreasing birth-rate and to demand larger populations to supply
                manpower for possible future wars. This has led to attempts at stringent repression
                of birth control education and service in the totalitarian states of <emph
                    rend="underline"><place>Germany</place></emph> and <emph rend="underline"
                        ><place>Italy</place></emph>, coupled with marriage grants, lower taxation
                for fathers of large families, and other forms of stimulation towards increased
                reproduction. <place reg="Soviet Union">Russia</place> also is pressing for a higher
                birth-rate, curtailing abortions, but it does not ban birth control or prohibit the
                sale of materials. The <emph><place reg="Scandinavia">Scandinavian
                    countries</place></emph> are studying their population problems, sanely and
                scientifically, without agitation against birth control. In <emph rend="underline"
                        ><place>England</place></emph>, also the <org
                    reg="Population Investigation Commission">Population Commission</org> is
                attempting to discover the social and economic causes for the lowered birth rate
                there but in the Parliamentary Debates on the subject, it was acknowledged that
                birth control was essential as a public health measure and had come to stay. One
                bill was introduced into <org reg="British Parliament">Parliament</org> to limit the
                sale of materials but was defeated. In the <emph rend="underline"><place>United
                        States</place></emph>, the committee on <org
                    reg="National Resources Committee, Committee on Population Problems">Population
                    Problems of the National Resources Committee </org>referring to a possible
                decline in population after 1938, stated: “<q who="NRCCPP">A halt in population
                    increase ... may on the whole, be beneficial rather than injurious to the life
                    of the Nation. It assures a continuance of a favorable ratio of population to
                    natural resources in the United States. this supplies the material basis for a
                    higher level of living.</q>”</p>
            <p><emph rend="underline"><place>India</place></emph> held its <org
                    reg="Confernece on Population and Family Hygiene, 2nd">Second Conference on
                    Population and Family Hygiene</org>, which included birth control and
                sterilization, in <place reg="Bombay, India">Bombay</place> in April, 1938. <org>The
                    All-India Women’s Conference</org> held in <place reg="Nagpur, India"
                    >Nagpur</place> in late December, 1937 passed a resolution urging the
                establishment of birth control clinics under public health direction.</p>
            <p><emph rend="underline"><place>Puerto Rico</place></emph>. The <person
                    reg="Cummings, Homer Stilee">Attorney General of the United States</person> was
                asked to pass on the legality of the laws relative to birth control passed by the
                Island’s Legislature in 1937, and ruled that they were in conflict with the Federal
                Penal Code applying to territorial possessions. No action on the part of the Federal
                District Attorney has as yet been taken, however, and there has been no interruption
                in the service of both governmental and private birth control clinics.</p>
            <p><emph rend="underline">United States</emph>. The extension in birth control clinical
                service has been marked. In October, 1938 there were 412 clinics functioning in the
                U.S., a large number of them supported by public funds and housed in public health
                institutions , hospitals and municipal buildings.</p>
            <p>The trend in legislation has been toward regulation of the sale of contraceptives an
                venereal disease prophylactics by confining their distribution to physicians and to
                licensed druggists.</p>
            <p><org>The American Medical Association</org> at its Annual Meeting in 1938 adopted a
                report which stated that the Association “desired to reiterate the stand taken” (on
                contraception) “by this house in 1937, that the problem is essentially a medical
                one.” the Section on Nervous and Mental Diseases passed resolutions asking for
                amendment of all existing legislation which hampers physicians, where contraceptive
                advice for patients or distribution of medical literature on contraception are
                concerned, and the Section on Obstetrics and Gynecology passed a resolution asking
                for action on recommendations of the committee on Contraceptive Practices passed by
                the A.M.A. in 1937.</p>
            <p><org>The Supreme Court of <place>Massachusetts</place></org> ruled that the State law
                provided no exception for physicians or those acting under their direction, in so
                far as prescribing contraceptives was concerned. this is the first time since
                passage of the so-called "<name type="law"
                    reg="United States Criminal Code, Section 211">Comstock laws</name>” in 1873
                that the highest court of any state has refused to recognize the right of the doctor
                to preserve the health or life of his patients. The <org
                    reg="United States Supreme Court">U.S. Supreme Court</org> in October, 1938
                refused to review the case, indicating that relief lay in amendment of the State
                law. It is announced by the <org>Massachusetts Birth Control League</org> that a
                more clearly defined "test case” will soon be made.</p>
            <p>In <place>North Carolina</place>, birth control service under direction of the
                    <org>State Health</org> Department completed its first year and in a report
                delivered at the <org>American Public Health Association</org> Annual Meeting in
                October 1938, it was stated that requests for this practical service from county
                health departments were greater than could be met. The example of North Carolina has
                encouraged other states to consider the adoption of similar programs.</p>
            <p>Public opinion favorable to the incorporation of birth control in medical practice
                and public health programs continues to express itself through popular polls,
                magazine articles, editorials, resolutions of national groups.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">RESEARCH</head>
            <p>In England, the <org>Birth Control Investigation Committee</org> incorporated with
                the <org>National Birth Control Association</org> has conducted research at
                    <org>Oxford University</org> under <person reg="Baker, John R.">De. John R.
                    Baker</person>, with the aim of developing a cheap, effective and harmless
                contraceptive which it is announced is now ready for distribution. Similar
                experiments in simplified contraceptive methods have been consistently carried on by
                the <org>Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau</org> in <place
                    reg="New York City, NY">New York City</place> through its affiliates in America
                and elsewhere, and statistical studies reveal encouraging progress.</p>
            <p>Research in many other aspects of contraception is being conducted in various
                universities of the United States. The time of evaluation at the <org>University of
                    Denver</org>, and at <org reg="Harvard University">Harvard</org>, spermatoxins
                at the <org>University of Pennsylvania</org>. In addition, the <org>National
                    Committee on Maternal Health</org> has extended its research grants, and has
                stimulated programs in a number of universities bearing on the biological and
                chemical aspects of contraception. The third year of the <org>Journal of
                    Contraception</org> reveals an ever-widening interest on the part of the medical
                profession here and abroad in the biological and clinical aspects of human fertility
                and its control. </p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
