<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Autograph fiction">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/06/10 AS Encoded</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/12/16 EK correct proof</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1912-08-19">19 Aug. 1913</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">The Soul-less Maid</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp143729</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers Library of Congress</bibl>
            <bibl>Library of Congress Microfilm, L130:575</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="love" level2="MS on"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <p>(Aug 19--1913.)</p>
        <p>She entered the florist shop <del>and</del>, looked searchingly about <del>for</del>as if
            to find <del>out the</del> something which she did not expect to find. Then her search
            rested on a vase of large blood red peonies, which she purchased &amp; departed.</p>
        <p>She felt satisfied and gently crushed them to her <add>dress</add>, feeling that in these
            lay her power to win forgiveness from her lover.</p>
        <p>Today she must be beautiful. True she was always beautiful but today she must be dazzling
            in that beauty-–superb magnificent-–and to this <del>purpose</del><add>and</add> she had
            most carefully adorned herself-- She had chosen a soft clinging cream white silk
            gown--showing beneath the faintest outline of two perfectly formed limbs--fluttered
            about in a delicate pink which gave (one) a sensation of a stolen glance at the
            forbidden mysteries of the sex.</p>
        <p>Her golden hair was coiled about her head like a halo--so when the white fur toque was to
            be removed--it would give the expression desired--</p>
        <p>This she knew. All her arts &amp; charms were needed today to win back that love in which
            she had basked like sunshine for the past six months--for she had cruelly hurt him.
            Often had she hurt him before--but a few caresses &amp; smiles brought him to her feet--
            This time however she <emph rend="underline">felt</emph> it was different and the
            woman’s intuition was right--</p>
        <p>She unlatched the door of his room--&amp; found him lying <add>on</add> his back <add>on
                a couch</add> one hand under his head, his black hair carefully parted &amp; brushed
            as if a certain determination had dominated the act. He had heard the click of the latch
            &amp; knew it was she--but he did not turn his head--he closed his eyes as if
            indifferent to her presence.</p>
        <p>She knew she had felt the truth-- Here was a difficult task-- She <add>had</add> relied
            upon her great beauty, but-- -- -- --perhaps it would fail her--she glanced hastily in
            the mirror over the mantle threw off her long coat &amp; placed her hat aside &amp;
            pinned one of the peonies to her bodice-- The others she arranged in a tall white vase
            &amp; stood before them in all the innocence of a vestal virgin pretending to arrange
            them-- <del>Good</del> “<q>I’ve brought you something <person>Juan</person></q>”--she
            said <del>Softly</del>gently. She glanced slyly at him, but he did not move. She saw tho
            the color run red over his face &amp; neck as if her voice had thrilled him to life--
            She knew the power of her <del>charms</del>voice-- She grew encouraged <del>&amp;</del>
            as she thought of it &amp; <add>as</add> spoke again-- “<q>Juan I’ve come to be
                forgiven</q>”-- As he did not move she went to him &amp; knelt on the floor beside
            him-- She took his hand in one of hers &amp; purred a gentle voluptuousness in his
                <unclear>being</unclear>. She smoothed back his hair, an act he ever loved &amp; she
            softly bit his chin, and lobe of his ear. The golden ringlets of her hair swayed across
            his face &amp; whispered memories to him-- Her hand crept close to his body &amp; she
            felt his heart beat ever a determined beat.</p>

        <p>“<q>Juan</q>” she whispered--“<q>look upon me just once again &amp; say I am forgiven
                &amp; I shall go then--</q></p>
        <p>She pressed her face to his--she lay full length beside him &amp; sought his lips--in
            ecstasy &amp; delight--</p>
        <p>He had felt lifeless-- He knew had he trusted himself to open his eyes. His senses would
            leave him all his resolve--for nought--but now that kiss--and what was that--an
            odor--peonies-- He opened his eyes, sat straight upward, &amp; caught her madly in his
            arms--</p>
        <p><name type="Deity">God</name>--how beautiful she was! <del>The peony first covered</del>
            Both arms were now about his neck, he was mad, with joy passion-- Her eyes opened
                <del>their</del> &amp; he looked into her being into the depths of her being
                <del>for</del> to find the traces of a soul-- She closed them &amp; he knew it was
            not there-- All his life--his hope, his desire, ambition he had given for this--&amp;
            found it souless-- She clung to his lips &amp; sucked them into her own--as if she must
            have felt his loss-- He was mad wild &amp; happy-- One thrust of the dagger through the
            peony which lay upon her heart <del>and</del> she lay quite still--and was
            forgiven--</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
