<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Autograph draft document">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-08-22 KH </prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-08-26 CH proof and enter tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2015-1-13 clean regs and correct proofreading EK</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1914-00-00">1914</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Superwoman-An Idea of a Movie</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236852</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Sophia Smith Collection</title> S73:0433</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Sanger drafted this screenplay around 1914-15. No final version has
            been found.</p>
        <index level1="women" level2="freedom and rights of"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="films by"/>
        <index level1="love"/>
        <index level1="spirituality"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Superwoman: An Idea of a Movie</head>
        <head type="sub">A play based on the power of the <add>spiritual</add> law of rights.</head>
        <p>A Superwoman who has earned the knowledge of great power by effort in past lives--by
            sacrifice--by faith in power of truth--always she followed the voice within &amp; always
            she haf passed through former lives in stress &amp; struggle but passed out of life in
            spiritual victory.</p>
        <p><person reg="Joan, of Arc (Saint)">Joan of Arc</person>--<add><name type="deity"
                    >Vashti</name></add>--the same came spirit upon earth many times in different
            bodies &amp; characters teacher--reformer, queen, priestess, <del>spy</del>,
                <unclear>man</unclear>, maid of all work evolving through all experience--gaining
            all knowledge for Soul growth faith, patience, humility, truth, strength, hope, etc.
            attributes of a great soul--</p>
        <p>Her life on this earth centers around a movement in <place>Russia</place>.</p>
        <p>Heretofore she has never in all her former lives given herself wholly to love-- She has
            walked alone--</p>
        <p>Her influence is tremendous-- Through meditation &amp; prayer she brings all victories to
            pass--harmonizes all influences &amp; forces--opens closed doors--opens jails--silences
            reactionary forces--</p>
        <p>In the meantime while looking over the field of battle for some one through which she
            could work she found only one who was so attuned to her Soul growth that she could
            vibrate &amp; make him act <del>attuned</del>
            <add>in harmony</add> to her will--</p>
        <p>He was a young uncouth Jewish lad--serious--a Student--one poor in body &amp; in mind--
            With him she fell in love--deeply--seriously and beyond her <add>very</add> power--</p>
        <p>Having through former lives learned control over her body &amp; mind and somewhat over
            her <del>illegible</del>own heart never having loved deeply before--this was her new
            test. Could she continue it. The Jew sensitive to her magnetism was attracted to
            her--and before long she gave her all--abandoned herself opened the doors of her
            treasured sanctuary &amp; enriched his knowledge &amp; power &amp; personality-- In a
            short time he grew to be a man of great magnetism-- He was leader of men--he had
            intuition--which meant wisdom and daily grew in the estimation of all. He <add>was</add>
            the man of the hour--</p>
        <p>The Revolution came--through her influence with powers unseen, the people elected him to
            be their guide.</p>
        <p>He accepted with glowing heart &amp; pride-- He was now as high as he could go in the
            affairs of men. The world acknowledged man of the hour--</p>
        <p>All men--like a fire rocket--go to their powers height--&amp; descend-- But some though
            they descend physically continue to heights unseen spiritually. Here was the moment for
            him. How would he take his hour--as egotistical as man or with humility &amp;
            acknowledgment of the Power whose instrument he is?</p>
        <p>Praise--power--flattery--filled his head--gradually he looked to love a younger
            woman--with more beauty &amp; less brains. Gradually he repulsed
                    “<q><person>Ione</person></q>” &amp; closed his heart to her love-- He was not
            unkind he was not cruel--in fact he knew he owed her much-- So he began to pay off his
            spiritual debts with material gifts--flower gifts--were sent to Ione--but the highest
            honor a man can pay a woman--he reserved for his new love-- He sought her hand in
            marriage--and she accepted his offer--</p>
        <p>Thus he stood at the apex of his career-- He thus sought to fill his cup of fame &amp;
            happiness--regardless of the debt he owed in gaining these.</p>
        <p>Ione struck to the heart with grief was silent-- All the old reactions of human nature
            returned to make her nights sleepless &amp; her days a torture, jealousy, bitterness,
            envy, hatred took possession of her and pray as she did--she could not drive them
            out.</p>
        <p><add><gap extent="missing pages"/></add></p>
        <p>Jewish influences of race &amp; family surround him. Old habits returned, dead parents
            haunted his dreams &amp; urge his marriage with one of his own race--</p>
        <p>His modern life has taught him to take all he can get and better himself thereby--not
            knowing the price the law exacts for everything we take.</p>
        <p>Tortured by memories &amp; desires &amp; uncertainty--his nights &amp; days are spent in
            agony where his <add>some fantasy</add> between the material and the spiritual.</p>
        <p>Such reactions in the human mind have their reflections in other minds &amp; soon
            discontent, envy, jealousy began to take form among the masses who had been peacefully
            laboring under a new government.</p>
        <p>What she felt--they felt, and thus the ideal suffered.</p>
        <p>Overcome by the trials which she thought she had overcome in her life--she became
            ill--she lay for days apparently beyond relief--</p>
        <p>She was however possessed with a power whereby she could have her body in a sleeping
            state &amp; her inner self soar to regions on earth &amp; elsewhere-- Here she
                <del>went</del>
            <add>was taken</add> to consult with higher powers--leaders of mens affairs--here she
            sought advice &amp; council--&amp; strength and light.  Here she counseled with great men who had
            once lived upon the earth &amp; suffered for the truth--<person>Socrates</person>,
                <person>Plato</person>, <name type="deity" reg="Christ, Jesus">Christ</name>, <person
                reg="Lincoln, Abraham">Lincoln</person>, <person reg="Bruno, Giordano"
                >Bruno</person>, and others who were waiting in turn for the world to be
                <add>made</add> a fit place that they might return to earth &amp; continue their
            progress--</p>
        <p>There she consulted--and from them she drew her light--</p>
        <p>In time she recovered--the masses were seething with discontent--  The leader whose
            strength had failed him became the target for their malice--  His own nights &amp; days
            had not been happy-- Something had gone from him--he did not know what--yet he knew he
            lived &amp; to this he clung desperately--frantically. Deliberately Ione cleansed her
            heart of all feelings of resentment--also of all feelings of love. She resigned herself
            completely to the law of right-- She closed the doors of her sanctuary--of her heart to man--forever.  With this decision
            came a new strength--and joy--</p>
            <p>But the law which operates this on one side of the Scales has a different effect in the other. Now the boy saw he was not so great as he had
            been--he knew something had gone wrong--he knew--he owed a debt somewhere and to someone
            &amp; that someone to Ione. His was the test spiritually--could he give up his new love &amp; the future he had
            pictured so brightly for a debt?</p>
        <p>Yes he owed this to Ione--the debt must be paid--joyously, abandonedly, &amp; happily. In
            no other spirit should it be cancelled. After days &amp; nights of torture he threw himself at her feet &amp; offered his
            all--what rightfully belonged to her--name--&amp; heart &amp; love--  A new light came into her eyes as she lifted him up. “<q>No</q>,” she said. “<q>Boy--I do not want
                you--</q>"</p>
        <p>It is not love, it’s the working out of the law.</p>
        <p>Through this love I gave you I learned my lesson of this life the control of the heart.</p>
            <p>Through your obedience to the law of right you have better fitted yourself for a trusted
            leader of man in days to come. Through both of us--the revolution is lost--but the real
            revolution can only accomplish the purpose when you in you &amp; the I in me become
            through experience &amp; suffering perfected  Vashtis awakening that women are not
            possessions--like cattle, female--servants etc to be viewed as wealth. Refused to be <unclear>received</unclear> by lords of <place>Persia</place> &amp; was dethroned for <person
                reg="Esther (Biblical)">Esther</person>. Became beggar &amp; outcast died of hunger &amp; alone--</p>
        <p>1. lessons from being personal possession</p>
        <p>2. lessons from worshipping false gods.</p>
        <p>3. lessons from</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
