<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Statement">
<mepHeader>
<prepDate>2003/07/15 SR</prepDate>
<prepDate>2003/07/28 SR</prepDate>
<prepDate>2003-07-28 CH</prepDate>
<prepDate>2004/07/01 CH</prepDate>
<prepDate>2014-03-04 CH checking regs</prepDate>
<prepDate>2014-11-12 CH more regs</prepDate>
<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
<docDate value="1921-12-20">
<supplied resp="MSPP">20 Jan 1921</supplied>
</docDate>
<docTitle>
<titlePart>Reply by Margaret Sanger to Archbishop Hayes' Statement</titlePart>
</docTitle>
<idno>msp237427</idno>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl> Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College.</bibl>
<bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Micriofilm, Smith College Collections</title>, S76:1165</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
<respStmt>
<resp/>
<name/>
</respStmt>
</mepHeader>
<headNote resp="MSPP"><p><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger</person> drafted this statement in
response to a Christmas pastoral letter issued by New York Archbishop <person
reg="Hayes, Patrick J.">Patrick J. Hayes</person> on December 17, 1921. For published version see
<title type="journal">New York Times</title>, Dec. 20, 1921.</p>
<index level1="birth control" level2="opposition to"/>
<index level1="Catholic Church" level2="birth control and abortion and"/>
<index level1="Catholic Church" level2="MS on"/>
<index level1="Hayes, Patrick J. (Archbishop)"/>
</headNote>
<docBody>
<head>Reply by Margaret Sanger to Archbishop Hayes' Statement</head>
<p>I am glad to learn from Archbishop Hayes' Christmas pastoral that the church has a clear
understanding of Birth Control separating it definitely from taking life after conception has
occurred.</p>
<p>Many people have been of the opinion that the church confused the two ideas and denied vigorously
that the church opposed prevention of conception as distinct from interfering with life after
conception has occurred. From Archbishop Hayes' statement we at last realize that there is a perfect
understanding by the church of what the Birth Control Movement stands for. For this I am
grateful.</p>
<p>I do not care to answer the Archbishop's theological statement concerning the will of the <name
type="deity">Almighty</name>. His arguments are purely those based on assumption and he knows no
more about the facts of the immortality of the soul than the rest of us human beings. What he
believes concerning the soul after life, is based upon theory and he has a perfect right to that
belief; but we, who are trying to better humanity fundamentally, believe that a healthy, happy human
race is more in keeping with the laws of <name type="deity">God</name> than disease, misery and poverty
perpetuating itself generation after generation.</p>
<p>There is no objection to the <org reg="Roman Catholic Church">Catholic Church</org> inculcating
the theories and doctrines in its own church and to its own people; but when they attempt to make
these ideas legislative acts and force their opinions and code of morals upon the Protestant members
of this country, then we do consider this an interference with the principles of this Democracy and
we have a right to protest.</p>
</docBody>
</doc>
