<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed statement">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2012-03-29 AW Initial Tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2012-04-04 CH Proofed Tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-08 EK clean tags</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1959-12-27">27 Dec 1959</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Margaret Sanger on Channel 13, Tucson</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp237527</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S72:0987</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="EISDW">Eisenhower, Dwight</name>
            <name id="DRACO">Draper Committee</name>
            <name id="USFP"><title>United States Foreign Policy: Possible Non-military Scientific
                    Developments and their Potential Impact on Foreign Policy Problems of the United
                    States</title></name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>The following are likely <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger's</person> statements
            televised in <place>Tucson, AZ</place>.</p>
       <index level1="Catholic Church" level2="political influence of"/>
    <index level1="birth control" level2="politicians and"/>
    <index level1="birth control" level2="socio-economic benefits of"/>
    <index level1="birth control" level2="foreign policy, and"/>
    <index level1="population control" level2="MS on"/>
    <index level1="overpopulation" level2="MS on"/>
    <index level1="population growth" level2="regulation of"/>
    <index level1="population control" level2="socio-economic benefits of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head rend="underline">MARGARET SANGER on Television Channel 13, Tucson</head>
        <dateline>December 27, 1959</dateline>
        <div>
            <p>1. I think President <person reg="Eisenhower, Dwight">Eisenhower</person> was
                mistaken in saying that Birth Control is no part of Government policy, but is merely
                a “<q who="EISDW">religious question</q>”. I believe he had insufficient information
                when he made those remarks. I hope he will revise his statement.</p>
            <p>I challenge him to debate the issue of whether or not Birth Control is a proper part
                of Government Health and Welfare policy for World Peace. I will be pleased to debate
                with him at any time and place.</p>
            <p>If he prefers to avoid a public debate, I will be glad to confer with him, at his
                pleasure, about Birth Control, Family Planning and Population Limitation for World
                Peace.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <p>2. The President ought to be guided by, and put into effect, the recommendations of
                the <org>Draper Committee</org> which he appointed. These recommendations are:</p>
            <p>"<q who="DRACO">We recommend that in order to meet more effectively the problems of
                    economic development, the <place>United States</place> (1) assist those
                    countries with which it is cooperating in economic aid programs, on request, in
                    the formulation of their plans designed to deal with the problem of rapid
                    population growth, (2) increase its assistance to local programs relating to
                    maternal and child welfare. . . .and (3) strongly support studies and
                    appropriate research. . . .to meet the serious challenge posed by rapidly
                    expanding populations. . . . .</q>”</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <p>3. World Peace can come only if leaders and statesmen of the world, including our
                President, recognize the importance of Birth Control, Family Planning, and
                Population Limitation. Prime Minister <person reg="Nehru, Jawaharlal"
                >Nehru</person>, Premier <person reg="Kishi, Nobusuke">Kishi</person>, and President
                    <person reg="Khan, Muhammad Ayub">Ayub</person>, among others, recognize this
                fact. They are making Birth Control part of official government services for Health
                and Welfare. President Eisenhower should help these other nations, and our own
                country, in a similar way to gain World Peace.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <p>4. It is a mistake to allow Roman Catholic prelates to influence the President’s
                thinking to the extent that his statements reflect their dogmatic view that Birth
                Control is merely a “<q who="EISDW">religious matter</q>”, rather than a medical,
                health, and World Peace benefit. The contrary declaration by the Roman Catholic
                officials in the United States should not be allowed to dominate this Government’s
                policy in our country of free religions where the majority of us are not Roman
                Catholics.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <p>5. Families and mothers in <place>Connecticut</place> and
                    <place>Massachusetts</place> ought to be granted freedom to obtain medical care
                from their own doctors, which includes contraceptive prescriptions.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <p>6. The <org reg="U.S. Senate Committee on Foreign Relations">Senate Foreign Relations
                    Committee</org> ought to be guided by, and to implement, the recommendations
                made at its request by the <org>Stanford Research Institute</org>. These
                recommendations are:</p>

            <p> “<q who="USFP">. . . .There is nothing to suggest complacency in the face of the
                    world’s threatening population and production problems. . . .population control
                    will therefore become imperative; the population problem is already acute in
                    some parts of the world. Current scientific developments indicate that. . .a
                    safe, effective, and inexpensive oral contraceptive, could soon be available if
                    the comparatively small amount of research now under way in this field were
                    stepped up . . . .</q>(p. 2)</p>

            <p>“<q who="USFP">World hunger and population control present major long-term
                    international policy problems to the United States and to the other nations of
                    the world. . .. Some means of controlling population growth are inescapable. The
                    traditional means have been disease, famine and war. If other means are to be
                    substituted, conscious national and international policies will be
                required.</q></p>

            <p> “<q who="USFP">Population pressures can become significant causes of social unrest
                    and war. In ceratin parts of the world overpopulation is already prevalent, and
                    new approaches to the problem are urgently required. While some $30 billion are
                    spent each year on the worldwide attack on mortality, only a few million dollars
                    are allocated to programs which affect birth rates. A possible approach would be
                    for the U.S. Government to study. . . .the possibility of providing research
                    funds to certain foreign agencies and laboratories. . . for the large-scale
                    human testing of devices, which is so necessary but difficult to conduct without
                    adequate cooperation and funds. In this way those governments and peoples that
                    feel the problem to be acute would be enabled to speed up their quest for the
                    physical, biological, and social knowledge needed to check population growth by
                    means other than disease, famine, and war.</q>” (p. 40)</p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
