<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2010/04/28 AC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2010/04/29 CH proofread/correct</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-11 CH clean errors</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1938-04-20">
            <supplied source="MSPP">20 Apr 1938</supplied>
        </docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>The Status of Birth Control: 1938</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp238617</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">The New Republic</title>, Apr. 20, 1938, pp. 324-26.</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title>, S71:1018</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp>
                <name id="HANAU">Hand, Augustus N.</name>
                <name id="Sec211">Section 211 of the U.S. Penal Code</name>
                <name id="AMA">American Medical Association</name>
            </resp>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">The section at the end of this article was published in an outlined box
        accompanying the article. <index level1="birth control"/>
        <index level1="abortion"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Comstock act"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Mississippi"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Oregon"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Connecticut"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Massachusetts"/>
        <index level1="birth contorl" level2="laws and legislation" level3="North Carolina"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Puerto Rico"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="legal cases"
            level3="U.S. V. One Package of Japanese contraceptives'"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="legalization of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="medical community and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="pessaries"/>
        <index level1="Comstock, Anthony"/>
        <index level1="law-breaking and direct action"/>
        <index level1="quackery"/>
        <index level1="obscenity"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="government" level3="birth control and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>The Status of Birth Control: 1938</head>
        <div type="section">
            <p>At last birth control is legal in the <place>United States</place>. The right to
                provide contraceptive information and service under medical direction is finally
                recognized under the federal law as now interpreted, and it also is legal under
                state laws in all but two states, <place>Mississippi</place> and
                    <place>Massachusetts</place> -- and the Massachusetts law is vulnerable on
                constitutional grounds.</p>
            <p>It is one of the anomalies of modern civilization that the forces of bigotry,
                reaction and legalism could so long have kept on the federal statute books a law
                that classed contraceptive information with obscenity and was interpreted to prevent
                physicians from prescribing contraceptives. Year after year this vicious law legally
                tied the hands of reputable physicians, while quacks and purveyors of bootleg
                contraceptives and “feminine hygiene” articles and formulas flourished. It was an
                absurd situation in which the federal law in effect nullified the laws of
                practically every state.</p>
            <p>But now mothers can be told! The story of how motherhood ultimately was rescued from
                bondage in an absorbing one. It required two-thirds of a century to remove the
                federal fetters placed upon birth control by <person reg="Comstock, Anthony">Anthony
                    Comstock </person>and a <org reg="New York Society for the Suppression of Vice"
                    >“reform” group</org> which induced a timid and overawed <org
                    reg="United States Congress">Congress</org> to pass the overreaching law. That
                famous, or rather infamous, law -- <name type="law"
                    reg="United States Criminal Code, Section 211">Section 211 of the United States
                    Penal Code</name> -- and supplementary laws, prevented the dissemination of
                birth-control information even by a physician, and barred anything pertaining to the
                subject from the mails or common carriers. Other sections were even more rigid,
                forbidding the possession of any article for preventing conception -- <emph
                    rend="italics">and there were no exceptions</emph>. While the original bill
                carried the exemption, “<q who="Sec211">except on a prescription of a physician in
                    good standing, given in good faith,</q>” these words were omitted from the bill
                which finally became law. Violations of the laws were punishable by fines of from
                $2,000 to $5,000, or imprisonment for five years, or both. The laws made no
                distinction between contraception and abortion, though they are as far apart as the
                poles. Birth control is the conscious control of the birth rate by scientific means
                which prevent conception. It is not interference with life after conception has
                taken place.</p>
            <p>And the laws had teeth. Many supplies and much literature were confiscated and
                destroyed. Although no outstanding, distinguished physicians were actually
                prosecuted for violating the law, this was mainly because they did not openly
                violate it. They were intimidated and kept in fear of prosecution. With federal and
                state laws in conflict and confusion, a physician might legally dispense information
                under state statutes, but it was illegal for him under a literal interpretation of
                the federal statutes to send or to receive the necessary technical information and
                medical supplies. The laws hampered the progressive physician, eager to adopt
                preventive health measures and willing to advise his patients privately, but
                reluctant to take a similar stand in public practice because of confusion as to his
                legal rights in this field of medicine.</p>
            <p>The Comstock laws not only thwarted efforts to protect mothers from excessive
                child-bearing and children from being born sick, weak, unwanted and unprovided for,
                but were responsible, directly or indirectly, for the deaths of a million mothers
                during the six decades in which they were enforced. These deaths occurred among
                mothers who were the victims of abortions or of bearing children when in unfit
                physical condition.</p>
            <p>Even today the situation is still appalling in some respects. Out of every four
                mothers who die in America, one death is due to abortion. Out of 15,000 mothers who
                die each year from causes due to childbirth or pregnancy, a large percentage are
                “poor maternity risks” from the stat. As for infant mortality, statistics of the
                    <org>United States Children’s Bureau</org> tell their eloquent but unheeded
                story. When the interval between births is too short, death rates climb. Babies born
                one year apart die at the rate of 147 per thousand; babies born two years apart have
                a mortality rate of only 98 per thousand. These figures are a challenge to the
                nation.</p>
            <p>For many years efforts to induce Congress to amend the Comstock laws were unavailing,
                but sentiment for changing them increased rapidly from 1930 onward. In the campaign
                undertaken by the <org>National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth
                    Control</org>, Inc., nearly a thousand organizations with approximately twenty
                millions of members eventually endorsed the lifting of federal restrictions, and
                325,000 individual endorsements were filed with Congress. Few causes have won such a
                vast number of active supporters.</p>
            <p>Through a liberal court, this informed and potent public opinion finally found
                expression. One of the judges, in a separate opinion, observed: “<q who="HANAU">A
                    statute stands until public opinion gets enough momentum to change it, which may
                    be long after a majority would repeal it, if a poll were taken.</q>” The
                National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control, Inc., had processed
                along both legislative and legal lines of battle. As confiscations of books and
                materials increased, a particularly strong test case was instituted by the Committee
                in behalf of <person reg="Stone, Hannah Mayer">Dr. Hannah M. Stone</person>, medical
                director of the <org>Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau</org> in New York. The
                government, through the <org reg="United States Customs Bureau">Bureau of
                    Customs</org>, had seized a package containing 120 pessaries to prevent
                conception, which the government alleged had been imported contrary to <name
                    type="law" reg="United States Tarriff Act, Section 305">Section 305 (a) of the
                    Tariff Act of 1930</name>, which stemmed from the Comstock law of 1873. These
                pessaries had been sent to Dr. Stone by a physician in <place>Japan</place> for
                trial in her practice, and she had been asked to give an opinion as to their
                usefulness for contraceptive purposes. Dr. Stone testified as at the trial that she
                prescribed the use of pessaries in cases where it would not be desirable for a
                patient to undertake a pregnancy.</p>
            <p>It was in this case, on November 30, 1936, that birth control under medical direction
                was finally recognized as legal. The <org>United States Circuit Court of Appeals for
                    the Second Circuit</org> rendered a decision that the federal obscenity laws do
                not apply to the legitimate activities of physicians, and that they may prescribe
                contraceptives in the interests of the healthy and general well-being of their
                patients. That enlightened decision brought birth control to the goal it had long
                sought through legislation and was an emancipation proclamation to the motherhood of
                America. Its objective won, the National Committee disbanded.</p>
            <p>With sharp, surgical precision the historic decision cut through the tangled
                confusion of federal laws. It removed the shadow of illegality and the stigma of
                obscenity and brought the federal statutes into conformity with most state statutes.
                In the few remaining states in which outmoded statutes await reinterpretation, the
                decision is a beacon for other courts to follow.</p>
            <p>The decision constitutes a <name type="law">Bill of Rights</name> for the medical
                profession in the field of contraception. The nation owes a debt of gratitude to the
                wisdom, the logic and the humanity of Judges <person reg="Hand, Augustus N."
                    >Augustus N. Hand</person>, <person reg="Swan, Thomas W.">Thomas W.
                    Swan</person> and <person reg="Hand, Learned">Learned Hand</person>, for
                upholding the previous decision of United States District Court Judge <person
                    reg="Moscowitz, Grover">Grover Moscowitz</person> that contraceptives imported
                for a lawful purpose did not come within the restrictions of the statute.</p>
            <p><person reg="Cummings, Homer Stille">Homer S. Cummings</person>, Attorney General of
                the United States, announced that the government would rest its case and not carry
                it to the <org>United States Supreme Court</org>. Thus the decision of the Circuit
                Court of Appeals became the law of the land, and the <org
                    reg="United States Treasury Department">Treasury Department</org> thereupon
                issued instructions to Customs authorities to admit contraceptive supplies addressed
                to physicians. For the ultimate victory we are also deeply grateful to <person
                    reg="Ernst, Morris L.">Morris L. Ernst</person>, counsel for Dr. Stone and the
                Committee, for his gallant and successful fight as well as his constant championship
                of civil liberties and clarification of obstructive laws.</p>
            <p>Medical as well as legal sanction for birth control at last exists. Less than a year
                after the legal decision, and following a long investigation by a special committee,
                the <org>American Medical Association</org>, in June, 1937, approved birth control
                as an essential part of medical practice and education, and urged the necessity for
                informing physicians of their legal rights in relation to the use of contraceptives.
                A resolution declared that</p>
            <p rend="blockquote">
                <q who="AMA"> ...it seems fair ... to assume that the state courts, if called upon
                    to construe the statutes relating to the dissemination of contraceptive
                    information, will adopt lines of reasoning similar to those followed in the case
                    cited (<name type="law" reg="United States vs. One Package">U.S. v. One
                        Package</name>) and in other cases decided by the United States courts,
                    leaving physicians free to give information concerning contraception when
                    required to meet the medical needs of patients.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This reference was to the Dr. Hannah Stone case. The public may now look to the
                Association to carry research in contraception and to promote the teaching of birth
                control in medical schools.</p>
            <p>Birth control, therefore, from a national standpoint, is at last freed. The federal
                statutes are no longer a stumbling block. However, there is need for clarification
                of state statutes in the few states where the literal wording of the law may still
                be invoked unless public opinion makes its force felt. In the past some states
                followed the lead of the federal government in enacting and clinging to obsolete
                statutes restricting the dissemination of contraceptive knowledge, but, fortunately,
                these statutes contain exemptions of many types and degrees as regards the medical
                profession. There are twenty-four states with statutes of this character. Some of
                them are confused, outmoded conglomerations of provisions aimed indiscriminately at
                birth control, obscenity, indecency, abortion, miscarriage, lotteries, nostrums,
                drops, pills, tinctures, compounds, poisons, drugs, prophylactics, lust, crime and
                “sex-exciting devices.” Nevertheless, these statutory relics of the past do not
                impose any obstacles for the medical profession. The situation is summed up in the
                box on page 324.</p>
            <p>There remain, then, three states. In one, <place>Connecticut</place>, the use of
                contraceptives is forbidden. This statute, incapable of enforcement, has long
                subjected Connecticut to ridicule, but this blue-law relic has remained as part of
                the code, despite earnest and repeated efforts to amend it. Nevertheless, seven
                birth-control clinics are in operation in Connecticut.</p>
            <p> Mississippi makes no exceptions in its statutes, which ban even oral information. An
                effort to amend the Mississippi law nearly succeeded during the past session. A bill
                passed the House and was defeated in the <org reg="United States Senate"
                    >Senate</org> by only six votes. In Massachusetts the state laws have been
                challenged. While they make no exception of any kind, eight birth-control clinics,
                directed and sponsored by outstanding medical and civic leaders of the state, have
                served the public for many years without legal hindrance. Meanwhile, repeated
                efforts have been made to modernize the Massachusetts laws, but without success. In
                the summer of 1937 three Massachusetts birth control clinics were raided. Doctors,
                nurses, social workers and officials were arrested, convicted and fined. Their cases
                are being appealed to the higher courts and pending decision all clinics in the
                state have closed. This reactionary step is a warning that while prohibitory laws of
                this type remain on the statute books, they constitute a continuing threat to the
                freedom of the medical profession and the welfare of mothers.</p>
            <p><place>Oregon</place> holds the distinction of being the first state to divorce
                contraception from abortion and obscenity. It is also the first state to attempt to
                safeguard its citizens by setting up a control of contraceptive products and
                advertising under its <org reg="Oregon State Board of Pharmacy">State Board of
                    Pharmacy</org>. To <place>North Carolina</place> goes the honor of being the
                first state to provide birth-control clinical service through its <org
                    reg="North Carolina State Department of Health">State Department of Health</org>
                and county physicians. <place>Puerto Rico</place> has also enacted progressive
                legislation.</p>
            <p>What lies ahead? It is not enough merely to establish the rights of physicians
                through the courts. This ethical gain must be used. We have taken a great step
                forward, but other hurdles must be cleared. With birth control legalized by court
                decisions, all states should now catch up with public sentiment, judicial
                interpretation and the demand for contraceptive services by clarifying and
                modernizing their laws. All state laws should be positive, not vague or negative.
                They should clearly and affirmatively declare and assure the right of medical birth
                control, not merely fail to forbid it, or limit it.</p>
            <p>Therefore I ask all who have so loyally made our legal and medical victories possible
                to join efforts with us again in the next important objective -- the inclusion of
                birth-control service in local, state and national health programs. In this way only
                can those mothers most desperately in need of this information obtain it through
                reliable medical channels. Help make it known to hospitals, relief agencies,
                philanthropic and public-health officials that the federal decision has freed their
                hands. Challenge all plans for the reduction of maternal and infant mortality that
                ignore the basic need for including contraceptive service in such programs.</p>
            <p>We must move fast, for women and children are dying needlessly. Individual and group
                effort can point the way and can do immeasurable good. But those guiding our
                programs for relief, for the reduction of maternal and infant mortality and for the
                control of syphilis, must recognize that the provision of scientific birth-control
                information is essential to the success of all such programs.</p>
            <p> Today there are more than three hundred and fifty birth-control centers in the
                country. Ten times that number are required to meet the need. There are 7,000
                hospitals and 10,000 other agencies where medical aid is sought by mothers too poor
                to pay the fees of private physicians which ought to provide contraceptive service.
                And medical-nursing service ought to bring birth control to thousands of forgotten
                women on farms and in isolated districts remote from medical centers. Their plight
                and pleas are among the most poignant of all. </p>
            <byline><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">MARGARET SANGER</person></byline>

        </div>
        <div type="box">
            <head>Birth Control in the United States</head>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub" rend="italics">Federal Law</head>
                <p>Birth control is legal under medical direction. A United States Circuit Court of
                    Appeals has held that the federal obscenity laws do not apply to the legitimate
                    activities of physicans and that they may prescribe contraceptives in the
                    interests of the health and general well-being of their patients.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub" rend="italics">State Laws</head>
                <p>It is legal under state as well as federal statutes in twenty-one states, which
                    have no provisions against it. They are <place>Alabama</place>,
                        <place>Arkansas</place>, <place>Florida</place>, <place>Georgia</place>,
                        <place>Ilinois</place>, <place>Kentucky</place>, <place>Maryland</place>,
                        <place>New Hampshire</place>, <place>New Mexico</place>, <place>North
                        Carolina</place>, <place>Oklahoma</place>, <place>Rhode Island</place>,
                        <place>South Carolina</place>, <place>South Dakota</place>,
                        <place>Tennessee</place>, <place>Texas</place>, <place>Utah</place>,
                        <place>Vermont</place>, <place>Virginia</place>, and <place>West
                        Virginia</place>. The same is true in the <place>District of
                        Columbia</place>, Puerto Rico, and the Territories of <place>Alaska</place>,
                        <place>Hawaii</place>, the <place reg="Philippines">Philippine
                        Islands</place> and the <place>Virgin Islands</place>.</p>
                <p>Ten states have limited laws, but physicians are exempt and drug-store sales of
                    contraceptives are premitted. They are <place>Colorado</place>,
                        <place>Indiana</place>, <place>Ohio</place>, <place>Delaware</place>,
                        <place>Iowa</place>, <place>Montana</place>, <place>Wisconsin</place>,
                        <place> Wyoming</place>, Oregon, and <place>Idaho</place>.</p>
                <p>Three states allow physicians to prescribe contraceptives, but druggists are not
                    mentioned. They are <place>New York</place>, <place>Nevada</place> and
                        <place>Minnesota</place>.</p>
                <p>Six states have atatutes aimed at indiscriminate advertising and distribution of
                    material. They are <place>Arizona</place>, <place>California</place>,
                        <place>Louisiana</place>, <place>Maine</place>, <place>Michigan</place> and
                        <place>Washington</place>.</p>
                <p>One state, <place>New Jersey</place>, allows the dissemination of information for
                        "<soCalled>a just cause</soCalled>."</p>
                <p>One state, Connecticut, forbids the <emph rend="italics">use</emph> of
                    contraceptives.</p>
                <p>Two states, Massachusetts and Mississippi, list no exemptions. Mississippi is the
                    only state forbidding oral information.</p>
                <p>One state, <place>Kansas</place>, exempts medical textbooks, and by implication
                    the medical profession.</p>
                <p>Three states, <place>Missouri</place>, <place>Nebraska</place> and
                        <place>Pennsylvania</place>, exempt chartered medical schools and medical
                    textbooks, and by implication the medical profession.</p>
            </div>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
