<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Printed article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2003/07/22</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2003/07/28 SR</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-09 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1923-05-00">May 1923</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Intelligence Tests for Legislators</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp238645</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title>, May 1923, 107-108.</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S70:1001.</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="xxxx"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Intelligence Tests for Legislators</head>
        <byline><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">MARGARET SANGER</person></byline>
        <p>The failure of the <org reg="New York State Assembly, Codes Committee">Codes Committee of
                the New York State Legislature</org> to approve our proposed amendment to the
            existing statute forbidding the dissemination of Birth Control information is no cause
            for discouragement. These lawmakers at <place reg="Albany, NY">Albany</place> may have
            exposed themselves as incapable of unprejudiced and clearsighted thinking concerning the
            problem of population, but the representatives of our cause were given an excellent
            opportunity to study State legislators at close range. The pessimistic observer of such
            democratic institutions as the <org reg="New York State Assembly">New York
                Assembly</org> might cite our experience in the legislative halls at Albany on April
            tenth as an example of the utter hopelessness of effecting any beneficial change in our
            statute books through the medium of such a body. But those of us who "carry on,"
            absolutely convinced of the final and inevitable triumph of the program for Birth
            Control, know that such opposition, immovable and hopeless as it seems to the
            inexperienced observer, can, with courageous effort, be dissipated.</p>
        <p>Ten years ago the very words "Birth Control" were taboo in the press. Today the subject
            is not only discussed by the press of the world, but intelligently presented and without
            the former bias. This is due to the ever-growing body of enlightened public opinion
            which is throwing into the Birth Control movement the weight of its valuable support. A
            State Legislature represents the last bulwark of prejudice, superstition and ignorance.
            The task of battling against these forces is one that demands all that we possess of
            courage and faith in our convictions. To be discouraged because the Codes Committee, a
            small group of adolescent minds, expresses its disapproval of a doctrine which has won
            the adherence of the finest intellects in the world, would be a confession of our own
            lack of faith. The battle for a better race and a greater America must go on, because
            our final triumph is inevitable. </p>
        <p> One great truth lifts its head above all the interesting facts thrust upon us during our
            recent pilgrimage to Albany. This is the immediate and pressing need for <emph
                rend="italics">intelligence tests for legislators</emph>. American schools have
            begun to test the intelligence of school children. Likewise, employers examine
            applicants for work as to their capability to fill the jobs they are seeking. There are
            mental as well as physical tests for recruits in the American army. Even the poor
            immigrant is refused admission to this country if he cannot show that his intelligence
            is equal to the complex problem of gaining a livelihood in these <place>United
                States</place>. Yet with a serene and bland indifference to the social well-being of
            the state and nation, American voters send to Congress and legislative halls noisy and
            ill-mannered politicians whose one outstanding talent seems to be their shrewd ability
            to catch votes. To understand the importance, the implications and the organic
            relationship of Birth Control to public health and racial strength, these men are
            apparently mentally and constitutionally unfit. This truth our Albany "hearing" has
            irrefutably demonstrated.</p>
        <p>We enclose the word "hearing" in quotation marks, because most of the members of that
            august committee refused us even the courtesy of listening to our arguments. Their
            attitude was that of schoolboys impatient to return to their game of marbles. When it
            came time to reply to the exponents of Birth Control, in support of which we had
            mobilized and marshalled the finest forces of reason, logic, science, public health,
            idealism and ethics, our opponents resorted to the weapons of vulgar personal abuse. A
            question which has compelled the attention, for at least a century, of the greatest
            economists, sociologists, scientists and thinkers in all fields of life, which has been
            formulated and crystallized upon the firmest foundations of logic, reason and vision, a
            problem which is daily coming to be recognized not merely as <emph rend="italics"
                >one</emph> of the greatest problems confronting contemporary civilization, but
            which, to quote the distinguished French savant, <person reg="Richet, Charles Robert"
                >Richet</person>, is basically the <emph rend="italics">only</emph> problem -- this
            question not only failed to penetrate into the consciousness of these legislators, but
            it was dismissed with a gesture that lacked even the redeeming merit of dignity. It is
            our duty to record this fact: that in this year 1923 our chosen representatives in the
            legislative body of the <place reg="New York">Empire State</place> have exposed their
            mental inability to grasp even the elements of a great pressing problem of the most
            incalculable and immediate importance to the individual and the community at large.
            Moreover, the gentlemen of the Codes Committee were to all appearances completely
            impervious to the fine example of patience, tact and persuasion offered by those who
            presented the case for Birth Control. Intelligence tests for legislators might also
            include a certain rudimentary realization of the value of dignity, courtesy and good
            manners.</p>
        <p>The situation is not so hopeless as at first glance it might appear. There is one way in
            which the intelligent voters in this and other states may appraise the fitness, not
            merely of candidates to the State Legislatures, but of all candidates for public office
            who appeal for the support of constituencies of American voters. There is no more
            certain manner in which to test the intelligence and honesty of such candidates than by
            asking for a public statement of their attitude toward the problems of public health and
            racial hygiene; whether they are ready and willing to safeguard and protect the
            child-life of the State or the nation from the widespread abuses and evils which have
            grown out of criminal neglect. Let us never forget that if we are not brave enough to
            express our own convictions on these matters, we cannot expect our legislative
            representatives to take the initiative.</p>
        <p>As long as vast amounts are drawn from the public and philanthropic treasuries--moneys
            collected not merely from taxpayers but from the pockets of every self-supporting member
            of the community--for the support of the delinquent, the defective and the incurably
            diseased elements of the community, as long as the diseased and unfit classes are urged
            irresponsibly to reproduce themselves, Birth Control must remain a question of the
            utmost political significance. Birth Control is not merely a personal and marital
            problem. Reckless breeding is a root evil that manifests itself in innumerable ways. And
            none of these is more costly, more extravagantly wasteful, than the expenditure of
            public funds for the upkeep and the perpetuation of unfortunate thousands whose very
            existence is a burden to themselves and to the vigorous and normal sections of human
            society. Such a procedure wilfully cheats the children of the next generation of their
            most sacred birthright, while it protects and coddles those defective stocks that should
            be in all kindness as rapidly extirpated from the human garden as is consistent with
            humane decency.</p>
        <p>Here, then, is a problem of the most immediate concern to every man, woman and child in
            these United States. It demands in particular the immediate attention of the woman
            voter--for in the final analysis, we women bear the burden and make the sacrifices that
            must be made as long as laws are made or mended by men who are elected to office by the
            very power of their own ignorance and by their skill in manipulating the prejudices and
            superstitions of the vast majority of American voters. But let us go one step farther:
            it is not enough for the enlightened and the intelligent merely to bemoan the lamentable
            condition of American politics. Such conditions will continue--and the evils must grow
            instead of diminishing--as long as we fail to make the intelligence tests I have
            indicated. The task is a long and discouraging one. But with coordination and
            concentration of effort, with a growing interest in watching and measuring the results
            of organization, the power of even a small minority standing back of such an
            organization as the <org>American Birth Control League</org>, forcing upon all
            candidates this problem and asking for a definite opinion on the matter, could not fail
            to make itself felt as a beneficent and directing force in American life.</p>
        <p>Convinced of the necessity of such tactics, we reiterate our call for Intelligence Tests
            for Legislators.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
