<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2003/08/04 SR</prepDate>
		<prepDate>05/09/2012 AW</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-04-09 CH clean regs</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-09 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1924-10-00">Oct 1924</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>The Passing of a Hero</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp238685</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title>, Oct. 1924, pp. 288-89.</bibl>
			<bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Smith College Collections</title>,
				S70:1052</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name/>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<index level1="Rutgers, Johannes"/>
		<index level1="Jacobs, Aletta"/>
		<index level1="Netherlands" level2="birth control in"/>
		<index level1="Netherlands" level2="clinics in"/>
		<index level1="birth control movement" level2="history of"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>The Passing of a Hero</head>
		<byline>By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></byline>
		<p>From its stormy beginning, now something more than one hundred years ago, that struggle
			for human freedom and the battle to liberate woman from the cruel slavery of enforced
			motherhood which today is known as the Birth Control movement, has produced a long list
			of martyrs and heroes known and unknown–-an honor-list of brave men and courageous women
			who, without thought of recognition or official medals, unflinchingly have carried on
			the thankless battle against blind prejudice. Some of them, like those dauntless
			pioneers, the <person reg="Drysdale, George R."><person reg="Drysdale, Charles R."
					>Drysdales</person></person>, have won a place in the history of human freedom
			that can never be wrested from them. Others must remain anonymous, though their valor
			has been scarcely less heroic. Propagandists, publishers, booksellers, active agitators
			like those men who first circulated the "diabolical handbill" at the very outset of the
			Neo-Malthusian movement–-all have carried on the torch and kept our ideal alive.</p>
		<p>Others have worked directly in the heart of the poor, in the midst of conditions an din
			the face of obstacles that would have discouraged men less staunch in their convictions,
			less loyal to the ideal of a liberated and regenerated humanity. One of the noblest
			heroes in this latter field has been Doctor <person reg="Rutgers, Johannes">J.
				Rutgers</person> of <place reg="The Hague, Netherlands">The Hague</place>. The news
			of whose recent death has just come to us from <place reg="Netherlands">Holland</place>.
			The severity of this blow to our cause is alleviated only by our realization of the
			profound influence exerted by this valiant worker in our movement. The work of a whole
			lifetime devoted with the highest idealism to a love of his fellow-men has not been in
			vain. The influence of Doctor Rutgers has been profound. For he was one of the first to
			realize that this whole problem of voluntary contraception is not one merely of
			controversy and discussion, of theory and polemic, the moral rightness of which may be
			decided solely by preachers or teachers. It is a problem of practical science, to be
			tested by intelligent men and women. And so, quietly, modestly, without any blaring of
			trumpets, actuated by the courage of his convictions and a profound love of humanity,
			Dr. Rutgers gave the Neo-Malthusian movement, as it was known during the latter half of
			the nineteenth century, a new direction and a new life. His instrument was the Birth
			Control clinic. To him we owe the establishment of Birth Control clinics in Holland.</p>
		<p>In 1915 I went to him to learn all the practical aspects of scientific contraception. I
			shall never forget the long hours I spent under his guidance in those Dutch clinics,
			learning from this quiet humanitarian much more than merely the practical education I
			had gone to acquire from him. First of all he taught me, not so much by word as by
			practical demonstration, the paramount importance of the clinic as a means of educating
			women in the hygienic and eugenic aspects of Birth Control. He taught me that real Birth
			Control could never be merely a matter of printed and published information, but of
			practical and scientific hygiene. And so from Dr. Rutgers I came to see that the clinic
			must be the true goal of all adequate and thorough education in Birth Control. As
			conceived in the mind of this valiant worker and humanitarian, the clinic becomes the
			surest instrument toward individual liberty and the regeneration of the race– profoundly
			eugenical and an institution of real hygienic education.</p>
		<p>While to Doctor <person reg="Jacobs, Aletta">Aletta Jacobs</person> must be awarded the
			high honor of being the first physician in Holland to offer practical advice to poor
			mothers, it was Dr. Rutgers' great achievement to organize the clinics, to educate
			nurses and midwives in this delicate work and to effect the establishment of clinics in
			the lesser cities and towns of the Netherlands.</p>
		<p>In the face of unforseen and almost insurmountable obstacles Dr. Rutgers carried on this
			great work to the point when the benefits of the clinics could be scientifically
			computed and practically demonstrated, to the point, in short, when the work, organized
			by the pioneer in this field, was officially recognized by the Dutch government as a
			humanitarian effort of national importance. By his devotion and tireless efforts, Dr.
			Rutgers had carried to fine fruition a lifework that at the beginning was almost
			blighted by neglect, misunderstanding, indifference and the enmity of his opponents.</p>
		<p>I am proud to realize that through my efforts educators and social workers of other
			countries have taught the importance of the clinic as a true instrument of eugenic
			education. My enthusiasm for Dr. Rutgers' clinic has led others to visit The Hague and
			to investigate his results for themselves. So that his example in the near future may
			have widespread influence, not only in the <place>Occident</place> but in the <place
				reg="Asia">Far East</place> as well.</p>
		<p>How much the contemporary Birth Control movement owes to the example of Holland, the
			pioneer nation in this field, we all realize. How much Holland owes to the fine and
			unflinching idealism of Dr. Rutgers, it is too early to say. His is an influence the
			benefits of which cannot be determined in a single generation nor in two. When we point
			to Holland as an outstanding example of what can be accomplished and what has been
			attained in the quality of breeding as opposed to the blind and inidiscriminate
			reproduction of mere numbers, we should not forget that this practical national
			demonstration of our conviction is the outcome of the tireless patience and
			indefatigable idealism of a single man-–Dr. J. Rutgers.</p>
		<p>Let us honor his memory as that of one of the true heroes fighting for the liberation of
			humanity through the Birth Control movement.</p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
