<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Printed Article">
<mepHeader>
<prepDate>2003/07/08 SR</prepDate>
<prepDate>2003/07/14 SR</prepDate>
<prepDate>2003/07/14 CH</prepDate>
<prepDate>2014-03-04 CH checking regs; added index terms</prepDate>
<prepDate>2014-11-13 CH clean regs</prepDate>
<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
<prepDate>2014-03-04 CH checking regs</prepDate>
<docDate value="1921-05-00"> May 1921</docDate>
<docTitle>
<titlePart>Politicians vs. Birth Control</titlePart>
</docTitle>
<idno>msp238944</idno>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl><title>The Birth Control Review</title>, May 1921, 3-4.</bibl>
<bibl><title>MSM</title>S70:0901.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
<respStmt>
<resp/>
<name id="UNK"> Unknown</name>
<name id="BATWI"> Bateson, William </name>
<name id="BIB">Bible</name>
</respStmt>
</mepHeader>
<headNote resp="MSPP">
<index level1="birth control" level2="politicians and"/>
<index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="New York "/>
<index level1="Brownsville Clinic" level2="arrests and trial"/>
<index level1="politicians" level2="MS on"/>
<index level1="women" level2="freedom and rights of"/>
</headNote>
<docBody>
<head>Politicians vs. Birth Control</head>
<p>Advocates of Birth Control must possess the power to face facts and to analyze them. Only upon
the basis of tested experience and actual scientific knowledge can we overcome the ignorance, the
stupidity and the prejudices which are the only formidable forces standing in our way. Our recent
legislative campaign at <place reg="Albany, NY"> Albany</place>, an account of which may be found on
another page of this number, has revealed in striking fashion the antagonistic attitude of the
typical American politician to the pivotal problem of society today. To expect aid or even
intelligent understanding of Birth Control from the typical Albany politician; to be disappointed
because of the ignorance of these so-called "legislators;" to be discouraged because of their
failure to remove the coercive and criminally obscene insult to American womanhood from the statute
books--this would be to succumb to emotion rather than to profit by the knowledge, the invaluable
knowledge, we have gained from our experience at Albany. The great fact is this: we can expect
nothing of the politician of today. If we must use the weapon of politics to further the progress of
Birth Control, it must be the politics created by ourselves.</p>
<p>When the first Birth Control clinic in <place reg="United States"> America</place> was declared a
"public nuisance," by the courts, we were advised by well-meaning friends that the legal way, the
political way, the legislative way, was the only safe and sane method of propaganda. This has now
been put to the test. And we discover that the successful politician is not only mentally unable to
understand the aim of Birth Control, but, moreover, he himself is the very product of those sinister
forces we are aiming to eradicate from human society.</p>
<p>As manifested in the United States today, current politics is the very outgrowth of overcrowding
and underfeeding: mental and physical. Your successful politician is the demagogue who knows the
best tricks to catch the greatest number of votes. He is the hypnotist of great, docile, submissive,
sheep-like majorities. He is interested in number, not intelligence. Therefore, to expect such
masters who, by hook or crook, ride roughshod into public office or slide into seats of the state
legislature to understand or support a program which aims at the creation of self-reliant,
self-governing independent men and women, would be to neglect one of the most important factors
among the resources of our opponents. But we did at least expect something more among men elected to
public office than the embarrassed giggle of the adolescent, the cynical indecency of the gangster,
in the consideration of a serious sexual and social problem.</p>
<p>Perhaps, moreover, we failed to take into consideration the vast power wielded today by the
politicians in the control and administration of the public charities, hospitals and "correctional"
institutions. Politician and office-holder indirectly benefit through these institutions for the
support and maintenance of the victims of compulsory motherhood. Impartial statistics make this
evident. Exclusive of privately supported industries and charities, New York City alone spends
annually approximately sixteen million dollars to maintain its various departments of charities,
hospitals and "corrections." In 146 of the largest American cities, the total expenditure for the
support of the dependent population amounts annually to no less than fifty millions of dollars.</p>
<p>Our politicians today profit from human misery. They have an interest, direct or indirect, in the
production through uncontrolled fecundity, of the unfit, the underfed, the feebleminded and the
incurably diseased. Their interest, financially, is in the increase of our institution populations,
with their insistent demands for appropriations from the city and state, as well as their unending
appeals to public and private sentimental generosity. Most eugenists dub the victims of out legal
and social barbarism "the unfit." But as <person reg="Bateson, William">William Bateson</person> has
recently shown, we need to revise and re-interpret our definition of the "unfit." The victims are
not the "unfit," but these blind leaders of the blind--the politician, the profiteer, the war-making
patriot, the criminal moralist who is urging men and women to "<q who="BIB"> increase and
multiply</q>." "<q who="BATWI">The crimes of the prison population</q>," declared Professor Bateson
in his recent <person reg="Galton, Francis"> Galton</person> lecture, "<q who="BATWI"> are petty
offences by comparison, and the significance we attach to them is a survival of other days. Felonies
may be great offences locally, but they do not induce catastrophes. The proclivities of the
war-makers are infinitely more dangerous than those of the beings whom from time to time the law may
dub as criminals. <emph rend="italics">Consistent and portentous selfishness, combined with dullness
of imagination are probably just as transmissible as want of self-control, though destitute of the
amiable qualities not rarely associated with the genetic composition of persons of unstable
mind.</emph></q>"</p>
<p>In delegating important powers to near-sighted, unimaginative, politicians and acquisitive
office-grabbers, the American public is submitting, with deplorable docility, to every sort of
injurious and grossly coercive legislation. Laws are passed as penalties for those who dare to
disagree with us. Our passivity in this respect is in effect placing upon the shoulders of the next
generation not merely the helpless victims of indiscriminate and uncontrolled breeding, but the
political parasites who wax so fat on the public charities and "corrections," who, consciously or
unconsciously, aim to foster and uphold this disastrous custom of compulsory motherhood.</p>
<p>How closely bound up with the enfranchisement of the mentally deficient is the deterioration of
American politics and politicians is indicated in <person reg="Ireland, Alleyne">Alleyne
Ireland's</person> recent study of the situation, "<title type="book">Democracy and the Human
Equation.</title>" Mr. Ireland is inevitably driven to the conclusion that there must be some
improvement in the quality of the American voter and the American politician before we can expect
anything of political action. The only hope he discovers on the horizon is eugenics. But eugenics is
futile and impractical, a vague flapping of wings, unless it is allied and strengthened by Birth
Control. Otherwise eugenics can only suggest a cradle competition between the "fit" and the "unfit."
In this mad race in over-population, the fit would very soon become the unfit; and we would be on
the road to a universal imbecility.</p>
<p>Thus we face the interesting possibility--a vision that should give us new strength and coverage:
If politicians cannot and will not help Birth Control, Birth Control must and will improve
politics.</p>
<p>The most amazing aspect of the present situation is to be found in the great overwhelming fact
that the women of America, especially the mothers of America, are demanding the sex hygiene and
education which the practice of Birth Control would bring to them. Letters from the over-burdened
mothers reach us in thousands; typical examples are presented in issues of the <title type="journal">
<rs reg="Birth Control Review">REVIEW</rs></title>. Superficial critics often remark that it is
impossible to carry the message of Birth Control to the women who need it most. This claim is belied
in all the heart-rending appeals from the victims of barbarous laws and outworn prejudices. If these
indomitable and courageous mothers were finally freed from the bondage of compulsory maternity, we
should witness the gradual but certain lifting of the curse of the "unfit" and the subnormal. It is
the pressure, the ceaseless constant pressure upon American womanhood that is productive of the
subnormal and mentally defective. This cursed section of humanity is not a matter of chance. It is
the inevitable result of a pressure upon the normal and healthy, a pressure--or cramping
restriction--that must somewhere find its outlet.</p>
<p>What the reactionary politicians fail to recognize is that human society possesses in itself, if
it were not impeded by outworn customs and barbarous laws, the power of regeneration, of recreation.
More and more evidence is coming to light that the number of enlightened and intelligent women is
increasing. American women are realizing that first and foremost the problem of bringing children
into this world is a personal and physical one. They are refusing to submit any longer to the
self-appointed dictatorship of the politician, who, instead of clearing the way for the great march
of civilization, is attempting to impede progress by defending decrepit statute and writing into the
laws of the land coercive measures.</p>
<p>When women awaken to the necessity of organizing a political method of their own, instead of
relying upon or expecting understanding and help from the man-made brand, the politician as he
expresses himself today will no longer be tolerated, and with the even of self-reliance and
self-government, the race of politicians will, fortunately for humanity, become as extinct as that
of the dinosaur.</p>
<byline>MARGARET SANGER</byline>
</docBody>
</doc>
