<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Printed Article">
<mepHeader>
<prepDate>2003/07/08 SR</prepDate>
<prepDate>2003/07/14 SR</prepDate>
<prepDate>2003-07-28 CH</prepDate>
<prepDate>2014-03-04 CH correct regs</prepDate>
<prepDate>2014-11-13 CH clean regs</prepDate>
<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
<docDate value="1921-01">Jan 1921</docDate>
<docTitle>
<titlePart>Women in Germany</titlePart>
</docTitle>
<idno>msp238951</idno>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl><title type="journal">The Birth Control Review</title>, Jan. 1921, 8-10.</bibl>
<bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Smith College Collections</title>, S70:850</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
<respStmt>
<resp/>
<name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
</respStmt>
</mepHeader>
<headNote resp="MSPP"><p>For an earlier article of the same title, see Birth Control Review, <xref
from="238950">Dec. 1920.</xref></p>
<index level1="Germany" level2="social and economic conditions in"/>
<index level1="feminism and feminists" level2="in Germany"/>
<index level1="Germany" level2="population policies of"/>
<index level1="Germany" level2="birth rate in"/>
<index level1="World War I" level2="MS on"/>
<index level1="World War I" level2="population"/>
<index level1="women" level2="health of"/>
<index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/></headNote>
<docBody>
<head>Women in Germany</head>
<byline>By Margaret Sanger</byline>
<div>
<dateline>
<date value="1920-09-07"/>
<place reg="Dresden, Germany">Dresden</place>
</dateline>
<p>The conditions in this city are somewhat better than in <place reg="Berlin, Germany">
Berlin</place>. The streets are cleaner, the people less hungry looking; the cars not so crowded.
But the working woman is reduced to the function of pack-horse. This morning I saw a young woman,
who could not have been over twenty-five years of age carrying a huge basket strapped to her back;
it horses, carrying produce from country towns to their homes or stores in the cities. They have
become drudge animals in the fields. There are four women to one man taking the place of the truck
and work horses. They nurse their babies beyond two years, to supply the milk which, in the absence
of cows' milk, they hope will keep life in the children.</p>
<p>It was a great pleasure to me to meet that splendid pioneer of the Woman's Movement in
<place>Germany</place>--<person reg="Stritt, Marie">Marie Stritt</person>, a woman of refinement,
culture, with a fine vigorous mind, speaking English with a care and better choice of words then
most well educated Americans. Marie Stritt was a Pacifist in the war. Thousands of Pacifists were
shot. She has been the pioneer in the Birth Control Movement in Germany, and organized the <org
reg="International Neo-Malthusian Conference,1912 (4th)">International Congress of the
Malthusians</org> in Dresden in 1912. She is the editor of the foremost official paper for woman's
suffrage here. She thinks it is not necessary to propagate the idea of Birth Control in Germany now;
she says that the birth rate has fallen so rapidly in the last few years, that there is no need for
spreading knowledge, or encouraging the idea. The organized movement is almost out of existence, but
the knowledge is spreading everywhere.</p>
<p>One of the most interesting achievements of Germany is Dr. <person reg="Hirschfeld, Magnus"
>Magnus Herschfield's</person>
<org>Institute of Sexual Science</org>. It is the only one of its kind in the world. Here is a
beautiful dwelling, with palatial and spacious rooms, which at one time belonged to a member of the
royal family. Since the Revolution it has been turned over to Dr. Herschfield, who has converted it
into a College where one may study all subjects relative to, or treating of the science of sex.
These are various departments, each with specialists in charge, each department equipped with
laboratories and X-rays.</p>
<p>I am delighted to find Dr. Herschfield so well informed on the subject of Birth Control. He is a
personal friend of Dr. <person reg="Rutgers, Johannes">Rutgers</person> of <place reg="Netherlands"
>Holland</place>, through whom he has been kept in touch with the work. There is also the
possibility of the subject of Birth Control taking its place as a department in this Institute. Dr.
Herschfield was most cordial and hospitable, and kindly extended to me an invitation to address an
audience if I would consent to speak in the Institute. As I was leaving Berlin in a few days, it was
impossible to do so, and I greatly regret missing this splendid opportunity of getting the message
before the physicians of Germany.</p>
<p>I am now on my way to <place reg="Munich, Germany"> Munich</place> to get the facts of the birth
strike so generally reported in <place>Europe</place>. Then, on to <place reg="Ravensburg, Germany">
Ravensburg</place> to investigate the clinical preventive which is said to be one hundred per cent,
perfect in safety and harmlessness, and is also reported as having the government's official
sanction.</p>
<p>There are few people in Germany who will not acknowledge that country as overpopulated today.
Everyone knows that, even though two million lives were sacrificed in the war, this deficiency has
been made up by the million and a half inhabitants who were returned to Germany from <place
reg="Alsace-Lorraine, France"> Alsace-Lorraine</place>. Also on the Polish side there was at least
the same number returned to the Fatherland, while hundreds of thousands of men and women were
deported from <place>England</place>, <place>France</place> and <place>Italy</place>, and sent to
the land of their birth. Thousands of them hate Germany--Germany is now a foreign and detested place
to them.</p>
<p>With all the facts of over-population before their eyes; with poverty, overcrowding, lack of
food, mothers starving, children doomed to die in a few years, yet those in Germany elected to guide
the destinies of the millions, will but reluctantly accept the idea of Brith Control for the
masses.</p>
<p>Of course they all accept and practice it themselves--always--but for the working women it is
different. I talked to many of the foremost physicians here, gynecologists and baby specialists.
Surely, I thought, these men, considering the kind of work they do, must have a better understanding
of the actual needs of the country than others. But in this also, I was disappointed. The physicians
are content that woman shall breed; no matter what she suffers, no matter what kind of child she may
bring forth.</p>
<p>I found not one physician, even of those in charge of all the appalling misery of Germany, who
dared to say that Birth Control should be encouraged. I found several, however, who stood for
women's right to have abortions--but for contraceptive advice, NO. "<q who="UNK"> It is knowledge
that is too dangerous,</q>" said one very well known gynecologist to me. He agreed that something
should be done during these years of chaos, and for the next five years to prevent more babies; but
abortion seemed better to him than Birth Control knowledge. Why? Because knowledge to prevent
conception involved woman's freedom. "<q who="UNK"> Once they know how to prevent, they will not go
back to their old ways again,</q>" said the learned gentleman. That is the 'rub' in Germany.</p>
<p>I went into one home where there were ten children living--the oldest was twelve years of age,
and too young to work. The father a locksmith, was out of work; he had been out of work for several
weeks. The family lived on one hundred marks which they received every eight days from the
Unemployment Insurance. This was Saturday; the money was to come on Monday. These children were
huddled together in two rooms, all living, cooking, sleeping there. They had had no breakfast; no
dinner; there was not one crumb or morsel of food in that house. They were waiting for Monday. The
father had gone to the woods to find mushrooms to keep them alive until their money came. Five of
these children had been born since the war began!!!</p>
<p>Many other families were in similar positions. They were all clean, but poverty and starvation
stamped their faces horribly.</p>
<p>The <org reg="Religious Society of Friends (Quakers)">Quakers</org>' food stations--which by the
way the children call "America"--are crowded to their fullest capacity. Only children who are ill
enough, can come for food. Only mothers pregnant over seven months or who are nursing babies under
four months, are allowed food. The spectacle of a nursing mother, or a pregnant mother, bringing her
two or three wee children (not ill enough to be admitted) to share her food is too sad and horrible
to dwell upon. The Quakers have a problem there, they can not put the children out, yet they want
that mother to eat the food herself, for the benefit of the unborn child. </p>
</div>
<div>
<dateline><place reg="Munich, Germany">Munich</place>, <date value="1920-09-11"> Sept. 11,
1920</date>.</dateline>
<p>There is a Birth Strike here. The common sense of the German mothers has caused it. It is not
organized as one was given to believe, but certainly, the women are agreed that their condition is
such that it is impossible for healthy children to be born or reared.</p>
<p>In this city--the most lovely in Germany--there is more life and greater abandon than in the
North. Munich is the <place reg="Paris, France"> Paris</place> of Germany. There is poverty and
hunger here in plenty, but there is more food in the shops, more clothing and greater activity than
in any of the other cities.</p>
<p>This is the city where, during the Revolution, the <place reg="Soviet Union">Soviet
Republic</place> flew its red flag from the housetops for over three weeks. I have met many of the
leading people on both sides of the political arena. The Conservatives claim that the Communists
were not able enough--that they were not capable of handling the situation. On the other hand the
leaders of the Communists claim that they lost because they were not cruel enough. Their
consideration, their ideals, their faith in human brotherly love, cost them their lives and their
liberty. </p>
<p>I talked to Mrs. <person reg="Muhsam, Kreszentia">Mushem</person>-- that <person
reg="Arc, Joan of (St.)">Joan of Arc</person> who, together with her husband, <person
reg="Muhsam, Erich">Erich Mushem</person> and <person reg="Landauer, Gustav">Landau</person>,
inspired the masses to revolution. Landau is dead. He was kicked and clubbed to death by the
<org>White Guard</org>. That gentle soul so believed in the good of man, that he talked and pleaded
with the soldiers to be brothers, and urged them not to take life. They answered him in Prussian
methods as they answered <person reg="Liebnecht, Karl">Karl Liebnecht</person> and <person
reg="Luxemburg"> Rosa Luxemburg</person>. Then, having finished with Landau they went to find Erich
and Mrs. Mushem. Machine guns were used to wreck their apartment; not satisfied that they did not
come out to escape, the <org reg="German Army">White Guard</org> stormed the place, breaking down
doors, etc. Fortunately, both Erich Mushem and his wife had been previously arrested and were safely
in jail. Erich Mushem is still in prison--his wife was released later.</p>
<p>There is bitterness in the breasts of the "Reds" because they were tricked and fooled by their
own faith in humanity. They say this has taught them a valuable lesson, and they shall not forget
it.</p>
<p>No wonder that the middle and upper classes will not give up their guns--they know this
bitterness, and they know too that the class struggle is not settled, even tho the Red Flag is not
flying over Munich. It is said that the upper and middle classes are prepared to make their escape
at a moment's notice' they have peasants' boots and costumes ready and plans and money put aside for
the emergency which all claim is bound to come.</p>
<p>I talked to the <person reg="Unknown">Medical Chief of the Soviet</person>--a well-known
practicing physician. He was tremendously interested in the subject of Birth Control. He told me
that women in <place reg="Bavaria, Germany"> Bavaria</place> are determined to stop having babies.
He has given practical information to thousands, and would have established clinics all over
Bavaria, had the Soviet Republic remained in power.</p>
<p>I forgot to say, that in Berlin the <org reg="Free Worker's Union of Germany">Syndicaliste</org>
has physicians who give lectures on the practical side of birth control to the women of that
organization.</p>
<p>It was only when physicians were allied with such radical organizations as the Syndicaliste that
they dared to come out for the practical side of Birth Control. I was glad to find these men far
more sympathetic and enthusiastic for the use of contraceptive methods than they were for abortions.
In this they differed from the conservative physicians, who fear to give woman knowledge which will
free her.</p>
<p>I visited hospitals in this city, and found them lacking in the simple and most ordinary articles
of decency. No soap--no cod-liver oil, no rubber sheets to protect the beds--no linen to give clean
bedding as required--and even the babies must be all day in wet napkins, because of the inadequate
supply for the proper changes. This has given rise to skin trouble, and the poor little waifs are a
sad, miserable lot. It would be a great kindness to let them die outright, I believe.</p>
<p>Another dreadful thing, which gave me the nightmare for weeks, was to see the children's little
mouths covered with horrible sores: and upon inquiring as to why this was so, and why so prevalent,
I was told it came from the meat and milk of the cattle suffering from "mouth disease."</p>
<p>The kind charitable folk may applaud the work which is keeping down the infant mortality rate in
Germany, but I am not certain that their benevolence is so wise as it may seem. The old fashioned
warrior who entered with sword and killed his victim outright has my respect after witnessing the
"Peace" conditions of Germany.</p>
<p>The <org reg="Unknown">Military Party</org> uses everything as "<q who="UNK">I told you so.</q>"
It accuses the Socialists of bringing defeat upon the country. There is also the general feeling
that had <place reg="United States"> America</place> not entered the war, a juster peace would have
been made--for then none would have been victors and none defeated. This they say would have meant a
lasting peace.</p>
<p>There seems to be no hatred towards Americans or the English, but only towards the French. All
foreigners are made to pay a hundred per cent above the native price in hotels, and thus to prevent
an influx of people who could easily live well at a small cost, owing to the difference in
exchange.</p>
<p>When I asked one physician what the doctors were doing to help tubercular women from becoming
pregnant, he replied, "<q who="UNK">for those who can afford it we advise articles of contraception,
but there is no use in advising women to purchase these articles who cannot buy bread, so such women
are usually aborted</q>" (legally).</p>
<p>I asked him if the medical profession, as a whole, was doing anything to prevent bringing into
the world those children whose backs were so weak that they could not sit up straight, with bones
too soft to hold the weight of the body, etc. His answer was "<q who="UNK"> they are doing their
best to cope with conditions as they find them. It is not <emph rend="italica">their</emph> work to
change conditions</q>."</p>
<p>Fortunately there is a very large number of women all over Germany whom Nature has protected from
pregnancy. The lack of fats and other foods necessary to the system, caused the suppression of the
menses. These facts were forcibly brought forth by Prof. <person reg="Kraus, H. J.">H. J.
Kraus</person>, Director of the <org reg="Charité-–Universitätsmedizin Berlin">Medical Clinique of
Charities</org> in Berlin, in his address before the <org>Congress of the United Medical
Societies</org>, December 18, 1918. Some of these women have become normal again, but thousands of
them have been made sterile.</p>
<p>The conditions of women and children are appalling. Thousands are suffering from tuberculosis,
and are in need of foodstuffs which, unless they soon have them, are doomed to death before the
winter begins.</p>
<p>The same official barriers exist in Germany as exist in England and the United States. Those who
are closely in touch with these suffering, overburdened, tortured women, hold from them the
knowledge which would best help them. The working women here--like those in England--<emph
rend="italics">want</emph> contraceptive advice. They ask their neighbors, their nurses, their
friends, everywhere they seek. Anything they try. But those best qualified to help them hold
off.</p>
<p>Is this refusal to advise over-burdened women against pregnancy caused by selfishness, I am
asked. Or is it a sub-conscious realization on the part of the medical profession that it will
affect their economic position in the community? Or is it a deeply-rooted conviction that it is
against the laws of <name type="deity">God</name>?</p>
<p>I asked these questions of a well-known man in London today, who answered, "<q who="UNK"> I think
it is the <name type="deity">Devil</name></q>."</p>
</div>
</docBody>
</doc>
