<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011-08-05 CN</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2013-04-23 CH Proofread</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2013-04-29 AW Corrected</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-07-02 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1953-08-17">17 Aug 1953</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>The History of the Birth Control Movement in the English-Speaking
                World</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp238954</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S72:0834</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="NIEFR">Nietzsche, Frederich</name>
            <name id="SANST">Sanger, Stuart</name>
            <name id="SANGR">Sanger, Grant</name>
            <name id="WELHG">Wells, H. G.</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>Sanger gave this speech at the <org
                reg="International Conference on Planned Parenthood, Fourth (Stockholm)">Fourth
                International Conference on Planned Parenthood</org> in <place>Stockholm,
                Sweden</place>. This meeting was sponsored by the <org>International Planned
                Parenthood Federation</org>.</p>
        <p>For other versions see <title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S72:816, 822, 827, 832,
            830, and 849.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="international"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="history of"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="autobiographical"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <opener>Fourth International Conference on Planned Parenthood, Stockholm, <dateline><date
                    value="1953-08-00">1953, <add>(August)</add></date></dateline></opener>
        <head>THE HISTORY OF THE BIRTH CONTROL MOVEMENT IN THE ENGLISH-SPEAKING WORLD</head>
        <byline>by <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>.</byline>
        <p>
            <person reg="Ottesen-Jensen, Elise">Mrs. Ottesen-Jensen</person>, distinguished guests,
            friends, and co-workers, this is a very great occasion; it is, indeed, one of the most
            magnificent audiences and sessions of congress that we have ever had. When I think of
            the title that has been given to me tonight, I shudder at the thought that I am to speak
            on the history of the birth control movement throughout the English-speaking world.
            That’s only a hundred years ago, so should I stand here all night and all day and speak
            for one week I couldn’t begin to cover the history and the story. </p>
        <p> It reminds me very much of another compliment that I once received, from one of my sons
            who was then in <org reg="Yale University">college</org>, and the <person
                reg="Sanger, Stuart">older boy</person> said to the <person reg="Sanger, Grant"
                >younger one</person> who was graduating from <org reg="Princeton University"
                >Princeton</org>, “<q who="SANST">What is going to be, what do you think you will
                have for your thesis?</q>”, and he looked a little perplexed and he said, “<q
                who="SANGR">Well, I’d really like to have an unusual subject -- the biology of
                death</q>.” And the older son looked at him and said, “<q who="SANST">Fine,
                wonderful, why don’t you do it?</q>” He said, “<q who="SANGR">Well, there’s too much
                research to do, I don’t believe I’ll have time</q>.” He said, “<q who="SANST">Time,
                research -- have one good hour’s talk with mother</q>.” Naturally, I slunk to the
            floor at such a compliment of having one good hour’s talk with mother. This is very much
            the way I feel to-night with the compliment of our Chairman that I could cover this
            great subject of the history of the movement which is over 100 years old.</p>
        <p> I’m reminded of the signs in the <place>United States</place>. As you go through from
            the East to the West you see signs -- “<q who="UNK">If you drink, don’t drive; if you
                drive, don’t drink</q>”. Very good signs too, but it reminds me of Mr. <person
                reg="Wells, H. G.">H.G. Wells</person>, when we gave a banquet for him in <place
                reg="New York, NY">New York</place> some years ago, and he was rather nervous about
            speaking, and he said, “<q who="WELHG">Speakers shouldn’t write, it spoils their
                techniques, and writers shouldn’t speak without copious notes before them, otherwise
                they go off into this air</q>.” And I’ve often thought of that, and so to-night
            without copious notes I may go off into thin air but I’ll try not to go for hot air. </p>
        <p> I think it’s a generally accepted thing to-day with most of the enlightened people of
            the world that the idea of birth control is a mature, practical subject that can solve
            many of our family, personal and even civic problems in the nation. It’s not generally
            recognized that the United States was also instrumental in stirring up this question
            from the practical point of view. </p>
        <p>You all know that it was 1800, or perhaps 1799, that the Reverend <person
                reg="Malthus, Thomas Robert">Robert Malthus</person> wrote his famous book <title
                type="book">ESSAYS ON POPULATION</title>. Well, that had a great stirring of the
            mind in <place>England</place> but mostly, it remained on the shelves to grow dusty, but
            about that time, in the nineteenth century, however, a great many other of the English
            brains and thoughtful people, like <person reg="Carlyle, Thomas">Carlyle</person>, and
            the different people -- <person reg="Mill, John Stuart">Mills</person>, and <person
                reg="Place, Francis">Francis Place</person>, and a number of them that were good
            speakers, all were interested and excited, and gave out little booklets and pamphlets
            about this question of limiting the size of the family. </p>
        <p>In our own country, we had two Presidents of the United States who also advocated the
            same thing -- <person reg="Jefferson, Thomas">Thomas Jefferson</person> and President
                <person reg="Madison, James">Madison</person>, but perhaps nothing became so
            practical and got out of the theoretical era as it did when the two famous free
            thinkers, <person reg="Bradlaugh, Charles">Charles Bradlaugh</person> and <person
                reg="Besant, Annie">Annie Besant</person> took a case out of a bookseller’s hands
            who was indicted for selling a book that had been written forty years before by a Doctor
                <person reg="Knowlton, Charles">Knowlton</person> in <place reg="Boston, MA">Boston,
                Massachusetts</place>. The bookseller had sold this book for perhaps a couple of
            shillings, and was indicted, and was sentenced, and I think not even fined, but was
            supposed to serve a certain term in jail. There was in that country at the time a great
            rallying of free thought and free press, and Annie Besant, who later became a
            theosophist, <person reg="Blavatsky, Helena">Madame Blevatsky</person>, and gave up all
            her ideas of birth control, she was a brilliant speaker and orator, and she with
            Bradlaugh decided to take this book and challenge the law, and for three days they sat
            in state and sold all these books. They had 288,000 of this book reprinted and sold, and
            defied the British law as to free press. </p>
        <p> Well, that practically shook the foundations of England I’ll tell you. And they won out;
            they won out on a technicality, and they had courage. And from that day until this,
                <place reg="Great Britain">Britain</place>, or the <place>United Kingdom</place>,
            has had no trouble about this question of contraception, or limiting or controlling the
            size of the family. </p>
        <p> Now, when we come in, with one of the pioneers, Charles Knowlton in Boston having
            written this book. I’ve never been able to find it, and I never know just exactly how
            much information he gave in it because when Bradlaugh and Besant re-wrote the book it
            was more on population and the general theory of Malthus than it was the practical
            indications which I was sure that Knowlton must have put in his book. Nevertheless, Dr.
            Knowlton went to prison, and no-one helped him because at that time such ideas were
            considered blasphemous and obscene. So what happened to Knowlton I don’t know, none of
            us know much about him, but the fact that this book of his forty years later had gone
            round the world........</p>
        <p> In the United States it was considered that rather a great deal of immortality was
            coming in in books and in pamphlets from <place>France</place>, with all due respect to
            that wonderful country, and so one man, named <person reg="Comstock, Anthony">Anthony
                Comstock</person>, a horrible old man, went to <org reg="United States Congress"
                >Congress</org> and frightened the lives out of the Congressmen, sort of intimated
            that they were all immoral, and they wouldn’t dare oppose him in this law that he was
            going to have set up. A <name reg="United States Penal Law, Section 211" type="law"
                >Federal law</name> was placed upon the Statute books which made it a crime and five
            years in prison and $5,000 fine, or both, to send any book or any article through the
            United States mails or common-carriers which gave any information on contraception or
            told anyone where it could be obtained. He also went before some other State courts, or
            the State legislatures and had this law put upon the statute, but not many, a few.</p>
        <p> Well, this was the situation when I came upon the scene very much later. But Comstock
            had been rather a laughing stock because he was so puritan that he arrested a whole
            crowd of people looking in a window at a beautiful picture of a little girl bathing in a
            brook with the sun shining through the trees about her lovely body, about eight or ten
            years old. And people were so entranced with this beautiful picture that he arrested all
            of them for looking in the window. Well, fortunately, our reporters have a sense of
            humour and a sense of justice, and they played this up pretty vigorously to the
            amusement of the population and the people. And, of course, the people were freed and so
            was the man, the <person reg="Unidentified">bookseller</person>, who had this picture in
            the window. </p>
        <p> Now, this pointed a finger toward Comstock and the other things that he was doing with
            the laws. Congress gave to him the sole right of opening any letter, or any box of any
            parcel that came from abroad which he might think had any so-called obscenity or
            blasphemy within, and that was the situation when I, as one working in the nursing field
            in the lower part of New York, dealing with people, with women mostly, obstetrical
            cases, came upon the scene. It was pretty difficult to be happy with yourself when you
            saw the things that happened in those homes -- children unwanted, children beaten,
            cuffed, pushed around, clubbed, tied down, pushed out into the streets, no place for
            them; mothers nervous, anxious, breathing a sigh of relief and thank-<name type="deity"
                >God</name> when a baby was born dead; men frantic, cross irritable; babies
            increasing, increasing, increasing year after year; women with the only thing they could
            do was to have an abortion or to interrupt a pregnancy, and if they couldn’t get a quack
            doctor to do it, they attempted to do it themselves, and day after day I saw these women
            taken off to hospitals, many of them never to come back. You saw all of these miseries,
            these wretched miseries, unnecessary miseries in a great country like we felt that we
            were. It was recorded in the year 1912 and 13 that there were 250,000 mothers, or women,
            who died mainly form the causes of pregnancy, and it was estimated that there were
            approximately two million abortions but, of course, there was no record of them, but
            from the results and from the drugs and so forth that they could find they said it ran
            about that. </p>
        <p> I tried to tell or to see what could be done but really, I practically knew nothing much
            myself and when you asked the doctors they said, “<q who="UNK">Don’t touch that, you’ll
                go to jail or to a penitentiary if you touch that subject.</q>” And when a <person
                reg="Sachs, Sadie">woman</person> would ask a doctor what to do so she wouldn’t have
            another abortion and she wouldn’t go through this great strain again, he’d shrug his
            shoulders and say, “<q who="UNK">Tell <person reg="Sachs, Jake">Jake</person> to sleep
                on the roof</q>”. That was the answer that these desperate mothers received from
            their best friend, the family physician. Now, it wasn’t because the physician didn’t
            feel this, but here were these laws which kept them in ignorance, in utter ignorance, in
            that country. </p>
        <p>So when I came upon the scene, I decided after all this that I didn’t want to live and do
            this work unless I could do something constructive and something about this horrible
            question, the waste of women’s lives; pregnancy year after year; the waste of
            motherhood, the waste of womanhood, the waste of childhood and family life. And I felt
            that I simply would not live and be happy to live unless something was done. So I
            decided to give the whole thing up and start in to do something about it, and of course
            fools go where angels fear to tread. Someone said, when I started a little papers called
                <title type="journal">THE WOMAN REBEL</title> that it was the first unveiled head,
            woman’s head, raised in America, and someone else facetiously said, “<q who="UNK"
                >Margaret Sanger came upon the scene with three children in her arms and a wild look
                in her eye</q>”, and I am sure I had the wild look, and which makes me think just a
            moment about the three children. </p>
        <p>The other day, a very charming young <person reg="unidentified">reporter</person> was
            asking questions. I was telling him something about the work, and he said, “<q who="UNK"
                >May I ask you a very delicate question?</q>” And I said, “Yes, yes, you’re going to
            ask me how old I am.” “<q who="UNK">No, I’m going to ask you if you’ve ever had any
                children</q>”, and I said, “Yes, I’ve had three”, and he said, “<q who="UNK">Were
                you married?</q>” So I was married, and I had three children, and then I began to
            confront these Comstock laws which had terrorised most of our thinking people. </p>
        <p> This little magazine that I had was stopped by the mails, forbidden to go through the
            mails, because I said it should be done, some information should be had, not that I was
            giving it in that paper. </p>
        <p> I finally gave up and went to France to see what was being done there, and came back
            with a little information. As you know, the French have always had what they call a
            small-family system and they believed definitely, not so much in control as limitation;
            they believed in family limitation. </p>
        <p> It’s a long story and I won’t take too much time to tell you, but, finally, the time
            came that I was going to try to arouse the nation as to this point of view and what to
            do about it, about this situation. And then I looked over the history from the time of
            Malthus to see what names -- because it’s very important to have a proper name for a
            good idea -- and I just wish I could read to you, perhaps I can for a minute, some of
            the names that they tried to bring this idea to the public. Of course, first, was the
            Malthus <title type="book">ESSAYS ON POPULATION</title>, and then <title type="book">THE
                ELEMENTS OF SOCIAL SCIENCE</title> by one of the <person reg="Drysdale, George R."
                >Drysdales</person>, and that book was translated into some thirty different
            languages, and went round the world for how many years and still perhaps is going round
            the world. I don’t know how much good it has done. and then there’s <title type="book"
                >MORAL PHYSIOLOGY</title>, another book, and then <title type="book">THE FRUITS OF
                PHILOSOPHY</title>, that was by Knowlton of Boston, Massachusetts that caused all
            the trouble. Then Francis Place, I understood it was attributed that he had the
            diabolical handbill in which he gave some information to women of what to do. And then
            came <title type="book">THE NEW MOTHERHOOD</title>, and then <title type="journal">THE
                NEW GENERATION</title>, and then <title type="journal">HUMAN REGENERATION</title>;
                <title type="journal">NEO-MALTHUSIAN</title>; <title type="book">FAMILY
                LIMITATION</title>, which I started on, and I wasn’t happy with that. And then a few
            of us got together and thought of “family control”, well, that wasn’t it; “conception
            control”, and finally, out of the blue came “birth control”. Now I want to say that the
            American newspaperman, you know, when you’ve got an idea you’ve got to say something
            snappy, it’s got to take, and “birth control” took. All these other names “Malthusian”,
            “Neo-Malthusian”, “New Motherhood” wouldn’t do at all, but “birth control” stuck, and
            there was a reason for it. It had a definition with it, and I consider that while we’ve
            given that up now and gone on to “planned parenthood”, “family planning”, and so-forth,
            which are very good names, at that time it was very important, for the American public,
            to say what this idea was, and it was “the conscious control of the birthrate by means
            that prevent the conception of life”. And we emphasised over and over again “control,
            not limitation”, “prevent and not interfere with life after conception has started”. And
            then I always liked to add “the conscious”, “the conscious”, “the awareness of what you
            are doing” because I believe that that is important with intelligent people to be aware
            of what you are thinking and what plans you have. </p>
        <p> Well, this definition, and this movement spread really like wild-fire. It went faster
            than most people would ever believe. I think perhaps one reason was that I was a mother
            with these three children and not just a suffragette, and also that I did know what I
            was talking about because I had been in the nursing field, and I knew these conditions,
            and I could tell them from firsthand. It wasn’t a theory with me, it was a practical
            side of life, and no-one could doubt the seriousness of your feeling and of your
            knowledge. </p>
        <p>There was an arrest, the Federation Law, of course, stopped the going on of this little
            magazine, or rather paper, that I had. Never the less, they had so many thousands and
            thousands of letters of protest and telegrams that the <person
                reg="Clayton, Henry Delamar, Jr.">Judge</person> just simply couldn’t even read
            them. Now this just happened, it was just one of those things that springs up with
            people that are ......; sympathetic people that want to help, and believe that you are
            doing something which is right, that they would like to do themselves. So their
            expression was to send a word to the Judge that this was a wrong thing to arrest or to
            imprison this woman who was trying to help mothers. And so, of course, the case was just
            dismissed and we hadn’t got any further than before. </p>
        <p>Those laws are still on the Statute book although I spent seven years trying to get them
            changed, and the best thing that we could do, through our attorney, <person
                reg="Pilpel, Harriet F.">Mrs. Pilpel</person> -- I wish I could find her here -- who
            was one of our attorneys who were able to get a decision through the Courts which did
            allow the medical profession to send articles or literature, or supplies through the
            mails and common-carriers, but we never got it through the legislature, through
            Congress, and just before I came away I was told that the <org
                reg="International Conference on Planned Parenthood, Third (Bombay)">Proceedings of
                the <place reg="Bombay, India">Bombay</place> Conference</org> had been held up in
                <place reg="Washington DC">Washington</place>, 300 copies of the proceedings of
            scientists, distinguished men and women, who attended this Conference; a wonderful
            message from Prime Minister <person reg="Nehru, Jawaharlal">Nehru</person>, but there
            were some chapters, or some papers on contraception and its technique. Well, we’ll have
            a wonderful fight when we get back to get those books. </p>
        <p>As a matter of fact, most of the pioneers in the United States who have done this work
            have been arrested, have been fined, jailed. And I had a very short sentence of only
            thirty days, nothing compared to some of the others. One <person reg="Unidentified"
                >man</person>, over seventy years old, had three years just breaking hard rock or
            something of the kind in one of the prisons in the Middle West, in <place
                reg="Chicago, IL">Chicago</place>, because he brought out a <title type="journal"
                >EUGENICS REVIEW</title>. (Where’s Dr. <person reg="Blacker, C. P."
            >Blacker</person>, who is the Secretary of the <org>Eugenics Society</org>?)</p>
        <p> So you can see what we have gone through with our laws. We’ve had a tussle to awaken
            people to these laws. It’s easy enough to put laws on the Statute books but it’s almost
            impossible ever to get them repealed. </p>
        <p> Nevertheless, after my visit to <place reg="Netherlands">Holland</place> looking for
            this Holy Grail, of where I could find some simple contraceptive, something that could
            be used by these wretched mothers. To my great amazement in Holland I found that there
            for a long number of years these little modest clinics had been going on with nurses or
            midwives, and they were giving contraceptive information and supplies to the mothers.
            And in the study of the first clinic -- Dr. <person reg="Jacobs, Aletta">Aletta
                Jacobs</person> who established it many years ago, within a radius of five miles of
            where she practised the whole conditions of the families, mostly working people, were so
            enormously changed that you had to believe that the practical part of this work would
            bring wonderful results. So, of course, I spent some time there; fortunately, I had to
            spend some time there because there was a blockade, there was a German blockade of
            Holland. So I studied this for about three months. And I came back to the United States
            with a new feeling and a great hope, because it was not a question of broadcasting this
            information in pamphlets or in booklets, but the privacy of the physician and the
            patient, the woman to the doctor, and it had to be from the kind of methods that we’re
            using now in the western world, that they had in Holland. It had to be someone who had
            knowledge of anatomy and physiology, and that would be a member of the medical
            profession. And so I set up a clinic in a very poor district of <place
                reg="Brooklyn, NY">Brooklyn</place> to show that this was what we wanted to do. It
            was a challenge to the <place>New York</place> State law, and I told the <person
                reg="Cropsey, James C.">District Attorney</person> what we were doing and that we
            expected to have a decision. </p>
        <p> Well, we were all arrested and <person reg="Byrne, Ethel Higgins">one went on a hunger
                strike</person>, and I, we were just about getting into the war, so I spent thirty
            very interesting days in the <org reg="Queens Count Penitentiary">penitentiary</org> and
            learned a great deal about most of the inmates of the penitentiary. They averaged eight
            children, all of them, and were just the kind of children that I saw in the slums where
            I had worked, except that they were grown-up and going to jail and to the penitentiary.
            And so we got a decision, we got a decision in New York State that -- of course, I was
            not a practising physician and had I been it would have been different, and so my
            conviction was perfectly proper and legal -- but any physician lawfully practising could
            give such information for the cure of prevention of disease. That wasn’t quite what we
            wanted but, nevertheless, doctors have their own way of analysing and interpreting the
            cure and prevention of disease, and this was a very important decision because on that
            decision of one State the other States have since sort of folded up and have gone on
            with clinics. We had at one time over 600 of these private birth control clinics. Since
            the war, which took many of the doctors away, I think that now we have somewhere in the
            500 region. these are all private clinics mostly, and they are staffed by physicians,
            medical practitioners and nurses, and they have very high standards. Dr. <person
                reg="Stone, Abraham">Stone</person> who is the Medical Director of our <org
                reg="Margaret Sanger Research Bureau">Bureau</org>, that was the first one started.
            There I think that we claim about 150,000 records and women that have been coming back
            to us through the years. </p>
        <p> We know now what birth control can really do. It’s no longer a theory, we know what it
            will do for the family, for the mother, and for the community. I think that there’s
            practically no doubt now of what it will do, except we haven’t gone far down enough, we
            haven’t gone down to the lower area of parenthood because we’ve not simple enough
            methods. The methods that we have now are technical and, as I said, mean that a
            physician must advise, and those poorest women with seven or eight children they can’t
            come to the clinics, you’ve got to go to them. And we have got to have a cheap, simple,
            harmless contraceptive that can be given to these people in the slums, in the jungles,
            in every place throughout the world if we really are going to make this work effective. </p>
        <p> I firmly believe that one of the first and most important efforts of this Conference, of
            all of us when we get back to our homes and back to our work, is to put all our efforts
            on research so that there will be a simple cheap contraceptive, to perhaps immunise the
            ovum -- I believe that that will be the safest thing and the thing that in the long run
            will be the best. Secondly, I believe that we should do something definite about making
            our officials responsible to the community, to our civilization, for allowing the
            breeding and multiplication of diseased families. Parents that we know and that the
            physicians know and our public officials know, and our officers in all the institutions
            know that these people have diseases, ......... and transmissible. They are allowed to
            go home on parole and what do they do but leave a pregnant wife usually at home. Our
            institutions are bursting at the seams with people who are mental defectives, morons,
            unhealthy, diseased people, and no-one seems to be responsible; no-one seems to demand
            of our officials that they ought to protect such people and the State; no-one seems to
            demand that they do something about this. And my own experience has been that some of
            these very poorest people who are practically morons, they say, “<q who="UNK">What can I
                do? I’m not right, my children aren’t right, but what can I do?</q>” She was out to
            work and she tied two or three children to keep them away from the stove until she came
            back at the end of the day, and those children are in line to go to one of the
            institutions just as soon as there’s an opportunity and another annex built to that
            institution.</p>
        <p> These are rather bad things to tell you about the United States, but nevertheless that’s
            why we’re in this work, that’s why we’re battling as we have battled for years, and
            eventually we’re going to win, but I think that all of us, what we want to do is to give
            a new outlook, you might say an inspiration to the great responsibility of motherhood. I
            believe it should be considered a noble assignment, a mutual responsibility, and I think
            that it is a great responsibility; it is really a great assignment, to bring into the
            world a human being and to help it fulfil its physical, mental and spiritual destiny.
            There’s an Indian saying, “<q who="NIEFR">Build thou beyond thyself but first be sure
                that thou thyself are strong and wholesome in body and mind</q>”, and that’s how I
            think we all have to think of ourselves in this great work, that we must be strong and
            wholesome in our attitude, in our devotion to this work, because it’s a great cause; it
            will live beyond our days and our children’s children’s children’s day, as a great
            constructive piece of work, and I believe that we are creating the structure that will
            eventually be the foundation for world peace.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
