<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Unpublished speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2010/03/02 AC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2010/03/18 CH proof</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2013-11-19 CH add reference to similar version.</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-13 EK clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1935-03-14">14 Mar 1935</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Family Planning</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp239180</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Papers Microfilm Edition, Smith Collection
                    Collections</title></bibl>
            <bibl>S71:0723</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person> delivered this
            radio speech on March 14, 1935 on <place reg="Boston, MA">Boston</place> radios station
                <org>WEEI</org>. For a very similar version broadcast on <place
                reg="Indianapolis, IN">Indianapolis</place> radio, on March 4, 1935, see <emph
                rend="italics">MSM</emph> S71:733.</p>
        <index level1="family size" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="family planning"/>
        <index level1="family size" level2="men and"/>
        <index level1="mentally disabled and diseased"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="health of"/>
        <index level1="poverty" level2="family size and"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="infant"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="maternal"/>
        <index level1="Massachusetts"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="federal"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>

        <p>Friends of the Radio: I want to talk to the mothers of <place>Massachusetts</place> this
            evening about family planning. By this I do not mean the planning you already do
            preparing the food, clothing and comforts in your household. I mean family planning
            which include the spacing of births and the regulation of the number of children to the
            family income.</p>
        <p> Every normal woman wants children. When she does not want them she should wait until she
            does; but there is a vast difference between a woman’s desire to have two, three or four
            children that she can adequately take care of, and the dread of having a large family of
            ten or twelve, knowing she cannot provide for their education or welfare.</p>
        <p> Scientific knowledge of birth control will help her. Remember that birth control means
            to <emph rend="underlined">prevent</emph> , <emph rend="underlined">not to
                destroy</emph>. It does not mean to interfere with life after it has begun. This is
            not necessary.</p>
        <p> “<q who="UNK">Prevention is better than cure</q>” is an old adage rightly applied in
            family planning. Every mother should have knowledge to help her do this. The father
            should have a right to say <emph rend="underlined">how many</emph> he can support and
            the mother should say when they should be born. But first, every mother has a right to
            consider <emph rend="underlined">her own health</emph> and the <emph rend="underlined"
                >health of her children</emph> in arranging for the number of children she plans to
            have. Again, they must be made in consideration of the husband’s earning powers and of
            the standards of living that the parents wish to maintain. If the father’s wages remain
            the same and babies continue to arrive year after year, the father soon gets
            discouraged, what with bills for nurses, hospitals, x-rays, specialists, for adenoid and
            tonsil operations, dentists and numerous other bills for the mother and the children,
            the father soon feels the burden which falls too heavily upon his already bent
            shoulders, even when he is fortunate enough to have an average paying job.</p>
        <p> There are also other conditions both physical and economic where parents should postpone
            the arrival of the baby until these conditions are changed. <emph rend="underlined"
                >1st</emph> and <emph rend="underlined">most important</emph> is; wherever there is
            transmissible disease which affects either the man or the woman, such as insanity,
            feeble-mindedness, epilepsy or venereal diseases. It is unfair to children to be born of
            parents where these diseases can be passed on to the unborn child. 2nd. <emph
                rend="underlined">The second</emph> condition is where the mother has tuberculosis
            or a disease of the heart or kidneys. Her health is directly affected when pregnancy
            takes place, and women often die of these diseases because of the complications which
            pregnancy causes. She should recover from these ailments <emph rend="underlined"
                >before</emph> she brings a child into the world.</p>
        <p> 3rd. The third is, that even a healthy mother should plan to space the births of
            children from two to three years, in order to regain her strength and vitality and plan
            to prepare for the birth of the next child that she may wish to have; and <emph
                rend="underlined">4th</emph> the fourth is the economic factor. Every sensible man
            or woman knows the hardships endured by children when they are born into grinding
            poverty. Millions of parents are at present married and anxious about the welfare of
            their living children. 11,000,000 people are still unemployed; 4,000,000 families are
            depending on public relief for a mere existence. It is not fair to the children, born or
            unborn, or to these mothers, to keep from parents scientific information which would
            enable them to prevent the coming of more children until those conditions are
            bettered.</p>
        <p> Federal laws were passed by <org reg="United States Congress">Congress</org> 62 years
            ago. These laws have operated to keep poor mothers of this country in absolute ignorance
            of such knowledge. We are fighting to change these laws. We want hospitals, clinics,
            public health agencies and members of the medical profession to help parents obtain
            clean, harmless, safe and reliable birth control information to enable them to have only
            the number of children they want and can bring up as a credit to the parents and the
            Nation.</p>
        <p> These obsolete Federal laws have worked a <emph rend="underlined">tremendous</emph>
            hardship on the motherhood of this nation. It is the poorest mother who has paid the
            penalty of ignorance. She has paid for her ignorance in ill health; in infant mortality,
            in maternal mortality, she has paid for it in over-crowding in slums, in unemployment
            and in child labor. Mothers have paid the price by living in constant fear and anxiety;
            fear of the coming of another child that could not be fed or cared for on the husband’s
            wage. It is this army of mothers who are now on relief. They have paid and are still
            paying the price of ignorance of birth control. These are the forgotten women. They are
            too poor to have influence with Congressman, they are too weak to rebel against their
            own conditions and they cry out for us to help.</p>
        <p> A few weeks ago a young mother came to me. She was only 21 years old. She was already
            the mother of five children, the youngest baby just three months. Her husband hadn’t had
            any work for two years. She did all her own housework and weighed only 90 pounds. They
            tried to live on five dollars a week, but what she wanted most was to be able to keep
            her family together and information by which she would not have to have more. Hers was a
            tragic pathetic case and there are millions like her.</p>
        <p> The nation is paying for this ignorance in human misery and the spread of social and
            transmissible diseases, it is paying for it in the general lowering of the standards of
            living, paying for it in out differential birth rate, in national unemployment. We are
            paying for it in ever <emph rend="underlined">mounting taxes</emph> and a <emph
                rend="underlined">condition of chaos</emph> which threatens to undermine our
            economic, social and cultural institutions upon which our civilization has been founded.
            Our population has increased 22,000,000 since 1920 and we continue to increase over 1
            and 1/2 millions a year.</p>
        <p> If you are in sympathy with the work I am doing, help me change our laws of
            Massachusetts, write to me in care of <org reg="radio station">Station WEEI</org>. We
            have petitions that we wish to present to the <personRef
                reg="Roosevelt, Franklin Delano">President of the United States</personRef>. We are
            asking him to help the mothers of the nation to free themselves from the hardships of
            enslaved maternity. Help the mothers of this nation to help themselves through the
            knowledge of birth control. </p>
        <p>
            <add rend="handwritten">Delivered over Station WEEI Thurs. March 14th 1935</add></p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
