<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
<mepHeader>
<prepDate>2003/07/22 SR</prepDate>
<prepDate>2014-03-04 CH correct regs</prepDate><prepDate>2014-11-18 CH clean more</prepDate>
<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
<docDate value="1923-09"> Sep 1923</docDate>
<docTitle>
<titlePart>The Vision of George Drysdale</titlePart>
</docTitle>
<idno>msp239148</idno>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl><title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title>, Sept. 1923, 225-227.</bibl>
<bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Smith College Collections</title> S70:1016.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
<respStmt>
<resp/>
<name id="DRYGE">Drysdale, George</name>
<name id="FRESI">Freud, Sigmund</name>
<name id="GER">German</name>
</respStmt>
</mepHeader>
<headNote resp="MSPP"><p>This article is the third in a four-part series of the same title. For the
preceding articles, see <xref from="225187">July 1923</xref>, <xref from="219520">August
1923</xref>; for final article see <xref from="2111447">October 1923</xref>.</p>
<index level1="Drysdale, George"/>
<index level1="sex education"/>
<index level1="birth control" level2="psychological benefits of"/>  
</headNote>
<docBody>
<head>The Vision of George Drysdale</head>
<byline>By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></byline>
<p>The revelation in modern psychology, for which we are mostly indebted to <person
reg="Freud, Sigmund">Sigmund Freud</person>, is marked by the shifting emphasis and interest from
the intellectual to the instinctive, from the descriptive to the behavioristic. It is based upon the
application of scientific determination to the mental sphere. It tends to become more and more
physiological and biological. It reveals the human mind as subject to natural automatic processes,
with sex as the unconscious dynamic and motivating force in all the more important phases of human
behavior. <person reg="Drysdale, George">Drysdale</person> was not merely a vague precursor of this
modern point of view. Though his contribution in this field is slight, he realized the absolute
interdependence of bodily and mental health, and cried out for a creative and illuminating
psychology which might free individuals from their invisible chains. It was because of his
insistence that this realm must be studied as scientifically as the human body, and his belief that
mental science must be free of all theoretical and metaphysical tradition, that he may be called one
of the true founders of the new psychology.</p>
<p>The spiritual and the physical life of man, he pointed out, are organically united. The one
cannot be understood without the other. The physical enters equally with the psychic element in
every human question. Insanity and all mental disease, of which there is a particular diseased
bodily state to correspond with each one; should all come, he felt, under the patient investigation
of the scientist. Drysdale foresaw the present development in psychology in indicating that the true
analyst must be familiar not only with physical habits, but with mental habits also. Just as
psycho-analysts are able to substantiate and illuminate their discoveries by examples drawn from
literature and art, history and biography, so Drysdale pointed out that in studying human nature the
scientists, to understand the general cause of health and disease, must become acquainted with the
world of creative expression. True scientists "<q who="DRYGE">should seek to enter into the thoughts
of religious and moral thinkers; for all of them are in their own sphere physicians, and their every
thought has a physical and moral import.</q>" To make any advance in this field, he pointed out,
perseverance and the combined effort of many workers are needed. Medicine must be combined with
other sciences, and, until the public is as well informed on physical as on psychic subjects and as
thoroughly conversant with their paramount importance, we cannot expect any true progress.</p>
<p>He also saw the advance of the method of analysis, in encouraging the patient to reveal himself.
Any true understanding of mental disease or unbalance, he felt would be barren and incomplete
without this self-revelation, just as morality and religion were barren and incomplete before men
began to think on these subjects for themselves. He deplored the fact that very few medical men had
ever thought of allowing their patients to speak for themselves in their diagnoses. Intent on
arriving at physical facts and physical conclusions, physicians of his day paid apparently little
attention to the mental state of the patient, which, as he pointed out, forms no less a part of the
disease. In questioning a patient they sought to bring him as soon as possible to the physical
point, "<q who="DRYGE">
<emph rend="italics">checking his digressions and the out-pouring of his suffering
heart.</emph></q>" On the other hand, the psychology of that artificial era was as barren and
unfruitful, as we could well expect it to be. It limited itself, as any reader of the old textbooks
remembers, to descriptive analysis of intellectual and mental processess, with no reference to the
unconscious physical or instinctive behavior of the individual.</p>
<p>Drysdale was one of the first to see that these two things, to be of any real benefit to
humanity, must be united and synthesized into a new science. The modern analyst has to base his
therapy upon the ever-increasing revelations the individual is able to make. Drysdale foresaw some
such method as this by speaking of the value of the patient's digressions, <emph rend="italics"
>confessions and outpourings</emph>. He realized that the physician and science were losing in a
great degree not only by the silencing of the feelings, but also by their lack of insight into the
psychology of health and disease. This, he insisted, is as valuable a part of medical knowledge as
any other, and as important for the prevention and treatment of disease and the advancement of
health. Every physical state has its peculiar mental one, and to discover what this is, and the
influence on the mind of all bodily states, such as hysteria and insanity, is a most essential
branch of medicinal science. This psychology of health and disease is to be obtained only by a study
of every individual's mind compared with his bodily condition, and a full knowledge of this can be
arrived at only by <emph rend="italics">his own revelations. We want a whole man to sympathize with,
not merely a body or a soul.</emph></p>
<p>"<q who="DRYGE">How few subjective records of physical life are to be found in history!</q>" he
exclaimed. "<q who="DRYGE">Among the numerous autobiographies that have been written by so many
noble human beings, who has given us any but the most meager details of his physical life, even
though its history may have been the most extraordinary, the most sadly eventful of the twin parts
of his nature? Hence do all these men present to us most imperfect pictures. Through all the tissues
of their loves we do not know what physical threads have been interwoven, and therefore we can pass
no satisfactory judgment on themselves or their actions. But how immensely does the world lose by
not having the fruits of their physical as well as their moral experiences! Had their penetrating
minds been as keenly directed to the physical goods and evils they encountered as to the mental
ones, had they used, each in his own case, the subtle insight which personal experience alone gives,
would the world have been in as wretched state as it is, with so low a physical standard that health
is not health, that there is a skeleton in every house, and a disease, secret or open, gnawing at
the vitals of almost every one of us! Would we still be stumbling on from age to age in the same
erroneous tracks, and falling one after the other, like sheep, into the same physical
pitfalls?...</q></p>
<p>"<q who="DRYGE">If we will not remain thus ignorant, we must imbue our minds equally with
physical knowledge. We must study the language of the body, a language not confined to an age or a
nation, but wide and universal as humanity, in order that we may attain to a higher
self-consciousness.</q>"</p>
<p>He reverts time after time, in the "<title type="book">Elements of Social Science,</title>" to this necessity
of a new psychology. One chapter is entitled "<title type="book">Subjective Medicine,</title>" another
"<title>Mental Disease</title>," while another chapter on hysteria seems to me to be fundamentally
in agreement with the epoch-making study of Freud, published in 1895, the first book of the great
Viennese pioneer. In his chapter on "<title>Mental Disease</title>," George Drysdale points out that
the mind, exactly like the body, operates according to fixed natural laws. Sorrow in the mind
corresponds to pain in the body. In Freud's first book "<title><foreign lang="GER">Studien über
Hysterie</foreign></title>" the point was made that "<q who="FRESI">sexuality plays a leading part
in the causation of hysteria.</q>" When we recall that <person reg="Charcot, Jean Martin"
>Charcot</person> was indifferent to the psychic side of his cases, that he regarded the recognition
of a sex element in the causation of disease as degrading, and that Freud and <person
reg="Breuer, Josef">Breuer</person> in 1895 first launched the doctrine of sexual suppression, which
is now the foundation pier upon which the whole structure of the new psychology rests, we can gain
some sense of Drysdale's importance as the true pioneer of the whole modern outlook.</p>
<p>Verification of this fact is to be strikingly found in his chapter on mental disease and
hysteria. He makes the unqualified statement that a morbid sexual state--both physical and
mental--lies at the root of hysteria. Compare this with the statement made by Freud in his first
book that "<q who="FRESI">the great majority of serious neuroses in women arise from the marriage
bed.</q>" With none of the equipment of modern psychology and modern science at his command.
Drysdale nevertheless reveals a definite and concrete insight, stated in unequivocal terms,
concerning the hysterical and neurotic character. He asks us to analyse the peculiar mental and
physical phenomena of hysteria, and to consider the disturbing influences which the systematic
denial and repression of natural desire must have on the delicate and susceptible girl. He says it
is impossible to avoid the conclusion that this suppression is the main cause of the disease: "<q
who="DRYGE">The natural emotions are checked and thrown back upon themselves, and it is inevitable
that they should become disordered and their disorder gradually implicate the whole nervous
system.</q>" How closely he anticipates the very phraseology of the twentieth century psychology is
indicated in this striking statement: "<q who="DRYGE">The stream of feeling, instead of being
allowed to flow onward in its natural channel in the light of day, gladdening and fertilizing all
around, is pent up in <emph rend="italics">the gloomy secret caverns of the mind</emph>, to cause
there a deluge and desolation. That, which should have been the young girl's pride and delight,
becomes her shame and torture; she must conceal and studiously repress her eager and beautiful
emotions; and can we wonder that bewilderment and timidity and impotence result? Nature cannot bear
this constant state of slavery, and ever and anon she shows in the hysterical convulsions, in the
wild delirious excitement of nymphomania, that she will not be repressed.</q>" He realized that an
age of spiritual Puritanism and repression was responsible for the inevitable spread of hysteria and
the increasing numbers of neurotic women. He saw that rank and morbid growth of sexual passions was
the outgrowth of these suppressions. Happiness is a sign of moral health; joy and sorrow, according
to Drysdale, are our guides to truth showing us where we are right and where wrong in the
exploration of our being. He saw long before the advance of modern psychology that the mental
element plays as important a part as any other in the causation of physical disease; and to cure the
latter, it is just as requisite to apply remedies to the mental as to the bodily state. To do this,
he said, we must first be able to recognize what is the mental disease and then to treat it
according to the principles of mental health. Our ignorance of the laws of our minds has involved
us, body and soul, in ruin. People pride themselves on their woes, and glory in their contempt of
health. Even to-day we have not outgrown this pride in sorrow and disease.</p>
<p>But Drysdale insisted, like the most advanced of modern psycho-biologists, that the human body in
its interacting mental and physical aspects is the touchstone of moral truth; that its health or
disease is "<q who="DRYGE">tangible and demonstrable.</q>" We see that joy and all the allied
feelings are linked most closely with the physical health and wellbeing, whereas sorrow and all its
miseries cause derangement and ill-health of the bodily functions in a measure exactly proportional
to their intensity and continuance." He saw that the great need of his time, as it is still of our
own, was to attain a true idea of what is health and what is disease. The physician of mind and body
cannot effect a cure if there is lurking in the physical or mental system, a disease or derangement
which is not recognized, and which may be at the bottom of all the symptoms. He saw that the true
origin of a great many physical diseases is in reality to be found in depressed or anxious state of
mind. In this way he preceded the modern theories of complexes and suppressions, of morbid fears and
compulsions. Thus he urged upon physicians to pay equal attention to mental disorder and to seek the
true roots of physical and mental unbalance.</p>
<p>How wide-spread the action of conventional sexual suppression and repression as restrictive and
enslaving agencies upon human nature, was fully realized by Drysdale. He saw this expressed in a
morbid curiosity caused by the dense ignorance and inhibitions, which gave rise to the demand for
prurient and stupid books published to gratify the sexually starved; in the degradation and
corruption of minds; in the infantilism and underdevelopment of men and women. Because of this
childish curiosity and ignorant imagination; because of the degraded feeling of mystery, shame or
disgust, varied only by vulgar pretences of knowingness, the society of his time was grossly
perverted on all sexual matters.</p>
<p>Drysdale insisted that the laws of mind are not one whit less definite and invaluable than those
of the body. He saw that if psychology was to make any advance it must give up its metaphysical and
supernatural assumptions. There is no thought, no emotion, no instinct within us that is not subject
to definite mechanisms, as certain and invariable as physical or chemical reactions. He realized
that the psychology of his day was still in a rudimentary and even stagnant state. "<q who="DRYGE"
>Its very first fundamental axioms are not admitted, but all is involved in a paradoxical mystic
supernatural obscurity.</q>"</p>
<p>It was his idea that the two great natural guides to the understanding of mental health and
disease are joy and sorrow, corresponding to the feelings of pain and pleasure in the body. The
ordinary standards of moral excellence were obviously unhealthy, according to Drysdale. Many of the
characters most admired by Victorian moralists were to him infected with disease. The great crying
need in mind as well as body, he insisted, is not humility nor spiritual sentiment, but
self-reliance, expressive energy and an active enjoyment of life--in a word, health. A true
enjoyment of moral and spiritual nature, Drysdale claimed, could only be obtained by the comparative
examination of the minds of all living beings and by tracing our faculties upward from their simple
expressions in the lowest animals to the very most complicated state in humans. Until this is done,
he was convinced that there could be no real psychology. "<q who="DRYGE">The science of comparative
psychology,</q>" he wrote, "<q who="DRYGE">though it has yet scarcely an existence, opposed as it
has been by our narrow conception of the human mind, will ultimately be recognized as equally
indispensable with comparative anatomy in order to attain a true knowledge of our nature.</q>" In
this statement we find in Drysdale a striking anticipation of the new psychology with its studies of
myth, folk-lore and primitive man.</p>
</docBody>
</doc>
