<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/07/07 NC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-21 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1940-09-02">2 Sep 1940</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Havana Radio Broadcast</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp239503</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Smith College Collections</bibl>
            <bibl><title>MSM</title>S72:0145</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>Sanger visted several Havana hospitals on September 1 and gave a radio address the next
            day.</p>
        <p>For a draft version with interlineations by Sanger see S72:0143.</p>
        <index level1="birth control"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to" level3="in remote places"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"
            level3="negative consequences of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="American"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="rights associated with"/>
        <index level1="working classes" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="health of"/>
        <index level1="upper classes" level2="birth control and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Havana Radio Broadcast</head>
        <dateline>
            <date>September 1940</date>
        </dateline>

        <p>Ladies and Gentlemen: It is a very great pleasure for me to speak to you tonight and to
            bring to the mothers of <place>Cuba</place> and to all others who may be sympathetic to
            our cause, the greetings of our organization for planned parenthood, The <org>Birth
                Control Federation of America</org>.</p>
        <p>The cause for which I have labored for the past twenty-five years is the cause of
            Motherhood itself. It has been a battle to free it from the dangers and the ignorance
            which makes child bearing a tragic waste of life for mothers and infants as well. There
            are more mothers lost in child birth in the world than there are soldiers killed on the
            battlefield. This loss of mothers’ lives is not necessary and can be avoided if the
            mother is given the information and instructed in the means to space the births of their
            children from two to three years. It should be her right to have only that number of
            children that her health will permit and her husband’s earning power can support.</p>
        <p>It is a tragic fact that the poorest mothers in the world today have the largest
            families. The well to do--the educated parents are informed as to what to do to control
            the size of the family but the working man’s wife is kept in ignorance and conscripted
            to spend her life in child bearing. Many of these children are doomed to death before
            they breathe the first breath of life. The mother hard work, her lack of proper food,
            her own diseased body and her ignorance all combine to deprive the unborn child of its
            rights to live through its first year.</p>
        <p>During the past ten years at the clinic of which I am Director, The <org>Margaret Sanger
                Research Bureau</org>, where poor mothers can come and obtain scientific information
            from our doctors, we have had over eighty thousand mothers whose case histories bear
            witness to the fact that women die needlessly in child birth. Their lives can be saved
            by giving them knowledge to space pregnancies or control or limit the number of children
            the mother should have. We have saved by our work thousands of lives and we are saving
            them everyday. Now we must insist that the <org reg="United States Government"
                >Government</org> through its Public Health workers shall also provide proper
            scientific information for the poorest mothers, the mothers on farms, in homesteads, in
            factories who now are unable to obtain this knowledge which will in many instances save
            their lives.</p>
        <p>Millions of dollars are being spent on health and welfare but nothing is being spent to
            help fathers and mothers to obtain means to help themselves. We want to save the lives
            of mothers and infants and to bring into the world only children sound in body and mind.
            It is not quantity we need but the quality of life must now be given proper
            consideration if we will bring Peace on Earth Good Will to Men” over the face of the
            Globe.</p>
        <p>I thank you and wish you Good bye.</p>

    </docBody>
</doc>
