<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed draft speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2010/03/10 AC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2010/03/10 CH review</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-11 CH clean up regs and other errors</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1928-00-00">
            <supplied>ca. 1928</supplied>
        </docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Woman and the Future</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp240448</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophis Smith Collection, Smith College</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title>, S71:0622</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="UNK"/>
            <name id="SANMA"> Sanger, Margaret</name>
            <name id="SHAWI"> Shakespeare, William</name>
            <name id="BYRGE"> Byron, George Gordon</name>
            <name id="WHIWA"> Whitman, Walt</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="birth control" level2="in marriages"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"/>
        <index level1="child spacing"/>
        <index level1="child welfare"/>
        <index level1="eugenics"/>
        <index level1="Family Limitation"/>
        <index level1="physicaly disabled and diseased" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="jails and imprisonment"/>
        <index level1="politicians" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="woman suffrage" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="enslavement of"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="freedom and rights of"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="gender roles and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Woman and the Future</head>
        <byline>By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></byline>
        <div type="sub">
            <p>Perhaps the title of my lecture today should be “The Women of the Future.” Perhaps it
                should be “The Woman of Tomorrow.” More truthfully it should be “The Woman of
                Today”. At any rate it should be “Women.” None of us can be expected to be very much
                excited about women of future centuries we shall never know nor see. If we are
                interested in the woman of the future, it is because we realize, in some mysterious
                way, that the woman of to-morrow, of the next generation, is going to be the
                daughter of the present generation. <emph rend="underline">We are the creators of
                    the woman of the future.</emph>
            </p>
            <p> We have fought for several generations to create the woman of today. The women of
                today must realize that the battle is not yet won. We must continue to struggle for
                the victory of tomorrow.</p>
            <p> So the women of today must clear the way for the woman of tomorrow. First of all,
                like all good gardeners or planters or builders, we have got to clear the field of
                obstructions and the rocks are the prejudices, the misconceptions, the fallacies
                about women that exist even today. Let us get rid of them! Let us blast them out of
                the human consciousness - especially out of the minds of men!</p>
            <p> You have all seen those large wooden painted watches that sometimes hand outside
                watchmakers shops. The other day a friend of mine said, as we were passing one. “<q
                    who="UNK">That painted clock is right to the very second!</q>” “Well,” I
                answered, “it can be right twice a day, if you happen to strike it.” And it struck
                me then that most men have created in their own minds a conception of women that is
                as wooden as those painted clocks. In their own minds they created the pretty wooden
                figure of the woman they love - and then they are disappointed because the real
                woman - the woman of flesh and blood - does not conform to the painted dummy they
                carry in their imaginations. The wooden image is always right - the living breathing
                woman is always wrong!</p>
            <p> Strangely enough, women of past generations spent a good deal of their time, trying
                to make themselves like the strange unreal images carried in the hearts and
                imaginations of their sweethearts or husbands. They did not claim for themselves any
                real independent lives of their own. their lords and masters demanded modesty in
                dress - and so they assumed modesty. They demanded servility - and so the women
                became servile. They wanted to feel superior to their wives - so the wives gave them
                ignorance and servility. The men wanted to feel strong - so the women pretended to
                be weak creatures, given to fainting and that strange thing called he vapours. We
                should be grateful that fainting and the vapours have long gone out of style!</p>
            <p> I am merely trying to point out the difference between the past and the present. In
                the past, the character of most women was determined by men, not by themselves. The
                woman was a slave, a dependent, a parasite. So she had to develop, for self
                protection the psychology of the slave and the parasite. She had to get her way by
                indirect actions, by stealth. She had to assume a part like an actress in a play.
                She could never be herself!</p>
            <p> Her tragedy was that she was always in the secondary role. The husband was the star
                of the play in every family. The wife and the mother was only of the supporting
                company. But it was not only the husband who was the lord and master. At every stage
                of a woman’s life, from infancy to old age, her activity was always dominated by
                some male. First the father, then the sweetheart or fiancé, then the husband, and in
                the event of death of the husband, possibly her brothers; and finally in old age, by
                the son.</p>
            <p>In the old days, men put all women into three- or possibly four- categories. Every
                woman was looked upon as a daughter, a wife or a mother. All the rest were
                prostitutes. You see that these categories were not determined by the real inner
                nature of women. They merely - all of them - expressed her relationship to the male
                world. Women were pretty, useless, childish creatures because men wanted them to be.
                There was a demand for that type, and women supplied the demand. But throughout
                history, there have always been women who refused to be pigeonholed into those
                categories. Women who became actresses, politicians, organizers, politicians, rulers
                of countries. There have been great women - more and more of them as we come down
                the ages - to demonstrate the fallacy of the masculine conception of womankind.
                There was <person reg="Elizabeth I (England)">Queen Elizabeth</person>, <person
                    reg="Catharine the Great (Russia)">Catharine the Great of
                    <place>Russia</place></person>, the great saints, the great writers, the great
                mistresses, all the rest of them. Were they exceptions? No. They prove the innate
                power that might be - and must be - developed - in all women! They were women who
                dared to be themselves - not merely some man’s mistaken idea of what they ought to
                be!</p>
            <p> Don’t forget that all the proverbs, all the catch words about the nature of women
                have been made by men. And each one of them is false. “<q who="SHAWI">Frailty! Thy
                    name is woman....</q>” <person reg="Shakespeare, William">Shakespere</person>!
                Isn’t that ridiculous? If Shakespeare had given birth to ten or twelve children
                perhaps he would not have written that line about the frailty of women! The
                masculine point of view, you see. Then there was <person reg="Byron, George Gordon"
                    >Lord Byron</person>, who flitted from flower to flower, and said that women
                were “<q who="BYRGE">uncertain, coy and hard to please.</q>” Maybe that was a
                confession of his own shortcomings. At any rate it is a notorious human tendency to
                discover in others your own faults. So men have traditionally blamed women for
                everything. You may say that I am too severe on the men - too unjust. On the
                contrary: I have the greatest admiration for the skill of the men of the past, who
                so cleverly and so completely domesticated woman as they domesticated animals. They
                devised customs, and laws, and religious regulations to keep women in a position of
                slavery and dependence. The individual woman who rebelled was confronted by all the
                solid power of laws, of customs, of religion. She had no economic independence, she
                had no sex independence. She had no freedom of any sort. She was like a hunted
                criminal.</p>
            <p> Worst of all, even Nature was against her. Once caught in the trap of maternity,
                there was no escape. With the birth of each successive baby, she found her body and
                her soul ever more closely chained. Don't forget, moreover, that the majority of
                women, in centuries past, and in practically every country and every tribe of the
                world, have not been exempted from hard physical labor. There are many tribes in
                which the women still continue to do all the hard physical work. Their noble lords
                reserve their time for the superior pleasures of fighting and gambling. Recently we
                saw and example of this in the “<title type="movie">Cossacks</title>” the
                motion-picture made from <person reg="Tolstoy, Leo">Tolstoy</person>’s early
                novel.</p>
            <p> In view of the hopelessness and the complexity of woman’s traditional slavery the
                surprising thing is not that we have made so little progress, but that we have made
                any progress at all. Yet when we look back at the last twenty-five or thirty years,
                we find amazing progress in the emancipation of women. It is the more encouraging
                because it is a progress that seems to go faster and faster. The future - that
                glorious hopeful word! - will be upon us before we know it. That is why it is
                imperative for every one of us to join in the effort to prepare the way for the
                advent of the woman of the future - the completely emancipated, completely developed
                woman who will have the opportunity to BE HERSELF!</p>
            <p> And being herself, she will demonstrate to men that she will give him the
                opportunity to Be Himself, in a far finer, complete manner that he ever could when
                she was a mere slave or parasite.</p>
            <p>How is this to be brought about?</p>
        </div>
        <div type="sub">
            <p>Let us trace briefly the various steps by which women have attempted to gain the road
                to freedom.</p>
            <p> Women have sought to escape from the age-old slavery of the past by various
                means.</p>
            <p> Some felt they could attain it by education. Surprising, isn't it, that in the past
                even the higher education was denied to women. They thought that if they could enter
                the learned professions, they would be freed. Well, many of them tried it. And still
                the old slavery persisted for most of them. It was hard to be a lawyer or a doctor,
                and the mother of a growing, ever-increasing family at the same time. But this was a
                step in advance, no matter how small it seems to the great majority of women.</p>
            <p> Then there arose the cry for economic independence. Women claimed the right to earn
                their own living. This was after all, not so great a victory. Men had always been
                willing to grant women the right to relieve them of the drudgery of the world. the
                impulse theat led women to demand economic independence rather than to remain
                content with the doubtful rewards of domestic slavery was certainly a healthy and a
                praiseworthy one. But in its working, out, too often they have found themselves in
                positions which are underpaid and which consist, to a great extent, of uninteresting
                and mechanical drudgery.</p>
            <p> Economic “Independence” - if you can call it that - has been at best an empty
                victory. I dont believe that it can legitimately be called a victory at all. Perhaps
                it has only been an automatic response to a demand for cheap labor.</p>
            <p> It has had the advantage, however, of getting thousands of women out of the close
                confines of the home - which is too often, as <person reg="Ibsen, Henrik"
                    >Ibsen</person> named it - a mere doll’s house. It has put women more on a basis
                of social equality with men. So far so good.</p>
            <p> Then they has been the long struggle for the vote. Personally, I feel that the
                actual struggle for suffrage, which lasted through several generations, was of
                equal, if not indeed of greater value that the actual attainment of the vote. The
                struggle itself brought out courage, daring, all the innate qualities of
                self-sacrifice and bravery. It proved that women could work together, and could
                withstand the jeers and ridicule of the unthinking public. It proved that women were
                capable of political thinking and political action. Since the attainment of the
                work, there comes the inevitable temptation to sink back, and to assume that there
                is nothing more to do.</p>
            <p> That is wrong. We would be untrue and disloyal to the memory of the great pioneers
                if we fail in our responsibility to use the vote as an instrument to the still great
                emancipation of womankind. Therefore American women need to educate themselves still
                further in politics and legislation, and to use their power toward the election of
                men who can assure them that their sympathies are with women. The vote is not an end
                in itself. It is of value to women only as it is used toward the more complete
                emancipation of women - and thus of the whole human race, particularly of the women
                and children of the future generations.</p>
            <p> Another great struggle had been made and won. We are apt to forget it today - or to
                minimize its importance. I mean dress reform. We have forgotten the ridicule and the
                abuse heaped upon the early pioneers of this movement. When you stop to think of the
                upholstery and the harness that used to make up the dress of women in the nineteenth
                century - the hoops, the bustles, the stays, the underpinning, the trailing dust-
                and germ-catchers that were called trains - when you compare all that with the
                freedom in woman’s dress today, you feel like giving three cheers to all those who
                first protested against the fashions which did so much to enslave the bodies and the
                souls of women! There is no doubt in my mind that freedom in dress, which permits
                vigorous, unhampered physical action, is of enormous benefit in freeing the mind as
                well. No wonder that tightly-corseted women were rendered thoughtless. They couldn't
                even breathe. They couldn't even walk. We have freed the diaphragm from its stifling
                corset. We have liberated the legs, and in so doing have signed the death-warrant of
                prudery. We have cut off the hair, got rid of “tats”, pompadours, hair pins and
                hatpins, and thus have given the brains a chance to develop. We have given girls the
                opportunity to become athletes, to develop their bodies. All thanks to the one piece
                bathing suit which has helped women and men to get ride of all prudish, perverted
                notions of false modesty, and has permitted them to walk like young gods and
                goddesses along the sunlit sands unashamed and with a new dignity. All these changes
                have not meant the death of romance, but have put it on a new healthy basis. These
                innovations have removed the vicious secrecy, the hypocritical modesty, and have
                made the simpering, artificial woman of the past, with her dishonest arts of
                concealment, as out-of-date as the dinosaur.</p>
            <p> Each of these steps toard freedom have been taken with a great struggle. Each has
                been significant. We have thus had; <list>
                    <item>1. the struggle for education.</item>
                    <item>2. the struggle for a place in the professions</item>
                    <item>3. the struggle for economic independence</item>
                    <item>4. the struggle for suffrage.</item>
                    <item>5. the struggle for the freedom of dress.</item>
                </list>
            </p>
            <p>In addition, there has been a struggle for social freedom - for divorce and human
                justice in the courts. This is still going on.</p>
            <p> Important as these steps are, it does not require much research to realize that none
                of them touches at the real heart of woman’s eternal problem. That problem is bound
                up with her <emph rend="underline">biological</emph> structure. As <person
                    reg="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</person> wrote of women: “<q who="WHIWA">You
                    are the gates of the body and you are the gates of the soul.</q>” Upon women
                falls a great more than half of the burden of bringing the next generation into the
                world. Because of this the great majority of women have been - <emph
                    rend="underline">and still are</emph> - condemned to practically incessant
                childbearing. You may tell me that all intelligent women, at this day and age, are
                emancipated from this harsh sentence imposed upon them by Church and State.</p>
            <p> But the women who are thus liberated form only a very small percentage of the grand
                total. You who are interested in social work, who cooperate, perhaps, with the
                organized charitable associations of this city and state, need not be told of the
                misery of the poverty-stricken mothers of the indigent classes. You know that the
                lower we go in the social scale, the higher the birth-rate is discovered to be. You
                know that the lower the wages of the father, the more children there are in the
                family. You know that the feeble-minded, the mentally defective, the delinquent
                classes have more children than the well-to-do, the intelligent, the responsible
                classes of society.</p>
            <p> Yet perhaps it has not been called to your attention that every, in city and in
                country, the over-burdened mothers are crying desperately for relief from the
                torture of incesant pregnancies.</p>
            <p> For fifteen years they have been appealing to me personally. Because for fifteen
                years I have been battling for everywoman’s right to birth control. I have received
                a quarter of a million letters from American mothers. Whenever any one tells me that
                Birth Control is of no importance, or that any intelligent woman knows what to do to
                prevent the conception of unwanted children, I begin to read some of these letters.
                They are letters from intelligent, self-sacrificing wives - young girls who fell in
                love, who looked upon marriage, as the first step to romance, and who -poor things!-
                expected “to live happily ever afterwards.”</p>
            <p> They were trapped. Trapped into slavery - from which they have been unable to
                extricate themselves. It is useless to talk to these poor things about the
                advantages of economic freedom, the higher education, or the great benefits to be
                derived from voting. What do they care about the new freedom in dress? They are
                interested only in getting clothes for their poor frail bodies, and their poor
                shivering children. Keep on breeding commands the Church and State. They have no
                choice in the matter. And so they keep adding to the surplus of the indigent, the
                defective, the delinquent. You pay for them. You, the intelligent, the responsible,
                the healthy element in American society are called upon to support the charity. You
                are taxed to maintain the reform schools, the homes for the feeble-minded and the
                defective, the prisons for the criminals. For the inmates of all these public
                instututions are recruited in the main from the over-large families. I have not the
                time to present statistics here. They are easily obtainable in any textbook of
                eugenics, or other analysis of vital statistics. Instead, I want to read to you a
                few of the letters from mothers who have appealed to me for Birth Control
                information.</p>
            <p> I have gathered these letters into a book which I call “<title type="book"
                    >Motherhood in Bondage</title>”. If anyone tries to tell you that the women of
                    <place reg="United States">America</place> have been spoiled by too much freedom
                and too many luxuries, please ask him to read this book. I offer these letters as
                Exhibit A in the case for Birth Control.</p>
            <p> But just let me read you a few typical, representative cases:</p>
            <p>(Read Letters chosen from “Motherhood in Bondage")</p>
        </div>

        <div type="sub">
            <p> Now, I want to ask: If we are going to create our women of the future out of the
                human material described in these letters, do you think our future is going to be a
                thing to be proud of?</p>
            <p> We cannot journey into the future by ignoring these cases. You may rest assured that
                they too, despite their high maternal mortality rate, their high infantile death
                rate, will keep us company. They will have to be looked after. they will fill our
                prisons, our poor houses, and our charitable institutes. they will drag down the
                level of intelligence of our public schools - these poor, underfed, underclothed,
                and defective children. They will be an increasing burden on you, the intelligent
                and the responsible.</p>
            <p> What are we going to do about it?</p>
            <p> We have, first of all, got to insure to each child who is brought into our American
                world, the birthright of health, the opportunity to develop, to be born with a sound
                mind in a sound body. We do not want to clutter up our public schools with defective
                children <add>constitutionally</add> unable by their <unclear resp="MSPP"
                    >feeble</unclear> heritage, to benefit by the instruction there offered. We do
                not want to increase our population of morons. We do not want to hold back our
                intelligent children by association with the sub-normal. We do not want to be taxed
                to support prisons instead of universities, We do not want to spend huge sums in a
                vain effort to control criminals and gangsters. We have other, and far nobler uses
                for our public funds.</p>
            <p> What is the first step?</p>
            <p> Before we can hope for the creation of the glorious woman of tomorrow, we must bend
                all our efforts toward effecting the biological emancipation of the enslaved woman
                of today. Toward the fulfillment of this task, we must use the instruments that are
                now at our command. The vote, for instance. The candidates ask for your support, in
                municipal, state and federal elections. Find out for yourself how they stand on
                these fundamental problems which involve the welfare of the children who are to
                become the citizens of tomorrow; how they stand on matters concerning the welfare of
                the mothers: how they stand on efforts to decrease the vast sums spent for the
                maintenance of prisons and public charitable institutions: how they stand on
                proposed legislation to decrease the population of defectives, delinquents and
                dependents. You will find, probably, that they have never given these problems a
                thought. Yet the whole future of our country and of the world at large is bound up
                with these racial questions.</p>
            <p> No; we cannot lay the foundations for a great civilization of the future, until we
                have removed the disorder, the chaos, the obstructions. These mothers whose
                desperate cries are <add>voiced</add> in this book (hold up book) are crying for
                bread, and America is offering them a stone. All of our boasted advances in comforts
                and luxuries - all our skyscrapers, our radios, our triumphs in aviation, all of our
                poetry and music, all of our immense prosperity mean nothing to these slave mothers.
                They are drowning, and instead of helping them, we are playing a noisy jazz
                symphony. Our prosperity may dazzle the world, but our radios and our jazz cannot
                drown out the bitter cries of these women.</p>
            <p> I seemed to have wandered far from the subject of my talk - Woman and the Future.
                But I wish to show you how closely bound up with the future is our immediate
                present. The future can be created only though the bodies of our living women. “<q
                    who="WHIWA">You are the gateways of life - you are the the gates of the body and
                    you are the gates of the soul.</q>” The mothers are the environment of the child
                for nine months before its birth and for many years after.</p>
            <p> How can she fulfill her duties in bringing up her child in the earliest and most
                critical stage of its development, if already she has been condemned immediately to
                a new pregnancy? The mind of the unwanted child is thus often marred and stunted in
                early infacy in a fashion which - according to the most competent modern
                psychologists it is impossible ever to remedy. We protest against this stunting. We
                protest against the dwarfing of the minds of future American men and women. We do
                not want their impulses and instincts stunted as a Japanese gardener dwarfs a
                tree.</p>
            <p> Let all of us - and the women of today especially - summon the courage to confront
                the vital, pivotal problems of life at their heart. Let us all join together and
                declare war upon the false, hypocritical modesty which has impeded our progress and
                delayed the fruition of a truly American civilization.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="sub">
            <p> Woman’s tragedy in the past - and with few exceptions it remains her tragedy today -
                is that she has been relegated to a secondary position. She must be restored to the
                central primary place to which she is entitled by nature and by her biological
                importance. The first step is to awaken her realization of her importance to the
                race and to civilization. We have seen that the steps thus far taken toward
                emancipation are important, but not of primary importance. Her biological freedom
                must be assured. Maternity may indeed the central function of the majority of women.
                But in order to fulfill this function intelligently and valuably, it must be
                self-directive, and free. Quality is more important than quantity.</p>
            <p> To repeat; women must be awakened to her pivotal importance. She can fulfill her
                function as wife, as mother, and most important of all, as individual, when she
                attains a new center of interest. She must acquire a new selfishness. She must place
                on higher value on her life and her love. She must be interested in her own latent
                powers. She must learn never to stop growing, mentally and spiritually. She must</p>
            <p>
                <list>
                    <item>SELF-DEVELOPMENT</item>
                    <item> SELF-EXPRESSION</item>
                    <item> SELF-REALIZATION</item>
                </list> Every woman must learn to analyse her deepest desires. She must decide for
                herself what she wants out of life. And she must learn at all costs not to place too
                much hope on external things or persons. Neither riches, nor beauty, nor comfort,
                nor luxury, nor husbands. For there are two types of desire: the one for the
                external things; the other for internal things. The woman who says “<q who="UNK">I
                    want to be loved</q>” is placing her wish on an external thing.</p>
            <p> The woman who says, “I love” is experiencing an internal joy. The latter is
                experiencing life, is on the road of self-development. The woman who loves cannot
                ever be deprived of that experience.</p>
            <p> Therefore, I say, choose the road of growth, of self-development. Let me explain
                why:</p>
            <p>
                <emph rend="underline">SELF-DEVELOPMENT</emph>
            </p>
            <p> Why is Self-Development important?</p>
            <p> Fundamentally Self-Development means <emph rend="underline">Growth</emph>. To grow!
                That is an absolute necessity for every living organism. The seed must be planted in
                a healthy nourishing soul if it is to spring into a strong, vigorous life. It must
                be tended, nourished, cherished, uncrowded, and given plenty of sunlight and care.
                It cannot be cramped, stunted, or forced, if it is to blossom and blossom into
                beauty.</p>
            <p> It is the same with each individual human life. We exult as each of our latent,
                innate powers develops into reality. We become conscious of an increased sense of
                power. We are living through the miracle of <emph rend="underline"
                    >Self-Development</emph>. We are happy in childhood and youth because this
                natural miracle keeps on repeating itself in ever changing and ever novel ways. We
                are unhappy, on the contrary, when that <emph rend="underlined"
                    >Self-Development</emph> is thwarted, either by external circumstances or
                people, or inner weakness, which brings with it a sense of futility or frustration.
                If it is our own fault, through laziness or weakness, we cannot escape a sense of
                guilt - and there is a strong temptation to blames others for our own secret faults.
                And on the other hand, when by our own efforts we confront and triumph over
                obstacles the victory is so much the greater, and the inner satisfaction a fine
                reward.</p>
            <p>
                <emph rend="underline">SELF-DEVELOPMENT</emph> presents a very difficult problem for
                all women. I am speaking of true Self-Development and not that conspicuous display
                of talent or acquired education. Freedom is its first essential. An enslaved or
                cooped animal cannot develop its innate potentialities. Its unused functions
                atrophy. And we can be as much enslaved by conventions, by a fear of what people
                will say, or a fear of disapproval, as by iron bars. Women have too long feared what
                men would think of them. Yet this has been a baseless fear. Men accept the changing
                styles and the new freedom. They no longer object to bobbed hair or short skirts. We
                know that they are proud of the new achievements of American women in athletics - in
                golf, tennis and swimming. Nowadays, women may be assured of the generous help of
                all right-thinking American men in her efforts toward emancipation.</p>
            <p> The truth is, men are discovering that in enslaving women they actually enslaved
                themselves. The free woman is more attractive, more lovely, a better companion than
                the so-called old-fashioned girl. And she too finds that the surest road toward
                emancipations lies not in competing with men, not in alienating their affection, but
                in joining together in a communal effort toward the unrestricted development of each
                individuality for the common good of all. </p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
