<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Draft Speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2011/07/97 NC</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014/02/11 CH correcting.</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-05-05 CH cleaning confusing issues</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-15 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1923-03-05">
			<supplied resp="MSPP">5 Mar 1923</supplied>
		</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Compulsory Motherhood</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp224706</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>Florence Rose Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</bibl>
			<bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Smith College Collections</title>
				S70:0758</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="BIB">Bible</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>This is a partial draft of a speech <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret
				Sanger</person> likely gave in <place>Connecticut</place>, possibly for the
				<org>Bridgeport Council of Jewish Women</org>, a the <org>Liberty Building</org>'s
			Business and Professional Women's Club Assembly Room. She was introduced by <person
				reg="Capitman, Frances N.">Frances N. Capitman</person>, president of the Council.
			For a related document see "<xref from="101790.xml">The ABC's of Birth Control</xref>,"
			1923. For coverage of this speech see "<title type="article">Women Jam Hall to Hear
				Address on Birth Control</title>," <title type="journal">Bridgeport Courier</title>,
			Mar. 6, 1923, p. 1 </p>
		<index level1="abortion" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="economic benefits and risks of"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits and risks"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="in marriages"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="morality of"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="American"/>
		<index level1="children" level2="rights of"/>
		<index level1="children" level2="unwanted"/>
		<index level1="family planning"/>
		<index level1="family size"/>
		<index level1="family size" level2="class-based"/>
		<index level1="family size" level2="men and"/>
		<index level1="physicaly disabled and diseased" level2="birth control and"/>
		<index level1="marriage age" level2="women"/>
		<index level1="motherhood"/>
		<index level1="motherhood" level2="consripted"/>
		<index level1="unfit to reproduce" level2="descriptions of"/>
		<index level1="venereal disease" level2="syphilis"/>
		<index level1="women" level2="maternal feelings"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<p>
			<gap reason="missing" extent="six pages"/>
		</p>
		<p>There are conditions in which a woman should not bear children at all. These conditions
			may exist either in herself or in the man to whom she is married. Such conditions are
			present when either man or wife is suffering from such diseases as tuberculosis,
			syphilis, gonorrhea, cancer, epilepsy, insanity or any mental disorder, or is addicted
			to drunkenness or to some drug habit. While it is not believed that most of these
			diseases can be inherited, it is known that a tendency to disease can be handed down
			from parent to child. The increase in tuberculosis cases is attributed to the fact that
			the doctors keep alive to propagate their kind many men and women who formerly would
			have died before parenthood. They do not bequeathe tuberculosis to their children
			directly, but the children probably inherit a greater liability to the disease than the
			children of normal parents.</p>
		<p>Syphilis can be inherited--“<q who="BIB">unto the third and fourth generation</q>”. There
			is no prenatal force which is so murderous for infants as this dread form of venereal
			disease. The babies in any syphilitic ward of a children’s hospital form a heart-rending
			spectacle--quite sufficient to convince any reasonable creature that breeding from a
			syphilitic stock is criminal as well as insanely foolish. As for the other diseases
			mentioned, and as regards also drunkenness and drug habits who can believe that parents
			so afflicted can produce and rear children who will be anything but a liability to the
			nation.</p>
		<p>Besides these diseases which ought to debar both parents from reproducing their stock,
			there are many conditions peculiar to the woman which ought to be taken into
			consideration before she enters upon pregnancy. She ought to be old enough for full
			development. She ought to be healthy and not suffering from recent illness or over
			fatigue. If she is affected with heart disease, kidney trouble or pelvic deformity, she
			risks her life if she bears a child, and no such risk should be imposed upon her without
			her knowledge and <del>her full consent</del>
			<add>without her giving</add> her free consent.</p>
		<p>It happens sometimes that a man and woman, both apparently healthy and sane, have
			defective children. In cases like this, however much they may desire parenthood, they
			have no right to impose the burden of such defectives on society, or to risk the injury
			that such children may do to the race if they in their turn become parents of
			defectives. The descendants of a single feeble-minded woman whose family has been
			carefully traced in <place>Massachusetts</place>, have been reckoned up into the
			hundreds with an expenditure of millions of dollars by society on court trials, prisons,
			and asylums for the army of criminals and defectives among them.</p>
		<p>Leaving aside these cases where some form of disease makes childbearing unwise for the
			parents and anti-social for the nation, we have still to consider the normal healthy
			woman, and to decide whether in her case child-bearing should be left to chance. There
			are again two points of view from which to judge the matter--the point of view of
			society, and the point of view of the woman herself. Fortunately the decision from both
			points of view is usually in close agreement; because what is bad for the woman is
			usually bad for society; and society is only benefited by the addition to its numbers of
			healthy, well nourished and well reared children.</p>
		<p>The bearing of children by very young mothers is not <del>eugenic</del>
			<add><del>wanted</del></add>
			<add>desirable</add>. As soon as pregnancy begins the mother’s own development is
			arrested. <del>A</del> The child mother is therefore stunted in growth <del>bothin</del>
			<add>both in</add> mind and body. She remains a child and never attains to the level to
			which her innate powers and inherited possibilities would have tended. Every breeder of
			animals understands this natural law, and keeps his young heifers or mares from breeding
			until they are grown and developed and ready for the strain. It is commonly asserted
			that women mature earlier than men, and that in <place reg="Asia">oriental
				countries</place> they are ready for marriage at a much younger age than in the
				<place>United States</place>. But it should be remembered that maturity of a kind
			comes with arrested development for either boy or girl, and the longer girlhood and
			later maturity of the American boys and girls who are given longer education and freedom
			from responsibility shed considerable light on the forcing process which <add>for so
				long</add> has made women <del>for so long</del> out of really immature girls.</p>
		<p>For the sake of the children, as well as for the sake of her own possibility of
			developing all that is in her, a girl should not become a mother before she is
			twenty-two years old. In America girls are not fully ready for motherhood before they
			are twenty-five. The children of a woman who has been given time to mature fully before
			she commences to reproduce will be better fitted for life and probably in every way
			better equipped than the children of very young girls. The mother will also have had the
			chance of developing to a higher level mentally and will therefore be better able to
			rear and train her children.</p>
		<p>No woman should bear children without adequate intervals for recuperation. It is a
			tremendous strain to which the female body is subjected when it forms out of its own
			material the little life to which it gives birth. Following the birth are the months
			during which the nourishment of the child must be provided by the mother. Many women
			begin another pregnancy before the nursing period is ended, or at any rate immediately
			on its conclusion. There has been no time to lay up any reserve of strength in the
			mother’s own body and this process, repeated time after time, makes a woman old long
			before her years, drains her of health and strength and all capacity for enjoyment and
			reduces her to the drudge who loses all her influence over her swarming brood of
			children. The large families of such necessarily incompetent mothers are more
				like<add>ly</add> to be a burden to society than an asset; and it is out of such
			homes that we get our supply of criminals and prostitutes.</p>
		<p>So far we have considered only the health aspects. There remains the very important
			question of the economic status of the family into which the child is to be born.
			Overpopulation of a country is not at base a general or national question. It is the
			definite result of too many children in the family of Mr. and Mrs. A and too many in the
			family of Mr. and Mrs. B. It is <del>all</del>
			<add>the sum of</add> these little “too manies” that make the problem for the statesmen
			who see that there is no longer room in a country for all the progeny of its people.</p>
		<p>There would be no such problem if <add>each</add> Mr. and Mrs. X had limited the number
			of their children to the few that they could afford to rear--to feed and clothe, to
			accommodate decently in the home of which they could pay the rent, and to educate to the
			point where the children would be able to make a good start in life for themselves. The
			number of children so reared would keep up the population of a country. If opportunities
			widened, if more wealth offered, if discoveries or inventions made possible the support
			of greater populations, the enlarged opportunities would induce parents to take
			advantage of them. Mother love and father-love can always be counted upon to be willing
			to undertake the labor of rearing children, if the burden is not greater than men or
			women ought to bear.</p>
		<p>It might seem that the father, as wage earner, would be the one most concerned with the
			economic problem. Many a man is crushed under the weight of his ever-increasing family
			and relief would be to him the greatest possible blessing. One has only to compare the
			young man, entering happily and <del>hopefully</del>
			<add>buoyantly</add> on married life, full of joy in living, of hope and belief in
			himself and in the opportunities that the world will offer him, with the same man after
			ten years, with a houseful of children, who have arrived far more rapidly than his wages
			have increased. Probably his wife has become an invalid--worn out with overmuch bearing
			of children and with the labor of caring for them. He is hampered by debts, and unable
			to meet the expenses of so large a family. Instead of moving into a larger house now
			that he has a family of eight--six children in ten years is a common occurrence-- he is
			obliged to <del>house</del>
			<add>reduce</add> the expense for rent, and the pleasant little home that he could
			maintain until after the second child was born has been relinquished for a crowded and
			shabby dwelling in the tenement regions.</p>
		<p>In spite of all this hardship for the man, it is the women upon whom the economic burden
			weighs most heavily. It is she who has to make a home out of the sordid tenement, and to
			find room for the living and sleeping of all the members of the family. It is she who
			has to make the scanty wages cover the ever-increasing needs of the family. It is she
			who first feels the pangs of hunger-- even though she may all the time be carrying
			another new life under her heart. The pregnant woman should be well fed, or both she and
			the infant will suffer. But the mother will not and cannot feed herself sufficiently
			while husband and children go hungry. The man’s hours of labor are probably protected by
			his union rules, or by the general custom of the trade. But the hours of labor of the
			mother with a large family of little children know no limit and the frequent illnesses
			of children, brought up with insufficient food and other hygienic deficiencies, lengthen
			out these hours of labor until the day holds no more.</p>
		<p>The economic problem is much wider than the individual family. It touches all the workers
			of the world. The servitude of labor in every nation is usually in direct proportion to
			the rate of increase of the population. In facing its own problems, labor has to some
			degree recognized the evil due to the competition of numbers; but it has never fully
			grasped the connection between the birth rate and the wage rate. It has never been
			willing to acknowledge that the only solution of its difficulties lies in the limitation
			of families, and that until this done, and done by the workers themselves, other
			remedies for low wages long hours, and oppressive conditions are palliatives. They may
			do considerable good, but the incoming horde of workers is ever threatening
				the<del>n</del><add>ir</add>
			<add>stability</add> and labor can never be secure in its victories until it is safe
			from this ever-increasing competition from its own children.</p>
		<p>The theories of Socialists and the attacks upon capitalism have served to absorb the
			minds of the Labor leaders and to distract their attention from the basal cause of their
			poverty as compared with the wealth that they produce, and they seem to have overlooked
			the fact that no matter what benefits they could secure by a change in the industrial
			system all such benefits would disappear, leaving scarcely a trace behind, if they had
			to share them with ever-increasing numbers.</p>
		<p>The trade unions, especially those of highly skilled workers recognize the relation
			between high wages and small numbers. They have steadily fought for the limitation of
			the number of apprentice, and for making conditions of entrance into their unions
			difficult. But these same men have apparently not recognized the general solidarity of
			labor, nor the fact that the uncontrolled entry into the ranks of labor of the younger
			generation makes ever more difficult the maintenance of the advantages they have secured
			for themselves. Even if their policy secures their own livelihood, it does nothing to
			open up opportunities for their children who must find places for themselves in the
			working world.</p>
		<p>As for “free” labor generally -- we have only to look at the state of the world after the
			close of the great war. Millions of the most perfect physically, the most capable and
			most intelligent of the young men of all the belligerent countries were killed or
			entirely disabled during the titanic struggle. There was a feeling during the war that
			the world would be short of workers, and that it would be necessary for those who
			remained to produce more per man then ever before. Yet within three years unemployment
			was the most striking fact that faced the workers, and in the winter of 1921-22, in
				<place reg="United States">America</place>, the richest country in the world, and
				<del>the</del>
			<add>a </add>country which had suffered nothing from the ravages of war, there instances
			of more than a hundred men applying for a single job of unskilled labor, and other
			instances of men, highly skilled in some trade, who from no fault of their own were
			begging the opportunity to earn a little by shoveling snow in the city streets.</p>
		<p>It is not only men who are competing against each other, and making more difficult the
			struggle for each of them. Large families mean child labor, and the children become the
			means of forcing down the wages of their parents. With a family of two or three children
			the self-respected working man can often afford to continue their education into the
			high school, and even sometimes to send them to college. When the children number six or
			eight, the eldest must necessarily go to work as soon as they can get their working
			papers, and sisters and brothers follow each other into the labor market at the earliest
			possible moment.</p>
		<p>The more children a woman has, and the greater the burden upon her at home, the greater
			is also the necessity for her to go out and earn something to eke out the family income.
			She is needed at home. The children will suffer from neglect if she goes to work. But
			the family must eat, and the greater need takes precedence. If she is still of child
			bearing age-- and it is the woman still bearing children, whose family, on account of
			the youth of the elder children, most needs the earning power of the mother. <add>out
				H</add>er health will probably break under the strain. Such a consideration cannot
			deter her. She goes to work under the lash of absolute necessity.</p>
		<p>These competitors in the labor market-- the women and the children-- are unskilled and
			unorganized. They are obliged to take low wages, in most cases any wage that the
			employer may offer, and thus their competition brings down the general level of
			unskilled labor. So runs the vicious circle--large families forcing more workers into
			the labor market, and more workers causing lower wages, which again increase the number
			of workers, through the forcing of women and children into the labor market.</p>
		<p>It is hardly necessary to emphasize further the importance of the problem; <del>but</del>
			it <del>is necessary</del>
			<add>remains</add> to find the solution of it. Modern civilization has outgrown the
			crude checks on population offered by the customs of infanticide or abortion. These
			methods are still in use. If, in most civilized countries, parents have ceased to drown
			or expose their superfluous children, there are easy methods of allowing them to die for
			want of proper care or feeding.</p>
		<p>Abortion is far more common than infanticide. It has been estimated that the number of
			abortions in the United States every year amounts to not less than one million. Every
			such operation is illegal, and being illegal, is not undertaken by reputable and
			well-trained physicians. Women, desiring to rid themselves of unwanted children are
			therefore driven to quacks and ignorant practitioners whose methods aggravate enormously
			the ill-effects and the danger of the operation. Abortion skillfully performed at an
			early stage of pregnancy is much less drain on the strength of the mother than the
			carrying of the foetus to full time and the normal birth of the baby. But abortion as
			usually performed on the poorer mother, by the ignorant and unsanitary practitioner is
			not only almost equivalent in its demand on the patient to natural birth, but also
			carries with it innumerable dangers to health and even to life itself.</p>
		<p>In any case--apart from the question of its morality--abortion is a wasteful procedure.
			From the moment conception takes place the mother begins to give of her life and
			strength to the coming infant. Every day that pregnancy continues means just so much
			more of a drain on the mother. Even the most skillful abortion requires time and rest in
			order that the patient may recover, and all this represents sheer waste of <add>time
				and</add> life and strength. Abortion is condemned, because it is a destruction of
			human life already in existence and because it is a waste of the health and strength of
			the woman submitting to it. The answer to the problem is not to be found either in
			infanticide or in abortion.</p>
		<p>The solution advocated through the birth control movement lies in the prevention of
			conception. Prevention carries with it none of the waste of infanticide and abortion.
			Nature provides in vast superabundance the possibilities of new life. She gives the man
			in his semen countless millions of living cells each of which under fit circumstances
			could fertilize an ovum. She gives the women thousands of ova, the greater part of which
			must necessarily <del><unclear resp="MSPP">be aborted</unclear></del>
			<add>fail to develop</add> into new human beings. The most prolific of men and women
			could use for reproduction only a tiny percentage of the cells with which nature has
			provided them.</p>
		<p>To claim that it is perfectly right to allow a thousand ova to go to waste naturally, but
			wrong to prevent designedly the fertilization of the one thousand and first, is a
			proposition too absurd for serious consideration. To avoid child bearing by preventing
			the coming together of the male and female reproductive elements if what is done
			continually by the unmarried and widowed and by faithful husbands and wives absent from
			each other. To carry this process further and prevent conception when married people are
			living together is the problem that science is now solving, and <del>in</del>
			<add>with</add> the solution she is making man master of his own fate <del>as he is
				already master</del>, as he is already master of almost every other natural
			force.</p>
		<p>Until modern science made known the exact nature of the vitalizing seminal fluid and of
			the ova of the female, there seemed only one way in which the prevention of conception
			could be carried out. That was by continence-- strict limitation of sexual relations to
			the very few occasions when procreation of a child was desired. There are still many
			advocates of continence as the only really moral method of birth control. Such advocates
			are making a demand of human nature which is beyond the power of the average man and
			woman living together in happy marriage. It is also making a demand which is positively
			immoral, if morality is tested by the good or bad effect of conduct on human
			welfare.</p>
		<p>Sexual relations between men and women are the basis of family life. The more happy the
			marriage and the closer the affection and sympathy between husband and wife, the more
			intolerable the strain of continence enforced in order to avoid the bearing of too many
			children. The restraint which is necessary for such continence produces the most
				marked<add>ly</add> evil effects on both the man and woman. The man probably suffers
			from such continence most severely, and there are few men of normally strong sexual
			emotions who can stand it for any length of time without developing nervous or even
			mental disorders. Continence may be possible and consistent with health for a very few
			abnormal men, and a small proportion of women. But it offers no solution for the great
			problem of the too-large family, because it is a course of conduct utterly impossible to
			enforce, and highly detrimental to health and happiness if it could be consistently
			adhered to.</p>
		<p>Nor is it necessary to impose this hardship on married people in order that they may be
			enabled to control the number of their children. The only thing necessary is to prevent
			the coming together of the vitalizing male principle and the ovum, and means of
			preventing this are not beyond the reach of intelligent human beings. As yet there has
			been little careful scientific research into the subject and it may be that the methods
			hitherto used will soon appear crude and clumsy. The object of the advocates of Birth
			Control is not so much to teach any particular method of preventing the conception of
			the undesired child, as to arouse interest in the subject of over-population and to
			create public opinion in favor of restriction.</p>
		<p>Compulsory motherhood is the corner stone of the subjection of women, and the subjection
			of women is the basis of all the evils of over-population. Birth is the woman’s problem,
			and she must be put in a position to solve it for herself. She must have the right to
			her own body, and the right to choose when she will bear a child. If this right be made
			absolutely hers, there will be an end to the bearing of children for whom the world has
			no room and no opportunities; there will be an end to the bearing of diseased and
			defective children, for even the most inferior mother has too much mother-love to desire
			to bring into the world a child who will cause her grief instead of joy, and be to her
			the deepest humiliation that a human being can know instead of the crown of glory of
			true and happy maternity.</p>


	</docBody>
</doc>
