<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2003-12-01 ML</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-03-04 CH correct regs</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-11-13 CH clean regs</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-20 CH proofread tags and entered</prepDate>
		<docAuthor><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1925-04-00">
			<supplied>Apr 1925</supplied>
		</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>Sixth International Birth Control Conference</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp300258</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>
				<title>
					<supplied resp="MSPP">Unidentified newspaper</supplied>
				</title>
			</bibl>
			<bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Papers Microfilm, Collected Documents Series</title>
				C16:254</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp>
				<name reg="UNK">Unknown</name><name id="MALTH">Malthus, Thomas Robert</name>
			</resp>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>This article was found in a scrapbook with no identifying information about the
			newspaper. Portions of the text were obliterated with a hole punch.</p>
		<index level1="conferences"
			level2="International Neo-Malthusian and birth Control Conference" level3="1925 (6th)"/>
		<index level1="Malthusian League"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>The Sixth International Birth Control Conference</head>
		<byline>by <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>, <supplied resp="mspp"
				>President</supplied>
			<org>American Birth Control <supplied resp="mspp">League</supplied></org>; first
			President <org
				reg="International Federation of Neo-Malthusian and Birth Control Leagues"
				>International Birth Control League</org></byline>
		<div type="section">
			<q who="UNK"><p>Editorial Note--Throughout the world wherever birth control is advocated
					or considered, Mrs. Sanger is known as the outstanding leader of the Birth
					Control movement in America and as an indefatigable and fearless advocate in her
					writings and lectures of conscious and willing motherhood.</p></q>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<p>No less than twelve nations of the Orient and Occident were represented at the
					<org>Sixth International Neo-Malthusian and Birth Control Conference</org>,
				recently brought to a successful close in<place reg="New York, NY"> New
				York</place>. The Conference was held under the auspices of the American Birth
				Control League and was the first gathering of its kind, made up of delegates from
				every civilized country of the globe, ever held in the <place>United States</place>
				to discuss problems of population and racial health.</p>
			<p>Perhaps the most important achievement of the conference was to place the movement
				for a OPTIMUM population <gap reason="torn document" extent="one word"/> all
				countries, as opposed to <gap reason="torn document" extent="one word"/> population,
				on a soundly <gap reason="torn document" extent="two words"/> basis. On its
				scientific, philosophical and humanitarian basis, the conference emphasized the
				remarkable unanimity of opinion and harmony of thought among the delegates from all
				countries. This unity of thought has led to the organization of an international
				league, and plans were made nature to convene in <place>Geneva, Switzerland</place>
				in August, 1926, immediately before the session of the Assembly of the <org>League
					of Nations</org>.</p>
			<p>The first <org reg="Malthusian League">Neo-Malthusian League</org> was organized in
					<place>England</place> some fifty years ago. Its activities were based on the
				celebrated Malthusian theory, and were mainly economic in character. While not
				discarding the Malthusian law that "<q who="MALTH">everywhere the pressure of
					population presses against the means of subsistence</q>," the Sixth
				International conference put greater stress on the problem of contraception (or as
				it is popularly known Birth Control) in its medical, scientific, eugenic,
				psychological and ethical aspects.</p>
			<p>Ten years ago, when I inaugurated my campaign for conscious and voluntary motherhood
				among the poor women of <place reg="United States">America</place>, I was denounced
				and persecuted. Four years ago, a <org reg="American Birth Control Conference, 1st"
					>mass meeting</org> was broken up by the police of New York. The International
				Conference triumphantly vindicates my campaign, and indicates a remarkable progress
				in American thought. Not only were all the sessions accurately and fairly reported
				in the daily press, but the Birth Control movement has enlisted the support of the
				most eminent authorities in all fields- not only economists, statisticians,
				biologists, geneticists, physicians and psychologists, but also many pastors of the
				various Protestant churches. This achievement is the greater in view of the federal
				and state laws in the United States which forbid, even to doctors, the dissemination
				of contraceptive information.</p>
			<p><place>France</place>, which was once the nation in which Birth Control was most
				universally practiced, has since the war, begun an active propaganda for large
				families. Yet delegates from that country pointed out that the real menace is not a
				lowering birth rate of the children born, and that the practice of Birth Control
				continued despite all efforts to encourage larger families.</p>
			<p>One of the most interesting features of the conference was the sessions, on methods
				of contraception, for physicians only, held without interference despite the
				rigorous statutes of the State against even the discussion of contraception. More
				than one thousand physicians attended these sessions, held simultaneously in the
				ball rooms of two great New York hotels.</p>
			<p>The Sixth International Neo-Malthusian and Birth Control Conference marks the
				initiation of a new era of international thought and the beginning of a closely
				coordinated movement toward world-peace.</p>
		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
