<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published testimony">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/03/14 VS initial tagging</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/03/20 CH proof tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/03/26 VS correct tags</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1935-03-08">8 March, 1935</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Statement before House of Representatives on H.R. 5370</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp300450</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="book">Offenses Against the Postal Service; Hearings before
                    Subcommittee #8 of the Committee on the Post Office and Post Roads, House of
                    Representatives, Seventy-Fourth Congress, First Session on HR 154, HR 3252, HR
                    5049, HR 5162, HR 5360 and HR 5370.</title>Washington, D.C., 1935, pp. 45-49 and
                95-100.</bibl>
            <bibl><title>MSMC15:902</title></bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="DOBDO">Dobbins, Donald C.</name>
            <name id="ASHWI">Ashbrook, William A.</name>
            <name id="GOOPH">Goodwin, Philip A.</name>
            <name id="HIGWI">Higgins, William L.</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">Sanger testified in opposition to H.R. 5370 before the seventy-fourth
        Congress on H.R. 5370, which provided a penalty for anyone who shall knowingly cause obscene
        matter to be delivered by mail or to be delivered at the place at which it is directed to be
        delivered <index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="suppression of"/>
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="doctor's only laws"/>
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Postal Code and Regulations"/>
        <index level1="birth control methods" level2="safe period"/>
        <index level1="Book Review" level2="response to a"/>
        <index level1="censorship" level2="in United States"/>
        <index level1="Europe" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Hearings Before Subcommittee No. 8 of the <org>Committee on The Post Office and Post
                Roads</org></head>
        <byline>H.R. 5370</byline>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Statement Of <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>,
                President <org>National Committee On Legislation For Birth Control</org></head>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger: I think that this <name reg="H.R. 5370">bill, 5370</name>, is unwise
                legislation. I think it is not only unwise as it stands without the amendment, but
                it can be dangerous, it can be vicious, it can be menacing to the highest thought
                and educational development of the country. </p>
            <p> Now, there has been a constant talk in the former hearing which I have read that
                this bill pertains only to indecent, obscene literature, but I have a copy of a
                letter that accompanied, or rather asked that this bill be drafted at the request of
                the <person reg="Farley, James A.">Postmaster General</person> in which it is
                indicated, and I think this letter is on record, in your committee, that one of the
                objects of this bill is to make it easier to prosecute those who send unsolicited
                literature advertising the sale of contraceptives so that very definitely this law
                does pertain to that one section which is only part of the law, so that I think you
                cannot disclaim, as has been intimated, that the objection is, only the use of
                pornographic or indecent literature. We should consider that this law was passed by
                    <org reg="United States Congress">Congress</org> 62 years ago, classifying every
                known thing relating to sex in an obscenity clause, abortion, prevention of
                conception, with no exemptions for members of the medical profession to use the
                mails, with no exemptions for literature that may be scientific, that may be
                medical, or which may be considered art. </p>
            <p> Now I am particularly concerned and I have been for the past 20 years, in trying to
                shake this law apart, and why I am here today is because I believe that the work of
                20 years has been successful to a certain degree in raising the level of
                intelligence regarding this question of what is obscene throughout the country today
                and 20 years ago. When I started this movement as a trained nurse I found the post
                office inspectors and officials thought everything was obscene and indecent. We had
                to educate a great many of them. I have had to patiently educate a great many of
                these people and shake this thing apart and make them realizes that certain things
                weren’t indecent and obscene or pornographic. We are the only country in the world
                today hat has classed contraception with obscenity. We are the laughing stock of the
                world so far as this particular law is concerned and now we are trying to tighten it
                up and make it even more difficult than it ever has been before. We have been
                gradually trying to get the people to look at this subject in the right way, to
                cultivate their minds, as to what is decent and what is obscene, and what is
                considered scientific. </p>
            <p> Now, I believe too, that this law should have the exemption for physicians and
                hospitals and public-health agencies, medical schools, since after all the doctors
                have been unable to teach contraception in their medical schools, as Dr. <person
                    reg="Willson, Prentiss">Willson</person> will tell you, because this law has
                been operating for the past 62 years. It has been said that the <org
                    reg="United States Post Office">Post Office Department</org> does not intend to
                investigate honorable high-minded members of the profession; some people say, no,
                they are not going to trouble them. Of course, any law-abiding doctor does not want
                to do anything to cause loss of life directly or indirectly, but due to these laws
                that you are asking to have amended to make them more vicious and dangerous, the
                damage that this law has caused is almost impossible to compute in human lives, in
                the death of women of child-bearing age. </p>
            <p> It has also been suggested that this law is similar to the <title type="law">Mails
                    Fraud Act</title>. I do not think that is a fair comparison because after all
                fraud is something that is more or less static. I know what fraud is, what the
                intention of that act is. But obscenity is not a static thing. It moves with the
                years. it moves with intelligence. It changes with geographical boundaries. I was in
                    <place>Japan</place> a few years ago with my small boy, 13 years old, and he
                looked bigger than 13, looked like a grown man, and as is the custom in our country,
                a mother going with her boy to take at train, he kissed me in getting on the train,
                and as you know, kissing is not practiced and is regarded as indecent or immoral in
                Japan, and I assure you it was with great difficulty that we escaped mobbing because
                it was an offense to the people of Japan to have my son kiss me in saying goodby.
                That is just an illustration of what can happen with geographical boundaries in
                construing what is decent or indecent. </p>
            <p> I am acquainted with this law, and with all due respect to the gentleman who is
                trying to amend it with bill H. R. 5370, and the one who drafted this bill, and I
                know the great harm it causes, because I have been watching this thing. I know that
                ideas of obscenity differ. There are marvelous prints that have been prohibited from
                coming into this country from Japan, prints that were hundreds of years old, and
                because of a lack of understanding on the part of the Post Office officials who do
                not know the difference between obscenity and art. I say it is vicious. I say you
                should not bring a person out of <place reg="New York, NY">New York</place> or
                    <place reg="Chicago, IL">Chicago</place> or some place else into a smaller
                community where the minds of your rural judge or officials may be more obligated to
                those in power than in New York, our large city. I consider that is an unfair thing,
                a dangerous thing; I think it is dangerous to the growth of the country, of the
                community, and that is why we are trying to do something about this. Parents are
                trying to educate their children in the concept of the sanctity of life and of the
                marital relations today. However, if we are to be subject to Post Office officials,
                to an inspector who may have a very low-class mind himself, if we have to take time
                to educate those people so that parents can have what may be considered decent, I
                think it is a very dangerous situation. </p>
            <p> There is much confusion as to what is obscene and what is not obscene. I have
                pamphlets and books here before me on which we have tried to get information from
                the Post Office officials. I, of course, am primarily concerned with this clause of
                the prevention of conception. Some of us who study the subject realize that there
                are many methods of contraception. This law, as I say, and as the doctors will tell
                you, has made no exemption for them. But in spite of this law we have painfully
                carried on and it has taken years to try to develop something so that we could help
                hundreds of thousands of mothers throughout the country because, unlike the Federal
                law, in most States the State laws are not prohibitive. There is only one State in
                    <place reg="United States">the Union</place> where the same tightness of the
                Federal law is operative in the State, and that is <place>Mississippi</place>. What
                other States do is to give some leeway o the medical profession. Methods are
                different as we find them all over the country, and we have tried to find out from
                the Post Office Department if there has been a change of attitude and if a physician
                could legally receive through the mails books and literature pertaining to the
                subject of conception. Here is an excerpt from a larger book on contraceptive
                practices brought out by a physician and we asked if this could go through the mails
                to doctors and medical schools. The decision was “no,” that it was nonmailable. This
                is a scientific medical piece of literature and word has come from the Post Office
                Department that it is not mailable. </p>
            <p> On the other hand, here is another piece of literature that goes through the mails
                and it is called “<title type="book">Rhythm</title>,” with an explanatory calendar
                enclosure. We asked about this book. This book happens to have “ecclesiastical
                approbation.” This book is stated by the Postmaster General to be mailable. One of
                these is unmailable to physicians, but this one, “Rhythm,” is going to the public
                through the mails. I say this is unfair. I say that this thing 211, says, any
                information showing how or by what means one may prevent conception is illegal, and
                when you open this book you will find that there is a calendar given here to show
                the exact hour when there may be a period of sterility when marital relations may
                occur without pregnancy. I consider this is far more dangerous to the welfare of the
                country and to womanhood, and much more immoral. </p>
            <q who="DOBDO"><p> Mr. <person reg="Dobbins, Donald C.">Dobbins</person>: May I inquire,
                    has the mailing of that been expressly approved by the Post Office?</p></q>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger: Yes; I have letters here showing that. Not only that but there is a
                little calendar that may be purchased for a dollar, to show how this theory may be
                worked, presumably making it easier and simpler, and there is no question about it.
                But this other medical book cannot be carried to the doctors because of the opinion
                of the Post Office officials. I say this thing is unfair, and I consider it to be
                very unfair to leave it in such a state. Here is another book, “<title type="book"
                    >Biological and Medical Aspects of Contraception</title>,” by scientists and
                medical men and women. This book happens to have both of these theories. It happens
                to be a combination because it as a summary of a conference that discussed both of
                those theories. This is all in the realm of medicine and science, and when this book
                was presented to the Post Office Deparment, finding that they had passed the
                decision on one method showing that it was nonmailable and on the other that it was
                mailable, and that this book contained both methods, they said they were not in a
                position to give a decision. </p>
            <p> I think It is unfair to leave this thing in this loose way and if you are going to
                tighten up on what is so-called “obscene,” I think we ought to say what obscenity is
                and I think we ought to take into consideration the attitude today compared to what
                it was when this law was passed 62 years ago. There has been a great change of
                public opinion. There is a greater conscience and a greater desire on the part of
                everybody, in my estimation, to have more knowledge to make the things of life a
                little more beautiful, and I say if we keep on putting off cultivating this
                knowledge, classifying scientific and medical knowledge in the obscenity statute, we
                are just simply going to continue regarding the subject as obscene and making it
                more difficult to enforce the law than ever before. H. R. 5370 will serve to
                strengthen the present confusion between contraception and pornography. It will
                affect publishers of what may be termed decent literature, both books and magazines,
                as well as actual pornography. If publishes are able to bring out and distribute
                anything dealing with the question of sex or marriage or contraception, it will not
                be by right but by privilege of the Post Office authorities. History has taught us
                that privilege is closely associated with the abuse of power, with tribute and with
                graft. </p>
            <p> Twenty years ago I was indicted through action brought by the Post Office officials
                on 9 counts. I had not sent any information through the mails except a discussion of
                the question really with less frankness than I am discussing here with you today,
                and yet on nine of those counts I was indicted. </p>
            <p> Thank heavens there were a few judges in New York who had more intelligence than the
                Post Office officials or I would have been spending 45 years in jail if I had been
                depending on the attitude and intelligence of a Post Office official. But there was
                a judge, and several Federal judges in New York, who looked upon this in a different
                way, and that is why I am here today. We have welcomed a finer attitude on the part
                of Federal judges in not lowering the level by bringing these men who write books or
                have information to a narrow circle where there is a possibility of indictment. </p>
            <p> I do not think the Post Office Department should recommend this bill without the
                amendment. I ask you gentlemen to consider this amendment sincerely, so that at
                least we will know that certain people are exempt from this law when they are
                qualified to be exempt, as I believe physicians and hospitals should be. </p>
            <q who="ASHWI"><p> Mr. <person reg="Ashbrook, William A.">Ashbrook</person>: May I
                    inquire of you when an opinion was rendered by the Post Office Department on the
                    first little book, that it was mailable?</p></q>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger: Mailable; yes. </p>
            <q who="ASHWI"><p> Mr. Ashbrook: When? </p></q>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger: February 20, 1934, and there have been several since. </p>
            <q who="ASHWI"><p> Mr. Ashbrook: And when was the larger book decided not
                mailable?</p></q>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger: March 9, 1934. You are welcome to see them all. </p>
            <q who="GOOPH"><p> Mr. <person reg="Goodwin, Ohilip A.">Goodwin</person>: Is the subject
                    matter similar in the two bulletins?</p></q>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger: No; they are not similar. One is this little book that pertains to the
                period of fertility or sterility in the menstrual cycle of the female. The other
                deals with scientific, chemical, and mechanical contraceptives. </p>
            <q who="GOOPH"><p> Mr. Goodwin: Would that be the reason for the decision?</p></q>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger: It may be, as far as the law is concerned, but it says any information.
                The law, section 211, definitely says, any information. </p>
            <q who="GOOPH"><p> Mr. Goodwin: H. R. 5370 is the obscene bill, so to speak. You are not
                    against that bill?</p></q>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger: I am not against that bill but I think without the amendment I should
                be. I think we need an amendment in all fairness to the whole public attitude
                throughout the country. </p>
            <q who="DOBDO"><p> Mr. Dobbins: With respect to the distinction between these two
                    proposed pieces of mail matter, did not the Department make a distinction that
                    one related to facts and the other mechanical, chemical, or actual acts of
                    contravention?</p></q>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger: No; that was not made clear in this. Of course, the law, section 211,
                does not make that distinction. </p>
            <q who="DOBDO"><p> Mr. Dobbins: It uses the word prevention, not avoidance. </p></q>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger: Yes, sir. </p>
            <q who="DOBDO"><p> Mr. Dobbins: With reference to the amendment proposed by our
                    colleague, Congressman <person reg="Pierce, Walter M.">Pierce</person>, you have
                    read that?</p></q>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger: Yes, sir. </p>
            <q who="DOBDO"><p> Mr. Dobbins: Do you believe in legalizing the promiscuous
                    distribution of information, advertisements, concerning contraceptives
                    throughout the mails to unsolicited persons who have not solicited that
                    information, school girls and boys?</p></q>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger: Let us clarify that. </p>
            <q who="DOBDO"><p> Mr. Dobbins: That can be easily answered. </p></q>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger: The amendment that Mr. Pierce submitted is very definite in that it
                says, “physicians and hospitals.”</p>
            <q who="DOBDO"><p> Mr. Dobbins: Mailed by them. </p></q>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger: Or under their control. </p>
            <q who="DOBDO"><p> Mr. Dobbins: You know that nearly all the people we indict for
                    sending this stuff through the mails are physicians who cannot secure a
                    legitimate practice, and retain their license and go into the advertising
                    business, sending their stuff through the mails. </p></q>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger: I am not sure of that. Dr. Willson can answer that. Regarding
                soliciting, how are physicians to know the means or methods that a laboratory has
                found or discovered? How can a physician know unless he is circularized? </p>
            <q who="DOBDO"><p> Mr. Dobbins: I cannot see any objection to sending from one physician
                    to another or from any source to a physician, but I am thinking of sending these
                    advertisements regarding contraceptives to those who are in the adolescent age
                    and who are eager to get such information. We have all passed through that and
                    we know the human attitude. </p></q>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger: Quite right. Exactly; that is why I believe this amendment that Mr.
                Pierce is asking today will take care of that. </p>
            <q who="DOBDO"><p> Mr. Dobbins: Do you not think it out to be confined to men like
                    physicians, nurses, and organizations of that sort, rather than promiscuous
                    distribution?</p></q>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger: Absolutely. </p>
            <q who="GOOPH"><p> Mr Goodwin: Where do nurses come in on this?</p></q>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger: Nurses are not mentioned in the bill at all. </p>
            <q who="DOBDO"><p> Mr. Dobbins: This related only to mails by doctors and lets any
                    doctor licensed mail it to anyone, to any list that he has purchased from a
                    magazine or somebody, and permits him to distribute it through the mails.
                </p></q>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger: I think Dr. Willson will testify on that when you get to him. </p>
            <q who="DOBDO"><p> Mr. Dobbins: We have them in great numbers. </p></q>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger: The medical profession takes care of that themselves. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Statement of Margaret Sanger-- Resumed</head>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger: I just want to say, so far as birth control is concerned, that we have
                not presented a case for it. We have brought in a few insignificant and conservative
                amendments in connection with the whole question. </p>
            <p> From those who have opposed this amendment this morning I gather than you have heard
                in a way only one side of the question. There is one point that <person
                    reg="Ryan, John Augustine">Monsignor Ryan</person> made that needs, in my
                opinion, to be clarified. Again and again he referred to the declining birth rate.
                He confused it with stationary or declining population. The population of the United
                States shows that population has increased naturally because we have had very little
                immigration since 1914 and scarcely any since 1924. We say that the population
                growth is a natural one. We have increased since 1920 and up to 1934 20,000,000. </p>
            <q who="ASHWI"><p> Mr. Ashbrook: How does that compare with the previous decade, if you
                    know?</p></q>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger: The birth rate has come down, but it does not mean so much because
                there are more thousands to compute the figures on. It is like a person saying one
                is poor because he gets only 5 percent and another saying he is rich, because he
                gets 50 percent. We cannot stop there-- it is 5 percent on what, 50 percent on what?
                Five percent on $1,000,000 and 50 percent on $1,000 are very different. </p>
            <p> Our birth rate goes down because there is a higher regard for the sanctity of life.
                The death rate has declined while the birth rate has gone down. We have to compare
                those where the birth rate and the death rate rise, as in <place>China</place> and
                other such countries, and those where the birth rate and the death rate have
                declined. That does not mean a decline in population. </p>
            <p> We have a better and a stronger national consciousness in this country than we had
                40 years ago. It is much stronger. One feels it in New York. You feel that the whole
                country of 120,000,000 population is more centered on what you are doing today than
                it was 10 or 12 years ago. It is growing as our population grows slowly. That is the
                thing I want to check. </p>
            <q who="DOBDO"><p> Mr. Dobbins: Have you any figures to serve as a comparison between
                    the United States and other countries covering the birth of infants who live to
                    the age of 1 year?</p></q>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger: Yes; our infant rate has declined. It has not, however, declined so
                rapidly as has <place>England</place>’s. England, <place>Australia</place>, and
                    <place reg="Netherlands">Holland</place> have very low infant mortality rates.
                England today has a lower birth rate than <place>France</place>. France has
                frequently been referred to as a country of stationary population. It is not
                stationary, but it has been growing slowly. It has not had organized birth control.
                They have based upon that one neighbor has told another, what one person has told
                another, without its being scientific. Everybody has had a formula to give to
                somebody else. </p>
            <p> Holland has organized, and she has a growing population. I studied this question
                there in 1915. The death rate has gone down more rapidly than the birth rate. Nurses
                go into the homes there when a child dies and find out the cause of death. They help
                to space the birth of children. They advise parents not to have children until they
                can afford them. </p>
            <p> We are the only country that confuses birth control and obscenity. Only two other
                countries, <place>Italy</place> and France, make the sale of contraceptive articles
                illegal. </p>
            <q who="HIGWI"><p> Mr. <person reg="Higgins, William L.">Higgins</person>: Would you
                    look with favor upon a proposal that this matter be clarified by embracing it
                    all in one law? </p></q>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger: Yes. </p>
            <q who="HIGWI"><p> Mr. Higgins: Could you persuade Mr. Pierce to make a change
                    accordingly?</p></q>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger: In making a law, in tightening this, we have to undo what you are
                doing. If you tighten this and let it go, and not allow physicians and hospitals to
                be expected from the law, we shall be going around in a vicious circle trying to
                undo such legislation as you are trying to pass with this bill. </p>
            <q who="HIGWI"><p> Mr. Higgins: By introducing a separate bill embodying Mr. Pierce’s
                    idea, all that you desire would be accomplished, would it not?</p></q>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger: Do you mean in straightening out the three codes? </p>
            <q who="HIGWI"><p> Mr. Higgins: Yes; the confusion. That has been tried, has it not, in
                    this present Congress? </p></q>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger: No; all we have asked is an amendment on three section, not only
                section 211. but other sections. </p>
            <q who="HIGWI"><p> Mr. Higgins: As a matter of fact the proposed amendment to section
                    211 has been there in the <org
                        reg="United States Congress Committee on the Judiciary">Committee on the
                        Judiciary</org> for some time and has been defeated?</p></q>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger: Not so far; we still have hopes. </p>
            <q who="DOBDO"><p> Mr. Dobbins: The legislation there was not as restrictive. I think
                    that legislation allowed the dissemination by-- </p></q>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger: In that bill physicians, hospitals, and clinics are exempted from the
                present statutes. We are not of the opinion that the free dissemination of
                information should be promiscuous. </p>
            <q who="DOBDO"><p> Mr. Dobbins: I think you allowed the information to be sent to them
                    by anybody. A physician might establish himself and send the information to
                    anybody in the United States under that bill. </p></q>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger: I think there is a distinction in those who should give information and
                those should get it. The person giving it should be properly qualified. That is my
                quarrel with this book on the <title type="book">Rhythm</title>. I feel that
                eventually we might find a period of sterility in the cycle of the woman’s life. it
                is said that premature abortions have increased since this book has been on the
                market. </p>
            <p> I am amused to hear Monsignor Ryan and Miss <person reg="Regan, Agnes Gertrude"
                    >Regan</person> talk in this absurd way when their own book and another such
                book with impramature by Cardinal <person reg="Hayes, Patrick Joseph">Hayes</person>
                is sold at random. I have sent for them. I have sent young girls from our office to
                Catholic book hops to get these books. The same effect is obtained by the safe
                period and a means of contraception. I think it is inconsistent to come here and
                object when we are simply trying to place this matter in proper hands, so that there
                will be some proper control over the dissemination of this information. </p>
            <q who="HIGWI"><p> Mr. Higgins: Would you favor an amendment to existing law that would
                    be the <title type="book">Rhythm</title> and put the word “avoidance” in the
                    same classification as the word “prevention”?</p></q>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger: It all should be in the hands of qualified persons. </p>
            <q who="HIGWI"><p> Mr. Higgins: Would you favor a law to bar that book from the
                    mails?</p></q>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger: I would have to think about that before answering. The idea of
                avoidance and prevention is splitting hairs. I am not an attorney and I should have
                to think about that before answering. But I will say that many of the points brought
                out here seem perfectly absurd. </p>
            <q who="HIGWI"><p> Mr. Higgins: It is my impression that the chief post-office
                    inspector, Mr. <person reg="Aldrich, K. P.">Aldrich</person>, would do a
                    commendable thing for the <org reg="Roman Catholic Church">Catholic Church</org>
                    if he barred that damn book the Rhythm from the mails. </p></q>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger: As I remember, Dr. Ryan stated that the <org>Associated Press</org> and
                the <org>United Press</org> had put out statements about the increases of the
                families on relief. One is by Professor <person reg="Bossard, James Herbert"
                    >Bossard</person>, <org>University of Pennsylvania</org>; another by Professor
                    <person reg="Sydenstriker, Edgar">Sydenstricker</person> and Professor <person
                    reg="Perrott, George St. John">Perrott</person>, of the <org>Milbank Memorial
                    Fund</org>, and another by Professor <person reg="Stouffer, Samuel Andrew"
                    >Stouffer</person>, of the <org>University of Wisconsin</org>. The studies cover
                three sections of the country and show that the birth rate of families on relief is
                from 45 percent to 60 percent higher than the births in families not on relief. </p>
            <p><supplied resp="MSPP">A transcription of a <title type="journal">New York
                        Times</title> article "<title type="article">High Birth Rates Worry Federal
                        Emergency Relief Administration Heads</title>" from May 10, 1935 and a
                        <title type="journal">Time</title> article, "<title type="article">Relief
                        and Babies</title>," from April 8, 1935, were not included in this
                    transcription</supplied></p>
            <q who="HIGWI"><p> Mr. Higgins: Is the amendment to section 211, which amendment is now
                    before the Committee on the Judiciary, as broad as this? </p></q>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger: It is broader but similar to this. It allows dissemination of the
                information by hospitals, physicians, and clinics. </p>
            <q who="HIGWI"><p> Mr. Higgins: You are not concerned with the same confusion that
                    concerns Mr. <person reg="Ernst, Morris Leopold">Ernst</person>?</p></q>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger: This book called “<title type="book">The Rhythm</title>” is allowed to
                go through the mails, while other related information is considered obscene; and I
                think that is a confusion. This is the opportunity to take the first step to clear
                this confusion; and that is my interest. </p>
            <q who="DOBDO"><p> Mr. Dobbins: You say you see no distinction between <title
                        type="book">The Rhythm</title>, which is a method of avoidance, and a means
                    to prevent?</p></q>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger: The law says “any information, directly or indirectly.”</p>
            <q who="DOBDO"><p> Mr. Dobbins: It links that up with its reference to contraceptive
                    devices?</p></q>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger: It does. Another section says drugs, but does not mention information. </p>
            <q who="DOBDO"><p> Mr. Dobbins: In other words, whether It be avoidance or prevention
                    through mechanical devices, you see no distinction in morals?</p></q>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger: No; absolutely not, insofar as morals are concerned. One is scientific,
                and the other is not. </p>
            <q who="DOBDO"><p> Mr. Dobbins: One involves having sexual intercourse and the other
                    involves not having it. </p></q>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger: The scientific point is that intercourse at that time, when nature has
                closed her doors, might be a detriment physiologically and physically to the woman. </p>
            <q who="HIGWI"><p> Mr. Higgins: It might be or is it known to be?</p></q>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger: It might be; when nature has closed the doors of the woman’s
                reproductive life, there is a question. Even the lower animals will not allow
                cohabitation at such times. Why should we have a law to have intercourse at that
                time and refuse scientific means when nature has not closed the door. </p>
            <p> -- </p>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger: Another such <name
                    reg="Catholic Faith, Based on the Catholic Catechism">book</name> states,
                “Written by <person reg="Scanlan, Arthur J.">A. J. Scanlan</person>, S.T. D.,
                approved by Patrick Cardinal Hayes, December 8, 1932.” If that is not approved by
                the Catholic Church, what does the English language mean? Then it is a fraud-- if
                church papers advertise these books that are not approved by the church. </p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
