<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="(Published testimony) ">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/04/02 VS initial tagging</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="(1932-07-23) ">23 June, 1932</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Testimony before the U.S. Senate on S. 4436</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp300447</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Birth Control</title> pp. 1-12</bibl>
            <bibl><title>MSM</title> or LCM C15:814</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="AUSWA">Austin, Warren Robinson</name>
            <name id="MSPP">Margaret Sanger Papers Project</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">Margaret Sanger testifies before the Comittee on the Judiciary of the
        United States Senate pertaining to S. 4436. <index level1="birth control"
            level2="distribution of information about"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits and risks"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"
            level3="negative consequences of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="physical justifications for"/>
        <index level1="birth control methods"/>
        <index level1="birth control methods" level2="condom"/>
        <index level1="birth control methods" level2="douche"/>
        <index level1="birth control methods" level2="efficacy of"/>
        <index level1="birth control methods" level2="female"/>
        <index level1="birth control methods" level2="male"/>
        <index level1="birth control methods" level2="pessaries"/>
        <index level1="Europe" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="freedom and rights of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Hearings before a Subcommittee of the Committee on the Judiciary United States Senate
            Seventy-Second Congress</head>
        <byline>First Session on S. 4436 A Bill to Amend Section 305 (A) of the Tariff Act of 1930,
            and Sections 211, 245, and 312 of the Cirminal Code as Amended.</byline>
        <dateline>June 24 and 30, 1932 <date value="1932-07-23 "/></dateline>
        <q who="AUSWA"><p> Senator <person reg="Austin, Warren Robinson">Austin</person>: Mrs.
                    <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger</person>, <org
                    reg="Committee on the Judiciary of the United States Senate">the committee</org>
                wanted to resume these hearings in order to get more definite information bearing
                upon the precise question of that the immediate necessity is for the passage of
                    <name reg="S. 4436">this act</name>, and there were certain ideas the committee
                wanted to develop. Perhaps you have others also, but if you do not mind, I would
                like to ask you a few questions which would indicate our objectives and the kind of
                evidence we would like to get. In he first place, I would like to ask you about the
                practical side of this thing. What knowledge is there that would be available that
                is not now available, regarding the use of contraceptives, if this act were
                passed?</p></q>
        <p> Mrs. Sanger: As to the practical side, perhaps, it may be of interest to the committee
            to know that until 1915 the information they had in this country at that time applied
            only to the use by the male. Practically nothing was known on the whole general subject
            of contraceptives. I say it with a certain amount of pride, personally, that when I
            began to study this question as a trained nurse, and realized that the people we were
            trying to help most were the ones where the husbands were not so concerned about helping
            the women. I, therefore, started to make a general survey of the whole subject. I went
            to <place>Europe</place> and studied in 1915 and 1916, and in <place reg="Netherlands"
                >Holland</place> I found that it was almost an old subject. They had proper
            information. They had different devices entirely, not depending upon the use by the
            male, but by the woman herself, placing the responsibility of the birth of a child
            mainly upon the woman’s shoulders, and Doctor <person reg="Mensinga, Wilhelm Peter"
                >Mensinga</person> and another doctor invented a kind of pessary, which was
            harmless. This pessary was fitted to each individual. They made plaster paris casts of
            the different women until they got a certain number of pessaries of different sizes. </p>
        <q who="AUSWA"><p> Senator Austin: How many?</p></q>
        <p> Mrs. Sanger: They have different kinds. When I was there I saw at least 15 different
            kinds, with at least 20 different sizes in Holland. They had been giving contraceptive
            advice; instructions in such a normal, natural way; it was part of their whole general
            economic living. </p>
        <q who="AUSWA"><p> Senator Austin: May I interrupt you and ask if those pessaries were used
                with gelatin?</p></q>
        <p> Mrs. Sanger: Not at that time. </p>
        <q who="AUSWA"><p> Senator Austin: Was their use accompanied by a douche?</p></q>
        <p> Mrs. Sanger: Douches, in most of those countries are rather difficult. They do teach
            them a cleansing process of a douche, a spray douche, but it was not necessary. They
            teach them cleansing with toilet paper, or cotton, or some means of cleansing, but the
            pessary was washed in soap and water. They use soap and water a great deal. It was very
            primitive, and they had to teach the women to use the things in the home because of the
            expense. </p>
        <p> In <place>France</place>, douching is more prevalent and more applied there than in
            Holland, but speaking of Holland, they have for 40 years used these contraceptive
            appliances which are removed so that the woman’s organs are kept healthy and in a normal
            condition. I found there that the infant mortality rate had gone down in proportion,
            that the birth rate had gone down, but the survival was very much higher than in any
            country in Europe. Infant mortality rate was the lowest at that time, in the cities
            where they had clinics, <place reg="The Hague, Netherlands">The Hague</place>, <place
                reg="Amsterdam, Netherlands">Amsterdam</place>, <place reg="Rotterdam, Netherlands"
                >Rotterdam</place>-- those cities had the lowest rate in the world. I was interested
            to discover how their practice of contraception would affect the morality of the people,
            and I went to the central bureau of statistics at The Hague, and told them what I
            wanted. I was practically challenged to find a native woman living in prostitution-- a
            native woman. They said, “We have prostitutes in Holland, but you will not find a Dutch
            woman living in prostitution.” I said, “Why, is there any difference in human nature?”
            and they said, “Our family life is different.” “We begin earlier and encourage early
            marriage among our younger people, and in that way when the girl and boy in our
            districts, in the butter and cheese districts, or in other districts are encouraged to
            marry early, they both work for one or two years after the marriage,” and the question
            of having a baby was considered very practical, for instance, in the light of or on the
            basis of purchasing a piano, or any other expense.</p>
        <q who="AUSWA"><p> Senator Austin: You do not mind if I interrupt you?</p></q>
        <p> Mrs. Sanger: No. </p>
        <q who="AUSWA"><p> Senator Austin: We have one hour to try and find out a great deal here.
                Of these various types of devices, are there any that are not available in this
                country at the present time? </p></q>
        <p> Mrs. Sanger: Yes, indeed: some very important ones. </p>
        <q who="AUSWA"><p> Senator Austin: What are they?</p></q>
        <p> Mrs. Sanger: There is a pessary which is of a special form, a special shape which they
            have in Holland and other countries, which protects the woman. In Holland,
                <place>Germany</place>, and in <place>England</place> there are no types of women
            that can not be protected, but have to depend on those bootlegged here. </p>
        <q who="AUSWA"><p> Senator Austin: Are they all made of rubber?</p></q>
        <p> Mrs. Sanger: Yes. </p>
        <q who="AUSWA"><p> Senator Austin: And the ring principle with the diaphragm involved in all
                of them?</p></q>
        <p> Mrs. Sanger: Yes; but all of them are different. Each woman has to be examined, and the
            kind that would fit one woman may not fit another. </p>
        <p> I would like to emphasize the fact that there is no one thing that we are pushing. We
            have no interest whatsoever in any particular device. </p>
        <q who="AUSWA"><p> Senator Austin: Is there any device excepting the pessary that they have
                in Europe which is not available here?</p></q>
        <p> Mrs. Sanger: Different kinds of pessaries! They are investigating, I think,
            experimenting with some interesting things there. There are three experiments. One is a
            serum that they believe will immunize the female from conception for a certain period of
            time. </p>
        <q who="AUSWA"><p> Senator Austin: Is that a sort of emulsion?</p></q>
        <p> Mrs. Sanger: No; I believe it is an injection of a special serum, like an antitoxin.
            That is an experiment. </p>
        <q who="AUSWA"><p> Senator Austin: Taken in the blood?</p></q>
        <p> Mrs. Sanger: Yes; in the blood. </p>
        <p> The next is the vitamin E, which they are experimenting with, which they claim has a
            definite effect on sterility or fertility of the male or female. </p>
        <q who="AUSWA"><p> Senator Austin: Is that permanent?</p></q>
        <p> Mrs. Sanger: No. They are experimenting, but they want them to be temporary. Where
            vitamin E is, there is a certain high fertility or low fertility in its absence, and
            then there is another extract made from the corpus lutem with which they are
            experimenting. All these new experiments are going on open and above board in <org
                reg="University of Oxford">Oxford</org>, <org reg="University of Cambridge"
                >Cambridge</org>, and in Europe .The plan will be of great importance and
            significance to the whole population. </p>
        <q who="AUSWA"><p> Senator Austin: Are there any other mechanical devices which you have
                suggested which might be available if this law were changed, that are not now
                available?</p></q>
        <p> Mrs. Sanger: Well, I should think mainly, as far as I know, they are the pessaries of
            different kinds and different types. Of course, jellies are also combined with the
            pessaries to-day, and chemicals are used. The intrauterine pessaries are advised by
            physicians, but that is in an experimental state. We leave it entirely to the physician
            to advise with the patient, and we do not desire to interfere with what he or she
            wishes, but simply to inform them, and they do the rest. </p>
        <q who="AUSWA"><p> Senator Austin: About the gelatins, are there numerous, different types
                of gelatins available?</p></q>
        <p> Mrs. Sanger: Yes. </p>
        <q who="AUSWA"><p> Senator Austin: Are they available in this country now?</p></q>
        <p> Mrs. Sanger: They came from Europe-- the original formula came from Germany, and, of
            course was sent back for a time, and finally the formula was sold to a manufacturing
            chemist in this country. When it was sold, it was not sold for contraceptive purposes,
            but mainly for some ailment like leucorrhea. That is mainly how these jellies are able
            to be sold to-day, for prevention of disease, but the market is being flooded in a
            dangerous way, because there is no control over them. </p>
        <q who="AUSWA"><p> Senator Austin: Are these gelatins available in tubes, with devices for
                employing them?</p></q>
        <p> Mrs. Sanger: Yes. Most of them are. </p>
        <q who="AUSWA"><p> Senator Austin: What about the medical lore on this subject? Do you know
                whether the state of medical science here in <place reg="United States"
                    >America</place> is up to the standard of that science aborad on this
                subject?</p></q>
        <p> Mrs. Sanger: Doctor <person reg="Moses, Bessie Louise">Moses</person> is here with us,
            and I would like for her to go into that. </p>
        <q who="MSPP"><p> [Conversation between Doctor Moses and Senator Austin was omitted]</p></q>
        <q who="AUSWA"><p> Senator Austin: Is the reason why you do not get these things [medical
                supplies] by automobile or private carrier because of the cost?</p></q>
        <p> Mrs. Sanger: <org reg="Cleveland Maternal Health Association">The Cleveland clinic</org>
            does that. They send a messenger to <place reg="Chicago, IL">Chicago</place> or <place
                reg="New York, NY">New York</place>. </p>
        <q who="MSPP"><p> [Conversation between Doctor Moses and Senator Austin was omitted]</p></q>
        <p> Mrs. Sanger: Would you mention how they [diaphragms] are fitted?</p>
        <q who="MSPP"><p> [Conversation between Doctor Moses and Senator Austin was omitted]</p></q>
        <p> Mrs. Sanger: Just before I came I looked in our book, and at <org
                reg="Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau">our clinic</org> in New York we have
            had 700 physicians come there to us to learn he technique of contraception. </p>
        <q who="AUSWA"><p> Senator Austin: What is the type of physician, what kind of men?</p></q>
        <p> Mrs. Sanger: A great many southern men. They have come to New York to a conference or
            something, and physicians have sent them to us, a large number of gynecologists or
            obstetricians. They want to know just what to do, and the physicians send them down to
            our clinic, and the same in <place reg="Washington, D.C.">Washington</place>. When they
            come here they are sent to the clinic at <place reg="Baltimore, MD">Baltimore</place> to
            Doctor Moses. </p>
        <q who="MSPP"><p> [Conversation between Doctor Moses and Senator Austin was omitted]</p></q>
        <q who="AUSWA"><p> Senator Austin: Can you not obtain these supplies without breaking the
                law?</p></q>
        <p> Mrs. Sanger: Not by common carrier, or express or mail.</p>
        <q who="AUSWA"><p> Senator Austin: You have an option as to whether you can do it one way or
                another.</p></q>
        <p> Mrs. Sanger: These is only one way. I suppose they get supplies from New York and
            Chicago. Unless you have a manufacturing center of these pessaries in every community,
            you have to violate the law. This section says express companies and common carriers,
            and not only that, but it is violating <name
                reg="Section 211 of the United States Penal Code">section 211</name> for us to tell
            another person where to go and give her the address where contraceptive information may
            be obtained. I have been written to by the <org
                reg="United States Department of Justice">Department of Justice</org> where
            complaints have been made that I gave the address of this clinic at Baltimore to a
            person who was a decoy, and that was all, gave no information, said “go to the doctor
            there, and they will probably give you such advice.” </p>
        <q who="MSPP"><p> [Conversation between Doctor Moses and Senator Austin was omitted]
            </p></q>
        <p> Mrs. Sanger: I was going to say as far as the physicians are concerned in this country,
            we have had to help the poor people. Where a poor woman writes to us, and especially to
            me, and asks what she can do, I advise her to go to a physician in her community, a
            physician who has come in and taken a course in technique, and these physicians are glad
            to help. We often pay her fare to the doctor’s office, and the doctor will giver her
            advice free. We get in contact with social workers and tell them to tell her to go to
            the doctor. I have letters from physicians asking me if I can tell them about the law.
            They say they do not want to break the law; they want to do the right thing, but the
            doctors are confused as to the law. </p>
        <q who="AUSWA"><p> Senator Austin: I want to ask a question, and you need not answer it if
                you do not want to. Have you had any evidence that the medical profession generally
                regards your activities as an intrusion into their particular sphere?</p></q>
        <p> Mrs. Sanger: I think at first they did, as a layman. Just a trained nurse. I think that
            was very much resented by them, my intrusion, first, because I was a layman, and they
            had a guilty conscience themselves. They knew every word about the conditions were true,
            and I had found means of contraception that were safer than any, and there was
            resentment. </p>
        <q who="AUSWA"><p> Senator Austin: If it were true the <org
                    reg="American Medical Association">American Medical Society</org> at its last
                meeting tabled this suggestion very abruptly and declined to act upon it one way or
                the other, what would your reaction be to that? What would you think that
                indicated?</p></q>
        <p> Mrs. Sanger: To me it would indicate the natural trend of events of the history of the
            medical profession as an organization. All throughout their history they have declined
            to take up certain things, and gradually the public conscience pushes them into it and
            they have taken it. I was not surprised at all. The division of gynecologists and
            obstetricians did come out with a statement concerning our objects, and this whole group
            of the American Medical Association, most of whom are general practitioners--very few of
            them are gynecologists or obstetricians-- are not brought face to face with this issue.
            It looked controversial and something that thy were divided on. Certain elements get
            into the organization, and I was not at all surprised at that. </p>
        <q who="AUSWA"><p> Senator Austin: I am glad to see you do not attribute any selfish or
                ulterior motive. </p></q>
        <p> Mrs. Sanger: No. I do not consider it in that way. </p>
        <p> Statement of Dr. Russell J. Clinchy </p>
        <q who="MSPP"><p> [Statement by Dr. <person reg="Clinchy, Russell J.">Russell J.
                    Clinchy</person> was omitted] </p></q>
        <p> Mrs. Sanger: <q who="MSPP">[About Dr. Clinchy]</q> We thought he could touch on the
            moral side of the question. </p>
        <q who="MSPP"><p> [Statement by Dr. Russell J. Clinchy was omitted] </p></q>
        <q who="AUSWA"><p> Senator Austin: Do you think if this law were passed it would be any more
                legitimate for letting the girl getting this information than before. </p></q>
        <p> Mrs. Sanger: I should not think it would be so easy. In a case where young, unmarried
            people are living together, they are not using this sort of pessary. They can not use it
            without a medical examination; in other words, if this law had some provisions for the
            physician to legitimately give proper advice 20 or 25 years ago, I believe we would not
            have our young people bootlegging it over the counter and getting anything at all. </p>
        <p> When our young men went to war there were two things that they were taught. The
            physicians taught our men two things, that they must not impregnate a girl in Europe and
            they must not run the risk of a venereal disease, and they were aught the use of
            condoms; that is mostly what these people are using. As soon as we can educate them not
            to take such risks and not to violate the sanctity and beauty of sex we will be
            accomplishing a great deal. Condoms are generally unsafe. </p>
        <q who="AUSWA"><p> Senator Austin: They are unsafe?</p></q>
        <p> Mrs. Sanger: They may be unsafe as they get them over the counter. </p>
        <q who="AUSWA"><p> Senator Austin: They still may conceive?</p></q>
        <p> Mrs. Sanger: Yes; there is no 100 per cent safety, but there is a possibility of 99 per
            cent safety when properly taken care of. I believe firmly that we are working in the
            right direction for clinics and physicians to instruct women and to have them go to
            qualified physicians to receive this information. </p>
        <q who="MSPP"><p> [Conversation between Doctor Moses and Senator Austin was omitted]
            </p></q>
        <p> Mrs. Sanger: To-day with the laws as stringent as they are, with no leeway, no
            exemption, we are having this terrific condition. We are trying to improve it. </p>
        <p> You asked a question about the immediate necessity. I believe there never has been the
            time that it is so necessary as it is to-day. We have had a number come to us who were
            ready to commit suicide, husbands out of work two or three years, and these women having
            the double burden, not only the economic burden but the constant worry and fear of the
            possibility of another pregnancy, when they do not know what they are going to do. A
            woman came in a few days ago and said that her husband is home all the time, not
            working. What are we going to do-- the anxiety and nervousness?</p>
        <q who="AUSWA"><p> Senator Austin: You are imparting information to these people?</p></q>
        <p> Mrs. Sanger: We can do it in <place>New York</place> for the prevention of disease. </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
