<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Testimony">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/01/24 VS initial encoding</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/1/30 CH proofread encoding</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-11-11 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1934-01-18">18 Jan 1934</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Testimony Before the U.S. Senate on S.
                1842</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp300449</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Birth Control: Hearings before a Subcommittee of the
                    Committee on the Judiciary United States Senate Seventy-Third Congress Second
                    Session on S. 1842</title> (Washington, 1934), p. 14-21, and 149-163.</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="HASDA">Hastings, Daniel</name>
            <name id="LOGMA">Logan, Marvel Mills</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
            <name id="LATLE">Latz, Leo</name>
            <name id="WALFM">Walshe, F. M.</name>
            <name id="NEEMA">Neely, Mathew Mansfield</name>
            <name id="RYAJO">Ryan, John Agustus</name>
            <name id="COUCH">Coughlin, Charles E.</name>
            <name id="BIB">Bible</name>
            <name id="LC">Lambeth Conference, 1930</name>
            <name id="GUTLR">Guthrie, L. R.</name>
            <name id="WARTH">Thompson, Warren</name>
            <name id="CRAFR">Crane, Frederick</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>The following excerpt from the hearings, includes Margaret Sanger's testimony and the
            questions she was asked. For the complete proceedings, see "Birth Control Hearings"
            above. The chairman of the meeting was Senator Marvel Mills Logan. </p>
        <index level1="abortion" level2="laws and legislation"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"
            level3="negative consequences of"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="consequences on"/>
        <index level1="Congressional bills" level2="S. 1842" level3="1934"/>
        <index level1="family size"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, William" level2="arrest, trial and imprisonment"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
        <index level1="Catholic Church" level2="birth control and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>STATEMENT OF MRS. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">MARGARET SANGER</person>, PRESIDENT
                <org reg="National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control">NATIONAL
                COMMITTEE ON FEDERAL LEGISLATION FOR BIRTH CONTROL INC.</org>; DIRECTOR, <org
                reg="Birth Control Clinicsl Research Bureau">BIRTH CONTROL CLINIC RESEARCH
                BUREAU</org>, <place reg="New York, NY">NEW YORK CITY</place></head>
        <div>
            <p>Mrs. SANGER. <person reg="Logan, Marvel Mills">Mr. Chairman</person>, this bill,
                    <title type="law">S. 1842</title>, concerns, in my estimation, the 32,612,792
                women of child-bearing age in this <place reg="United States">country</place>. I
                believe that it concerns that number of women, because every woman, when she becomes
                of adult age, naturally looks forward to the time when she may be married and become
                a mother. There are 20,441,719 married women of child-bearing age in this
                country.</p>
            <p>I have had the privilege of coining the term by which this bill is likely to be know,
                “birth control” legislation. I would like to say that birth control means the
                control of the birth rate, by means that prevent conception. It does not mean that
                it interferes with the development of life; it does not mean that it interrupts the
                process of life nor that it takes life. The prevention of conception is not any more
                an interference with the process of life than remaining single or living in
                continence or celibacy. In the control of the birth rate we do not mean that we must
                limit the birth rate. It means to control the size of the family, but it does not
                mean limit it to 1 or 2 or to any specific number of children. We want the first
                consideration to be of the health of the mother; then the consideration of the
                health of the children that are already here; then consideration of the father’s
                ability to earn a living for his family and the standard of the living that the
                parents wish to maintain for the cultivation and the education of the family. I
                would just like to make that definition clear for that is what we are talking about
                in using the term “birth control”, as it may be used by other speakers.</p>
            <p>Some years ago as a trained nurse, I found that I could not discuss this question
                with mothers; that I was unable to get information to assist them, even after they
                had been told by the doctors that another baby would cost them their lives. We found
                that the main thing in the way of doing that was <title type="law"><rs
                        reg="section 211 of U.S. Penal Code">sections 211</rs> and <rs
                        reg="section 245 of U.S. Penal Code">245</rs> of the Penal code</title>,
                passed by the <org reg="United States Congress">Congress</org> 61 years ago.</p>
            <p>Mr. Chairman, in looking over the record and the history of that law and the way it
                was placed upon the statute books, I contend and believe that Congress at that time
                never intended that persons should be deprived of knowledge by which they could
                reasonably rear and care for their children. The whole law and all the discussion
                around it at that time, as we find it in the record, has relation to obscene
                literature coming to this country that was being curculated among young people. The
                intention of the law was to stop the circulation of indecent literature, and the
                prohibition of information to prevent conception never was intended in the sense of
                its rightful use. I cannot believe that any Congress then or today would want to
                deprive mothers of knowledge they rightfully should have for the benefit of the
                family and really for the benefit of the community and the country.</p>
            <p>The law as it is set forth in sections 211 and 245 makes no exception. It does not
                exempt the medical profession or permit them to use the mails or the common
                carriers. It makes no exemption for scientific or medical literature, to permit such
                to go through the mails or by common carriers. We fell that the <org
                    reg="United States Postal Service">United States mails</org> should be opened
                for information on this subject to those qualified to make propers use of it for the
                good of the country</p>
            <p>I have here, Mr. Chairman, the laws to which this bill pertains and a small leaflet
                that we brought forth on Federal interference with the administration of State laws,
                with which we contend this law does interfere; and also a brief summary and a
                general exemption in certain cases. In <place>New York</place> State, through my
                spending 30 days in jail, I was able to have a court decision that interpreted one
                of the laws of our State, by which the physician could give information for the “<q
                    who="CRAFR">cure and prevention of disease</q>.” Many of the other States have
                similar laws. Some of the States give the right to anyone; other States allow
                teaching of the subject in medical colleges and universities, and so on</p>
            <p>If you will permit it, I would like to place this in the record, as indicating what
                has been done in the way of Federal interference with the administration of these
                State laws</p>
            <q who="LOGMA"><p>Senator LOGAN. You may do so</p>
                <p>(The statement of the present law and summary of the State law referred to was
                    marked “Exhibit B”; and the pamphlet entitled “<title type="journal">Federal Interference with
                        the Administration of State Laws</title>”, was marked “Exhibit C”; both of
                    which appear at the close of the sxtatement of this witness.)</p></q>
            <p>Mrs. SANGER. Because of these state laws and under the authority and the right of the
                State laws, people who are interested in this subject and are connected with social
                and civil work in the communities have established over 150 of what we call
                “birth-control clinics” throughout the country. those are legally established
                centers, but they have to bootleg their supplies from New York and <place
                    reg="Chicago, IL">Chicago</place>, where the large manufacturing concerns are
                located. That is the situation today, and it is a situation that, to my mind, is
                very reprehensible and that we hope to change through this bill, S. 1842, by
                allowing the physicians, licenced clinics, and hospitals the right to use the States
                mails and common carriers for that legitimate and rightful purpose Section 211 also
                makes it a crime for anyone to tell anyone else where such information may be
                obtained. In other words, these clinics that are legally established in various
                States not only have to bootleg their supplies but also bootleg any proper modern
                information than the people had 40 or 50 years ago, which should being in the ark.
                In order to get any new, scientific information, they have to bootleg it. Most
                physicians do not like to put themselves in that position.</p>
            <p>Mr. Chairman, I have had a million letters from women in this country from the time I
                began this campaign of education up until about 4 years ago. I have had a million
                personal letters about the hardships of some of these women. I have had to
                jeopardize my freedom, run the risk of a $5,000 fine and five years in prison for
                violating section 211, by telling these women where in their own States they could
                obtain that which they were legally entitled to under their own State laws</p>
            <p>That is what we are fighting for. We want to do away with this bootlegging.
                Representative <person reg="Pierce, Walter">Pierce</person> told you about that
                article in the <title type="journal">New Republic</title> called “<title
                    type="article">Birth Control’s Business Baby</title>.” He did not ask you to put
                it in the record, because it does show the things we are trying to do away with;
                that these things are surreptitiously done; that the manufacturers of commercial
                products are producing them at very high prices because of the laws which have
                created this situations</p>
            <q who="LOGMA"><p>Senator LOGAN. That may be incorporated in the record.</p>
                <p>The document referred to was marked “Exhibit D”, and is printed in full at the
                    close of the statement of this witness.</p></q>
            <p>Mrs. SANGER. There is no particular avenue or direction for these people to go in
                which to get the right information. They have to go to the drug store and have it
                whispered over the counter that this or that will do. And we know from our recent
                research that many of these products are not effective. We have purchased 100
                so-called “contraceptives” and put them through scientific tests. We put them
                through laboratory tests and had clinical tests, and submitted them to physicians,
                and we found that 43 out of the 100 were practically of no use whatever. Purchasing
                those things has caused many women serious injury. We have not gone into that very
                thoroughly yet, because we have just tested them as to their efficaciousness, and 43
                out of the 100 were of no use. It means a fraud is being perpetrated upon the
                public. This is a brief statement of the results of our research that I would like
                to have go into the record.</p>
            <q who="LOGMA"><p>Senator LOGAN. That may be incorporated in the record.</p>
                <p>(The document referred to was marked “Exhibit E”, and is printed in full at the
                    close of the statement of this witness.)</p></q>
            <p>Mrs. SANGER. If I may stress this, by way of a little explanation when we talk about
                the question of preventing contraception we claim there are three methods of
                preventing conception. The first is continence. No one objects to continence. We
                have no objection whatever to certain religious orders claiming that is the only
                method the church can sanction. There is nothing in the law against it. They may
                practice it, and we say that this is their own affair, their own individual
                right.</p>
            <p>The next is sterilization. Sterilization is for people who have to responsibility
                toward parenthood or toward children. It is becoming more and more prevalent, as you
                know from reports from <place>England</place>, <place>Germany</place>, and other
                countries. We have in this country over 24 states that have sterilization laws,
                allowing certain authorities to advise sterilization in special cases where there
                are transmissible diseases or certain transmissible ailments. That is not a part of
                our provision.</p>
            <p>Then there is the chemical or the mechanical means of contraception, which is one
                that places in the hands of the parties involved the legal right to use means to
                prevent contraception, and it is around that group that most of the discussion seems
                to be centered.</p>
            <p>There is nothing mandatory about this bill. We are not imposing any method upon
                anybody. We are not claiming that every family must obtain this information, but we
                do say for those who wish to use some means they should have the legal right to do
                it, and those who wish to use one particular means or no means at all should not
                have the right to impose that upon the whole community. We claim that we have a
                perfect right to use such method as our Physician indicates is the right one for the
                individual.</p>
            <p>As we have stated, we are making no claim that any one means or method is a panacea
                for all. Various women differ. They differ as to the number of children, and their
                physical conditions become different. The economic situation is also different. We
                want to place the giving of information in the hands of those who can disseminate it
                properly, so that those desiring it may receive instructions and necessary
                scientific advice from those who are qualified to give it. It is just the same as
                the 10-cent pair of glasses in a 10-cent store. That is no way for people who need
                to have them to have glasses fitted. We want this subject removed from the 10-cent
                store and the gasoline stations and placed in the hands of those who are qualified
                in every way to explain the relations of parenthood properly.</p>
            <p>Mr. Chairman, we have had to go through many difficulties in connection with this
                subject since 1914. Some of us have served time in jail, We have been arrested time
                and again, just because we wished to exercise the right of freedom of speech and
                help educate those who were in need of help. We have been able to get some decisions
                from the courts that have in a way interpreted these laws in different ways,
                especially in the States. Members of Congress have said to us:</p>
            <p><q who="UNK">You will never get anything through Congress. Why do you not go to jail
                    and get your court decision?</q></p>
            <p>I say Congress should be ashamed to compel us to go to such extremes and to resort to
                such methods for our laws. Why should we have to go to the courts to have our laws
                made? That is what Congress is for. People have a right to look to Congress and to
                bring these questions before it. We should not have to go to the expense of lawsuits
                and go to courts to have our laws made. I think you will all agree with that. </p>
            <p>Now, then, as to the clinics: There are 157 birth-control clinics in this country. I
                have a statement here of the number of those clinics and the location, but I do no
                know whether I can put that in the record or not. There may be some question of a
                violation of section 211.</p>
            <q who="LOGMA"><p>Senator LOGAN. That may be filed with the committee, and we will treat
                    it as a privileged communication.</p></q>
            <p>(The document referred to was marked “Exhibit F”, and is filed with the
                committee.)</p>
            <p>Mrs. SANGER. I want to talk a little about the waste of life, a fact which brought me
                into this cause more than anything else. First, I was to refer to the terrific
                number of abortions that are going on, which is a colossal number. I think we can
                show from the record that it runs over a million a year, and that does not begin to
                tell the story. There is the waste of women’s lives, the waste of child life, and
                the terrible suffering of women. No woman can keep her health and continue to go
                through these operations with increasing pregnancy every year, especially when it is
                done surreptitiously. The condition of those nervous and unhealthy women is
                something really beyond our belief or understanding, and it is terrible that we
                should have to make it necessary for the women of America to go into these dangerous
                conditions and live under those conditions which I would call an underworld of
                suffering. It seems to me to be a state of barbarism.</p>
            <p><person reg="Woodbury, Robert Morse">Dr. Woodbury</person>, of the <org>United States
                    Children’s Bureau</org>, published some very interesting data where he clearly
                shows that too short an interval between childbirths markedly affects the infant
                death rate. Where the interval between births is 3 years, the infant death rate is
                80.5 per 1,000 births; when the interval is 2 years, the rate is 98.6; and when it
                is only 1 year, the infant mortality goes up to 146.7. Certainly that is a very
                striking increase.</p>
            <p>In homes, for instance, where the average number of persons per room is less than 1,
                the infant death rate is 52.1; where it is 2 or more persons per room the death rate
                is 135.7. Furthermore, in families where the per capita income from the father’s
                earnings was less than $50 the infant mortality rate was 215.9, as compared with a
                rate of only 60.5 where the per capita amount averaged #400 or over. These figures
                clearly and strikingly indicate the influence of family over-crowding upon family
                well-being.</p>
            <p>I would like to read this little thing about Jimmy. Nobody wanted Jimmy, but he was
                born anyhow, and died three weeks later. His mother was sick with worry before he
                came. Childbearing in 1925, 1927, 1929, and 1931 had left her in miserable health,
                with bad varicose veins. his father was a $25-per-week mechanic working part time.
                Which of us, under such circumstance, would look forward to the birth of Jimmy? The
                community did not want him. <place reg="Philadelphia, PA">Philadelphia</place>’s
                relief burden in 1932 was approximately $11,000,000.</p>
            <p>Yet this community gave his mother prenatal care, which amounted to $6.75. A social
                agency boarded his 4 brothers and sisters over 13 weeks, at a cost of $170.50. His
                mother was in the hospital 20 days, at a cost of $80. The layettte for the baby cost
                $7. He contracted meningitis at home and was given medical care and nursing by the
                city, at a cost of $15.25. He died and was buried free by the community, which cost
                $30. So his short and painful life cost the community $309.50.</p>
            <p>Ask yourself, was it fair for Jimmy to be born at this time, with no chance for a
                happy childhood? Was it fair to his brothers and sisters when the father made enough
                money for food only, with no money for rent or clothing? Was it fair to the
                community which is now supporting over 70,000 families?</p>
            <p>We believe that a child’s first right is to be wanted. We believe that hunger and
                fear cannot create a wholesome home for a baby. We believe that during this crisis
                the community cannot now keep in health and decency the children who are here.</p>
            <p>I also have some interesting statistics submitted by <person
                    reg="Spengler, Joseph J.">Prof. Joseph J. Spengler</person>, <org>University of
                        <place>Arizona</place></org>, in relation to conditions in
                    <place>Colorado</place>, to which I should like to call attention to very
                briefly.</p>
            <p>In Weld County, <place reg="Greeley, CO">Greeley, Colorado</place>, the county
                commissioners pay for birth-control supplies. The cost of supplying the patient with
                birth-control supplies is approximately $1.50. The cost of the indigent woman either
                through a confinement case or through a miscarriage, which averages about once a
                year, in each case was $50 for hospitalization, nursing, and pre-natal and
                post-natal care. This is the actual cost to the county and does not include the cost
                of caring for the child later.</p>
            <p>The county estimated that there are about 200 such cases yearly, making a total cost
                of $10,000 per year. For $300 it was possible then to save $10,000.</p>
            <p>We wish to point out, however, since this clinic is a branch of <org
                    reg="Denver Birth Control Clinic">the <place reg="Denver, CO">Denver</place>
                    clinic</org>, and obtains birth-control supplies from the Denver clinic, that we
                find the country breaking the Federal laws by having birth-control supplies shipped
                through the mails.</p>
            <p>I have just two or three letters here that I would like to call you attention to. The
                first is from <place>Corydon, KY</place>., and reads as follows:</p>
            <q who="UNK"><p>I read your address in the <title type="journal">Evansville
                        Press</title>, and I wonder if you could help me any. I have two children.
                    My mother has 10. I am only 20 years old, I live in fear all the time for I
                    never know when I will get that way again. My oldest child is hairlipped and we
                    want it fixed; part of it has been fixed but haven’t the money to do any more.
                    My husband only makes $10 a week so you see it is all we can do to live. I will
                    never forget it if you will tell me how to keep from having children. I will
                    tell my mother; her youngest child is younger than mine. It is terrible; if you
                    will only tell me I will do anything in the world for you I can.</p>
                <p>Please.</p>
                <p>Yours truly.</p></q>
            <p>This woman could have been sent to <place reg="Louisville, KY">Louisville</place>
                where there is a birth-control clinic. We could have had a social worker take her
                there. It would pay the people of <place>Kentucky</place> to pay her carfare to that
                point and take care of her. In order to try to save that woman I had to jeopardize
                my freedom and run the risk of a $5,000 fine to tell her where she could go to get
                decent information to protect herself.</p>
            <p>Here is another letter from <place reg="Memphis, TN">Memphis</place> along the same
                lines, which I should like to read:</p>
            <q who="UNK"><p>In regard to Birth-control bill S. 1842, how I wish all those people,
                    priest and all that are so bitter against birth control, had to have babies
                    every 9 months and know what it is to see little children hungry and cold, not
                    to say anything about the slave life the poor mother is living and the suffering
                    she goes through. I will do all I can for the cause. I haven’t any money - we
                    are sure having a struggle these days to make ends meet. Only hope the bill goes
                    through for we poor women need help if anything or anybody does.</p>
                <p>I worry so much. I have such a hard time. Oh, I don’t want any more babies - am
                    half crazy - am half tempted to leave my husband, but then how would I get
                    along, and there are the children, and we all love one another, and he doesn’t
                    want any more babies either, so write my, dear unseen friend.</p></q>
            <p>Here is one from <place reg="Maxwell, IA">Maxwell, Iowa</place>. I should also like
                to read this into the record: <q who="UNK">I have been married 10 years and during
                    that time have given birth to 5 children: 3 girls and 2 boys. After the third
                    one was born, I suffered a severe breakdown in health. It weakened my heart and
                    stomach to such an extent that I am unable to do a big day’s work. Whenever I
                    do, I am so tired and exhausted I cannot sleep for hours. I have lain awake many
                    and many a night, so tired my heart just pounded and thumped. Oh, but it is
                    terrible. No one knows what it is like unless they have it to go through with.
                    The children are so close together. They are all just like babes yet and are so
                    noisy and fight and fuss till I am almost crazy. The oldest one died, so I have
                    only four living but that is enough. I did not act right when the last one was
                    born. I just had to gasp for breath and had such a strangled feeling. If we had
                    lots of money I might get along better than I do, but my husband is a laboring
                    man and there is no money to pay expensive doctor fees and laundry bills, and so
                    forth. If I could do something harmless to keep from raising any more children
                    my husband and I both would consider it a godsend. e cannot take proper care of
                    the ones we have, let alone any more. My baby is 2 months old and I want to find
                    out something to do before I have the chance to get pregnant again.</q></p>
            <q who="UNK"><p>Miss Sanger, if you know of anything to help me stop all this, please
                    inform me, for I am getting desperate. I have been tempted to commit suicide
                    many a time. If I had good health, it would not be so bad but I wish you could
                    see me. I married when I was 16. I will be 27 my next birthday and I look older
                    than my husband and he is 35. And I feel older than I look. Everybody speaks
                    about how tired I look and I am tired. So tired, nervous, and worn out I feel
                    like I could drop in the floor and die without a single shudder.</p></q>
            <p>What would this law do? In the first place, it would place the proper responsibility
                for the giving of information upon the medical profession and hospitals where women
                go to have their babies, and to these maternal wards in the hospitals. It would give
                the poor women, who are unable to go to the hospital, the opportunity to go to some
                member of the medical profession, who has a right to judge such matters. If she
                could go to the hospital to have her baby, she should be able to get proper
                information there. It gives the poor woman the right that only the well-to-do have
                had.</p>
            <p>We should like to do more than this law asks for, and I hope before long we can ask
                for more an appropriation for this work in various States, especially in mountainous
                sections where women have a difficult time getting to a hospital. We would like to
                have regular Federal birth-control clinics, maternal-health clinics, where these
                women may get advice and where they may get proper attention. We hope before long
                that we may ask for just such an appropriation from the Federal Government.</p>
            <p>In closing, may I saw there are many aspects of this question that are beyond our
                scope to deal with today. in my estimation, the placing of information in the hands
                of qualified persons and permitting them to give out such information would be very
                beneficial. I would like to see such information given out, regardless of whether
                there is overpopulation or underpopulation; regardless of whether there is a high
                birth rate or a low birth rate; regardless of whether there is going to be more or
                less baby carriages or baby bottles sold.</p>
            <p>Regardless of all these commercial and material interests, I would like to see the
                mothers themselves receive consideration, and we must trust the mother that she is,
                going to use that advice, not only for the benefit of her child and her family but
                for the benefit of the community and the country. I believe that we should consider,
                under the <title>Constitution</title> of this country, that every woman should have
                the right of life, liberty, and the pursuit of happiness; and I ask you favorable
                consideration of this legislation. [Applause]</p>
            <p><q who="LOGMA">Senator LOGAN. Thank you, Mrs. Sanger.</q></p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head>FURTHER STATEMENT OF MRS. MARGARET SANGER, CHAIRMAN, NATIONAL COMMITTEE ON
                LEGISLATION FOR BIRTH CONTROL, <place>WASHINGTON D.C.</place></head>
            <p>Mrs SANGER. Mr. Chairman, I would like to cover just one point of rebuttal and, if
                you will allow me, I would like to have <person reg="Wilson, Prentiss">Dr. Prentiss
                    Wilson</person> speak later.</p>
            <p>Mr. Chairman, there seems to be a good deal of confusion concerning this law and the
                amendment that is proposed. As <person reg="Stevenson, Adlai">Stevenson</person>
                said, “<q who="STEAD">condemnation is misunderstanding</q>.” I should like to feel
                that is exactly the situation here, that it is misunderstanding. In the first place,
                the amendment that we are proposing and that is under discussion is not the law. The
                laws are already on the statute books in sections 211, 245, and <rs
                    reg="Section 312 of the U.S. Penal Code">312 of the Criminal Code</rs>. They
                were enacted by Congress over 60 years ago.</p>
            <p>All the conditions our opponents claim would happen in case this bill or this
                amendment passes are taking place with the law as it is now and as it has been for
                over 60 years. All that we ask is that this amendment exempt the medical profession,
                hospitals, and clinics from the penalties of the law. The amendment is simple, it is
                comprehensive and it is in plain English, so it seems to me any one should
                understand it.</p>
            <p>Now, the reason, in my estimation, that there is this confusion and all the conflict
                going on that none of us like to see is because there has been such confusion
                between the State and Federal laws. Forty-seven States allow the physician to give
                the contraceptive instruction for the “<q who="CRAFR">cure or prevention of
                    disease</q>;” other States do not mention the physician at all or do not mention
                or limit the giving of information to the physicians ; and other States allow the
                medical colleges to instruct.</p>
            <p>And so it varies in all of the States. In 24 States they have no restriction
                whatsoever. We claim that the licensed physicians, hospitals, and clinics are proper
                sources of information in every State, and we are trying to educate the public
                accordingly.</p>
            <p>All that we are trying to do, I repeat, is to pass this amendment, which affects only
                the United States mails and common carriers in regard to physicians, hospital and
                clinics all licenced by their respective State laws. It does not affect these
                circulars and these things that are already in existence and that have already been
                forwarded through the mails. We all are opposed to these objectionable things. But
                one of the reasons they are circulated is because there is no control over this
                particular kind of literature.</p>
            <p>No physician is going to give contraceptive advice on the telephone nor is a
                physician going to use the United States mails to instruct a patient. It is absurd
                to even think of it. What the physician is going to do, is to get through the mails
                and common carriers better instruction and information himself, as well as necessary
                supplies, which he has not been able to have because of this law. As we have shown
                in the hearing, medical publishers will not publish articles in medical magazines
                nor in books, nor will they print textbooks on contraception for the medical
                profession, because of this law. they will not distribute copies or circularize
                copies of their magazine which might get them into a row by publishing something
                that is against the law. The consequence is that the medical profession has not, so
                far, had the advantage of obtaining up-to-date contraceptive information that is
                freely permitted them in other countries. Not only that, we know from our experience
                in clinics and our studies and research that advice alone is not enough, there must
                be some device, either a mechanical or medical means to carry out the doctor’s
                instruction for the patient as he prescribes.</p>
            <p>I don’t know anything else I can say about these laws. This bill will not permit
                information to be given indiscriminately, to make it more clear and definite. We
                must go back to the States and place the responsibility squarely up to the States as
                to the physician who misuses the law. We will have nothing to do with that. That is
                a matter for the physicians themselves, to control, and, as the bill states, he must
                be a legally licensed physician to practice medicine. Now, if the State or Territory
                is going to license that physician, it is supposed to find out what kind of a doctor
                he is, and if they give him the right to practice medicine within the proper limits
                of the law then certainly he should have the same right to use the mails and common
                carriers.</p>
            <p>We have already put into the record the laws, so I won’t discuss them in detail, but
                bear in mind that they have already been admitted. They have gone into the record to
                show exactly what the State laws are.</p>
            <p>The confusion seems to be that because there are obscenity laws in the various
                States, that they must include also the prohibition on contraceptives, which is not
                true. We are placing the information in the hands of physicians who are licensed to
                practice under the State laws. I wish we could get that clear, because I think it is
                very much to the advantage of all to understand this point.</p>
            <p>The other day there were a good many questions asked about the other countries. I
                think it might be of interest to state that there are two other countries in the
                world that have laws concerning or prohibiting the dissemination of birth-control
                literature - <place>Italy</place> and <place>France</place>. These laws have only
                been in operation since 1918, or since the close of the war. But in neither of these
                countries is there such a law as we have here in section 211. Their laws do not
                affect the physician and they do not prohibit the physician from advising the use of
                contraceptives in his medical profession. They simply do not allow the promiscuous
                use of articles and advice and information to be hawked on the street corners and in
                the shops.</p>
            <p>The same may be said about England. Very recently there was a bill before the
                    <org>House of Lords</org>, proposed by <person reg="Dawson, Bertrand">Lord
                    Dawson</person>, who is the <person reg="George V">King</person>’s physician. In
                England there has never been any restriction on contraceptive advice or information
                since 1876. Now Lord Dawson has asked the House of Lords to pass a bill which will
                not allow the sale of contraceptives on the street corners, or hawked on the
                streets. The Lords passed the bill 46 to 6; with only 6 of the members against it,
                because they wanted no restriction whatsoever. There was no question of restricting
                the physician or medical practice, but those six Lords wanted no restriction
                whatever because they felt that was not the way to go after abuses, but that
                necessary reforms had to go further down into the moral conscience of the
                individual.</p>
            <q who="HASDA"><p><person reg="Hastings, Daniel">Senator HASTINGS</person>. I suppose it
                    is you contention, Mrs. Sanger, that freedom in England has not destroyed the
                    morality of the youth of the nation?</p></q>
            <p>Mrs. SANGER. That is my contention. It is the same with <place reg="Netherlands"
                    >Holland</place> and the other countries. In Holland, for instance, birth
                control has been better organized than any other country in the world. Over 60 years
                ago they had placed it in the hands of midwives and nurses and doctors and had the
                practice of contraception properly directed. They followed up their death rate, and
                if the child died they sent a nurse into the homes to find out why it died, and in
                this way they attempted to decrease the death rate. Consequently they have earlier
                marriages and a large increase in population, which is a very interesting point
                because , as you can see from their statistics, they have a lower death rate than
                any country in <place>Europe</place>, so much lower death rate than
                    <place>Japan</place>, for instance, that their survival is practically the same.
                In other words, Holland has protected its women, has protected all of its women and
                children, and has done away with, you might say useless, needless deaths of its
                mothers; and they have more of a population increase proportionately. I think that
                is a very interesting point in answer to <person reg="Ryan, John Agustus">Dr.
                    Ryan</person>’s point made here as to the question of decreasing population
                which I will refer to later.</p>
            <p>There are one or two points which I would like to include, among which are the
                following:</p>
            <p>Here is a book that has been brought out entitled <title type="book">Sex
                    Rhythm</title> published with “ecclesiastical approbation” by the <org>Latz
                    Foundation of Chicago</org>, and under the heading of <quote>“Consequences of
                    contraception”</quote> there is this question:</p>
            <q who="LATLE"><p>Question. Are all Catholic doctors in agreement as to the serious
                    physical consequence of contraception?</p>
                <p>Answer. Very few have had the occasion to express themselves on this subject in
                    print. Probably the majority of Catholic practicing physicians would subscribe
                    to <person reg="Walshe, F. M.">Dr. F. M. Walshe</person>’s statement in the
                        <title type="journal">Catholic Medical Guardian</title> of July 1927
                -</p></q>
            <p>And so on. I would like to include that, if I may. It says:</p>
            <p><q who="WALFM">Hence, however great our forebodings as to the physical evils which
                    may be associated with birth-control practices, we cannot decently initiate an
                    active medical campaign against them, and remain inactive and silent where a
                    much greater evil obtains.</q></p>
            <p>Then, under the heading of procreation in the same book it says:</p>
            <q who="LATLE"><p>Question. Are married people obliged to bring into the world all the
                    children they can?</p>
                <p>Answer. Far from being of obligation, such a course may be utterly indefensible.
                    Broadly speaking, married couples have not the right to bring into the world
                    children whom they are unable to support, for they would thereby inflict a
                    grievous damage upon society.</p></q>
            <p>I would also like to include that.</p>
            <p>I would also like to present a statement by <person reg="Wolman, Leo">Dr. Leo
                    Wolman</person>, chairman of the <org
                    reg="National Recovery Administration, Labor Advisory Board">Labor Advisory
                    Board of the N.R.A.</org> and a member of the <org>National Labor Board</org> of
                    <place>Washington D.C.</place>, as an economist and a man of vision and
                experience.</p>
            <q who="NEEMA"><p>Senator NEELY. You may do that; you may put them all in.</p></q>
            <p>[Statement by Leo Wolman was excluded and not transcribed.]</p>
            <q who="NEEMA"><p>Senator NEELY. Your time is getting short; 15 minutes has
                gone.</p></q>
            <p>Mrs. SANGER. I have 20 minutes?</p>
            <q who="NEEMA"><p>Senator NEELY. Yes; but you have used 16 minutes now.</p></q>
            <p>Mrs SANGER. I only have a little more.</p>
            <p>Here is a ruling from the Post Office Department for a booklet called <title
                    type="journal">Contractptive Practices</title> addressed to <person
                    reg="Moore, Mrs. H. G.">Mrs. H.G. Moore</person>, stating that the use of mails
                was prohibited.</p>
            <p>[Letter to Mrs. H. G. Moore from the Post Office Department was excluded and not
                transcribed]</p>
            <q who="NEEMA"><p>Senator NEELY. All of these documents may be printed in the record,
                    without taking your time to discuss them; but if you wish to discuss them, you
                    may proceed.</p></q>
            <p>Mrs. SANGER. Thank you very much. Those are some of the various statements [handing
                papers to Senator Neely].</p>
            <p>[Statements produced by Margaret Sanger to Senator Neely were excluded and not
                transcribed]</p>
            <p>Mrs. SANGER. I would like Mr. Chairman, before Dr. Wilson speaks, to read one letter
                written to me, because it is about a woman who came here from <place>West
                    Virginia</place>.</p>
            <p><person reg="Guthrie, L. R.">Mrs. Guthrie</person> has authorized me to furnish you a
                report of my findings in her case. Mrs Guthrie, many will remember, came as the
                miner’s wife from West Virginia, a mother of 12 children; and here is a summary of
                her case as we found it when she came here:</p>
            <p><q who="UNK">The patient is a white woman in late middle life who gives her age as
                    43, though her physical characteristics are those of a woman at least 10 years
                    older. She states that she hs given birth to 12 children and has had two
                    miscarriages.</q></p>
            <p>I find it goes on to tell the condition of this woman, and the doctor says:</p>
            <q who="UNK"><p>I have seldom seen such a deplorable pelvic condition in any woman.
                    Unquestionably it is due to her too-frequent bearing of children.</p>
                <p>Mrs. Guthrie must be, without delay, subjected to extensive pelvic surgery. Above
                    all things her precancerous condition must be remedied at once. In addition to
                    her rectocele should be repaired, her uterine support reestablished, and a
                    surgical sterilization should be performed in order that the bearing of more
                    children may not undo this extensive work of surgical repair.</p></q>
            <p>Here is a woman who came here to testify on behalf of the other miners’ wives, and
                she was found to be in such a deplorable state of condition. We have a letter from
                this woman today, who pleads for the support of this bill, and concludes her letter
                as follows:</p>
            <q who="GUTLR"><p>As the mother of 12 children I will have to close and get ready to go
                    to the hospital, asking the prayers of every religious person. As I believe in
                        <name type="diety">God</name> I also believe in birth control for humanity’s
                    sake.</p>
                <p>Mrs. L. R. GUTHRIE</p></q>
            <p>Father Ryan stated:</p>
            <q who="RYAJO"><p>I call attention to the obvious fact that unemployment and depression
                    could not be attained to any appreciable extent through birth-control practices
                    for 15 or 20 years.</p></q>
            <p>He overlooks the factors of human distress and mental anguish of millions of mothers
                living in constant fear of pregnancy, which could be immediately removed by the
                passage of this bill. Furthermore, families who are at present on the relief rolls
                of this country, of which there are approximately 4,000,000 today, and those now on
                the border line, who would be placed on relief if another child were born into that
                family, could secure immediate relief, if able to go to public-health care clinics
                and secure information to limit the size of the family during this period of
                depression and unemployment.</p>
            <p>To quote further from the book Rhythm, by <person reg="Latz, Leo">Dr. Leo
                    Latz</person>, published with "Ecclesiastical approbation":</p>
            <p><q who="LATLE">Burdens that test human endurance to the utmost limit and to which all
                    too many succumb will be lightened. I speak of economic burdens, the burden of
                    poverty, of inadequate income, of unemployment which make it impossible for
                    parents to give their children and themselves the food, the clothing, the
                    housing, the education, and the recreation they are entitled to as children of
                    God.</q></p>
            <p>Father Ryan says:</p>
            <p><q who="RYAJO">Every well-informed person is aware that the change in the Penal Code
                    proposed by this bill would not substantially increase the knowledge or the use
                    of birth control by any class of the population. Prof. <person
                        reg="Thompson, Warren">Warren Thompson</person> admits this fact in the
                    statement put into the record of the hearings before the <org
                        reg="U.S. House of Representatives, Juciciary Committee">House of Judiciary
                        Committee</org>, the 18th of last January.</q></p>
            <p>I quote the passage referred to:</p>
            <p><q who="WARTH">I do not believe that keeping the laws as they are will have any
                    appreciable effect in preventing the decline of the birthrate. * * * I regard
                    contraception as one of those great movements toward human freedom and the
                    rationalization of life. * * * If the Members of Congress could only be made to
                    feel the inevitability of this great movement toward human freedom they would
                    certainly not oppose it.</q></p>
            <p>Obviously there is nothing in Professor Thompson’s statement to warrant Father Ryan’s
                assumption.</p>
            <p>When Father Ryan stated that there was a decline in the birth rate from 1921 to 1932
                he failed to mention that during these very years the population increased nearly 20
                million in the United States. As the population grows larger, the rate of increase
                must slow down. This has been true for the last 100 years. He should take into
                consideration the decrease in the general death rate and the infant-mortality rate,
                lessening human suffering and waste of human life.</p>
            <p>Father Ryan challenged the statement that the general practice of birth control would
                stimulate the birth rate in the educated classes. We reply, it has been shown in the
                cities of northern and western Europe that the democratic practice of birth control
                has stimulated the birth rate of the educated classes, and they are now having more
                children per family than the poorer classes (<person reg="Edin, Karl Arvin"
                    >Edin</person> and <person reg="Bergdorfer, Fritz">Bergdorfer</person>).</p>
            <p>Father Ryan criticized our criticism of <person reg="Coughlin, Charles E.">Father
                    Coughlin</person> who said it was a biblical injunction to <q who="BIB">be
                    fruitful and multiply.</q> Our criticism was that Father Coughlin by his
                celibacy had failed obey this injunction. Father Ryan’s explanation is that 30,000
                priests and 80,000 nuns in this country would not effect the population increase,
                for if they married they would provide only 275,000 children or about 2 1/2 to each.
                Our answer is that if 80,000 nuns were not practicing birth control they could be
                potential mothers of 800,000 children, providing they did not interfere with the
                Divine command to <q who="BIB">increase and multiply.</q> Father Ryan states that
                the contention of the proponents of this bill is that <q who="RYAJO">the duty of
                    providing for the poor rests upon themselves rather than the State - by
                    foregoing normal family life or by having no children or very few
                children.</q></p>
            <p>Yes, we do contend that self-respecting people “poor” or “near poor” prefer to help
                themselves and keep free from public or private charity, by bringing into the world
                only the number of children they can decently provide for. The practice of birth
                control through the passage of S. 1842 will enable such families to live normal sex
                lives. It will make possible the natural relations of family life by bringing a
                family of 10 or 15 children to become a public charge on the community often
                becoming inmates of prisons, insane asylums, almshouses, or public institutions.</p>
            <p>When Father Ryan claims that <q who="RYAJO">a change in the law now would be
                    tantamount to a public declaration that the long-established legal attitude and
                    policy were wrong</q>, he made the weakest point in his long chain of weak
                arguments. We believe that it was never right to couple contraception with abortion,
                indecency, and obscenity. Congress made that blunder 60 years ago. It will amend
                this law as it repealed the eighteenth amendment, when public opinion demanded
                it.</p>
            <p>Finally, Dr. Ryan says:</p>
            <p><q who="RYAJO">We oppose any change in the law which we believe and know to be
                    intrinsically and profoundly immoral - the natural law which forbids
                    contraception.</q></p>
            <p>To what law does he refer? It is a natural law for man to use his reason, his
                intelligence, and “inborn” intuitive faculties, drawn from Nature herself. It is
                natural to desire children. It is natural to desire only the number of children one
                can decently provide for. It is also natural for people endowed with a sense of
                responsibility for their children to use their natural intelligence to apply
                scientific knowledge to their problems, for the welfare of their children, the
                community, and the country as a whole. Intelligence is a part of nature as well as
                the animal function of reproduction.</p>
            <p><person reg="Gibbs, Mrs. Rufus">Mrs. Gibbs</person>’ testimony should be disregarded
                as an opponent to bill S. 1842. Her position is ridiculous.</p>
            <p>She stated that she had borne four children in 6 years. For 20 years she has had an
                ophthalmic goitre, and has had no further pregnancies, her physician having advised
                her how to avoid further childbearing. How selfish and hypocritical to oppose the
                granting of similar information to other mothers. Mrs. Gibbs is fortunate to live in
                    <place reg="Baltimore, MD">Baltimore</place> and have the means to obtain proper
                information which has safeguarded her health and life. Yet she would deny the right
                to less fortunate women to receive the same advice. Her case proves to be one of our
                contentions that pregnancy may jeopardize the life of women.</p>
            <p><person reg="Burton, Ralph">Mr. Burton</person> introduced <person
                    reg="Chase, William Sheaf">Reverend Chase</person> as representing the
                    <org>International Reform Federation</org>. This is incorrect. We have already
                filed a statement from <person reg="Wilson, Clarence True">Rev. Clarence True
                    Wilson</person>, vice president of this organization, which states that the
                International Reform Federation has taken no action on the legislation. The
                statement of Reverend Chase is merely his personal opinion.</p>
            <p>Canon Chase infers the <org>Lambeth Conference of Bishops</org> went on record as
                opposed to birth control, which is untrue. We take exception to this statement and
                quote herewith a paragraph from this statement of Lambeth Conference which reads as
                follows:</p>
            <p><q who="LC">If there is a good moral reason why the way of abstinence should not be
                    followed, we cannot condemn the use of scientific methods to prevent conception
                    * * *</q></p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head>WHAT THIS CHANGE IN THE LAW WILL DO</head>
            <p>First, it will give the doctors, hospitals, clinics, dispensaries, public, State, and
                county health agencies the right to order and receive, through the mails and common
                carriers, the articles needed to protect the health of these women who need such
                protection.</p>
            <p>It will place the giving of this information in the hands of qualified persons who
                will be responsible for its dissemination.</p>
            <p>The opponents did not refute nor can they refute the scientific facts, medical and
                economic, as presented by the proponents of this bill. They did not deny that
                maternal health is jeopardized by too many births; that abortions are the result of
                too frequent pregnancies,; that physicians should have the legal right to give
                contraceptive advice when necessary.</p>
            <p>They admit that 47 States allow the dissemination of contraceptive information.</p>
            <p>They admit that the laws as they stand today are violated on a wholesale scale.</p>
            <p>They admit that the whole subject is out of control of the law, contraceptive
                articles being scattered promiscuously, regardless of their need or proper use.</p>
            <p>On all major facts we are in agreement.</p>
            <p>To the proponents it is a question of national health, economic responsibility, and
                individual liberty.</p>
            <p>The opponents have thus far not produced a distinguished scientist, either economist
                or sociologist, eugenicist, or population authority, at any of these hearings, nor
                have they had representatives of any non-Catholic organizations, except Mr. Ralph
                Burton, their chairman.</p>
            <p>While non-Catholic individuals have opposed this bill, they each and every one have
                proclaimed they represented no organization. Mrs. Rufus Gibbs; <person
                    reg="Morgan, Gerry">Dr. Gerry Morgan</person>, dean of medical school of
                    <org>Georgetown University</org>, a Catholic university; <person
                    reg="Boorde, Thomas">Rev. Thomas Boorde</person>, Canon Sheafe Chase; <person
                    reg="Cattell, W. Henry">Dr. W. Henry Cattell</person>; <person reg="UNK">Mr.
                    Soloman</person> - all others represent Catholic organizations and thus attempt
                to impose their “beliefs” upon the American people.</p>
            <p>We could respect and understand, though profoundly disagree with, our opponents, if
                they came here and said:</p>
            <p>This is our conception of morality. It is our religious belief that birth control is
                wrong. We cannot concede to any interference with the laws of Nature and we prefer
                slums, overcrowding, disease, filth, maternal, and infant mortality, child labor,
                prostitution, illiteracy, unemployment, crime, imbecility, national decadence, and
                wars to any change in these laws --</p>
            <p>But we cannot respect the attitude, the loose thinking, and the hypocrisy of those
                who oppose birth-control practices and offer no practice alternative to take its
                place.</p>
            <p>They base their entire case on Catholic morality, and would impose this upon the
                American people, which is an arrogant assumption of authority.</p>
            <p>I wonder if Dr. Wilson would tell us something of the medical conditions, or the
                consequences. </p>
            <p>[Statement of Dr. Prentiss Wilson, M.D. was excluded and not transcribed]</p>
            <p>Mrs. SANGER. Dr. Cattell mentioned in his letter the Federal Council of the Churches
                of Christ in America, as to their stand on birth control. Here is a pamphlet that
                was brought out by the <org>Committee on Marriage</org> and <org
                    reg="Federal Council of the Churches of Christ in America">Home of the Federal
                    Council</org> which I would like to put into the record. It contains excerpts
                from statements made by religious leaders. I think it has not gone in as yet.</p>
            <p><q who="NEEMA">Senator NEELY. If it is in the record, we will not duplicate it. It
                    apparently seems to have been lost. Is that all, Mrs. Sanger? </q></p>
            <p>Mrs. SANGER. Yes.</p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
