<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/06/01 CE</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-18 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1936/12/29"><supplied resp="MSPP">29 Dec 1936</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>A Momentous Decision</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp301424</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Alice Park Papers, Hoover Institution Archives, Stanford University</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microflm</title>, C16:0398</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="USVOP">United States versus One Package of Japanese Contraceptives
                decision</name>
            <name id="COMBIL">Comstock Act of 1873</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>For an earlier draft, see Margaret Sanger Microfilm S71:0876.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Comstock act"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Federal"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="MS on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="legal cases"
            level3="U.S. V. One Package of Japanese contraceptives'"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="legalization of"/>
        <index level1="physicians" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="government" level3="birth control and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>A MOMENTOUS DECISION</head>
        <p>The decision handed down by the <org>United States Circuit Court of Appeals for the
                Second Circuit</org> may be acclaimed as the close of one epoch and the dawn of
            another. It brings to an end the sixty-three year reign of muddle and tyranny
            inaugurated by the so-called <name type="law"
                reg="United States Criminal Code, Section 211">Comstock legislation</name> enacted
            in 1873, and clarifies once and for al future time the position and the rights of the
            American physician in the legitimate use of scientific contraceptives.</p>
        <p>The most significant passages of this decision, signed by Justices <person
                reg="Hand, Billings Learned">Learned Hand</person>, <person
                reg="Swan, Thomas Walter">Thomas W. Swan</person>, and <person
                reg="Hand, Augustus Noble">Augustus N. Hand</person>, cannot be too often quotes:
                “<q who="USVOP">. . . While we may assume that Section 305 (a) of the <title>Tariff
                    Act of 1930</title> exempts only such articles as the <name type="law"
                    reg="Comstock Act of 1873">Act of 1873</name> excepted, yet we are satisfied
                that this statute, as well as all the acts we have referred to, embraced only such
                articles as <org reg="United States Congress">Congress</org> would have denounced as
                immoral if it had understood all the conditions under which they were to be used.
                Its design, in our opinion, was not to prevent the importation, sale, or carriage by
                mail of things which might intelligently be employed by conscientious and competent
                physicians for the purpose of saving life or promoting the well-being of their
                patients</q>.”</p>
        <p>The distinction between therapeutic abortion and criminal abortion has been clearly
            established. We have long felt the injustice of a law which permits abortion when it is
            necessary for life and well being, but makes no distinction between lawful and unlawful
            contraception. This is all the most inconsistent since reliable birth control, in large
            measure, obviates the necessity for abortion.</p>
        <p>From this viewpoint, the following excerpt from the decision is particularly significant.
                “<q who="USVOP">The word ‘unlawful’ would make this clear as to articles for
                producing abortions and the courts have read an exemption into the act covering such
                articles even where the word ‘unlawful’ is not used. The same exception should apply
                to articles for preventing conception . . . It is going far beyond such a policy to
                hold that abortions, which destroy incipient life, may be allowed in proper cases,
                and yet that no measures may be taken to prevent conception, even though a likely
                result should be to require the termination of pregnancy by means of an operation.
                It seems unreasonable to suppose that the national scheme of legislation would
                involve such inconsistencies and should require the complete suppression of
                articles, the use of which in many cases is advocated by such a weight of authority
                in the medical world . . . The decree dismissing the libel is affirmed</q>.”</p>
        <p>As originally introduced in the <org reg="United States Senate">Senate</org>, the
            so-called Comstock Bill contained the words “<q who="COMBIL">except on the prescription
                of a physician in good standing, given in good faith</q>,” but these words were
            omitted from the bill as it was ultimately passed. The decision of the Circuit Court of
            Appeals restores this implicit interpretation, sustaining the interpretation of other
            courts and tribunals. Thus while government officials have sought a literal
            interpretation of the Act of 1873 and the <name type="law"
                reg="United States Tariff Act, Section 305">Tariff Act of 1930</name>, involving the
            importation of contraceptives, the Bench has given a larger, more humane, logical, and
            far-seeing interpretation to the confusing statutes which have stood as obstacles to
            progress for sixty-three years.</p>
        <p>It is not enough merely to assert the right of the physician and the scientist form the
            ethical point of view. His right and his humane duty must be established by the Courts,
            just as the inventor must establish his right to his patent. This ethical gain is now
            placed on the soundest basis. As far as physicians are concerned, the momentous decision
            of the Circuit Court removes restrictions in the use of the mails and the importation of
            contraceptives. The <org>National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth
                Control</org> is gratified at this decision, which should be looked upon as the dawn
            of a new enlightened era. For the past five years, this Committee has concentrated its
            efforts upon the task of persuading Congress to enact an amendment exempting duly
            authorized physicians, hospitals and medical schools from the restrictions of the
            so-called “obscenity” statutes; but Congress has failed to recognize the importance of
            the logical distinctions now drawn with such sharp and surgical cleanness by the
            decision of the Circuit Court of Appeals.</p>
        <p>Our Committee has vigorously and insistently sought to educate constituencies and to
            organize public opinion as to the necessity of liberating physicians and scientists from
            the shackles of the confusing and muddled Comstock statutes. Thousands of enlightened
            physicians have stood with us in this crusade. Time and time again many distinguished
            doctors have taken time from their crowded practices to testify in our behalf before
            Congressional hearings, and have testified in court proceedings in support of our
            position.</p>
        <p>The future well-being of the country owes a debt of gratitude not only to these men, but
            no less to the attorneys-at-law who generously volunteered their services in battle
            after battle, in our struggle to establish basic rights.</p>
        <p>The decision of the United States Circuit Court of Appeals demonstrates that these
            manifold efforts have not been in vain. In acclaiming this momentous victory, however,
            we must recognize that it is but one step forward. Other obstacles persist; other
            hurdles must be jumped. For the moment we may rest content to call the attention of the
            medical profession to this gift--this right which, let us not forget, can be maintained
            and developed in the service of humanity only by its use. Legal rights, not unlike
            bodily muscles, must be exercised to grow in health and strength.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
