<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2009/07/15 LL</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-10 CH clean regs </prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1931-00-00">Add date in standard format</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Proceedings of the Seventh International Birth Control Conference</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp229941</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
                <title/>
            </bibl>
            <bibl><title>MSM</title> S71:0277</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="FRE">French</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>For other versions see MSP S71:0277 and 0274 and Library of Congress 131:0489 and
            0493.</p>
        <index level1="conferences" level2="Zurich Conference" level3="1930"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="research"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="international"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="international conferences on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="goals and strategies"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>INTRODUCTION</head>
        <p> On September 1, 1930, an earnest group of experts--men and women--from various parts of
            the civilized world gathered quietly together in <place>Zurich, Switzerland</place>.</p>
        <p>These men and women were delegates to the <name type="conference">Seventh International
                Birth Control Conference</name>. They came together in the interest of the
            scientific quest for contraceptive knowledge.</p>
        <p>For five days, more than one hundred scientists, physicians and clinicians discussed the
            technical problems of contraception. They compared notes, reported progress made in
            research laboratories and birth control clinics, and proved beyond doubt that the much
            troubled subject now universally known as Birth Control had entered a new phase of
            development.</p>
        <p>All theories, all propaganda, all moral and ethical aspects of the subject were left in
            abeyance--practically forgotten--in the unanimity of cool, scientific conviction that
            today contraception as an instrument in racial progress is on the way to be reliable and
            efficient and may in the very future be perfected.</p>
        <p>As the first international conference of its kind ever organized in the history of
            humanity, the Zurich Conference represents a milestone in the history of modern
            civilization. For this reason, I believe that it is highly desirable that the record of
            this conference be preserved in the present pages.</p>
        <p>Civilization is being remade, not in parliaments, not in the conferences of international
            financiers on the <place reg="Quai d'Orsay, Paris, France">Quai d’Orsay</place>, but by
            obscure scientists in laboratories, by earnest workers in clinics, by the silent
            victories of modest physicians in preventive therapy. Just as the great spectacular
            achievements in aviation--the trans-atlantic and round-the-world flight--would never be
            possible without the vastly increased perfection of design which insures reliability and
            efficiency, so today contraception as an instrument of individual and racial well-being
            would not be possible without the efforts of these scientists, the bio-chemists and the
            clinicians through the agency of whose laboratories new methods, new materials, new
            processes can be effectively developed and proven.</p>
        <p>A milestone and landmark this Conference must remain, because it has lifted the whole
            problem out of the troubled atmosphere of theory where previously it had been battered
            by the winds of doctrine and the brutal attacks of prejudice into the current of serene,
            impersonal, scientific abstraction. That such a gathering, widely international in
            character, coolly yet compassionately humanitarian in temperament, could become a
            reality in my own time, instead of a wish hoped for yet hardly to be attained, indicated
            to one soldier at least in the long battle that a new orientation in race welfare had
            indeed arrived.</p>
        <p>For many years past I had been acutely cognizant of the fact--to me distressing and
            seeming insurmountable--that many of our most able physicians were absolutely lacking in
            knowledge of the technique of contraception. Even those who were familiar enough with
            the methods available recognized that the percentage of efficiency and safety were
            widely fluctuating. Such was the condition of affairs in the <place
                reg="United States of America">United States</place> which impelled me to call
            together the men and women actually working on the problem in the various scattered
            clinics of <place>Europe</place> and <place>Asia</place>.</p>
        <p>It was a sad commentary on the progress of medical science, with its recent emphasis on
            preventive therapy, that while it is roughly estimated that the number of abortions
            performed annually in this country amounts to no less than one million, the methods of
            contraception had not been advanced since the days of Mensinga. The medical attitude
            toward contraception has only recently changed. Its indifference may have been, to a
            large extent, influenced by the early crusaders for birth control, which until my own
            advent in the field hid under the name of Neo-Malthusianism. For almost a century they
            had been fighting in the fields of economic and social doctrine. Implicitly they had
            assumed that the known methods of contraception were already one-hundred per cent
            effective, and required only to be disseminated by the written or spoken word.</p>
        <p>That this was a fallacy was soon discovered in the controversy of technique and methods
            by modern students of clinical contraception. But the first necessity was to ascertain
            what methods were being advised; how the method was applied; what percentage of success
            or failure attended the various methods. This was demonstrated in the experience with
            the diaphragm pessary as used in the clinics by Dr. <person reg="Haire, Norman">Norman
                Haire</person> and Dr. <person reg="Stone, Hannah">Hannah Stone</person>--two
            different phases of technique by two competent students of gynecology through the means
            of the same pessary. This and other differences will be noticed as brought out in the
            papers as well as in the discussion.</p>
        <p>It is of interest to note from the Proceedings of the Conference that greater advance in
            scientific contraception has been made in America and <place>England</place> than in
            continental countries (not excepting <place reg="Netherlands, The">Holland</place> and
                <place>France</place> where the practice of birth control has long been a part of
            family life). This is the result of directing the movement along professional lines,
            where emphasis has been placed on the keeping of records as well as on a greater
            consideration of contraception, keeping it separate and apart from sex hygiene and
            abortion.</p>
        <p>Just as demand and supply are related to all economic questions, so is propaganda a
            related part of scientific research in the realms of sex psychology. The medical
            profession will ultimately meet the issue on the demands of public opinion.</p>
        <p>The next and most important step in the progress of the movement is to perfect a method
            of contraception giving a greater security and confidence to those workers in the
            field.</p>
        <p>In the early days <person reg="Bradlaugh, Charles">Charles Bradlaugh</person> and <person
                reg="Besant, Annie">Annie Besant</person> had been tried in <place
                reg="London, England">London</place> for circulating Dr. <person
                reg="Knowlton, Charles">Charles Knowlton</person>’s “<title>Fruits of
                Philosophy</title>,” a pamphlet written by the <place reg="Boston, MA"
                >Boston</place> physician about half a century previous and detailing in the
            sketchiest fashion crude methods upon which it would today be folly to rely.</p>
        <p>The following year--1878--<person reg="Truelove, Edward">Edward Truelove</person>, a
            London publisher, was sentenced for selling a similar book, <person
                reg="Owen, Robert Dale">Robert Dale Owen</person>’s “<title>Moral
            Physiology</title>,” which was far more innocuous, from the point of view of
            contraception, than its advocates supposed. From the first publication of <title>The
                Malthusian</title>, which began its work in 1879 with the sub-title of “<title>A
                Crusade against Poverty</title>,” the advocates of birth control at the time
            unconsciously assumed that methods of contraception were already reliable, effective,
            and practically perfected. Statistics were unavailable; clinics which might have kept
            records, were either forbidden by law or unheard of; and the medical profession, as a
            whole, remained antagonistic or at best indifferent to this vast and complicated problem
            of human life.</p>
        <p>However, it would be unjust to minimize the progress made by the courageous physicians
            and pioneers of the movement. Dr. <person>Stille</person>, a physician of <place
                reg="Hanover, MD">Hanover</place>, as well as <person reg="Hausmeister, Max">Max
                Hausmeister</person> and <person reg="Lotter, Karl">Karl Lotter</person>, who in
            1889 founded the <org>Sozial Harmonische Verein</org> in <place reg="Stuttgart, Germany"
                >Stuttgart</place>, devoted themselves mainly to theoretical and economic aspects of
            the small family system. We may read of the enormous decline of the birth rate in
            certain German towns at the period; but it is impossible to definitely correlate in a
            precise scientific manner the two phenomena. In France, the birth rate had indeed been
            declining since 1831, and more sharply since 1871, although the late <person
                reg="Robin, Paul">Paul Robin</person> had not founded his <org>
                <emph rend="Italics">
                    <foreign lang="FRE">Ligue de la régéneration humaine</foreign>
                </emph>
            </org> until 1896.</p>
        <p>In 1900 the <name type="conference">first International Neo-Malthusian Conference</name>
            was held in <place reg="Paris, France">Paris</place>--in the office of M. Robin’s
            League. Delegates from four countries--England, France, <place>Germany</place> and
            Holland--took part in what for those days was considered a thorough discussion of
            technical methods of contraception. Dr. <person reg="Rutgers, J.">J. Rutgers</person> of
            Holland in particular, we are informed, presented a discussion of such methods, both
            historical and contemporaneous. This, it seems, was the second international conference
            on methods, the first having taken place at an <org>International Medical Congress</org>
            in 1879 in <place reg="Amsterdam, The Netherlands">Amsterdam</place>.</p>
        <p>Paul Robin had proposed the formation of an <org>international federation of
                Neo-Malthusian leagues</org>, and Dr. <person reg="Drysdale, C.R.">C. R.
                Drysdale</person> was elected president of this organization. A <name
                type="conference">second international conference</name> was called in <place>Liége,
                Belgium</place>, in 1905. Records of this meeting indicate the swing of interest
            away from technical aspects of contraception to the problems of propaganda and
            popularization. At the Liége meeting the Neo-Malthusians came into sharp conflict with
            the Marxians, who were the advocates of larger and larger families as the surest method
            to precipitate social revolution. This clash of ideas had the effect of propelling
            public interest away from the technical and hygienic aspects of contraception to the
            social aspects of population pressure.</p>
        <p>Subsequent international conferences followed: in <place
                reg="Hague, The, Netherland, The">the Hague</place> (July, 1910); participation in
            the <org>International Congress of Hygiene</org> in <place reg="Dresden, Germany"
                >Dresden</place> (1911) in which representatives of thirteen countries participated.
            Two German women pioneers, Dr. <person reg="Stöcker, Helene">Helene Stöcker</person> and
            Frau <person reg="Stritt, Marie">Marie Stritt</person>, acted as organizers. It was not
            until 1922 that the <name type="conference">Fifth International Conference</name> was
            held. In 1914 I had initiated the so-called Birth Control movement in the United States,
            and this movement, with its emphasis on the personal and racial aspects of
            contraception, had in less than ten years become a world movement. In 1922 in London,
            not only Europe, but the Americas, <place>Japan</place>, <place>China</place> and
                <place>India</place> were represented by delegates. In 1925 the <name
                type="conference">Sixth Neo-Malthusian and Birth Control Conference</name> was held
            in <place reg="New York, NY">New York City</place>, and delegates from sixteen countries
            attended.</p>
        <p>Since 1914, in ever increasing numbers we had gradually succeeded in effecting the
            adherence of economists, sociologists, biologists and geneticists, the effect of which
            was to convert the intelligent laymen to the principle of birth control. In this field
            indeed, the battle seemed to be won. Because public opinion supported birth control, it
            was possible, despite the still strenuous opposition, to open and maintain contraceptive
            clinics--except in such countries as France and <place>Italy</place>, engulfed in waves
            of post-war reaction.</p>
        <p>More and more it became apparent to me that a new direction was necessary. The theories,
            the ramifications, the racial aspects of birth control had been thoroughly threshed out.
            It was but a matter of time that these fundamental ideas should percolate to the
            masses--the masses indeed were already crying aloud for “<soCalled>safe and
                harmless</soCalled>” methods. But since the opening of the century, Medicine itself
            has evolved from its dogmatic stage. Prevention indeed was the cry--the prevention of
            epidemics, the prevention of disease, the conquest of the great scourges like
            tuberculosis or syphilis, instead of their alleviation. Medicine indeed was fast
            becoming, as a penetrating observer recently expressed it, the most personal of our
            sciences, and was advancing from the art of curing to the art of prevention. Science was
            effecting a veritable revolution in sanitation and general health education. The
            practical step then to take is to apply scientific knowledge to improve conditions of
            life.</p>
        <p>From the beginning, I had insisted upon the establishment of birth control clinics as the
            swiftest, most effective, and most scientific method of advancing the cause of
            contraception.</p>
        <p>Yet all of this work going on in various countries, under the most diverse conditions,
            must be correlated, coordinated, unified into a common human ideal. For this reason,
            after organizing the <name type="conference">first World Population conference</name>,
            assembled in <place reg="Geneva, Switzerland">Geneva</place> in 1927, I began work on
            the problem of bringing the scientists, the research workers, and the directors of
            clinics together. The success achieved is recorded in the accompanying pages.</p>
        <p>Not without significance, to me, was the quiet earnestness of this unheralded gathering.
            The press did not intrude upon the deliberation of the men and women assembled in the
            charming little town in the Alps. No publicity was sought. The most important as well as
            the most delicate of all human relationships was discussed without shame and without
            prejudice, and problems most deeply affecting the well-being of every individual man and
            woman, the health of all future generations, and the stability of nations, were brought
            closer to satisfactory and permanent solution.</p>
        <p>Here indeed, the impartial observer might have discovered the true spirit of
            internationalism, the fundamental brotherhood of man, rather than in the bickerings and
            disagreements of <org>the League of Nations</org> at Geneva, or the truce in the warfare
            of governmental finances.</p>
        <p>For these reasons, the record of the Zurich Conference demand permanent place in the
            annals of human progress.</p>
        <p>New York, U.S.A.</p>
        <byline>MARGARET SANGER</byline>
    </docBody>
</doc>
