<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2003/07/30 SR</prepDate>
		<prepDate>21014-04-16 EK clean regs</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1924-02-23">23 Feb 1924</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart type="article">The Case for Birth Control</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp301540</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="journal">The Woman Citizen</title>, Feb. 23, 1924, 17, 28.</bibl>
			<bibl><title type="mf">Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Collected Documents</title>
				C16:212</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name/>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>This article was reprinted by the <org>American Birth Control League</org> in 1925 <title
				type="book">Margaret Sanger Microfilm: Collected Documents</title>, C16:273.)</p>
		<index level1="abortion"/>
		<index level1="American Birth Control League"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="and marriage"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="medically controlled"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="socio-economic benefits of"/>
		<index level1="child spacing"/>
		<index level1="child welfare"/>
		<index level1="eugenics"/>
		<index level1="marriage" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="&quot;feeble-minded&quot; persons" level2="allowed to reproduce"/>
		<index level1="poverty" level2="family size and"/>
		<index level1="population growth"/>
		<index level1="pregnancy" level2="health risks"/>
		<index level1="sex education" level2="birth control and"/>
		<index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>The Case for Birth Control</head>
		<byline>By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></byline>
		<p>Everywhere we look, we see poverty and large families going hand in hand. We see hordes
			of children whose parents cannot feed, clothe or educate even one-half of the number
			born to them. We see sick, harassed, broken mothers whose health and nerves cannot bear
			the strain of further childbearing. We see fathers growing despondent and desperate,
			because their labor cannot bring the necessary wage to keep their growing families. We
			see that those parents who are least fit to reproduce the race are having the largest
			number of children; while people of wealth, leisure and education are having small
			families.</p>
		<p>It is generally conceded by sociologists and scientists that a nation cannot go on
			indefinitely multiplying without eventually reaching the point when population presses
			upon means of subsistence. While in this country there is perhaps no need for immediate
			alarm on this account, there are many other reasons for demanding Birth Control. At
			present, for the poor mother, there is only one alternative to the necessity of bearing
			children year after year, regardless of her health, of the welfare of the children she
			already has, and of the income of the family. This alternative is abortion, which is so
			common as to be almost universal, especially where there are rigid laws against
			imparting information for the prevention of conception. It has been estimated that there
			are about one million abortions in the <place>United States</place> each year.</p>
		<p>To force poor mothers to resort to this dangerous and health-destroying method of
			curtailing their families is cruel, wicked and heartless, and it is often the mothers
			who care most about the welfare of their children who are willing to undergo any pain or
			risk to prevent the coming of infants for whom they cannot properly care.</p>
		<p> There are definite reasons when and why parents should not have children, which will be
			conceded by most thoughtful people.</p>
		<list>
			<item><emph rend="italics">First.</emph>--Children should not be born when either parent
				has an inheritable disease, such as insanity, feeble-mindedness, epilepsy or
				syphilis.</item>
			<item><emph rend="italics">Second.</emph>--When the mother is suffering from
				tuberculosis, kidney disease, heart disease or pelvic deformity.</item>
			<item><emph rend="italics">Third.</emph>--When either parent has gonorrhea. This disease
				in the mother is cause of ninety per cent of blindness in newborn babies.</item>
			<item><emph rend="italics">Fourth.</emph>--When children already born are not normal,
				even though both parents are in good physical and mental condition.</item>
			<item><emph rend="italics">Fifth.</emph>--Not until the woman is twenty-three years old
				and the man twenty-five.</item>
			<item><emph rend="italics">Sixth.</emph>--Not until the previous baby is at least three
				years old. This gives a year to recover from the physical ordeal of the birth of the
				baby, a year to rest, be normal and enjoy her motherhood, and another year to
				prepare for the coming of the next. We want mothers to be fit. We want them to
				conceive in joy and gladness. We want them to carry their babies during the nine
				months in a sound and healthy body and with a happy, joyous, hopeful mind. It is
				almost impossible to imagine the suffering caused to women, the mental agony they
				endure, when their days and nights are haunted by the fear of undesired
				pregnancy.</item>
			<item><emph rend="italics">Seventh.</emph>--Children should not be born to parents whose
				economic circumstances do not guarantee enough to provide the children with the
				necessities of life. A couple who can take care of two children and bring them up
				decently in health and comfort, give them an education and start them fairly in
				life, do more for their country and for mankind than the couple who recklessly
				reproduce ten or twelve children, some of them to die in infancy, others to survive
				but to enter the mill or factory at an early age, and all to sink to that level of
				degradation where charity, either state or private, is necessary to keep them alive.
				The man who cannot support three children should not have ten, notwithstanding all
				pleas of the militarists for numbers.</item>
			<item><emph rend="italics">Eighth.</emph>--A woman should not bear children when
				exhausted from labor. This especially applies to women who marry after spending
				several years in industrial or commercial life. Conception should not take place
				until she is in good health and has overcome her fatigue.</item>
			<item><emph rend="italics">Ninth.</emph>--Not for two years after marriage should a
				couple undertake the great responsibility of becoming parents. Thousands of young
				people enter marriage without the faintest idea of what marriage involves. They do
				not know its spiritual responsibilities. If children are born quickly and
				plentifully, people consider that the marriage is justified. I claim that this is
				barbaric and wrong. It is wrong for the wife, for the man, for the children. It is
				impossible for two young people to really know each other until they have lived
				together in marriage. After the closeness and intimacy of that relation there often
				comes to the woman a rude awakening; the devoted lover becomes careless and
				dissatisfied. If she becomes pregnant immediately she becomes physically disturbed,
				nervous and irritable. The girl has changed, and the boy who knew her as a happy
				smiling sweetheart finds her disagreeable and disgruntled. Of course thousands of
				people learn to adjust themselves. Nevertheless, I maintain that young people should
				marry early and wait at least two years to adjust their own lives, to play an read
				together and to build up a cultural and spiritual friendship. Then will come the
				intense desire to call into being a little child to share their love and happiness.
				When children are conceived in love and born into an atmosphere of happiness, then
				will parenthood be a glorious privilege, and the children will grow to resemble
				gods. This can only be obtained through the knowledge and practice of Birth
				Control.</item>
		</list>
		<p>P.S.--The <org>American Birth Control League</org> desires that the instruction in Birth
			Control should be given by the medical profession. Only through individual care and
			treatment can a woman be given the best and safest means of controlling her offspring.
			We do not favor the indiscriminate diffusion of unreliable and unsafe Birth Control
			advice.</p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
