<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011-08-04 NC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2012-04-04 CH Proofed Tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-08 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1954-01-24">01 Jan 1954</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Mrs. Slee Outlines Problems of Population</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp302094</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Arizona Daily Star</title> June 24, 1954</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> C16:0446</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>For draft version see <title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S72:906 and 911.</p>
        <index level1="population growth" level2="natural resources and"/>
        <index level1="population growth" level2="regulation of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Mrs. Slee Outlines Problems of Population</head>
        <head type="sub">World-Famous Worker Reports on Crucial Job to be Done</head>
        <byline>By Mrs. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger Slee</person></byline>
        <p>A recent article headlined in the <title type="journal">Arizona Daily Star</title>
                “<title type="article">Growing Pace of Population Stirs Warning</title>” was all too
            brief in its story of the alarming situation of population growth throughout the world.
            The report quotes was issued by the <org>Population Reference Bureau</org> in <place
                reg="Washington, DC">Washington, D.C.</place> This bureau is maintained by
            non-government scientists, mainly demographers, and is free and independent to study
            situations and report them to its readers. The report called upon the <place>United
                States</place> and other nations to face squarely and realistically the population
            problems in the world today, and thus avoid the tragedy caused by hungry people, who
            will eventually resort to violence or succumb to the false promises of communism, as the
            Chinese have done and groups in other overpopulation countries are trying to do.</p>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Glimmering of Hope</head>
            <p>Fortunately there is a glimmering of hope, at last an awakening on the part of some
                governments like <place>Japan</place> and <place>India</place> to see the importance
                of controlling population growth. The census report of 1951 by the <org>Government
                    of India</org> called upon the planning commission to undertake an intensive
                campaign throughout India to control the birth rate, in order to avert national
                disaster caused by the rapidly growing population, now 357,000,000, and soaring at
                the rate of five million every year. Attention is called to the fact of the total
                world population, estimated at 2,465,000,000 in 1951, increasing by 75,000 persons
                every day, or 30,000,000 a year, all of which increases daily and yearly because of
                the fact of medical science, improved satisfaction, which cuts down the death rate
                in these countries, which otherwise would not be so rapidly increasing.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Chaos Predicted</head>
            <p>A recent book by a distinguished demographer, Professor <person
                    reg="Osborne, Fairfield">Fairfield Osborne</person>, presents a persuasive
                survey, in his recent book “<title type="book">The Limits of the Earth</title>”,
                showing the connection throughout the ages between agricultural resources,
                population increase and the advance and welfare of civilization. He, like other
                experts and demographers, believes that improved techniques and agriculture, etc.
                can somewhat increase food production, but even with the development of new areas,
                and it is doubtful that there are many, that the increase of food production cannot
                keep up with the present increase of population, unless there is a general policy of
                slowing down the birthrate, a national spacing of children in families, and in
                certain cases the limitation of numbers. Unless this slowing down and spacing can
                occur on a large scale, ultimate world chaos is bound to result.</p>
            <p>As one becomes acquainted with the survey and the serious studies of experts in the
                field of soil erosion, population growth and the general deterioration of standards
                and the overcrowding in cities and schools and transportation, one wonders why this
                wild mad race calling upon people to increase their numbers.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Previous Catastrophe</head>
            <p>Should not the purpose of government be a happier, better, healthier existence for
                its people here and now? Have we not seen the catastrophe of this madness with
                    <person reg="Mussolini, Benito">Mussolini</person>, <person reg="Hitler, Adolf"
                    >Hitler</person>, and the warmongers of Japan? Where has this madness led their
                people? It is all too obvious today where overpopulation can lead any country. The
                movement for the control of the birth rate and the spacing of children in families
                has been in most countries like the voice in the wilderness. Fortunately in the U.S.
                in all our large cities between 500 and 600 private clinics have been set up where
                parents may come and receive individual, personal, scientific information on
                controlling the size of the family. But this is a wee drop in the ocean compared to
                what needs to be done, and especially in reaching down to the strata of our
                population where ill health, poor housing, and overcrowding have caused and are
                causing social conditions that most nations cannot be proud of.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"><place reg="Tucson, AZ">Tucson</place> Lauded</head>
            <p>We are fortunate in this city of Tucson to have such a <org
                    reg="Tucson Mother's Clinic">Planned Parenthood clinic</org>, which has for the
                past 18 years has helped parents. It is a proud record where more than 6,430 parents
                have availed themselves of proper knowledge and today can demonstrate the good
                fortune of small healthy family units. The majority of the mothers who apply for
                such information are often in poor health, usually financially unable to meet the
                needs of the three or four, or six and eight children they already have. The clinic
                does not charge for this information. </p>
            <p>The board of directors are volunteers and must go to the people of Tucson to help
                meet the cost of this service. Perhaps the greatest advancement as to the humanity
                of this work is the fact that the overcrowded countries of the Orient are accepting
                it as a way to a better life and a better civilization.</p>
            <p>The one obstacle in the way of more far-reaching results is the lack of a simple,
                cheap, generally acceptable method of contraception, or methods that could be used
                by the ignorant, primitive people throughout the slums and jungles of the world.
                This means laboratory research, of which I am proud to say four projects are already
                valiantly struggling for existence in this country and one in
                <place>England</place>. The technicians are struggling on pennies, where the
                research on atom bombs and other destructive forces has millions in its
                disposal.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Population Commission</head>
            <p>Research for this project scarcely has pennies. The world looks to the United States
                for the answer, as we have been foremost in projecting and carrying the ideals of
                controlling population for the past several decades. The <org>United Nations</org>
                has now a population commission to study these problems and has called a <org
                    reg="World Population Conference (Rome)">meeting</org> in September, 1954 to
                convene in <place>Rome, Italy</place>. What comes of this commission no one can
                say.</p>
            <p>But we in Tucson will go on struggling as valiantly as possible, helping and
                educating and advising parents and mothers and fathers to be and about to be,
                wherever and whenever they request such information. </p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
