<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2007/07/17 AP</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2009/07/30 LL</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-03-10 CH clean regs</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-22 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-23 CH combine this with two other
			draft/excerpts.</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1928-03-15">15 Mar 1928</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Address on Return from Europe </supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp302113</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Support for Birth Control</title>,
					<title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title> Apr.
				1928, p. 107-8; <title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Collected
					Documents Series</title> or C16:288;</bibl>
			<bibl>Engineer's Auditorium Speech, Library of Congress Microfilm
				130:725B; and </bibl>
			<bibl>Engineer's Auditorium Speech Opening notes, <title type="mf"
					>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Smith College
					Collections</title> S71:122.</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>On returning from an extended trip in <place>Europe</place>, Sanger
			spoke at a joint meeting of women's groups in New York's
				<org>Engineer's Auditorium</org> to protest the failure of a
			state birth control bill to be reported out of Committee. No
			complete version of the speech exists, this text has been compiled
			from an excerpt from a summary of the event, partial speech notes,
			and draft notes for opening.</p>
		<index level1="population" level2="birth control and"/>
		<index level1="eugenics" level2="birth control and"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<div type="section">
			<head>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">From opening draft</supplied>
			</head>
<head type="sub">A Warm Welcome</head>
			<p>Mrs. Sanger, the last speaker, whose appearance after her long absence was </p>
			<head type="sub">Mrs. Sanger on Population</head>
			<p>Science is now bordering on the infinite and the most powerful
				brain seems feeble in the face of tasks which are glimpsed. If
				one is to judge by the present predicament of the world, we may
				assume that there is no individual nor group whose intelligence
				is equal to the tasks that the international situation demands.
				It seems almost as if the knowledge required exceeds our
				capacity for understanding.</p>
			<p>It is to the science of population that we must now look for
				future guidance. It must point the way for population regulation
				which in this country, in particular, could soon deliver society
				from more than half of its terrific burdens. It could soon help
				us to eliminate the possibility of increasing dysgenic stocks,
				such as those with inherited or transmissible diseases. It could
				soon lessen the burden of philanthropic demands which are fast
				growing beyond the cultural needs of this generation. Sane
				legislation would indirectly direct reproduction towards
				adaptation to future conditions by raising the mean level of
				brain power. The importance of numbers belongs to the past
				rather than to the future.</p>
			<p>The needs of manual labor in the future will be greatly reduced
				by the progress of chemistry, physics and the possession of
				unlimited sources of heat and force at a minimum of expenditure.
				On the other hand, we shall need brains highly resistant to work
				and capable of a degree of education surpassing that of the most
				intelligent skilled artisan today. Vaster memories must be
				forged, sharper insight must be gained and with the discovery of
				the laws of inheritance men can choose whether we shall evolve
				to the expression of the highest within us, or revert to the
				stage of the barbarian. It is for man to decide.</p>
			<p>With all the knowledge that we today posses, it is obvious that
				it is a crime for generations to come, it is a crime against our
				civilization to encourage the reproduction of mediocre, diseased
				or inferior types of groups. Such offspring can only be a burden
				to the future and retard the progress of the present
				generation.</p>
			<p>It has become clear that the population of the earth is fast
				arriving at its possible maximum; that its density is badly
				distributed; that redistribution of space can only be rectified
				by displacements; and that Birth Control in overpopulated
				countries is the first and surest method whereby the balance may
				be peacefully restored.</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<p>
				<supplied>Notes for the Introduction</supplied>
			</p>
			<p>To receive so warm a welcome on one's return, makes me glad to go
				away, so as to want the pleasure of coming back.</p>
			<p>The ABCL. during the past two years has faced a test
					<add>of</add> which any organization can be proud -- to
				exist, to function, to carry on in the prolonged absence of its
				Pres. The League, I am happy to say, has met this Emergency
				bravely, cheerfully, and to its credit &amp; my delight has
				averted the usual annual financial crisis</p>
			<p>I find the various departments strengthened through effort. New
				ties have been formed; New friendships gained; <unclear
					resp="MSPP">bring</unclear>
				<del>and</del>a new vitality &amp; sturdiness which ensures a
					<add>almost</add>certain victorious future.</p>
			<p>For this we are indebted to the loyalty &amp; devotion of our
				Board of Directors and also to the hard work &amp;capables
				direction &amp; management of our Presiding officer Miss R.J
				--</p>
			<p>To Europe to get <unclear resp="MSPP">rust</unclear> out of
				brain</p>
			<p>Internationalist -- Feminist <add>humanist</add>
			</p>
			<p>Ailments of Europe laid at the door of USA</p>
			<p>Women have the vote but -- not equality --</p>
			<p>Like to see emblazened in letters of gold over the doors of every
				legislature in this country -- She notes words of <person
					reg="Mill, John Stuart">J.S. Mill</person>. The triumph of
				Science, once the forces of nature, can never become the means
				of improving and Elevating Mankind until -- in addition to just
				institutions, the increase of Population shall be judiciously
				controlled"</p>
			<p><place reg="England, UK"> England</place>s acheivement -- home of
				BC last ten years</p>
			<p>
				<person reg="Besant, Annie">Besant</person> + <person
					reg="Bradlaugh, Charles">B.</person> trial 1878 theories
				advanced small groups idealists to educate -- not the masses --
				educated -- </p>
			<p>Successful-- differential birth rate -- upper classes --
				aritisans but birth rate down to 16 per 1000 death rate
					<supplied resp="MSPP">correspondingly</supplied> Mal League
				closed its doors in victory 50 years agitation. quality-- now
				the watchword </p>
			<p>22 B.C. Clinics -- private companies</p>
			<p>Infant-- maternity welfare centers govt support over 1000 </p>
			<p>Here reach B.C. population health &amp; Economic needs</p>
			<p>Govt approval --</p>
			<p><person reg="Buckmaster, Stanley">Lord Buckmaster</person>
				resolution House of Lords--</p>
			<p>Commons turned it down -- try again. <place>Australia</place>,
					<place>Canada</place>, first govt in world to endorse
				BC--</p>
			<p><place>France</place> looks to the past instead of future. 2
				million 50 yrs. Germany 28, Italy 16, -- birth rate higher than
				England. survivial lower -- ignored hygeine &amp; prophylaxis --
				driving up births <unclear resp="MSPP">enormously</unclear>--
				less attention to deaths. <place>Poland </place>-- 70,000 in one
				year 1926 -- Russians -- Greeks --</p>
			<p><place>Germany</place> -- no laws -- Drs problems -- devil &amp;
				deep sea</p>
			<p>Marriage advice Bureaus, 98% govt support -- <unclear resp="MSPP"
					>panic</unclear> extinction</p>
			<p>Dr. Rieses solution Ins. Co. kissed her hands -- tears</p>
			<p>Dr Grotjans claim -- I've had my three, now to <unclear
					resp="MSPP">buy them up</unclear></p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<p>
				<supplied resp="MSPP"/>
			</p>
			<p> It has long been hoped by some of us that a sound international
				population program might be advanced. We have seen that manuala
				broader bird’s eye view of the problem was necessary if it was
				to fit international and modern conditions. It was quite natural
				that the militarist should look upon the subject only with a
				view of armies; the demographer with the number of births,
				deaths, marriages in a given city, country over a given
				period.</p>
			<p>The anthropologist is concerned with the division into races
				within a population, especially in respect to their adaptability
				and the effect of social selection and colonization, while the
				economist, biologist and statistician--each expert in his own
				line--was bound to propose measures according to the limits of
				his inquiries; consequently, formidable errors were bound to
				arise when it came to practical issues.</p>
			<p>It was with this in mind that I went to <place>Europe</place> for
				the objects of bringing together scientists from various
				countries of different departments to correlate their views,
				experiments and programs, and to establish, if possible, a
				permanent organization for further studies and research along
				population lies.</p>
			<p>This <org
					reg="International Union for the Scientific Study of Population Problems"
					>Population Union</org> has now been launched and it is
				hoped that there will be a recognition through their studies of
				the fact that there can be no solution to the population problem
				without the recognition of the human factors which make this
				problem. I refer to the parents who produce populations--and
				especially the mothers who bear and rear the children.</p>
			<p>The intelligent thinkers in Europe, many with whom I had
				conversed, believe that the empty spaces on the globe are
				becoming rare; that populations are so increasing in every
				country that governments are at a loss to know how to deal with
				the problems arising therefrom; that Europe is today faced with
				a problem of having more men than bread, and this problem has
				become acute, because of the attitude of the <place
					reg="United States">United States</place>,
					<place>Australia</place> and <place>Canada</place> in their
				recent immigration legislation.</p>
			<p>It is now recognized that each country needs its own available
				food supply. Each country is guarding its own labor market,
				fearing unrest, unemployment and revolution. Soon every nation
				will reserve its potential resources for its own people, and
				already most of the European countries have overdrawn on their
				margin of self-sufficiency. <place>Germany</place>,
					<place>Italy</place>, <place>Poland</place> and all the
				central European countries should be encouraged to limit their
				population to their natural resources, but they are all dreaming
				of colonization, for colonization over seas was the solution of
				overpopulated Europe since the conquest of the Atlantic.</p>
			<p>There is no doubt that this has made civilization almost
				worldwide, and yet, there are doubts that this solution was of
				permanent value, for we now see that economic greed caused
				nations to overlook fundamental principles, and the future
				potentialities of nations have been sacrificed for immediate
				gain.</p>
			<p>Colonial expansion is still the dream of those militarists who
				clamor for big battalions of babies, and we see from the past
				that colonization has aroused a hatred of peaceful nations
				against the white race, and everywhere in <place>Asia</place> is
				the growing determination to free themselves from their
				political domination.</p>
			<p>Immigration legislation in the United States has caused much
				bitterness in Europe, for there is current a feeling that
				various nations have expended through generations much of their
				most valuable human material in order to furnish America with
				ready-made workmen--skilled in the arts and crafts--thereby
				impoverishing herself of valuable stocks, with the obvious
				results of creating a rival, today more powerful than all of
				Europe combined.</p>
			<p>America, on the other hand, considers that she has been
				overstocked with undesirable elements; that her dream of the
				melting-pot of assimilating the various races, colors, grades of
				mentalities through education by an American type of
				intelligence, has not succeeded. She now regrets her mistake,
				and has established a rigid system of immigration barriers for
				her own national and racial protection; and one can assume that
				from the <name type="law">Immigration Act of 1924</name>, the
					<org>United States Government</org> recognizes that there is
				a population problem in this country; that the resources of the
				land are limited; that unrestricted population increase through
				unrestricted immigration is bound to invite disaster to the
				social and racial life of the country. Consequently, a bar is
				raised to the free entrance of aliens into the United States,
				and even, when by the quota such aliens are given permission to
				enter the country, there are still social considerations to be
				grappled with.</p>
			<p>The government claims the right to exclude immigrants whose
				condition is likely to be a source of danger to the well-being
				and happiness of the country. Thus there are excluded all
				idiots, imbeciles, feeble-minded persons, epileptics, insane
				persons, persons of psychopathic inferiority, persons afflicted
				with tuberculosis in any form, or with any loathsome, dangerous
				or contagious disease, paupers, professional beggars, vagabonds,
				persons likely to become a public charge, polygamists,
				anarchists, criminals, prostitutes, or persons coming to U.S.
				for purposes of prostitution, or for any other immoral purpose.
				There are also provisions for the exclusion of illiterates, or
				of persons 16 years of age, physically capable of reading, but
				who cannot read English or some other language. All are refused
				admission into U.S.A. The procedure for the enforcement of these
				restrictive and selective measures is mandatory. Detailed
				regulations are laid down for the examination of these
				immigrants before entry, and for their deportation in case of
				exclusion.</p>
			<p>The government goes even further than this, for even after
				entrance the government reserves the right to pursue the policy
				of selection in such cases of criminals or those who have become
				a public charge--even five years after entry--are liable to
				deportation at any time.</p>
			<p>In no other immigration country is the restrictive policy carried
				out so far as in U.S.A. This rigid policy of the U.S. Government
				is the result of its short-sightedness in the past, for while
				this government never openly encouraged immigration, she took up
				a neutral attitude toward the question until 1914. She was much
				like the parents who--not really knowing what shall happen if
				their family continues to grow--nevertheless do nothing to
				prevent it. She now has had to adopt a negative, selective quota
				where she might have in the past adopted a positive, selective
				quota, and this country would today have been in a pos