<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc>
<mepHeader>
<prepDate>2001-08-21 MH</prepDate>
<prepDate>2001-09-05 CH</prepDate>
<prepDate>2002-08-09 CH</prepDate>
<prepDate>2002-08-15 KH</prepDate>
<prepDate>2014-03-04 CH correct regs</prepDate>
<prepDate>2014-11-13 CH clean regs</prepDate>
<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
<docDate value="1928-08">August 1928</docDate>
<docTitle>
<titlePart>The Need for Birth Control</titlePart>
</docTitle>
<idno>msp302115</idno>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl><title type="jouranl">Birth Control Review</title>, August 1928, pp. 227-228</bibl>
<bibl>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Collected Documents Series, C16:293.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
<respStmt>
<resp/>
<name id="DECL">Declaration of Independence</name>
<name id="ita">Italian</name>
</respStmt>
</mepHeader>
<sourceNote>For an earlier draft see LCM 130:0235, a duplicate version appears on
S71:0144.</sourceNote>
<headNote>
<index level1="Eugenics" level2="birth control and"/>
<index level1="population" level2="birth control and"/>
<index level1="birth control" level2="class-based"/>
<index level1="birth control" level2="health and"/>
<index level1="birth control" level2="socioeconomic benefits"/>
<index level1="child spacing"/>
</headNote>
<docBody>
<head>The Need for Birth Control</head>
<byline>
<emph rend="italics">BY</emph>
<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
</byline>
<p>THE population problem of the world is no longer a mere question of quantity. It involves quality
as well. Civilization can no longer be estimated by mere numbers. More important, from our modern
point of view, is the <emph rend="italics">kind</emph> of population a country or a century
produces. The <place reg="Florence, Italy">Florence</place> of the <foreign lang="ita" 
>Quattrocento</foreign> was, from the point of views of numbers, ridiculously underpopulated, but it
was rich in genius. On the other hand, the proportion of genius, of talent, of intelligence of
inhabitants to the total number in any of our great world-metropolises today is deplorably small.
Opponents of the Malthusian thesis may be right in their contention that the world is physically
able to support a far greater population than at present lives upon it. But any such rapid increase
of population would be maintained only by lowering the standard of living both physically and
spiritually. It is already evident that even under present conditions, the defective, delinquent and
dependent classes are multiplying with reckless irresponsibility and at an ever-increasing expense
to society at large. Leaving aside, as purely hypothetical and academic, all such questions as the
ultimate saturation point in world population, and attacking this problem in its immediate and
imperatively pressing aspects, we find ourselves here and now confronted with a tangibly definite
qualitative overpopulation. Any intelligent analyst must admit that tody there are too many of the
wrong kind of people in our world, and too few of the right kind. Even the most compassionate and
least snobbish of observers must admit this.</p>
<p>EDUCATION in Birth Control offers an immediate, practical and constructive method of combating
this qualitative over-population. It is not proffered as a wholesale magic panacea which would cure
the evils of the world overnight. It is immediate and practical because it can be taught--indeed, it
is already taught--to the individuals involved without prohibiting their enjoyment of live, without
interrupting "<q who="DECL">life, liberty and the pursuit of happiness.</q>" It is constructive in
its immediate and in its ultimate benefits. It is constructive from the educational point of view
because it stimulates habits of intelligent self-direction and control, gives parents the autonomous
conduct of their own lives, and awakens a sense of their responsibility in bringing children into
the world. It is, moreover, based upon a recognition of the vast amount of native and latent
intelligence among the mothers and fathers of the poor and upon the conviction that this
intelligence can be awakened and formed into an efficient instrument to control and eventually to
eliminate that dysgenic tendency in modern societies whereby the elements least fit to reproduce and
multiply do actually perpetuate themselves into a predominating and overwhelming class. Birth
Control is of inestimable value not only to the individual parents; but its popularization would
enable us to draw a definite line between the worthy, intelligent and self-respecting types of
parenthood among the poorer classes and delinquent and irresponsible. Until this dividing line is
definitely established, it will be impossible for society to establish any definite, just,
constructive and yet withal self-protective policy in its dealing with the complex problems of the
criminal, mental defective and feeble-minded classes. Sterilization will undoubtedly become a
necessity; but unsupported by the practice of self-directive Birth Control a policy of arbitrary
sterilization could not without in justice be imposed upon the people at large.</p>
<p>THE first great need of modern society is the encouragement of Birth Control education among
potential parents of those poorer strata of society where poverty is correlated with disease, poor
health, and physical or mental defect. It goes without saying that, first of all, parenthood should
be forbidden to the insane, the feeble-minded, the epileptic and to all those suffering from
transmissible diseases. Modern methods of sterilization make this possible without the infliction of
undue hardships or unhappiness.</p>
<p>Women who are suffering from such maladies as tuberculosis, cardiac, kidney or other diseases
which are aggravated by pregnancy and which make recovery impossible should not jeopardize their
lives and those of possible infants by undergoing this risk until a cure is effected. When defective
children are born of apparently normal adults the later should refrain from further experiments in
parenthood.</p>
<p>Birth Control makes possible the "spacing" of children. Each new infant can thus be given a
proper start in life, physically and psychically, before a new arrival takes central place in the
mother's care and attention. This system is of equal benefit to both mothers and children.</p>
<p>FINANCIAL, economic and social conditions cannot be lightly swept aside as unimportant,
especially in the first years of marriage. These conditions should be courageously analysed by young
husbands and wives, particularly in relation to the potential child or family. Surely it is
injustice to an infant to be brought into a home that cannot provide necessities for a proper start
in life. Even when these factors seem satisfactory, it is well that young wives who have just been
released by marriage from the arduous labors of shops, factories, or any industrial or workaday
employment, should have a year for rest and readjustment to the new duties of wifehood. It is a
brief enough period for any young women before she plunges into the physiological strain of
maternity. Mentally and physically she must be prepared for the long complex process of
gestation.</p>
<p>Maternal and infant welfare centers would immeasurably increase their efficiency were they so
inaugurate their ministrations, not merely with so-called pre-natal or ante-natal care, but with the
education of young women from their maturity in the duties and responsibility of maternity. Maternal
education begins with marital education, with the assurance of physical strength and emotional
stability. It is just here that the Birth Control clinic, given adequate support and encouragement,
might demonstrate its efficacy as a social agency. Yet the clinic need not attempt to supplant those
social welfare agencies already existent. With little inconvenience or expense the latter might
enlarge their scope to include this specific educational work. Ultimately such work would relieve
the State from the expense of maintaining institutions for the delinquent and dependent, from the
deadweight--the unproductive deadweight--of its dysgenic classes upon generations yet unborn, and
would result in the creation of a self-directive instrument of population-control.</p>
<trailer>This article appeared in <title type="journal">Time and Tide</title> (<place
reg="London, England">London</place>), June 8, 1928.</trailer>
</docBody>
</doc>
