<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "file:/S:/TRANSCRIPTIONS/XML%20Drafts/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2003/06/10 SB</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/23 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007/06/27 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/08/30 EK</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-26 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-12-03 EK Correct Proofreading</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1917-01-00">Jan 1917</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Portet and Ferrer, continued</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp302120</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journaL">The Modern School</title>, Jan. 1917, 157-160</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm: Collected Documents</title>, C16:100</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="PORLO">Portet, Lorenzo</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
            <name id="FRA">French</name>
            <name id="SPA">Spanish</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>This is the second of a three part series. For the first article see "<title
                type="article">Portet and Ferrer</title>" <xref from="302119.xml">Dec. 1916</xref>;
            for final article see "<title type="article">Portet and Ferrer</title>" <xref
                from="302090.xml">Feb. 1917.</xref> For a draft version see LCM 13:366.</p>
        <index level1="Modern School movement" level2="in Spain"/>
        <index level1="Spain" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="Ferrer, Francisco"/>
        <index level1="Portet, Lorenzo" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="Spain" level2="radicals in"/>
        <index level1="Spain" level2="political conditions in"/>
        <index level1="labor movement" level2="strikes"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>PORTET AND FERRER, continued</head>
        <p>This was a picnic of all the Rationalistic Modern and Lay schools together on Good
            Friday, when the picnickers defied the laws of Church and God by not only eating meat,
            but fish with the meat, which seems to be the most outrageous infraction. This called
            the attention of the clericals to the <org>Modern School</org>s and for the next few
            years. until 1916, the vigilant eye of the <org reg="Roman Catholic Church">Church</org>
            was waiting patiently for an opportunity to close them.</p>
        <p>This came when, at the wedding procession of the <person reg="Alphonso XIII (Spain)">King
                of <place>Spain</place></person> from the Church to the Palace, an attempt was made
            by <person reg="Morral, Mateo">Mateo Morral,</person> who threw a bomb from a window.
            Several people were killed. The <person reg="Eugenia (Spain)">Queen</person>'s wedding
            dress was in places drenched in blood, but she and King Alphonso escaped. Young Morral,
            who was a well educated man of wealthy middle-class parents, had become interested in
            libertarian education and had taken his younger sister to attend school, under <person
                reg="Ferrer, Francisco">Ferrer's</person> direction in the <org>Modern School</org>.
            Morral had often assisted at some of the evening work at the school, and this fact now
            drew the power of the <org reg="Spanish Government">Government</org> down upon Ferrer
            and the Modern School.</p>
        <p>Ferrer was arrested as an accomplice of Morral (in 1906), all the schools were closed,
            and the teachings greatly maligned by the clericals. During these years <person
                reg="Portet, Lorenzo">Portet</person> and Ferrer had seen much of each other and had
            become close friends. Portet lived with his family in <place>England</place>, but made
            several trips to <place reg="Barcelona, Spain">Barcelona</place>, where he and Ferrer
            consulted together over the advancement of the schools, books, translations, etc.</p>
        <p>Upon receiving the news of Ferrer's arrest, Portet and friends again started an agitation
            to protest against Ferrer's arrest. In <place>France</place>, <place>Belgium</place> and
                <place>Italy</place>, where both men were known, the agitation was widespread, and
            continued until Ferrer was released by a Civil Court (which differed from the Military
            Court of his second trial).</p>
        <p>One year later nearly all the schools were opened again. Books had been examined and
            passed upon though at the second trial these same books were considered "criminal". All
            the secular and rational schools continued with their work, but the Modern School could
            not open its doors without special permission from the Church. Ferrer would not ask it.
            He consulted together with his friends, and the workers who had established the
                <org>Rationalist Schools,</org> upon the best plans to pursue. He decided to publish
            advanced textbooks and advanced educational books, of which there were almost none in
            Spain, and accordingly opened the publishing house in Barcelona, of which Lorenzo Portet
            has so fittingly said: "<q>Ferrer opened a school for all Spain when the <foreign
                    lang="SPA">Escuela Moderna</foreign> of Barcelona was closed</q>".</p>
        <p>Ferrer left the publishing house in the hands of capable men, and went to <place
                reg="Paris, France">Paris</place> to seek good and fitting literature for
            translations. He published a monthly magazine in Paris, "<title type="journal"><foreign
                    lang="FRA">L'Ecole Renovee</foreign></title>" and tried to convince the French
            Syndicalists of the necessity for schools where their children should be taught
            clear-cut ideas, against the poison of patriotism, capitalism, etc.</p>
        <p>Ferrer had become well known through his first trial and had now many friends who were in
            sympathy with his revolutionary ideas regarding education. Among these was <person
                reg="Reclus, Elisee">Elisee Reclus</person>, the well-known author of "<title
                type="book">Man and the Earth</title>", and numerous others prominent in French
            educational circles. During these years he was active in France and
                <place>England</place>, gathering the best known books and selecting them for
            publication.</p>
        <p>Then came the last trip to England in 1909, and the hurried call to Barcelona on the
            death of his brother's child, who lived with him on his farm called <foreign lang="SPA"
                >"Mas Germinal"</foreign>. He arrived in Barcelona when the <place>Morocco</place>
            affair was in full blast. The reserves had been asked for in Morocco of the Spanish
            troops.</p>
        <p>Many of these were poor married workers, and those with money could buy a poorer one to
            be sent in his place. This war was not popular in Spain even with those who had but few
            ideas. Barcelona took the initiative to protest against the war, by calling a general
            strike on July 24. This was not difficult to do, for the storm of indignation and
            protest had been gathering; so on Monday morning the demonstration, led by women,
            compelled the workers in the factories, workshops, stores,--everyone who was a wage
            earner--to come out on strike. The whole city of Barcelona was on strike and the workers
            were masters of the city for four days. The strike spread to all the provinces. The
            strikers formed themselves into groups to carry out different parts of a general plan
            for a republic. Convents and Churches to the number of 53 were set on fire after warning
            had been given to the occupants to get out.</p>
        <p>Many priests barricaded themselves within and shot at the people through the windows.
            Streets were barricaded and cannon set ready for use. Troops were called, of whom many
            had refused to shoot the strikers, and on several occasions when the priests witnessed
            this, they themselves shot the soldiers in order to enrage them against the strikers.
            The workers attacked all the places where arms and ammunitions were sold or stored and
            prepared themselves for attack. <org reg="Spanish Civil Guard">The Civil Guard</org>
            were the fiercest in their attacks on the workers as there were few soldiers left in
            Barcelona.</p>
        <p>Over on hundred of the Civil Guard were killed, while the whole city, with convents and
            churches burning, continued in revolt for nearly a week. Then two regiments were sent to
            quell the revolt; they succeeded, by arresting two thousand people in Barcelona, and
            proclaiming martial law.</p>
        <p>When I asked several comrades the cause of their failure to establish a republic when
            almost everything was in their favor to do so, the reply came:</p>
        <p>"<q>The one mistake in Barcelona was the revolutionists failed to capture the banks and
                take as hostages about fifty of the principal citizens of the city.</q>"</p>
        <p>This, together with a sad lack of personal direction, no doubt contributed to the failure
            of the revolt. By the end of the week all was quiet in Barcelona, every person known or
            suspected of advanced ideas was arrested. Several escaped across the frontier into
            France.</p>
        <p>Ferrer, unfortunately, had not been particularly active in this revolt on account of the
            illness and recent death in his home, so that he made no attempt to escape. It was not
            until he read that the revolt had been instigated by him that he knew he was in danger.
            A few days after, his house was surrounded by Civil guards night and day. There was now
            no time to escape. He, however, was able to be in hiding in his house, and although the
            guards searched and spent days in searching in every crevice and corner of the house,
            taking up parts of the floor, removing parts of the walls, and ceilings,--everywhere
            they looked, but did not discover him.</p>
        <p>In Barcelona and the Provinces all papers were suppressed, except those authorised by the
            Government. The schools closed, trade-unions dissolved. All clubs and places of social
            interest closed. Only the clericals and clerical press had full sway.</p>
        <byline><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">MARGARET H. SANGER</person>.</byline>
        <trailer>To be continued</trailer>
    </docBody>
</doc>
