<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2002-08-08 KH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2002-08-09 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2002-08-15 KH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2003/08/14 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/08/09 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/08/13 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2001/03/11 CH Entered corrections suggested by Andy Carloff.</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-11-12 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011-11-21 CH typo</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1929-05-26">26 May 1929</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Shall the Citizens of Boston be Allowed to Discuss Changing Their
                Laws?</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp302511</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Clarence R. Skinner, Ed.,<title type="book">A Free Pulpit in Action</title>, New
                York: 1931, 172-85</bibl>
            <bibl><title>MSM</title>C16:0351</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="SKICL">Skinner, Clarence R.</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
        <p>Sanger gave this speech at the <place reg="Boston, MA">Boston</place>
            <org reg="Community Church of Boston">Community Church</org>, along with <person
                reg="Skinner, Clarence Russell">Clarence R. Skinner</person>. In the transcript of
            the question and answer session following the speech, questions not addressed to <person
                reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person> have been omitted. For a similar
            version see LCM 130:226.</p>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="autobiographical"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="propaganda and publicity"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="hospitals and"/>
        <index level1="physicians" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="state"
            level4="New York (1145 Penal Code)"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits and risks"/>
        <index level1="child spacing"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
        <index level1="Catholic Church"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="opposition to"/>
        <index level1="Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau" level2="raid of"/>
        <index level1="Europe" level2="birth control clinics and leagues"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head rend="italics">Address by Mrs. Sanger</head>
        <div>
            <p>It was <person reg="Hugo, Victor">Victor Hugo</person> who said that there is no
                force in the world so great as that of an idea whose hour has struck. I believe that
                the hour for birth control has struck, because there is no other question that has
                so large a practical significance, which, it seems to me, cuts so deeply into the
                foundations of social evolution. There is no other question of equal importance that
                has been left so long in obscurity, and yet I think it is safe to say that there is
                no other question that has so dramatically arisen upon our horizon of national and
                international interest as this subject has within the past ten years. Ten years ago
                it was a Federal offense to discuss the merits of birth control, and to write or to
                print that discussion and to send it through the <place>United States
                </place>mails.</p>
            <p>This battle for free discussion of birth control has had far better success in its
                being fought out in the courts rather than in the legislatures. <person
                    reg="Shaw, George Bernard">George Bernard Shaw</person> says that this idea is
                the most revolutionary of the twentieth century; <person reg="Wells, H.G.">H. G.
                    Wells</person> says that it is the most momentous fact of modern life, and he is
                inclined to believe that birth control is the intelligence test of modern life.</p>
            <p>I believe that this is a very fitting place--in a church--to stand for the right to
                discuss this great subject. I also believe that with the change of opinion, with the
                education that is constantly going on in this country, we may yet see the same thing
                happen that happened to me in <place reg="Los Angeles, CA">Los Angeles</place> a few
                months ago. I went there to speak, and was met at the station by a large group of
                camera and newspaper and moving picture men, and also accompanying this group was a
                group of policewomen. This was not altogether new in my experience, but to my great
                amazement and surprise one of the policewomen stepped forward and said: "<q
                    who="UNK">We, policewomen of Los Angeles, extend to you a hearty welcome.</q>"
                That was a new experience in this long, interesting battle for the right to discuss
                the merits of birth control. I was not quite sure whether that welcome was the
                spirit of <place>California</place> or whether it was the gentle influence of the
                women in the police department. </p>
            <p>But I arrived back in <place reg="New York, NY">New York</place> and went to work in
                the <org reg="Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau">Research Bureau</org>
                pondering over this great manifestation of intelligence and hospitality. Soon my
                mind was put at rest, because about four weeks ago, while we were quietly attending
                to the hundreds of poor, wretched, spiritless women who come to our birth control
                clinic, we were invaded by seven policemen and two policewomen, who came into our
                clinic and arrested two of our doctors and three of our nurses. I began to realize
                that it was not the gentle spirit of the policewomen in the department of
                California. One of the policewomen had come to us as a decoy patient and said that
                she was the mother of three children. She was given information, she was treated as
                all patients are treated, kindly, considerately, and went through the usual routine.
                She came back again to discuss the merits of the subject in its practical aspect in
                her particular case, and was again given certain consideration, and then on the
                third visit she brought her friends, the policewomen and seven policemen.</p>
            <p>The doctors were herded into the usual Black Maria, taken to the police station, and
                treated as common, ordinary lawbreakers, and were about to be finger printed when
                some of us, knowing something about the offense, stopped that process.</p>
            <p>A very great piece of good fortune happened at this time. The policewoman who was
                conducting the raid did not really know the law herself, and she began to go through
                the files, our medical records, and helped herself right and left to one hundred and
                fifty cards that seemed to be easiest for her to take and several other very
                important histories. The Irish say that it is a poor wind that does not blow good
                for some one, and this certainly was the wind that blew good for us, because she, in
                taking these records, attacked and invaded the most precious rights of the medical
                profession, and this aroused the indignation of the medical men and women of New
                York. A mass meeting was held; the doctors came to testify in our behalf; and I do
                not know of any time in the past fifteen years when there has been such indignation
                and such an aroused interest as this police raid aroused in New York City among all
                sections of the community--in clubs, women's organizations, men's clubs in Wall
                Street, churches. Medical meetings were held, protest meetings, and without
                qualification the expressed indignation was sent to the <org
                    reg="New York City Police Department">Police Department</org>, with the result
                that <person>Grover N. Whalen</person>, the Police Commissioner, apologized to the
                    <org reg="New York Academy of Medicine">Academy of Medicine</org>, and as a
                gesture for good behavior in the future, he demoted the policewoman who conducted
                the raid. But even better than that, doctors of such distinction of <person
                    reg="Kennedy, Foster">Foster Kennedy</person>, the neurologist, and <person
                    reg="Haddon, Frederick">Frederick Haddon</person>, and Ex-Chief Commissioner of
                Health, <person reg="Harris, Louis">Louis Harris</person>, took the witness stand
                and testified to our right to establish and run this birth control clinic; and not
                only that, but they testified that a woman had a right to knowledge of birth
                control, not only for the cure or prevention of disease but also to space the births
                in her family. By that testimony of these experts we won more in that great decision
                than we would win fighting in the legislature. Our case was dismissed by the
                magistrate. It was impossible for them to do otherwise, by the opinion that was so
                marvelously expressed in every avenue of thought, liberty and freedom in New York
                City.</p>
            <p>Now, the laws in this country are peculiar. In <place>New York </place> State we have
                two laws, first Section 1142, which, like your law in <place>Massachusetts</place>,
                states that no one can give to anyone information to prevent conception. But some
                one in New York was a little wiser in making laws than you in Massachusetts, and
                they made another law offsetting the severity of Section 1142, and Section 1145
                states that any physician lawfully practicing can give such advice to patients for
                the cure or prevention of disease. That law was put on the books just a little later
                than Section 1142, but in all my nursing experience I never found any doctor who
                interpreted it for himself. To test out this law I had two women, one with a severe
                transmissible disease, taken to every hospital and dispensary in New York and <place
                    reg="Brooklyn, NY">Brooklyn</place>, and with the exception of one hospital,
                they were refused advice. They were told that they could come back and be treated
                for their various ailments, and that in case of pregnancy, there might be an
                interruption to save their lives, but so far as birth control advice was concerned,
                this was a Sing Sing offense and they could not give it. That was a challenge for
                me, for some one in the community to test out that law; and I, in 1916, opened a
                clinic in a very overcrowded section of Brooklyn. I could not get a doctor to help,
                but got some nurses, and together we announced that we were going to give all
                married women advice in regard to conception; we were going to challenge the
                constitutionality of that law.</p>
            <p>We were all arrested and spent one month in jail, but we carried that case to the
                highest courts, and in that conviction and testing out this law we received from the
                Court of Appeals a decision that the conviction was sustained because I was not a
                physician, but that any physician lawfully practicing in New York State had a right
                to give contraceptive advice under Section 1145; and then there was a labored
                interpretation and definition of the word "disease." In fact, I think instead of
                going to a medical dictionary the court went to Webster's, and they got a definition
                of disease which was broader.</p>
            <p> When we got that decision it was time to act, and we opened another clinic in 1923.
                We had a physician in charge. We took only cases for the prevention or cure of
                disease as interpreted by the court, and we went on increasing our nurses and staff
                until a few weeks ago. We had been investigated by the Academy of Medicine, by the
                    <org reg="New York State Board of Charities">State Board of Charities</org>, and
                the <org reg="New York City Board of Health">City Board of Health</org> and found
                running in good order and according to the laws, so that you can imagine our
                surprise and dismay to have the police officials come in there to try to break up
                this work. I refuse to accept that the police department are the authorities to
                investigate a medical organization that is conducted by the medical profession.</p>
            <p>You in Massachusetts have a law even more vicious than that in New York State,
                because after all there is a little leeway to our law. The physicians in this state
                cannot give advice even for transmissible disease, even when the woman is suffering
                from tuberculosis or heart disease, in which we know that a pregnancy endangers and
                threatens her life. The best the physician can do is to interrupt her pregnancy and
                send her back home with a death sentence hanging over her head.</p>
            <p>That is what you are standing for in Massachusetts to-day, and the hands of the
                medical profession are tied. They are not here to challenge laws, they are here to
                obey the laws. It is for us as citizens to see that the laws are changed so that
                they shall have full freedom in doing their work.</p>
            <p>In respect to this law Massachusetts is the blackest state in the Union. I believe
                that all it takes in this state is a handful of courageous citizens to stand behind
                a birth control clinic. Get your doctor, if he wants to be a martyr, to interpret
                the law from a medical point of view to stand behind this group, and take it to the
                highest court, not only in this state but of the United States; and I am perfectly
                positive as I stand here to-day that you will win, because that is the force of a
                right idea whose hour was struck. You can no longer deny to a doctor his right to
                save a woman's life, and information to prevent conception will do that.</p>
            <p>In our organization of this clinical research bureau we have had over 13,000 women
                who have come to us within this period of time. We have more women who come to us
                to-day than we can possibly take care of. We have the charity associations, the
                social organizations, doctors and nurses who send to us women who should be taken
                care of and should be instructed and advised, and we take them. In fact, if we had
                ten clinics in New York City to-day they would be filled, and to me that is the
                marvelous part of this movement to-day. It is not a movement like others in which
                you must inject the idea into the minds of the public. This is a movement that is
                far ahead of the organization to administer to it. Women everywhere in the poor
                walks of life are asking, begging for information to free them from excessive child
                bearing; they are asking doctors, midwives, nurses, for advice.</p>
            <p>In our federal law we also have a law (Section 211) which will not allow anyone, not
                even a doctor, to send information through the mails, even to another doctor. He
                cannot send a book, a pamphlet, anything written or printed, or any material or
                article designed to prevent conception. And worst of all, we cannot tell you in case
                there was a clinic or a physician in this stat where it might be legal to have
                information, the federal law will make it a crime, with five years' imprisonment to
                tell you to go to that doctor or give his name. So we have two things to do, first,
                change your state law, and then clear up this federal law, which also is injurious
                to the proper functioning of the medical profession.</p>
            <p>Not long ago one of our contributors had deducted his contribution from his income
                tax. It was challenged by the government which claimed that he had supported an
                illegal organization. As we were incorporated under the laws of New York State, it
                was rather a surprise to say that we were illegal, and we were shown a letter which
                I had written to a woman in <place reg="Baltimore, MD">Baltimore</place> telling her
                to go to <org reg="Johns Hopkins University Medical School">Johns Hopkins Medical
                    Department</org> where we know physicians do give advice on birth control. It
                was perfectly legal for the doctor of the state of <place>Maryland</place> to give
                her advice, but it was illegal for me under the federal law to tell her to go to
                that hospital and doctor.</p>
            <p>We have found in our clinic and in the work we are doing there that it is no longer a
                question of what birth control is going to do. We know what it will do. We know what
                it has done in the past five years. We know that it is able and that it is reducing
                infant and maternal mortality. We have thousands of these women who have come to us
                as a last chance to save their lives, to whom their physicians have said, "<q
                    who="UNK">One more pregnancy and I cannot be responsible for your life.</q>" And
                these women are living to-day, and their health is improving; they are living to
                bring up their three or four children better. Homes have been made happier. We have
                seen the good results of birth control. We proclaim that in the first place, any
                many or woman suffering from a transmissible disease, such as syphilis, insanity, or
                feeble-mindedness, such a couple should not have children. We further say that any
                mother or woman suffering from heart disease, tuberculosis, etc., should not become
                a mother until her disease is cured. Third, we say that those parents who already
                have subnormal children should not have more children. We further say that women
                should have information to prevent conception in order to space the births of the
                children, that there should be at least two years, and three years is even better in
                many cases, to give the woman a chance to recuperate, to regain her health and
                strength after the ordeal of the birth, to give her a chance to enjoy her motherhood
                and to prepare for the next one.</p>
            <p>Further than that we cannot go. But I maintain that we must change our laws and
                public opinion so that we may go further, and so that any man or woman who is unable
                to support two children should not be allowed to have nine or ten. We further say
                that a young couple starting out their life together in marriage with happiness and
                hopes of adventure, should not take upon themselves the responsibility of parenthood
                until they have adjusted their married lives first. We want them to have a year or
                two just to get acquainted, just to know each other, and after all it is not so easy
                adjusting themselves in this day. It is a great responsibility, and love is one of
                those tender plants that has to be nurtured, has to be given sunshine and health in
                order to strengthen it to grow. What chance have we to strengthen the bonds of
                marriage when a young couple starts out so gayly and joyously in marriage and finds
                itself in the condition of parenthood before they have adjusted their lives.</p>
            <p>We have never given womanhood a chance. We have given motherhood too many burdens;
                and I claim it is time for us to speak up for womanhood and to make womanhood
                something lovely and have it precede motherhood. Womanhood has its best possibility
                for growth and happiness after marriage. You find a young girl going from girlhood
                into motherhood without any chance to prepare for motherhood by blossoming out to
                fulfill her destiny as a mother. Birth control is going to make for happier lives,
                better lives and better marriages, when women have a chance to adjust themselves to
                the husband, to the man they love; when there is a chance to think, prepare, enjoy,
                to build up the cultural side of their lives. When children are coming to them by
                choice, plan, and not by accident, we find that women not only have their first and
                second child, but their third and fourth child, and enjoy each one of them in the
                process. That is what we want in the future. We want children to be conceived in
                love, born of the parents' conscious desire, and given the heritage of sound bodies
                and minds. We further want the young to look upon their bodies as holy temples and
                to make these bodies fit and perfect instruments of the soul, to take their part in
                the mysteries of material being.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head>FORUM</head>
            <p>Q. (Mrs. Sanger.) <q who="UNK">Tell us something about some of the European countries
                    which have sanctioned birth control, and the results, especially in <place
                        reg="Netherlands">Holland</place>.</q></p>
            <p>A. In Europe to-day there are only two countries, <place>France</place> and
                    <place>Italy</place>, in which information of birth control cannot be given.
                    <place>England</place> is making tremendous strides. There are already
                twenty-six clinics there, and a fight is going on to have the government allow
                information to be given at the maternal centers. The House of Lords went on record
                with a resolution asking the government to have this happen. Holland is perhaps the
                inspiration of us all in this movement. Up to 1914 there was the lowest infant
                mortality in the three cities where this was going on, <place
                    reg="Amsterdam, Netherlands">Amsterdam</place>, <place
                    reg="Rotterdam, Netherlands">Rotterdam</place> and <place
                    reg="The Hague, Netherlands">the Hague</place>. There was a decreasing birth
                rate. There was the highest standard of education for children; there was less
                prostitution, and especially with the native inhabitants, of any country in
                    <place>Europe</place>. I cannot say what has happened since 1914. Holland is a
                splendid example of what birth control will do when it is properly organized and
                directed.</p>
            <p>Q. <q who="UNK">What has the birth control group done to influence physicians to
                    protect these clinics, and also to bring pressure upon legislators?</q></p>
            <p>A. The best that we could do was to find a physician who was courageous enough to
                give us two years of his time to go out into the country to address medical
                societies. That is the way we have been able to get the medical profession and
                societies to have some understanding of what we are trying to do, and I think we are
                succeeding.</p>
            <p> Q. <q who="UNK">What do you find to be the greatest secret source of opposition to
                    your work?</q></p>
            <p>A. I should say that ignorance was the greatest secret force, but I should say that
                the Roman Catholic Church was the greatest outward, open force opposed to the birth
                control movement.</p>
            <p>Q. <q who="UNK">Can you tell us the information in the pamphlets which were being
                    sold in New York City in the streets in February?</q></p>
            <p>A. I do not know about any pamphlets which were sold in February. I know that there
                is the <title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title> which is a magazine which
                is sold at the Grand Central Station and at Thirty-fourth and Thirty-fifth Street.
                That is a monthly magazine, perfectly proper, with mailing privileges in the United
                States post office.</p>
            <p>Q. <q who="UNK">If the law be not enforced, will not the unmarried mother take
                    advantage of that law?</q></p>
            <p>A. In our experience we have had some unmarried mothers come to us, but they have
                come to be placed where they could take care of their babies. So far as unmarried
                women coming to us, we have had a few, perhaps a very small percentage, when they
                have had a condition of health which would not justify their marriage or pregnancy
                after marriage. In all of these cases we ask them to bring a letter from their
                physicians. In many cases the mothers have come with them, and said, "<q who="UNK"
                    >If you give her this treatment we will sanction the marriage.</q>" I believe
                that if birth control clinics are established and properly run it will do away with
                a great deal of immorality, because it is going to allow young people to be married
                earlier and to take their time to have children. It will be a factor for morality
                and not immorality.</p>
            <p>Q.<q who="UNK"> Do you know the size of the families of legislators and judges who
                    oppose this law?</q></p>
            <p>A. At one time we did take a poll of their families and we found there was a certain
                percentage of them who were bachelors, and that not over two had more than five
                children, the others had small families.</p>
            <p>Q. <q who="UNK">Why can't the state take charge of the larger families in the case of
                    poorer people?</q></p>
            <p>A. The state is already doing that, as well as private charities and philanthropic
                societies. That is what we do not want.</p>
            <p>Q.<q who="UNK"> If birth control was practiced many years ago, might not society have
                    been deprived of great individuals, such as <person reg="Lincoln, Abraham"
                        >Lincoln</person>, <person reg="Washington, George">Washington</person>, and
                    others?</q></p>
            <p>A. It is difficult to say, but assuming that we might have been deprived of these
                great individuals, I think we might also have been deprived of a large group of
                imbeciles, feeble-minded, and general mental incompetents, and we probably would
                have more great individuals because they would have had a chance to develop their
                individuality.</p>
            <p> Q.<q who="UNK"> How much cooperation do you receive from the Protestant
                clergy?</q></p>
            <p> A. As individuals, I think a great deal. Beginning with <person
                    reg="Inge, William Ralph">Dean Inge</person> of <org>St. Paul's Cathedral</org>,
                they have never ceased to stand behind and with us. In the <org>Episcopal
                    Church</org> there has been a fine support, not officially, but from
                individuals, and also from the Methodists and various others. So far as the
                Unitarians are concerned, we have had it from the beginning.</p>
            <p>Q. <q>Does not the <org reg="Roman Catholic Church">Catholic Church</org> confuse
                    abortion with conception?</q></p>
            <p>A. I was under that impression for a long time, but I had it from Cardinal <person
                    reg="Hayes, Patrick J.">Hayes</person> that they did not. I had a statement
                which was printed in the <title type="journal">New York Times</title> that Cardinal
                Hayes said that the Catholic Church did not confuse abortion with conception, that
                it understood well what the birth control movement was trying to do, and that it
                preferred abortion to birth control, because the soul that is aborted has started
                its journey to life and is sent back, while the prevention of conception denies that
                soul the right to start life and is a mortal sin; and it is the right and duty of
                all of us to make it possible for souls to have the glory of God in Heaven, etc. I
                asked Cardinal Hayes the question: why then he was living a celibate life and was
                not doing his duty.</p>
            <p>Q. <q who="UNK">Don't you think that the hidden hand that instigated the raid on your
                    clinic will not lie quiet but will continue trying to break up your
                work?</q></p>
            <p>A. It is very possible they will try it, but we are going to be very alert.</p>
            <p>Q. <q who="UNK">Will you tell us the physician of <place>Massachusetts</place> who
                    was courageous enough to go about talking on birth control?</q></p>
            <p>A. Dr. <person reg="Cooper, James F.">James F. Cooper</person>.</p>
            <p>Q. <q who="UNK">In your program, would you place restrictions on the productivity of
                    men and women who were perfectly normal and where there was no handicap to the
                    woman having as many children as she pleased?</q></p>
            <p>A. In regard to a perfectly healthy couple that has adequate means, I would certainly
                place no restrictions on them. It is a question of what the individuals desire.
                There is no compulsion on our part where people are able to maintain the children
                they bring into the world.</p>
            <p>Q.<emph rend="italics"> (Mrs. Sanger.) </emph><q who="UNK">Doesn't our government
                    know that birth control has been practiced for centuries, and if physicians
                    would wake up couldn't they control the laws better in regard to it?</q></p>
            <p>A. I had not known that it had been practiced for centuries. There have been
                infanticide, abortion, etc., but I had not known that the same kind of birth control
                that we practice has been practiced for centuries.</p>
            <p>Q. <emph rend="italics">(Mrs. Sanger.) </emph><q who="UNK">Is it true that Dr. Cooper
                    gave birth control information in Boston?</q></p>
            <p>A. <emph rend="italics">(By Mr. Skinner.)</emph>
                <q who="SKICL">He said the other night that he had brought some fifteen hundred
                    children of the North End into the world, and that it was there that he gained
                    interest in the question of birth control. I do not know whether he has given
                    definite information in clinics or in his private practice. I can not answer
                    that personally.</q></p>
            <p><emph rend="italics">(By Mrs. Sanger.)</emph> I know he did in his private practice,
                because in one of the medical societies in <place reg="Chicago, IL">Chicago</place>
                he brought some one hundred or one hundred and fifty cases he had followed. </p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
