<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Publushed article ">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-04-15 JK initial tag</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1938-/--/-/--/ ">1938</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Forward to Laws Relating to Birth Control in the United
                States and its Territories</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp302933</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">"Forward to Laws Relating to Birth
                    Control in the United States and its Territories</title>
                <title type="book">Laws relating to Birth Control, New York;
                    BCCRB,</title> 1938.</bibl>
            <bibl><title>LCM C16:422</title></bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/><index
            level1="motherhood"/><index level1="birth control"
            level2="distribution of information about"/><index
            level1="birth control movement" level2="MS on"/><index
            level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Federal"/><index
            level1="Comstock Laws"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Foreward</head>

        <p>Only those among us who have had intimate contact for years with the
            problems of women who want, need, and cannot get authentic
            information on birth control can realize the misery that has
            resulted from the passage of the so-called <person
                    reg="Comstock, Anthony">Comstock</person>
                <org reg="Government of the United States">Federal</org>
                laws and the state laws patterned on them. They have
            intimidated physicians; they have made the study of methods in
            medical schools difficult; they have hampered research; they have
            made public notification of clinical service illegal; they have
            forbidden general dissemination of information on methods, even when
            written by doctors; they have prevented untold numbers of mothers
            from obtaining scientific information on family limitation and
            driven them to quacks and abortionists; and they have been
            responsible for flooding the nation with unwanted children many of
            whom are a burden to both their parents and the community. </p>
        <p>The passage of the Federal laws classing contraception with obscenity
            will forever remain a dark chapter in the annals of American
            history. These laws have done more to prolong the suffering and
            slavery of women than any other single factor. Owing to these laws
            we have the appalling spectacle of the death of thousands of women
            from abortions. Could we but view the accumulated damage in human
            misery since these statutes went into effect it would put to shame
            even the most callous of our opponents. In fact it would make
            “countless thousands mourn.”</p>
        <p> It is after all the mothers of the nation who have suffered most
            from these laws; it is the mothers who have staggered under their
            inhumane mandate. it is they who have paid in the sacrifice of their
            own lives, in the high infant death rate, in the multiplication of
            the feebleminded and the unfit. They have paid for it in the fact of
            poverty, in the fact of unemployment, in hopelessness and despair.
            We are paying for it in the ever increasing burden of taxes as well
            ass in the deterioration of our national stamina and of the race. </p>
        <p>As we read these statutes and realize how carefully their framers
            thought out ways and means to block any knowledge of the prevention
            of conception, we are more than ever grateful to the Justices of the
                <org reg="United States Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit"
                >Circuit Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit</org> whose
            sane and liberal interpretation of the Federal law in 1936 now makes
            it possible to incorporate birth control in programs of public
            health and preventive medicine in almost every state in the <place
                reg="United States">Union</place>. When such service is complete
            we can begin to feel that our goal, “Every Child a Wanted Child,”
            may be reached. By this means we shall build for the future a
            better, strong, more healthy race-- in mind and body-- than this
            country has ever known before, a race worthy to carry on the
            tradition of our pioneering forefathers whose courage and stamina
            started the young nation on its upward path. </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
