<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2003/05/29 RK</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2003/07/01 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2003/08/07 CH Index</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/23 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/26 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007/06/25 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011-03-11 CH Entered corrections suggested by Andy Carloff.</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/03/13 EK clean regs</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-14 EK proofing corrections</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1916-04-00">Apr. 1916</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>A Message to Mothers</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp302957</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Physical Culture</title>, Apr. 1916, Vol 35: No 4, p.
                15</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Papers Microfilm: Collected Document</title>C16:99</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>A brief editorial note directing readers to an update on <person reg="Sanger's, Margaret"
                >Sanger's</person> trial that precedes this article was omitted.</p>
        <index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="propaganda and publicity"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="enslavement of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="opposition to"/>
        <index level1="motherhood" level2="MS on"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>A Message to Mothers</head>
        <byline>By Margaret H. Sanger</byline>
        <p>"<q>Motherhood is sacred!</q>" How many times have we heard that platitude -- that sweet,
            sickening lie in view of the horrible truth that motherhood has so often been a
            profanity -- the very incarnation of recklessness, carelessness, and blindness to future
            misery? Through involuntary motherhood misery and disease and ignorance and stupidity
            have been multiplied a million fold in this world. A weak and exploitable humanity has
            perpetuated itself for the benefit of its Machiavellian masters.</p>
        <p>Such at least must be the impression of one like myself. For in this work I have had the
            great response from the mothers of <place reg="United States">America</place>
            themselves, hundreds, even thousands of letters and requests coming to me for this
            knowledge. The only opposition has come from those who have established themselves
            behind the ramparts of privilege and power, or from those who derive their huge revenues
            from the weak and disinherited humanity which is the result of reckless procreation.</p>
        <p>Some are of the opinion that the practice of Birth Control by American Mothers will
            result in the improvement of the quality of the race, even though it diminish the
            quantity. I prefer to emphasize the direct and immediate benefits to be derived from
            Birth Control. Certainly we need fine, well-born children. To get them, we need strong
            mothers, strong women--spiritually strong and physically strong.</p>
        <p>When I started my propaganda for Birth Control--a fight that has been a dark and hopeless
            one against the forces of authority and ignorance--I was resolved to give women the one
            effective weapon with which they might assert their <emph rend="italics">central</emph>
            and <emph rend="italics">radical</emph> function in human society.</p>
        <p>If the mothers of America--especially the mothers of the poor--were asking for safe
            methods of birth control, in order to alleviate and remove their misery, has the doctor,
            the social worker, the nurse--has anyone in possession of it--the right to withhold it?
            Or withholding it, must he not therefore be held responsible for the unlovely results of
            forced or reckless parenthood?</p>
        <p>The weapon of Birth Control would place into the hands of all women the power to
            decide--to make the important choice. It would--indeed it already has--raised Motherhood
            to a position of the greatest responsibility. We are now in a position to hold every
            woman to a strict accountability for the children she brings into this world. Women must
            now realize that they are bringing men and women into the world--not merely babies to
            sentimentalize over.</p>
        <p>"What right have you to bring this child into the world?" This is the question every
            mother must now answer.</p>
        <p>"What right have you to expect me to bring men and women into the world?" This, in turn,
            is the question every woman must ask Society.</p>
        <p>Oh! if I could rouse enough women--enough mothers of my class, the working class--to ask
            this stern question of American society--women fully conscious of the <emph
                rend="italics">true</emph> sacredness of motherhood, women ready to demand an honest
            answer and determined to make this world into a fit place to receive <emph
                rend="italics">their</emph> children--then would we not effect an immediate
            concentration upon the solution of social problems?</p>
        <p>The women and the mothers of America, not the courts, alone have the <emph rend="italics"
                >power</emph> to decide the cause of Birth Control.</p>
        <p> ASSERT THAT POWER!</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
