<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2012-03-23 AW</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2012-03-27 AW</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-02 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1957-09-00">1957 Sept</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Too Many People!</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp303195</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Together</title> Sept. 1957 p. 16-18</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> C16:492</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="TMC">The Methodist Church</name>
            <name id="JEPL">Japanese Eugenic Protection Law</name>
            <name id="LIDEQ">Li, Dequan</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="birth control" level2="population and"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="increase in"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="efforts to reduce"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="population growth and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="socio-economic benefits of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to" level3="international"/>
        <index level1="overpopulation" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="Methodist Church"/>
        <index level1="planned parenthood" level2="and the Methodist Church"/>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="overpopulation and"/>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="infanticide in"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="mortality rates" level3="infant"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="overpopulation and"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="birth control movement in"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="Five Year Plan in"/>
        <index level1="China" level2="overpopulation and"/>
        <index level1="China" level2="population policies of"/>
        <index level1="sterilization" level2="in Puerto Rico"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="overpopulation in"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="population growth in"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="pill"/>
        <index level1="abortion" level2="illegal"/>
        <index level1="International Planned Parenthood Federation"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Too Many People!</head>
        <byline>By MARGARET SANGER</byline>
        <div>
            <p>The world is exploding at the seams. Population growth is outracing our ability to
                produce more food and goods. From the Orient to South America, from Eastern Europe
                to the <place reg="United States">U.S.</place>, soaring birth rates are posing
                future problems potentially more dangerous than the H-bomb.</p>
            <p> Just look at these facts:</p>
            <p> • By this time tomorrow, there will be at least 70,000 more people in the world than
                there are today.</p>
            <p> • If the current birth rate had started the year <person reg="Jesus Christ"
                    >Christ</person> was born, there would be <emph rend="italics">1 million</emph>
                people in the world for every <emph rend="italics">one</emph> now alive.</p>
            <p> • In 3 ½ years Red <place>China</place>’s population alone has shot up by 42
                millions -- more than the total population of <place>New York</place>,
                    <place>California</place>, and <place>Pennsylvania</place>, the three most
                heavily populated U.S. states.</p>
            <p>At present, demographers -- scientists who devote their lives to studying population
                problems -- estimate that there are 2.7 billion people in the world. By 1980, they
                expect this to soar to 4 billions; by the year 2000, to 5.5 billions. In theory,
                ways can be found to feed that many human beings -- on a scale of living like that
                of Red China or <place>India</place>’s masses. (For a close-up of what that means:
                an estimated 100 million Chinese have died of starvation in the last 100 years.) But
                few, if any, experts foresee any way in which 5.5 billion people, even half a
                century from now, can enjoy a standard of living remotely approaching that now
                enjoyed by this country.</p>
            <p>What is the answer? Birth control or, to give it another name, planned
                parenthood.</p>
            <p>This is going to be a bitter pill in Roman Catholic countries, where the <org
                    reg="Roman Catholic Church">official church</org> still boils down to this:
                Abstinence, or the far-from-certain rhythm theory, are all that can be countenanced
                in the way of planning one’s family. On the other hand, The <org>Methodist
                    Church</org> has officially endorsed planned parenthood. The 1956 edition of the
                    <title rend="italics" type="book">Discipline of The Methodist Church</title>
                contains a series of resolutions on the Christian family, adopted by the <org
                    reg="Methodist Church, General Conference">General Conference</org> last year.
                Included is this highly important statement on planned parenthood:</p>
            <p>"<q who="TMC" rend="italics">We believe that planned parenthood, practiced in the
                    Christian conscience, may fulfill rather than violate the will of <name
                        type="deity">God</name>.</q>"</p>
            <p>Beliefs of this sort, put into intelligent practice the world over, hold the only
                promise of forestalling a world-wide explosion from population pressures. Have-not
                nations, with millions more mouths to feed each year, must spill over their borders
                in unending aggressions, searching for more and more food-producing areas -- unless
                their sky-rocketing birth rates are pulled down. Eventually, the threat of
                starvation will hang over everyone unless the problem is faced squarely -- right
                now.</p>
            <p>Paradoxically, the root of the problem is man’s progress and advancing knowledge. We
                have cut infant mortality to a tiny fraction of its former toll. At the same time,
                we have extended the span of man’s years. And advancing prosperity has encouraged
                larger families. Add the three together and you get a population mushrooming more
                ominously than the cloud over any atom-bomb explosion.</p>
            <p>Let’s take a look at what some of the hardest-pressed countries are doing under this
                threat:</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <p><emph rend="bold"><place>Japan</place></emph>: In 1922 I was forbidden to discuss
                birth control from a lecture platform in <place reg="Tokyo, Japan">Tokyo</place>.
                Japan’s population then totaled 66 millions, was increasing at 800,000 a year. We
                all know now how the resulting pressures helped bring about aggression and war in
                the Pacific. Now, with defeat and the return of millions of Japanese from her
                conquered “overseas empire,” nearly 90 millions are crammed into a vastly shrunken
                area -- and once-shunned planned parenthood is becoming a cornerstone of government
                policy.</p>
            <p>In the past, infanticide provided a partial -- and brutal -- remedy to oversized
                Japanese families. Then, in 1948, the Japanese government took a big step forward by
                enacting the <name type="law">Eugenics Protection Law</name>, which approves the “<q
                    who="JEPL">termination</q>” of pregnancies whenever the mother’s health may be
                    “<q who="JEPL">seriously injured</q>” because of “<q who="JEPL">physical or
                    economic conditions</q>” -- in other words, Japan has legalized abortions where
                families feel they can’t afford another child.</p>
            <p>Latest official figures place the number of legal abortions at 1.7 millions a year,
                or about one for every live birth. How many clandestine abortions are performed is
                anybody’s guess. But the number is undoubtedly large. This is a tragic
                situation.</p>
            <p>In recognition of this, the Japanese government is also encouraging dissemination of
                information on contraceptives, but has hardly made a beginning in this work. Until
                thousands more midwives can be trained to teach married couples the use of
                contraceptives, and until the government can bring the price of these materials
                within the reach of the poorest peasants, legalized abortion will have to be the
                mainstay in keeping the Japanese birth rate down. And, bad as it is, it is a big
                step upward from infanticide.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <p><emph rend="bold">India</emph>: Indian scientists are proud that infant mortality has
                dropped from 215 per 1,000 live births in 1901 to 114 in 1956; that it is expected
                to fall to 35 by 1964. But they are worried because population is zooming at the
                rate of 5 millions a year, is heading for 512 millions by 1980. With the masses
                already living on a less-than-subsistence level, the outlook is far from happy.</p>
            <p>At present, the Indian government’s Five Year Plan officially endorses contraception.
                Health-service centers, operating on an $8 millions budget, are spreading
                information on planned parenthood and supplying free contraceptives. The nation’s
                second Five Year Plan calls for setting up 2,100 maternal and child-health centers
                in rural areas and 2,300 birth-control clinics.</p>
            <p>Indian leaders pull no punches in describing their predicament. As they see it, they
                face a grim choice: If they don’t check the runaway increase in population, each
                person will be eating 5 per cent less food each year than he did the year before. On
                the other hand, if fertility can be cut in half, by 1986 each person will be able to
                consume 50 per cent more than he can today, thanks to improved methods of
                agriculture and production. For India, it is literally the hour to choose between
                cutting the birthrate or facing starvation.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <p><emph rend="bold">China</emph>: Red China’s official census in 1953 put its
                population at 583 millions, increasing at the rate of over 12 millions a year. At
                latest estimates, the total is 625 millions -- half again as much as India. <place
                    reg="Peking, China">Peiping</place>’s overlords realize, despite their mouthing
                of Communist propaganda, that no Five Year Plan or magical improvement in
                agriculture or industry is ever going to catch up with increases such as these. </p>
            <p>Already the ruling hierarchy is practicing birth control. Families of most leaders
                are limited to an average of two children each, setting a theoretical example to the
                masses. But actually reaching the millions of rural peasants is a task of the first
                magnitude. Last year the <person reg="Li, Dequan">minister of health</person>
                ordered an all-out propaganda drive to win these families away from their age-old
                desire for “<q who="LIDEQ">many sons</q>” and into the field of planned parenthood.
                Officials claim China’s women are enthusiastically backing the campaign, but admit
                that China lacks the birth-control devices to meet even a fraction of anticipated
                demand.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <p>Turning to the Western Hemisphere, we find that the Latin American countries are
                growing at an even faster rate than the Asiatic. However, because they have not yet
                been brought under the intense population pressure of the Oriental countries, and
                because most of these are Catholic nations, their situation is not being faced by
                their governments.</p>
            <p>Except in <place>Puerto Rico</place>. Perhaps because of its close ties with the
                Protestant U.S. mainland, or because its population has already reached the
                explosion point, that island is turning to an unusual solution. Despite Catholic
                opposition, it is using sterilization to limit the size of families.</p>
            <p>The operation is performed most often on women immediately after childbirth.
                Perfectly legal, it is done only when the woman, her husband, and their doctor
                agree.</p>
            <p>Within the U.S. itself, population is growing all too fast. It has been estimated
                that by 1975 we may have 249 million people -- although surveys show over 80 per
                cent of American white women of childbearing age practice birth control. Actually,
                planned parenthood is becoming more accepted all the time. Not too many years ago,
                advocates of birth control were thrown in jail. It was illegal for a doctor to give
                information on spacing children.</p>
            <p>Now, however, planned parenthood has become an accepted part of our life. Information
                and devices are available in hundreds of hospitals, clinics, and public-health
                centers. New methods are being tested in leading laboratories; even the
                    <org>Rockefeller Foundation</org> is donating liberally to this work.</p>
            <p>Too, U.S. scientists report encouraging results in experiments with an oral
                contraceptive, taken by women 20 days each month. Years of further testing remain,
                but the search for a “birth-control pill” appears to be bearing fruit. </p>
            <p>All these things make the picture appear bright. But there is a darker side. The size
                of families is increasing, population is soaring, too many people refuse to look at
                the handwriting on the wall. A recent national survey shows 36 per cent of all
                births were unplanned. Too, there still remain thousands of frightened, unknowing
                women to whom illegal abortion remains the only known way of controlling the
                family’s size.</p>
            <p>It has been estimated that, in addition to the comparative handful of legal
                abortions, 2 million illegal operations are performed every year in this country,
                and that racketeers net $50 millions annually from these terrorized women. How many
                victims die? Some sources say well over 100 a week, and probably considerably more,
                since most of these deaths are listed under some other cause.</p>
            <p>And did you know that nine out of every 10 abortions in the U.S. reportedly are
                performed on married women between 25 and 35, with three or more children?</p>
            <p>That is the frightening picture of “enlightened” womankind in this country in this
                year of grace, 1957. </p>
            <p>What, then, is the world-wide situation? Progress is being made -- but time is
                running out. Some countries, especially those pushed to the brink of starvation, are
                at last teaching their people the elements of planned parenthood. In others, such as
                the U.S., the picture is confused. Birth control once a forbidden subject, is
                widespread and an accepted pattern of married life for millions. But for many others
                there still remains only that last desperate step -- the illegal abortion -- if the
                size of the family is to be limited.</p>
            <p>In all, 18 nations now are members of the <org>International Planned Parenthood
                    Federation</org>, whose next meeting will be held in <place reg="Washington, DC"
                    >Washington</place> in 1958. But over all, federation members or not, hangs the
                threat of a P (for Population) bomb explosion.</p>
            <p>Most nations, preoccupied with the threat of atomic wars and mass destruction, are
                unable -- or unwilling -- to face the stark specter of starvation which, in varying
                degrees of nearness, is drawing in on all of them. Authorities agree that there is
                nothing in the teachings of most major religions to forbid the practice of having
                children when they are really wanted. There seems, therefore, to be but one humane
                solution to the problem. That is best summed up in those simple words, quoted
                earlier, of The Methodist Church in its 1956 <title rend="italics" type="book"
                    >Discipline</title>:</p>
            <p><q who="TMC" rend="italics">“We believe that planned parenthood, practiced in
                    Christian conscience, may fulfill rather than violate the will of God.”</q></p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
