<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2003/06/09 SB</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/23 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007/06/25 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/03/11 CH Entered corrections suggested by Andy Carloff.</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011-11-30 CH typos</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-01 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1916-07-00">Jul 1916</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Birth Control</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp303217</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">The Melting Pot</title>July 1916, 5-6</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> C16:90</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="BIB">Bible</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="birth control" level2="class-based"/>
        <index level1="birth control"  level2="working classes and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"/>
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="socio-economic benefits of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="labor movement and"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="efforts to increase"/>
        <index level1="Catholic Church" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="Catholic Church" level2="abortion and"/>
        <index level1="Catholic Church" level2="population and"/>
        <index level1="censorship"/>
        <index level1="free speech and free press"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="infant"/> 
        <index level1="physicians" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="politicians" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="enslavement of"/>
       
      
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Birth Control</head>
        <byline>By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">MARGARET H. SANGER</person> 163 Lexington Avenue,
                <place reg="New York, NY">New York City</place></byline>
        <p>We in the <place reg="United States">United States</place> are entering upon a
            fight for moral liberty, much as our parents entered the fight for political and
            religious liberty in the past.</p>
        <p>Freedom in political, religious and moral thought are absolutely essential to the
            progress of every civilized country. We have fought for freedom for the first and
            second, but the third has been slumbering and we have not awakened it. Now we find our
            moral censors forbidding any discussions of the subject of small families for the
            working woman.</p>
        <p>We are allowed to discuss matters like "preparedness," submarines, liquid fire and life
            destroying gasses, but are forbidden to break the conventional silence of how to prevent
            bringing children into the world we cannot feed, clothe and care for.</p>
        <p>Our statesmen, clergymen, medical men (and militants, of course), have a wide license to
            demand that women supply the race with more babies, and try to frighten us about race
            suicide unless they do so. All of these are either themselves interested parties or
            under the influence of interested parties who profit by the big battalions of working
            women's babies. Take the clergy, (Catholics especially). They are the beneficiaries of
            the church that has made breeding its main source of revenue. They preach from a
                "sacred book" to "<q who="BIB">multiply and replenish the
                earth</q>," knowing that large families among working people tend to preserve their
            influence and authority. They tell us that every baby is a new soul presented to
                <name type="deity">God</name>, and for his glory and honor women must produce as many souls as
            possible.</p>
        <p>Just as the Church has the market on souls, so has the medical profession the vested
            interest in bodies. Birth is a direct and indirect source of revenue, through maternity
            fees, abortions, infantile diseases, and finally death bed attendance.</p>
        <p>The politician is usually a representative of the great trusts whose demand for more
            babies is made for an economic purpose. He desires to provide abundant labor for the
            employing classes and thus keep down wages, and also to swell the ranks for military
            duty. He wants "hands" to compete in the labor market, or soldiers in the fighting line.
            These are what "more babies" mean to him and the priests.</p>
        <p>Is a creature owned by the big moneyed interests which depends for their profits upon
            cheap labor to be our instructor in the matter of birth?</p>
        <p>With all these powerful forces against us, is it any wonder that we have given more time
            to discuss the making of warships and other instruments for murder than to the saving of
            infant lives and the control of their creation?</p>
        <p>We find the real reason that 300,000 babies died last year in the United States was that
            their fathers could not make enough to keep them alive. The more mothers must work in
            factories and sweat shops, the larger the number of deaths among their babies. To the
            father who makes $25.00 a week the death rate of infants is less than 84 per 1000. If he
            makes less than $10.00 a week, they die at the rate of over 256 per 1000. Every 300,000
            babies that die from poverty and neglect has 600,000 parents who remain in ignorance of
            the means to prevent 300,000 more babies from coming into the world the next year to die
            of poverty and neglect.</p>
        <p>Every woman who tries to exist on her husband's wage of $10.00 or $12.00 a week knows she
            cannot decently care for a large family. She does not want more than two or three
            children and is made to become a child bearing machine because of her ignorance of how
            to prevent it. She dreads the coming of another baby and lives in constant terror of
            unwanted pregnancies. The husband on the other hand is also unable to cope with the
            burden of a large family. It is this which keeps him compelled to accept any wage. It is
            the cries of the little ones which compel him to be the last one out on strike and the
            first one back. It makes it impossible for him to save a cent for a "rainy
                day" or for sickness, which in turn compels him to remain in one place,
            while his brother with one or two children can seek better conditions elsewhere.</p>
        <p>Everything is against the working man with a large family. Factories and mills are hungry
            for his children. Juvenile Courts and dens of prostitution, jails or the trenches of war
            are waiting for his growing sons and daughters. The facts are that the working class
            produce too many children, too many for their own personal comfort, too many for the
            health and development of the mothers, too many for he good of their class. It is they
            themselves who are the sinners, in thus making worse their own wretched conditions by
            perpetuating poverty for generations to come. We have the statistics regarding
            unemployment, emigration, maternal and infantile mortality, and they all prove that
            there are too many babies born form the working class parents.</p>
        <p>All down the ages the working people have produced themselves too rapidly for their
            economic welfare. The history of labor has been of an ever unsuccessful attempt of the
            man to make his labor power bring enough to supply his unlimited offspring with the
            necessities of life. It has ever been a losing battle. The argument is so simple that I
            can never see how anyone can oppose it. Give a man a wage of $12.00 a week; is it not
            better to support upon it a family of four than a family of eight? When he attempts to
            support eight upon this wage it means abject poverty, distress, charity, loss of
            independence and humiliation. It all seems so simple, and yet millions, through their
            own ignorance, are incapable of bettering their conditions in this way.</p>
        <p>When a man applies for a position in any given trade or occupation do you find the man
            with ten children receiving a higher wage for the same work than the man with two
            children? Assuredly not.</p>
        <p>Wage slavery, even in its worse aspect, is largely the consequence of the careless
            breeding of wage slaves, and it will continue so long as wage slaves continue to
            reproduce new beings necessarily condemned to lives of poverty and ignorance. Such
            offspring are bound to be the victims of priestcraft and cunning politicians.</p>
        <p>And the woman! She has spent her whole adult life in bringing children into the world,
            not because of her desire for them, but because of her ignorance of how to prevent it.
            Many of these do so because they do not know that conception can be avoided, or knowing
            it fear the miserable threats of priests and preachers.</p>
        <p>The laws have been made strong and barbarous in their cruelty for violating this
            particular section. Unjust laws keep women in bondage, and men in slavery. Shall we who
            love mankind be content to obey them? I for one shall never lend myself to a wrong which
            I condemn. Has the United States only prisons and jails for us who dare speak and act
            for liberty? One thing is certain; knowledge to control birth is the most important
            immediate step the working class must take to reach the goal of its emancipation.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
