<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2010/03/02 AC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-11 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1935-02-04">Standard Date</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Important Reasons for Amending Exisiting Birth Control Laws</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp303370</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Records of the Children's Bureau, RG 102, National Archives and Records
                Service</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title>, C16:0373</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Comstock act"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Federal"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="State"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="medical community and"/>
        <index level1="obscenity"/>
        <index level1="physicians" level2="birth control and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Important Reasons for Amending Existing Birth Control Laws</head>
        <p>
            <list>
                <item>1 Federal Laws Passed in 1873, class birth control with <emph rend="italics"
                        >obscenity</emph>. This stigma should be removed from a subject affecting
                    public health.</item>
                <item>2 Federal laws conflict with State laws. Doctors are confused as to the legal
                    status of the subject. Physicians fear giving contraceptive advice. Study and
                    medical research are hampered.</item>
                <item>3 Physicians legally giving advice in their <place reg="United States"
                        >States</place> are forced to “bootleg” their contraceptive supplies and
                    scientific information, for Federal Laws forbid using U.S. mails or common
                    carriers to obtain or send contraceptive information or supplies. Physicians may
                    choose to violate Federal Laws in private practice; <emph rend="italics"
                        >but</emph> they cannot do so in hospitals, dispensaries, etc., lest the
                    charters and endowments of such institutions be revoked. Consequently, poor
                    women are unable to obtain this knowledge.</item>
                <item>4 Commercial agencies masquerade under misleading names--exploiting the needs
                    of these women.</item>
                <item>5 Federal laws make it illegal to send the <emph rend="italics">address</emph>
                    of birth control clinics (legally operating under State laws) to overburdened
                    mothers seeking help. </item>
                <item>6 The medical organizations most familiar with this subject have gone on
                    record in favor of amending these laws: The <org>American Gynecological
                        Society</org> (1925); <org>Section of Obstetrics, Gynecology and Abdominal
                        Surgery of the American Medical Association</org>; The <org>Medical Women’s
                        National Association</org>; <org>National Committee on Maternal Health, Inc.
                    </org></item>
                <item>7 Increased knowledge of contraception would mean a reduction in the number of
                    criminal abortions. Over 15,000 women each year die from this cause alone. </item>
                <item>8 Lastly: During this period of economic distress and unemployment, wives and
                    mothers should be able to obtain through responsible medical channels, this form
                    of constructive relief.</item>
            </list>
        </p>


    </docBody>
</doc>
