<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2002-01-07 CH</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2002-08-09 CH</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2004/07/26 CH</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2004/08/09 CH</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2011/11/28 CH correct typos</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-04-10 CH clean regs</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-20 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1925-03-30">30 Mar 1925</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>The Children's Era</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp303355</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>, ed. <title type="book"
					>Proceedings of the Sixth International Neo-Malthusian and Birth Control
					Conference, Volume IV</title> New York, 1925, 53-58. </bibl>
			<bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Collected Documents Series</title>
				C16:283</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name/>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote>
		<p>Sanger gave this address at a public meeting at <org>Scottish Rite Hall</org> in <place
				reg="New York, NY">New York</place>, as part of the <org
				reg="International Neo-Malthusian and Birth Control
            Conference, 6th"
				>Sixth International Neo-Malthusian and Birth Control Conference</org>. Other
			speakers appearing at the event were Norman Thomas, <person
				reg="Drysdale, Charles Vickery">Charles Vickery Drysdale</person>, <person
				reg="Jensen, Thit">Thit Jensen</person>, <person reg="Cooper, James F.">James F.
				Cooper</person>, and <person reg="Hale, Ruth">Ruth Hale</person>. </p>
		<index level1="International Neo-Malthusian and Birth Control Conference, Sixth "/>
		<index level1="eugenics"/>
		<index level1="child welfare" level2="and birth control"/>
		<index level1="&quot;unfit&quot; to reproduce" level2="descriptions of"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits and risks"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>The Children's Era</head>
		<byline>By Margaret Sanger</byline>
		<p><person reg="Thomas, Norman">Mr. Chairman</person>, Ladies and Gentlemen:</p>
		<p>My subject is "The Children's Era." "The Children's Era!" This makes me think of <person
				reg="Key, Ellen">Ellen Key</person>'s book--<title type="book">The Century of the
				Child</title>. Ellen Key hoped that this twentieth century was to be the century of
			the child. The twentieth century, she said, would see this old world of ours converted
			into a beautiful garden of children. Well, we have already lived through a quarter of
			this twentieth century. What steps have we taken toward making it the century of the
			child? So far, very, very few.</p>
		<p>Why does the Children's Era still remain a dream of the dim and distant future? Why has
			so little been accomplished?--in spite of all our acknowledged love of children, all our
			generosity, all our good-will, all the enormous spending of millions on philanthropy and
			charities, all our warm-hearted sentiment, all our incessant activity and social
			consciousness? Why?</p>
		<p>Before you can cultivate a garden, you must know something about gardening. You have got
			to give your seeds a proper soil in which to grow. You have got to give them sunlight
			and fresh air. You have got to give them space and the opportunity (if they are to lift
			their flowers to the sun), to strike their roots deep into that soil. And always--do not
			forget this--you have got to fight weeds. You cannot have a garden, if you let weeds
			overrun it. So, if we want to make this world a garden for children, we must first of
			all learn the lesson of the gardener. </p>
		<p>So far we have not been gardeners. We have only been a sort of silly reception committee.
			A reception committee at the <org>Grand Central Station</org> of life. Trainload after
			trainload of children are coming in, day and night--nameless refugees arriving out of
			the Nowhere into the Here. Trainload after trainload--many unwelcome, unwanted,
			unprepared for, unknown, without baggage, without passports, most of them without
			pedigrees. These unlimited hordes of refugees arrive in such numbers that the reception
			committee is thrown into a panic--a panic of activity. The reception committee arouses
			itself heroically, establishes emergency measures: milk stations, maternity centers,
			settlement houses, playgrounds, orphanages, welfare leagues and every conceivable kind
			of charitable effort. But still trainloads of children keep on coming--human weeds crop
			up that spread so fast in this sinister struggle for existence, that the overworked
			committee becomes exhausted, inefficient and can think of no way out.</p>
		<p>When we protest against this immeasurable, meaningless waste of motherhood and
			child-life; when we protest against the ever-mounting cost to the world of asylums,
			prisons, homes for the feeble-minded and such institutions for the unfit, when we
			protest against the disorder and chaos and tragedy of modern life, when we point out the
			biological corruption that is destroying the very heart of American life, we are told
			that we are making merely an "emotional" appeal. When we point the one immediate
			practical way toward order and beauty in society, the only way to lay the foundations of
			a society composed of happy children, happy women and happy men, they call this idea
			indecent and immoral. </p>
		<p>It is not enough to clean up the filth and disorder of our overcrowded cities. It is not
			enough to stop the evil of Child Labor--even if we could! It is not enough to decrease
			the rate of infantile mortality. It is not enough to open playgrounds, and build more
			public schools in which we can standardize the minds of the young. It is not enough, to
			throw millions upon millions of dollars into charities and philanthropies. Don't deceive
			ourselves that by so doing so we are making the world "Safe for Children."</p>
		<p>Those of you who have followed the sessions of this Conference must, I am sure, agree
			with me that the first real step toward the creation of a Children's Era must lie in
			providing the conditions of healthy life for children not only before birth but even
			more imperatively before conception. Human society must protect its children--yes, but
			prenatal care is most essential! The child-to-be, as yet not called into being, has
			rights no less imperative.</p>
		<p>We have learned in the preceding sessions of this Conference that, if we wish to produce
			strong and sturdy children, the embryo must grow in a chemically healthy medium. The
			blood stream of the mother must be chemically normal. Worry, strain, shock, unhappiness,
			enforced maternity, may all poison the blood of the enslaved mother. This chemically
			poisoned blood may produce a defective baby--a child foredoomed to idiocy, or
			feeble-mindedness, crime, or failure. </p>
		<p>Do I exaggerate? Am I taking a rare exception and making it a general rule? Our opponents
			declare that children are conceived in love, and that every new-born baby converts its
			parents to love and unselfishness. My answer is to point to the asylums, the hospitals,
			the ever-growing institutions for the unfit. Look into the family history of those who
			are feeble-minded; or behind the bars of jails and prisons. Trace the family histories;
			find out the conditions under which they were conceived and born, before you attempt to
			persuade us that reckless breeding has nothing to do with these grave questions. </p>
		<p>There is only one way out. We have got to fight for the health and happiness of the
			Unborn Child. And to do that in a practical, tangible way, we have got to free women
			from enforced, enslaved maternity. There can be no hope for the future of civilization,
			no certainty of racial salvation, until every woman can decide for herself whether she
			will or will not become a mother and when and how many children she cares to bring into
			the world. That is the first step.</p>
		<p>I would like to suggest Civil Service examinations for parenthood! Prospective parents
			after such an examination would be given a parenthood licence, proving that they are
			physically and mentally fit to be the fathers and mothers of the next generation.</p>
		<p>This is an interesting idea--but then arises the questions "Who is to decide?" "Would
			there be a jury, like the play jury?" Would a <org reg="Republican Party"
				>Republican</org> administration give parenthood permits only to Republicans--or
			perhaps only to <org reg="Democratic Party">Democrats</org>? The more you think of
			governmental interference, the less it works out. Take this plan of civil service
			examination for parenthood. It suggests Prohibition: there might even be bootlegging in
			babies!</p>
		<p>No, I doubt the advisability of governmental sanction. The problem of bringing children
			into the world ought to be decided by those most seriously involved--those who run the
			greatest risks; in the last analysis--by the mother and the child. If there is going to
			be any Civil Service examination, let it be conducted by the Unborn Child, the
			Child-to-be.</p>
		<p>Just try for a moment to picture the possibilities of such an examination. </p>
		<p>When you want a cook or housemaid, you go to an employment bureau. You have to answer
			questions. You have to exchange references. You have to persuade the talented cook that
			you conduct a proper well-run household. Children ought to have at least the same
			privilege as cooks.</p>
		<p>Sometimes in idle moments I like to think it would be a very good scheme to have a bureau
			of the Child-to-be. </p>
		<p>At such a bureau of the unborn, the wise child might be able to find out a few things
			about its father--and its mother. Just think for a moment of this bureau where
			prospective parents might apply for a baby. Think of the questions they would be asked
			by the agent of the unborn or by the baby itself. </p>
		<p>First: "<q who="BABY">Mr. Father, a baby is an expensive luxury. Can you really afford
				one?</q>"</p>
		<p>"Have you paid for your last baby yet?"</p>
		<p>"How many children have you already? Six? You must have your hands full. Can you take
			care of so many?"</p>
		<p>"Do you look upon children as a reward--or a penalty?"</p>
		<p>"How are your ductless glands--well balanced?"</p>
		<p>"Can you provide a happy home for one? A sunny nursery? Proper food?"</p>
		<p>"What's that you say? Ten children already? Two dark rooms in the slums?"</p>
		<p>"No, thank you! I don't care to be born at all if I cannot be well-born. Good-bye!"</p>
		<p>And if we could organize a society for the prevention of cruelty to unborn children, we
			would make it a law that children should be brought into the world only when they were
			welcome, invited and wanted; that they would arrive with a clean bill of health and
			heritage; that they would possess healthy, happy, well-mated and mature parents.</p>
		<p>And there would be certain conditions of circumstances which would preclude parenthood.
			These conditions, the presence of which would make parenthood a crime, are the
			following: </p>
		<list>
			<item>1. Transmissible disease<lb/>
			</item>
			<item>2. Temporary disease<lb/>
			</item>
			<item>3. Subnormal children already in the family<lb/>
			</item>
			<item>4. Space out between births<lb/>
			</item>
			<item>5. Twenty-three years as a minimum age for parents<lb/></item>
			<item>6. Economic circumstances adequate<lb/>
			</item>
			<item>7. Spiritual harmony between parents.</item>
		</list>
		<p>In conclusion, let me repeat:</p>
		<p>We are not trying to establish a dictatorship over parents. We want to free women from
			enslaved and unwilling motherhood. We are fighting for the emancipation of the mothers
			of the world, of the children of the world, and the children to be. We want to create a
			real Century of the Child--to usher in a Children's Era. We can do this by handing the
			terrific gift of life in bodies fit and perfect as can be fashioned. Help us to make
			this Conference which has aroused so much interest the turning point toward this era.
			Only so can you help in the creation of the future. </p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
