<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2001-11-06 MH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2002-08-22 KH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2003/12/08 CH clean up codes and xref</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007-05-30 CH Oxygen cleanup</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2013-04-30 CH fix links</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-07-02 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1912-12-01">1 Dec1912</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>What Every Girl Should Know: Girlhood -- Part II</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp303438</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">New York Call</title>, Dec. 1, 1912</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> C16:0027</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
        <p>This is the third article in an 12-part series. For "Introduction," see <xref
                from="304533.xml">Nov. 17, 1912</xref>, for "Girlhood-Part I" see <xref
                from="300177.xml">Nov. 24, 1912</xref>, for "Puberty-Part I" see<xref
                from="304920.xml"> Dec. 8, 1912</xref>, for "Puberty-Part II" see<xref
                from="304921.xml"> Dec. 15, 1912</xref>, for "Sexual Impulse--Part I" see <xref
                from="304922.xml">Dec. 22, 1912,</xref> for "Sexual Impulse-Part II" see<xref
                from="304923.xml"> Dec. 29, 1912</xref>, for "Reproduction--Part I" see <xref
                from="304924.xml">Jan. 2, 1913</xref>, for "Reproduction--Part II" see <xref
                from="304925.xml">Jan. 19, 1913</xref>, for "Some Consequences of Ignorance and
            Silence--Part I" see <xref from="304926.xml">Jan. 26, 1913</xref>, for "Some
            Consequences of Ignorance and Silence--Part II" see <xref from="304927.xml">Feb. 2,
                1913</xref>, and for "Some Consequences of Ignorance and Silence--Part III" see
                <xref from="304928.xml">Mar. 2, 1913.</xref></p>
        <index level1="sex education" level2="need for"/>
        <index level1="adolescence"/>
        <index level1="working classes"/>
        <index level1="upper classes"/>
        <index level1="sex education"/>
        <index level1="sexuality" level2="women's"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>WHAT EVERY GIRL SHOULD KNOW</head>
        <byline>By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">MARGARET H. SANGER</person>.</byline>
        <head type="sub">Girlhood -- Part II.</head>
        <p>The organs of sense are also awakened to activity in the adolescent girl. The sense of
            smell becomes extremely acute; offensive odors are VERY offensive, while pleasant ones
            are greatly enjoyed and desired. Thus we find perfumes used lavishly in girlhood, and
            alas! too often indiscriminately.</p>
        <p>With the development of the other senses the sense of color is awakened. The girl who
            yesterday allowed her elders to choose clothing and colors for her at this time becomes
            most exacting in her own selection of ribbons and dresses. Sunsets and forests have
            become beautiful, and often the girl with artistic talent decides at this age to choose
            her life work. Laces, jewelry, trinkets, ribbons and shop windows become her world.
            Indeed, so great is her desire to possess ornaments that she has been known to resort to
            petty thievery, when unable to avail herself of the means to obtain them otherwise.
            Certain authorities, who have made vice and kindred subjects a study, assert that it is
            this great desire for trinkets, silk petticoats, etc., which induces girls to sell their
            bodies and enter prostitution. Such authorities fail to see the economic significance of
            these unsatisfied desires. There is something wrong with a system of society which
            allows its women to sell their bodies for such trifles, the desire for which is part of
            their natural development.</p>
        <p>Is flesh and blood and the virtue of the mothers of the future so cheap in this land of
            plenty that it can be sacrificed for such passing whims? It is impossible to suppress
            that inherent and natural desire in the adolescent girl to adorn and beautify herself.
            She must and will do it.</p>
        <p>The girl of wealth, of the so-called upper class, can beautify herself and adorn her body
            with the costliest jewels and fabrics. All eyes are upon her in admiration of her
            exquisite taste and attractive appearance. Yet this same manifestation in a working girl
            is condemned. Any attempt on the part of a working girl to give expression to the desire
            to be beautiful is considered "dangerous to her welfare"; is spoken of as her "awful
            desire for trinkets."</p>
        <p>The women of wealth set certain standards for themselves and their class, but separate
            and distinct standards for the women of the working class. It is about time the
            reformers and philanthropists do something other than shake their heads over these bad
            "symptoms" shown by working girls.</p>
        <p>A craving for beauty and pleasure, dancing, music, singing and laughter, an innate,
            hereditary desire to adorn and beautify herself, which comes down to her from primitive
            woman, together with a burning desire for and love of romance, characterize the
            adolescent girl and often remain with her far beyond the adolescent age.</p>
        <p>When the imagination is thus aroused it is not unusual to learn that the young girl
            yields to it, tells strange tales about herself, and is, therefore, often accused of
            lying. But this and petty thievery disappear as reason and will power are developed. </p>
        <p>The change of voice in a girl is not so distinct as in a boy, but the voice gradually
            becomes softer, fuller and of a more womanly pitch, though the change is quite
            unnoticeable while it occurs.</p>
        <p>The hearing becomes keener, noises which a few months ago were considered a joke are now
            disturbing (such as father's loud sneeze). Music and singing have charms, which in
            childhood were unappreciated.</p>
        <p>Parents and teachers who do not appreciate the change taking place within the girl at
            this period, have small patience with such doings, calling her "giddy" and "affected"
            when in reality it is all part of her development and can be guided and directed into
            beautiful channels. Together with her personal adornment comes interest in her
            surroundings. New and elaborate decorations furnish her bedroom, and toilet accessories
            become objects of pride. Primitive colors are displayed, largely in curtains, bed
            coverings, wall paper, etc., all of which explain the independent ego in the stage of
            transition.</p>
        <p>There are many forms of disturbance which the girl suffers at this period, such as
            hysteria and insanity, which, however, we will not dwell upon here. Enough has been said
            on the subject to impress upon my readers the cause of these physical and mental
            disturbances, and to realize that special care and consideration should be given at this
            particular age of the girl.</p>
        <p>The emotional nature also plays a most prominent part in the developing girl, and
            justice, I feel, would not be shown her here, unless we cover briefly this most
            interesting part of her nature. One of the strongest emotions which very few girls,
            passing from childhood into womanhood, escape is the religious awakening of one kind or
            another. It is said by some investigators that 80 per cent of the conversions of women
            in the churches take place before the age of 20. From 30 to 40 years only a very small
            percentage occur--something like 1 or 2 per cent.</p>
        <p>It is also shown that more young girls join the church than boys. Some girls seem almost
            consumed by the desire to do good and be good in every thought and word and act, and
            have been known to go through various forms of self-punishment, such as fasting,
            sacrificing pleasure, etc. Again, others spend hours in absolute devotion to the neglect
            of health and studies. It is very easily seen why the church takes its "flock," while
            still in the adolescent period, for at no subsequent time is the girl's mind so plastic
            or impressionable. If the same girl who enters the convent at 18 years had waited until
            22 she would very likely not have entered, for the mental changes are most intense from
            16 to 18 years of age.</p>
        <p>Another common emotional awakening of girlhood is the affections. In boys this awakening
            causes them to gather together in gangs. They follow the leader whom they greatly admire
            and obey. In girls it assumes a more simple form, the devotion to a girl friend of her
            own age, and the affection between them is deep and intense while it lasts. They tell
            their most private thoughts in secret to each other, dividing all honors, pleasures and
            gifts; they are almost inseparable, and I have known a girl whose affection was so deep
            for her "chum" that she wore mourning when the chum's father died.</p>
        <p>Another form of affection which the girl of this age manifests is that for an older
            woman, often a teacher or neighbor. Parents sometimes look askance a this relation, and
            rightly so, for a friendship can be beneficial or harmful according to the character of
            the older woman. But with all these interests there is nothing so all-absorbing or so
            interesting the adolescent girl as HERSELF. She has become conscious of SELF. Now she
            burns with ambition to go out into the world and do mighty things. She feels sure she
            will be a great singer, or a dancer, or, perhaps, an actress. Again, she feels she will
            write a wonderful book--about herself--or at least she will be the heroine. Or she will
            write a wonderful tragic play; or she will nurse on the battlefields and care for the
            sick and dying. These, together with thousands of other desires, burn in her mind, and
            can be increased or lessened according to the character of the books she reads. The
            literature placed in a girl's hands at this age has as great an influence on her
            thoughts and acts as her companions.</p>
        <p>In early adolescence this self-consciousness manifests itself strongly. I mentioned last
            week in the first part of this article the physical awkwardness of the girl. With this
            comes the blushing, and giggling, which are all signs that she is conscious of that
            inner self of the ego.</p>
        <p>It is at this stage when the mother tries to explain what the menstrual period means to
            the girl that she is met with an icy indifference. She refuses to talk on this subject,
            or any thing pertaining to the sex subject, because she has just become conscious of her
            sex, and everything connected with it seems offensively personal.</p>
        <p>She most likely has received her sexual information from some one else, and the mother is
            astonished at the stubborn silence on the part of her daughter. She fails to realize
            that some one else has that confidence which belongs to her and which she should have
            gained many years earlier. There is a strong tie between the adolescent girl and her
            sexual informant. The influence of an older girl over a younger, between whom there are
            confidences regarding sex is surprisingly great. The mind at this age is very
            susceptible to influences of any kind, and the ideals instilled into a girl's mind are
            of paramount importance.</p>
        <p>These are only a few of the disturbances of the adolescent girl. But they are sufficient
            for us to know that at the bottom of all these disturbances is the mysterious influence
            of sex, gradually unfolding itself and finally claiming its own.</p>
        <p>At the time these emotions are in full sway along comes a newer and deeper one. The boy
            with whom she has played for the past several years, run races, played house, ball and
            games, one day looks into her eyes--and something happens.</p>
        <p>Perhaps that look was accompanied by a pull at her hair, a pinch on her arm, or a hit
            with an apple core, but the glance was one which awakened within her a new instinct; the
            consciousness of sex, and upon her horizon man appears.</p>
        <p>Those who have investigated boy and girl love affairs seem to be of the opinion that they
            are invariably of short duration. Out of 100 high school girls interrogated, two had
            married while at school, and one of these had received a divorce shortly after. This
            goes to prove that the boy a girl is willing to elope with, or even starve for at 18, is
            quite forgotten at the age of 25.</p>
        <p>Thousands of girls marry between the ages of 19 and 20--the years when they are
            developing in body, mind and character. They are at a loss to understand themselves,
            because they are ignorant of the fact that the wonderful instinct of sex is making
            itself felt. For thousands of years this instinct has been in the germ of life. When
            they have reached that age nature is preparing them to proclaim its right, to perform
            their natural functions, to propagate.</p>
        <p>As the knowledge of the sex functions is one of the most important to the health and
            happiness of the girl, we shall next consider the girl in the period, when nature has
            developed and prepared her to carry out its plan, in the Age of Puberty.</p>
        <trailer>(To be continued.)</trailer>
    </docBody>
</doc>
