<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="(Published testimony) ">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/04/02 VS initial tagging</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="(1931-02-13) ">13 February, 1931t</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Title of the document</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp303736</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Birth Control Hearings</title>pp. 2-5, 76-84</bibl>
            <bibl><title>MSM</title> LCM C15:736</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="MSPP">Margaret Sanger Papers project</name>
            <name id="GILFR">Gillett, Frederick Huntington</name>
            <name id="AMA">American Medical Association</name>
            <name id="BURHI">Burton, Hiram Ralph</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">Sanger testifies before U.S. Senate concerning S. 4582 on 13th-14th
        February, 1931. <index level1="birth control" level2="Bible and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits and risks"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="physical justifications for"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="legalization of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="medical community and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="religion and"/>
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Postal Code and Regulations"/>
        <index level1="poverty" level2="family size and"/>
        <index level1="racial/ethnic references" level2="to Jews"/>
        <index level1="United States Congress" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="Voluntary Parenthood League"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="health of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Hearings before a Subcommittee of the Committee on the Judiciary United States Senate
            Seventy-First Congress Third Session</head>
        <byline>S. 4582 A bill to Amend Section 305 (A) of the Tariff Act of 1922, as Amended, and
            Sections 211, 245, and 312 of the Criminal Code, as Amended.</byline>
        <dateline>February 13 and 14, 1931<date value="1931-02-13 "/></dateline>
        <p> Statement of Mrs. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></p>
        <p> Mrs. Sanger. Mr. <person reg="Norris, George William">Chairman</person>, and gentlemen
            of the committee, the essential object of the <org
                reg="National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control">committee on
                Federal legislation for birth control</org> in supporting this bill, <name
                type="law">Senate 4582</name>. is to amend the existing Federal laws which prevent
            the dissemination through the mails of information relating to the subject of
            contraception. We want to make it possible for mothers have safe, scientific information
            to prevent conception so that they may regulate the size of their families, so that they
            may space out the number of children in the family in consideration of the mother’s
            health, of the father’s earning capacity, and the welfare of each child. </p>
        <p> I want to say, Mr. Chairman, that this is the first time that this bill, this particular
            kind of bill, has been introduced in the <org reg="United States Senate">Senate</org>.
            It has been introduced by Senator <person reg="Gillett, Frederick Huntington"
                >Gillett</person>, the chairman of this committee, and it may be referred to by the
            speakers following as the “doctor’s bill,” or the “birth control bill.” I want to say
            that the reason it has been referred to as the doctor’s bill is to distinguish it from
            other pieces of legislation on the same general subject, especially one bill that was
            introduced in <org reg="United States Congress">Congress</org> in 1925, and known as the
            “open bill.” That bill aimed to take the whole subject of the prevention of conception
            out of the law, while this bill only asks that exceptions shall be made in this law, or
            in these laws, for physicians and for the regular practice of the medical profession. </p>
        <p> We not only want motherhood to be a conscious and controlled function but we want
            parenthood to be something other than the consequences of a reckless, careless
            shiftlessness. We want parenthood to be regarded as a fine commission, a noble trust, a
            splendid assignment, and it can be so considered only when it becomes a conscious
            responsibility. </p>
        <p> In the laws, which this bill, Senate 4582. will amend, contraceptive information has
            been classified with obscenity, pornography, and abortion. Information concerning
            contraception does not belong there. </p>
        <p>
            <name reg="Section 211 of the United States Penal Code">Section 211 of the criminal
                code</name> was passed by Congress in 1873 and at that time very little was known of
            the technique of contraception. Gradually knowledge of its importance has grown. The
            need for better information, for more scientific data on this important subject has been
            recognized. And there has gradually arisen in this country a movement in favor of birth
            control. We find to-day that parents consider birth control information not only a
            health measure, not alone an economic expedient, but a principle of social welfare by
            which the future advancement of the individual and the country itself is safeguarded. </p>
        <p> These laws which we are trying to amend have made no exception in their prohibitions for
            literature of a scientific character. Nor have they made an exception for the physician
            in his regular practice, or for hospitals or clinics, or for patients of these hospitals
            or clinics, or for the general and proper distribution of medical supplies. These laws
            have been the means of suppressing properly authorized scientific literature on the
            subject of contraception because no publisher will jeopardize his freedom or risk his
            reputation in publishing books when there is a law against their circulation. </p>
        <p> These laws interfere with the importation of articles, and of the results of research
            which is undertaken in other countries. Such data and such results of laboratory
            research would be of great assistance to the medical profession of his country in the
            proper functioning of their profession. </p>
        <p> These Federal laws interfere with the proper dissemination of information to prevent
            conception in 47 States of this Union although there are already laws in those States
            enabling physicians to give advice to patients in their regular practice, and there are
            in this country to-day over 50 legally operating birth control clinics distributed over
            12 states. These birth control clinics are medically established and medically directed,
            and have been organized solely for the purpose of giving contraceptive information by
            the medical profession. </p>
        <p> I should like, Mr. Chairman, if I may, to present for the record the names of the
            clinics, and their locations. </p>
        <q who="MSPP"><p> (The list appears at the conclusion of the day’s hearing.)</p></q>
        <p> And, also a summary of the laws of the various States concerning the subject. </p>
        <p> The bill that we are advocating asks that the Federal laws which it would amend shall
            not apply to any licenced physician or hospital or clinic when the desired information
            has been published in the agency, medical society, medical school, or medical journal,
            nor shall it apply to reprints after such publication. This bill also asks that the name
            and address of any physician, hospital, or clinic where such birth-control advice is
            legally given may be sent through the mails. Under the laws now, especially section 211
            of the Criminal Code, it is a crime for me or for anyone to send to a mother, a sister,
            or relative situated in any of these States the address of any clinic lawfully operating
            in that State, even though such an individual may be poverty stricken or diseased, even
            though she may have a right under that State law to have this information for her health
            and for her family happiness. The Federal law makes it a crime for anyone to send
            through the <org reg="United States Postal Service">United States mail</org> the address
            of a physician or a clinic where such information may be obtained. This bill asks that
            there be an exception in these cases. </p>
        <p> Mr. Chairman, we believe that this bill as presented is constructive, logical, and
            conservative. There is nothing in this bill which makes it mandatory or compels anyone
            to use this knowledge of contraception. There is nothing in this bill which makes any
            physician read such or which makes anyone apply for such literature, but we do ask for
            the thousands, and even hundreds of thousands, of mothers who in many cases are
            inarticulate to ask this for themselves; we ask that these mothers have the right to go
            to their physician, to apply to their hospitals or clinics, and get proper scientific
            information suitable for their individual requirements. </p>
        <p> We want no wholesale distribution of indecency or pornography or obscenity. This bill,
            which we are advocating to-day, as it is presented, leaves the law exactly as it was,
            except that we remove the subject of the prevention of conception from the clause
            relating to indecency, obscenity, and pornography, and place it in the hands of the
            medical profession, where it rightfully belongs. </p>
        <p> Most of us believe that the original object of these laws was to prevent the
            dissemination of pornographic literature through the United States mails and to restrict
            its entrance into this country. We fully concur in the prevention of the distribution of
            pornographic or obscene literature. We believe, however, that is it unfair to classify
            medical and scientific information or literature in this class and to do so places a
            great hardship upon the general practice of the medical progression and upon our welfare
            agencies. The effect of keeping these laws on our statute books is to increase the
            surreptitious circulation of unscientific or harmful information which tends to increase
            crime and to multiply abortions. </p>
        <p> The laws, in effect, have already been responsible for a great deal of harm, and I think
            if we could measure the injury that has been done to women, and were aware of their
            damaged conditions, physiologically and mentally, the harm far outweighs the good that
            these laws have accomplished. </p>
        <p> It is roughly estimated that since this law was established in 1873 over 1,500,000
            mothers have passed out into the great beyond from causes due to child bearing, and we
            know today that the subject of contraception is intimately associated with the deaths of
            mothers and affects our maternal mortality. </p>
        <p> It is also roughly estimated that, since that law was passed, over 15,000,000 children
            have passed out of life during their first year of infancy, many of them were children
            born in conditions of poverty and their mothers’ ill health. A great majority of them
            may have been living to-day had their mothers had a chance to recuperate from the ordeal
            of previous pregnancy instead of using up the vitality of the child before it was born. </p>
        <p> We, Mr. Chairman, believe that the effect of keeping these laws on the statute book is
            to keep alive hypocrisy, evasion, and a general increasing disregard for laws. We
            believe that there is nothing to be gained by keeping such laws on the statute books
            when they are known to be inimical to the personal health of mothers, to the family
            happiness, and to the general welfare and progress of <place reg="United States">the
                Nation</place>. </p>
        <p> Mr. Chairman, may I also present some of the protests of the medical profession, medical
            associations, and other organizations against such laws?</p>
        <p> Mrs. Sanger: I would like to make a few remarks. There has been misrepresentation
            expressed here his morning based upon a certain undated circular, sent broadcast to
            various organizations, within the past week or two by an organization represented here
            this morning, the <org>National Catholic Welfare Council</org> or Conference. It has
            been the cause of a great deal of malicious confusion, and first I want to read into the
            record a letter from the <org>Bureau of Jewish Social Research</org> of <place
                reg="New York, NY">New York City</place> in answer to this circular. It is directed
            to one of the representatives who sent it, and the letter, of which I have a copy, reads
            as follows: </p>
        <q who="BURHI"><p> Mr. <person reg="Burton, Hiram Ralph">Burton</person>: I think we should
                know what the statement is that was made by the National Catholic Welfare Council.
            </p></q>
        <q who="GILFR"><p> Senator Gillett: Does that statement appear there?</p></q>
        <p> Mrs. Sanger: I have it here .It is an official statement by the National Catholic
            Welfare Council. </p>
        <q who="GILFR"><p> Senator Gillett: That may be filed then. </p></q>
        <p> Mrs. Sanger: It is far too long to quote it. </p>
        <p> The reply to the circular is as follows: </p>
        <q who="MSPP"><p>(The reply to the circular has been omitted.</p></q>
        <p> Mr. Chairman, that letter represents the feeling on the part of a very large number of
            social organizations from whom we also have heard. I have not attempted to enter the
            statements into the record because yesterday the chairman stated that he would not
            include all of the letters that were sent on the subject. </p>
        <p> Just as briefly as I can I should like to comment on the discussion that went on this
            morning. </p>
        <p> The inference has been, and it has been constantly stated, that the bill that we are
            proposing would open the United States mails and common carriers to pornographic and
            obscene literature. The circular to which reference has been made included such a
            statement. I deny that allegation. I think that such statements wilfully misrepresent
            what this bill specifically intends to do. It is untrue to say that the bill would
            practically remove all existing restriction. We only ask that the medical profession in
            this country should have the right to receive contraceptive articles and literature, and
            that medical journals should have the right to issue such articles, which are almost
            always of a scientific nature. I should think that the medical profession would resent
            the statements made here this morning that the articles which we are asking to have
            legally sent through the United States mails are articles that might be designated as
            pornographic and obscene. I should think that was and should be considered an insult to
            the profession. </p>
        <p> I want to read to you two of the resolutions that have been passed by branches or
            departments of the <org>American Medical Association</org>. The American Medical
            Association itself has not taken a stand on this bill, but I wish to point out that two
            of its principal departments or sections have put themselves on record in favor of the
            principle of this kind of legislation. The first resolution was passed by the section on
            obstetrics, gynecology, and abdominal surgery at <place reg="Atlantic City, NJ">Atlantic
                City</place>, May 29, 1925: </p>
        <q who="AMA"><p> Resolved, That we hereby recommend the authorization of existing laws
                wherever necessary so that physicians may legally give contraceptive information to
                the patients in the regular course of practice. </p></q>
        <p> Further, the <org reg="American Gynecological and Obstetrical Society">American
                Gynecological Society</org> at the same time indorsed the following amendment to the
            existing Federal laws: “Standard medical works, standard medical and scientific
            journals, and reprints therefrom, which contain information with reference to the
            prevention of conception are not nonmaliable [non-malleable] under this section.” </p>
        <p> Now, Mr. Chairman, these are the two departments or sections of the American Medical
            Association most intimately concerned with the question of contraception, with child
            bearing, and with mothers’ and womens’ health. </p>
        <p> When the <org>American Federation of Labor</org> went on record, as far as the letter
            read this morning was concerned, you will note that it referred to a bill of 1925, a
            bill that was not sponsored by the committee that supports Senate bill 4582 now. This is
            the first time that this bill has ever been introduced in the Senate, and the opposition
            of the Federation of Labor, according to the letter and the statement made here this
            morning, was directed to another kind of bill entirely. This bill, as you will see, asks
            only that the medical profession, medical books, journals and reprints therefrom, and
            articles designed for the prevention of conception, used by the medical profession in
            hospitals, clinics, and so forth, shall have the right to use the United States mails
            and common carriers. </p>
        <p> The circular sent out by the National Catholic Welfare Conference may have been
            responsible for the confusion as it stated that the bill was drafted and introduced at
            the request of the <org>Voluntary Parenthood League</org>. That statement is untrue.
            This bill is sponsored by the Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control, and it
            has not been endorsed by the Voluntary Parenthood League at all. </p>
        <p> Now, Mr. Chairman, if I may just briefly take a little time to go through some of the
            other points that were made this morning, just the essential points, I will not take a
            great deal of your time. </p>
        <p> Mrs. Sanger: Dr. <person reg="Cattell, Henry">Henry Cattell</person> referred to certain
            contraceptive materials this morning. He called them “Sanger Pro-Tex Tubes,” and the
            implication was that I sponsored the devices named. I have never sanctioned nor given
            permission for the use of my name nor indorsed any article on contraception. Nor have I
            allowed the use of my name for any commercial purposes whatsoever, and I protest against
            the statement and the insinuation that certain devices and medical supplies have my name
            or my sanction. Something was said here this morning about the <org
                reg="Government of the Soviet Union">Soviet Government of Russia</org> approving of
            birth control. That is immaterial, absolutely immaterial. The whole birth-control
            movement was begun in this country in 1914 before there was a Soviet Government, and
            indeed I feel highly complimented if we have been able to bring sane, safe, and
            constructive ideas about the control of population to the Soviet Government. </p>
        <p> I want to say also that not only governments like Russia, but the <org
                reg="Government of the United Kingdom">British Government</org> has also gone on
            record through certain of its departments as approving of the practice of birth control.
            Just within the last year the <org>Lambeth Conference</org> in <place>England</place>
            sanctioned the right of individuals to practice birth control according to their
            conscience. </p>
        <p> The <org>British Medical Association</org> has also gone on record in favor and the <org
                reg="United Kingdom Department of Health">Ministry of Health</org> in England has
            approved the practice of allowing the patients who come to the maternal and infant
            welfare centers to have contraceptive advice by Government authority, so that all
            governments are seeking some solution to this question of population. </p>
        <p> I also want to say, Mr. Chairman, that we who are advocating this bill are trying to do
            away with the surreptitious and harmful information that is at present being spread
            around the country without being authorized, or controlled by experts who have the right
            to give it. I believe that the only way to do away with the harmful information which
            has been mentioned here this morning is to put the subject in the hands of medical
            profession to be properly controlled. </p>
        <p> When some one says that the happiest families are the largest ones, and that the world’s
            great leaders have been large families, I would like to all to your attention that the
            great leader of Christianity, <name type="diety">Jesus Christ</name> himself, was said
            to be an only child. </p>
        <p> Now, Mr. Chairman, I am not going to take much time, but I want to say that the
            controversy really concerns the question of differing methods of birth control. The
            method of self-control recommended by some of those who are here to-day, is open to
            them. They may use such methods. We are not imposing any method upon any individuals.
            There are said to be 120,000,000 people in this country, and I suppose that a large part
            of that number, perhaps 15,000,000, we will say to be generous, or even 20,000,000. are
            Catholics, but there are 105,000,000 left who are non-Catholics. They are not imposing
            any legislation upon the Catholics. We in no way try to inflict our ideas upon them.
            They have a perfect right to use the method of self-control if they wish, but we do
            believe that we have just as much right under the Constitution to enjoy health, peace,
            and the right to the pursuit of happiness as we see it. </p>
        <p> So I want to say that this whole group this morning, who have represented perhaps
            certain moral organizations of the country, seem to me to be like the boy who is
            whistling to keep up courage. No doubt there has been a falling away from grace, we
            might say, in the past several years, and they who represent such moral standards must
            see that they have failed to a considerable extent when we consider that they have had
            so much power. They have had the laws with them, the wealth, the press, and yet they
            have come to-day to say they are afraid of the morals of their people if they have
            knowledge, if they do not continue to be kept in fear and ignorance. Then I say their
            moral teachings are not very deep. </p>
        <p> I want to say just one thing further. We have birth-control clinics that are legally
            operating throughout the United States, and in almost every one of the birth-control
            clinics we have the same records. Women come to us, regardless of religion, desperate
            women, women trying to live decently, trying to avoid the conditions that unwanted
            pregnancy and too frequent pregnancy bring. These women come in equal proportions. It
            runs about 33 per cent Protestant, 32 per cen Catholics, and 31 per cent Jewish women.
            They all come with the same cry, “Give us a chance to space our children. It is not that
            we do not love children, because we do love them; but because we want to give them a
            better chance than we have had, and we know that another child born into this family
            only deprives the children that are already here of a decent living with the ideals that
            we have for them.”</p>
        <p> Further, when you get 500 Catholic women in one clinic, with confessions of 597
            abortions, Mr. Chairman, I say that it is time for us all to consider this problem
            intelligently. It is time for us all to consider a fundamental need, the fundamental
            question that is involved here. Catholic women are no different from any other women. It
            is all the same. The great majority of women who come to birth-control clinics are
            seeking some means of controlling the size of their family because heretofore they have
            had to resort to these harmful methods. This is what we are trying to eliminate. We are
            trying to save mothers from this great hardship, from this unnatural ordeal. In the past
            many women who desired to control the size of their families have had to resort to an
            interruption of pregnancy, a method of which we disapprove, and which this law is going
            to do away with eventually, I am quite certain. </p>
        <p> Mr. Chairman, we say that we want children conceived in love, born of parents’ conscious
            desire, and born into the world with healthy and sound bodies and sound minds. </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
