<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2001-10-29 MH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2002-08-22 KH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/02 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/08/13 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007-05-30 CH Oxygen cleanup</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/03/11 CH Entered corrections suggested by Andy Carloff.</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-12 CH clean regs </prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1912-02-18">18 Feb 1912</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>The Fighting Women of Lawrence</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp304679</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">New York Call</title>, Feb. 18, 1912</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm </title>, C16:19</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
        <p>An editor's note at the top of the article identified <person reg="Sanger, Margaret"
                >Sanger</person> as one of the committee who brought the striker's children to
                <place reg="New York, NY">New York</place>.</p>
        <index level1="working classes" level2="revolution and"/>
        <index level1="working classes" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="labor movement" level2="Lawrence, MA Strike, 1912"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>The Fighting Women of Lawrence</head>
        <byline>By Margaret H. Sanger.</byline>
        <p>To those who witnessed the scene at <org>Grand Central Station</org>, Saturday night,
            when the children of the <place reg="Lawrence, MA">Lawrence</place> strikers came from
            the trains, it was a demonstration not soon to be forgotten. </p>
        <p>Thousands of men and women stood waiting for the little ones to come, and many had been
            waiting since early in the afternoon, so when at last they did appear in the evening
            their enthusiasm knew no bounds. Shouting, cheering with tears in their eyes, hundreds
            of these men broke through the ropes. Tearing off their own coats they wrapped them
            around the cold and ragged little bodies, placed them upon their shoulders, and marched
            on with the throng.</p>
        <p>Everywhere were men with tears streaming down their faces, tears of joy and gladness at
            this wonderful demonstration of working class solidarity; at this glorious slap in the
            face to capitalists in general, and charity organizations in particular; at this great
            fact that no matter what our nationality or creed, no matter what our methods of gaining
            our goal, the working class will take care of its own. Italian men carried Polish
            children, German men carried Italian children; Scotch, English, Polish, Italians and
            French, were one and all carried upon the shoulders of class-conscious men, who felt
            only that every child was a workingman's offspring, and as such has to be tended and
            cherished.</p>
        <p>The children of these strikers have been reared in an atmosphere of class-consciousness
            and solidarity. "<title type="song">THE INTERNATIONAL</title>" IS THEIR SONG.</p>
        <p>At <place reg="Boston, MA">Boston</place> while waiting for the train to New York, the
            French children sang the "<title type="song">International</title>" in their native
            tongue. After they had finished the Italian children sang the same song in their
            language with fervor and emphasis.</p>
        <p>So sweet were their childish voices, so fervent was their singing, that hundreds of
            people gathered about them to inquire what this song was and the meaning of it. </p>
        <p>Here was the REAL demonstration, greater even of love, solidarity, class-consciousness,
            heroism, self-sacrifice than was shown at their arrival. Mothers pressed their children
            to their hearts, clasping them with all the tenderness and love of a mother king: kissed
            them and passed them on to the train. Every child a woman picked up to place on the
            train, she kissed and caressed as lovingly as her own before it was passed on. The
            French women especially were an example of heroism, devotion and self-sacrifice. Tears
            in their eyes, but relief in their hearts, they waved their hands, shouted and cheered
            as the train moved slowly away. They were brave, they were firm, they knew the cost to
            them all--should they lose that strike. Better anything than that terrible cry of hunger
            in a mother's ears. Nothing is so sure to weaken a father's resolve as that cry.</p>
        <p>The mothers know this well, and were thankful and relieved that some of their children
            would be cared for until the strike is won. They all feel stronger in their spirit and
            more cheer in their hearts to fight this fight to the finish--to fight this monster who
            has been feeding upon the blood of these workers, and is only waiting to feed upon their
            children as soon as they are able to trot to the mills. They know what a future is in
            store for their children unless they win this strike.</p>
        <p><person reg="Unknown">One Italian mother</person> expressed this in her broken way,
            saying: "<q who="UNK">Good-a-lady, taka my boy--by a by all happy.</q>"</p>
        <p>In the station at Boston an <person reg="Unknown">elderly man</person> came up to inquire
            why these children should be sent to New York City. He informed a few of his listeners
            that "<q>good old <place>Massachusetts</place> could take care of her children,</q>" and
            seemed incensed and hurt that New York City should intrude to feed, and clothe the
            children of "<soCalled>good old Massachusetts</soCalled>."</p>
        <p>A <person reg="Unknown">French woman</person> who came down as far as Boston to assist
            with the children and get them across the city on to the train for New York was also in
            the gathering and stood this just as long as she could. Then she turned on the poor old
            patriot with all the fierceness of a tigress defending her young.</p>
        <p>Over and over again, first in one language then another, they sang their song of
            INTERNATIONAL FREEDOM.</p>
        <p>The first plans had been that the parents bring the children to the large meeting hall at
            noon, but upon later information it was found train connections could not be made to get
            the youngsters into New York until very late at night, so a change of plans had to be
            made. Late at night men and women were sent scurrying about from house to house to tell
            the parents of the change and to bring the children to the halls at 8 o'clock in the
            morning. For many mothers this was impossible, and they decided to keep the children
            until a later date, when other little ones will go. Others, however, were so pressed for
            food and clothing that they were compelled to accommodate themselves to these plans, and
            through the biting cold they trudged to save the children from starvation.</p>
        <p>At the hall the co-operative kitchen was running in full blast. Here the little ones had
            hot milk and coffee, and what other food was available. Too excited to eat much, their
            breakfast was very scant, but large boxes of sandwiches and fruit were sent out by the
            co-operative kitchen and large cans of milk and coffee to be taken on the train.</p>
        <p>At the Lawrence station many parents were already there with children. Fearing to miss
            the train, they did not go to the hall, but brought the children straight to the
            station.</p>
        <p>Though it registered several degrees below zero, there were hundreds at the station to
            see the children safely on the train. Each child had its name, address, age and
            nationality on a paper pinned to its cap or coat, a duplicate of which was in a book of
            the secretary. Every child also wore a white ribbon tied to its coat, which helped to
            keep an eye on them and distinguish them from other youngsters, if the papers should be
            lost or torn off.</p>
        <p>"<q who="UNK">Sure,</q>" she said. "<q who="UNK">Good old Massachusetts! ha, ha!
                Massachusetts send soldiers to shoot children's fathers. Massachusetts say to
                fathers, 'You work, work, all day you work.' Fathers say,'No more I work and
                children hungry.' Massachusetts say, 'Then we shoot!' Good old Massachusetts, ha,
                ha! </q>" She snapped her fingers in his face and walked away.</p>
        <p>Needless to say the reverend gentleman left the station rather hurriedly. Perhaps he had
            enough of such heresy, or perhaps he saw the glaring eyes and angry expressions of the
            men and women who were anxiously waiting to express their views on the generosity of
                "good old Massachusetts."</p>
        <p>At any rate, there were several other patriots who also were there to defend his views,
            and they had the benefit of these looks and expressions. But when the collection basket
            was passed around these patriotic gentlemen could not be found.</p>
        <p>It was surprising to hear the women of different nationalities, Italians, Polish and
            French, apparently unable to speak or understand English, when an opportunity came to
            defend their class, got on their feet in a moment, and with all the bitterness of their
            hearts and the eloquence of their broken English they put many cock-sure gentlemen to
            shame at their own ignorance and stupidity. Always with fire in their eyes and courage
            and solidarity in their hearts, their English served them well and had more effect on
            the listeners than the polished English of the educated Bostonians.</p>
        <p>These children and women of the Lawrence strikers could teach the working class of our
            city much in the line of solidarity. They breath it and act it and live it. What could
            be grander than that children be taught international solidarity? The teachers of this
            spirit are fighting one of the greatest battles of this day.</p>
        <p>On with the fight, Comrades, you cannot lose!</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
