<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
<mepHeader>
<prepDate>2003-11-24 ML</prepDate>
<prepDate>2014-03-04 CH correct regs</prepDate>
<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
<docDate value="1925-03-25
"><supplied>25 Mar 1925</supplied></docDate>
<docTitle>
<titlePart><supplied>Address of Welcome, <title>Sixth International Neo-Malthusian and Birth Control
Conference</title></supplied></titlePart>
</docTitle>
<idno>msp305432</idno>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl><title type="book">"International Aspects of Birth Control", Proceedings of the Sixth
International Neo-Malthusian and Birth Control Conference,</title>(<place reg="New York, NY">New
York</place>,1925) 3-8</bibl>
<bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Papers Microfilm, Collected Documents Series</title>, C16:241</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</mepHeader>
<headNote resp="MSPP"><p><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person> gave this speech to
open the <org>Sixth International Neo-Malthusian and Birth Control Conference</org> at the
<org>Hotel McAlpin</org> in New York City. For a draft version see LCM 128:267.</p>
<index level1="Drysdale, Charles Vickery"/>
<index level1="England" level2="birth control in"/>
<index level1="Malthusian League"/>
<index level1="conferences" level2="International Neo-Malthusian and birth Control Conference"
level3="1925 (6th)"/>
<index level1="United States" level2="birth control in"/>
</headNote>
<docBody>
<head>Address of Welcome</head>
<byline>by Margaret Sanger<lb/>President of <org>American Birth Control League</org></byline>
<p>Mr. President and Delegates:</p>
<p>In the name of the American Birth Control League I welcome you to <place reg="United States"
>America</place> and to the Sixth International Neo-Malthusian and Birth Control Conference. I am
proud of this privilege. For the first time in the history of these United States men and women have
come from other countries to these shores to consider the population problem. Such a conference as
we now inaugurate is unique in our experience and in our national history. It is, moreover, fitting
that it should meet here in the center of our greatest city. For almost a century ago- just ninety-
five years, to be exact- <person reg="Owens, Robert Dale">Robert Dale Owen</person> published <emph
rend="italics">in this city</emph> his brief and plain treatise on the population question and birth
control, entitled "<title type="book">Moral Physiology</title>." And only two years afterward, in
1832, Dr. <person reg="Knowlton, Charles">Charles Knowlton</person> published in <place
reg="Boston, MA">Boston</place> his epoch-making "<title type="book">Fruits of Philosophy</title>."
His little book wandered for forty years around the world. It was translated into several languages.
It was reprinted again and again. Its circulation was at fist unmolested. In 1857, it was edited and
revised <person reg="Drysdale, Charles Vickery">Mr. President</person>, by your courageous
uncle,<person reg="Drysdale, George">George R. Drysdale</person>. Its circulation in <place>Great
Britain</place> led finally to the historic trial of Mrs. <person reg="Besant, Annie">Annie
Besant</person> and <person reg="Bradlaugh, Charles">Charles Bradlaugh</person>. This was just a
little less than half a century ago. This little book, written by a courageous American, republished
by courageous Englishmen, became internationally famous, and was instrumental in the founding of the
first Neo-Malthusian leagues, by <person reg="Drysdale, Charles R.">Charles R. Drysdale</person> and
<person reg="Vickery, Alice">Alice Drysdale Vickery</person>, our honorary president, and the
illustrious, courageous parents of the president of this conference, whom we welcome here today.</p>
<p>We welcome you to the presidency of this Conference, Dr. Drysdale, fully aware of the honor you
confer upon us. You come here as the living representative of a family of indomitable heroes and
founders of the Neo-Malthusian and Birth Control movement. your presence links this gathering with
that great historic movement for racial salvation which began with <person
reg="Malthus, Thomas Robert">Robert Malthus</person> himself. Without the unselfish, disinterested
courage of your father and mother, and your self-effacing uncle, we would not be gathered here
to-night. I wish to thank you for the honor you have conferred upon us, in crossing the Atlantic, to
act as president of this Conference. We look upon this act of generosity as a sign that you consider
us worthy to keep alive and to carry on the torch of Neo-Malthusian truth, which for three quarters
of a century has so nobly been held aloft by the heroic Drysdale family. May we in America who
ourselves worthy of the Drysdale tradition!</p>
<p>To delegates from all foreign countries, I wish to extend a welcome no less grateful. I want also
to apologize-- if I may do so without any disrespect–- for the obstacles you have had to meet, the
obstructions placed in your way by some of the rules and regulations of our American government. Not
being familiar with all our customs, perhaps you do not know that the government of the United
States has enacted laws aiming to exclude from this country all "undesirable" foreigners. These
laws, like all such restrictive legislation, make it difficult for all foreigners to pass unmolested
our famous Statue of Liberty. There is a <emph rend="italics">Quota</emph> restriction. Only so many
foreigners from each country are allowed to enter each month. No: this is not Birth Control, though
it is a crude method adopted by the United States to <emph rend="italics">control</emph> our
population. It is the latest method adopted by our Government to solve the population problem. And
so you delegates from foreign countries have been made the innocent victims of an unsuccessful
attempt of the <org reg="United States Government">American Government</org> to cut down the number
of "undesirable" citizens. I am glad that you have overcome these obstacles. As convinced
Neo-Malthusians I knew you would. I welcome you to this Conference.</p>
<p>While the United States shuts her gates to foreigners, and is less hospitable than other
countries in welcoming visitors to this land no attempt whatever is made to discourage the rapid
multiplication of undesirable aliens--and natives--within our own borders. On the contrary: the
Government fo the United States deliberately encourages and even makes necessary by its laws the
breeding-- with a breakneck rapidity--of idiots, defectives, diseased, feeble minded and criminal
classes.</p>
<p>Billions of dollars are expended by our state and federal governments and by private charities
and philanthropies for the care, the maintenance, and the perpetuation of these classes. Year by
year their numbers are mounting. Year by year more money is expended. The American public is taxed-
heavily taxed- to maintain an increasing race of morons which threatens the very foundations of our
civilization. More than <emph rend="italics">one-quarter</emph> of the total incomes of our States
is spent upon the maintenance of asylums, prisons and other institutions for the care of the
defective, the diseased and the delinquent. Do not conclude however, that all of our feeble-minded
and mentally defective are segregated in institutions. No, indeed. This is a free country, a
democratic country, a country of universal suffrage. We can all vote, even the mentally arrested.
And so it is no surprise to find the morons vote as good as the geniuses. The outlook is not a
cheerful one.</p>
<p>You, friends from foreign countries who have come here to our greatest city, must have noticed
the intricate systems of signals which regulates the crowded traffic in our streets and
thoroughfares. By this system, the pedestrian is assured some degree of safety. But while the
congestion of American population in our cities has forced upon us a system to regulate traffic in
city streets and country roads, America as a nation refuses to open her eyes to the problem of
biological traffic and racial roads. Biologically this country is "joy-riding" with reckless
carelessness to an inevitable smash-up. Is it too late to prevent national destruction? This
question we must face- and answer.</p>
<p><place>France</place> is making a vain attempt to increase her population by awarding bonuses to
those parents who will produce large families. The day is here when the Government of the United
States should award bonuses to discourage large families. If the United States were to expand some
of its vast appropriations on a system of bonuses to decrease or to restrict the incessant and
uninterrupted advent of the hordes of the unfit, we might look forward to the future of this country
with less pessimism. If the millions upon millions of dollars which are now expended in the care and
maintenance of those who in all kindness should never have been brought into this world were
converted to a system of bonuses to unfit parent, paying them to refrain from further parenthood,
and continuing to pay them while they controlled their procreative faculties, this would not only be
a profitable investment, but the salvation of American civilizations. If we could, by such a system
fo awards or bribes or whatever you choose to call it, discourage the reproduction of the obviously
unfit, we would be lightening the economic and social burden now hindering the progress of the fit,
and would be taking the first sensible step toward the solution of one of the most menacing problems
of the American democracy. It is not too late to begin. </p>
<p>From the moment this gathering was planned, it has been my deepest desire that this Sixth
International Conference, brief as it must necessarily be, might be made a real turning point in the
never ending battle for human emancipation. Let us, all of us from other countries and from other
fields, aim to convert these few crowded house into an assembly of world importance. Let us aim to
carry on the great tradition of honesty, courage, and bravery which is so nobly personifies for us
in the figure of our president,Charles Vickery Drysdale. Let us express our innermost convictions.
Let us not fear opposition, nor the sharp clash of opinion. Apathy, not opposition, is the only real
enemy of truth. And it is truth and the love of truth that has brought all of us here together. Let
none of us be afraid to express his truth, to bring it in to play in this conference, for we must
not forget that it is the truth which is going to set us free. I hope we do arouse opposition. For
in arousing opposition, are killing apathy and lethargy. It is my hope that this conference will be
instrumental in lighting and spreading the fire of truths so illuminating they cannot be
extinguished.</p>
<p>You, Dr. Drysdale, and you; delegates from older and wiser countries than this; you do not wear
decorations or medals. But I know that all of you hide the scars of wounds won in our never-ending
warfare for the emancipation of the human race. I welcome you. And to all of you, my fellow
citizens, who have so generously responded to our call and have cooperated with us in our effort to
make this conference of international as well as national significance, I extend the warmest welcome
of the American Birth Control League. And I know that all of you join me in welcoming to the
presidency of the Sixth International Neo-Malthusian and Birth Control Conference our President,
Charles Vickery Drysdale.</p>
</docBody>
</doc>
