<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2010/03/02 AC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-11 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1935-04-11">Standard Date</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Family Planning: A Radio Talk</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp306297</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title>, C16:0380</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="birth control"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="economic benefits and risks of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits and risks"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="in marriages"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"
            level3="negative consequences of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Comstock act"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Federal"/>
        <index level1="child spacing"/>
        <index level1="child welfare"/>
        <index level1="children" level2="unwanted"/>
        <index level1="family size" level2="class-based"/>
        <index level1="infant mortality rate"/>
        <index level1="motherhood"/><index level1="mortality rates" level2="maternal"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="government" level3="public health programs"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Family Planning</head>
        <byline>A Radio Talk By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
            <org reg="Columbia Broadcasting System">Columbia Broadcasting System</org>, <org>Station
                W.A.B.C.</org>, <place reg="New York, NY">New York</place>, April 11, 1935</byline>
        <p>YOU have heard a great deal about National Security through National Planning. The time
            has come for us to think of Family Security through Family Planning.</p>
        <p> Every good housewife accepts the idea of planning for the comfort of her household. She
            plans her budget to meet the necessities of food, clothing and shelter, of education and
            recreation. She tries to plan for sickness and unemployment, and for the comforts of
            life in old age. But there is still another factor, which is vitally important for the
            security of the family and the security of the nation as well. One other kind of
            planning, the most important of all, must not be overlooked, if a family is to have
            health and security, is to bring up happy children to become useful citizens. This is
            planning for the number of children, and for the spacing of their births in accordance
            with the health of the mother, the earning power of the father, and the standard of
            living for all.</p>
        <p> In order to space the arrival of the children so that they will not come too close
            together, in order to have no more children than can be safely born and adequately
            reared, mothers must have reliable, scientific birth control instruction.</p>
        <p> There has recently been a great deal of confusion about what birth control is. There has
            been a lot of loose talk about birth control “operations.” There is no such thing as a
            birth control operation. Remember this: birth control means to prevent, not to destroy.
            It does not mean the destruction of life after it has begun.</p>
        <p> Every normal woman, every normal man wants children. The joys of parenthood are joys
            which every married couple want to experience. But there is a vast difference between a
            woman wanting two, three or four children that she can adequately care for, and the
            dread of having a family of ten or twelve without being able to give them food and
            clothing, let alone education and a start in life.</p>
        <p> Every father has a right to knowledge which will permit him to plan his family in
            accordance with how many children he can support. If the father’s wages remain
            stationary, as is all to apt to happen now-a-days, and the babies continue to come year
            after year, no planning is possible. No family can feel secure when this condition
            prevails.</p>
        <p> There are many things to be considered in planning the size of the family, but there are
            three very important and obvious ones that should have special attention:</p>
        <p>
            <emph rend="italics">First, the mother’s health</emph>: No woman should attempt to bring
            a baby into the world if she is suffering from tuberculosis or a heart of kidney
            disease. These are diseases which usually can be cured, if taken in time, and if they
            are not complicated by pregnancy. It is unfair to put upon a frail woman, with any of
            these ailments, the further task of motherhood. It is also unfair to the father and to
            the unborn child.</p>
        <p>
            <place reg="United States">America</place> is the only country in the world, with modern
            medical care, that has laws keeping contraceptive knowledge from mothers suffering from
            these diseases. This is, in large part, why we have a high maternal mortality rate, and
            we shall doubtless continue to have it until mothers have knowledge of birth control,
            and can use this knowledge to protect their health.</p>
        <p> S<emph rend="italics">econd, the father’s earning power</emph>: This is a very obvious
            consideration, and yet millions of parents today who are on relief rolls and are unable
            to provide for the children already born, cannot get information about how to control
            the number of their children. Approximately four million families are on general relief,
            and the birth rate is higher in these families than among those of the same social
            status among the employed.</p>
        <p> Think of these parents, already burdened with poverty and debts, fearful of the future.
            The mothers are depleted and exhausted from too frequent childbearing. They cannot look
            forward with any hope, because they cannot meet the uncertainties which large families
            entail. And what about the children? What is to become of them? Millions of them are
            physically or mentally handicapped to meet the difficulties of life, yet they continue
            to arrive regardless of the parents’ ability to provide for them.</p>
        <p>
            <emph rend="italics">Third, child spacing</emph>: Even a healthy mother should space the
            births of her children at intervals of not less than two years, preferably three. Only
            in this way can she fully regain her strength and vitality after childbirth, and be a
            fit mother for the children already born and for those to come. Studies made by the <org
                reg="United States Children's Bureau">United States Children’s Bureau</org> show
            that children born one year apart die at the rate of 147 per thousand, while children
            born at two year intervals have a death rate of only 92 per thousand. Maternal mortality
            rates also show the dangers of too many pregnancies and too closely spaced
            childbirths.</p>
        <p> The Federal laws which class birth control information with obscenity and which forbid
            the sending of birth control information or supplies by mail or common carrier, were
            passed sixty-two years ago. They keep mothers, especially the poor mothers, who are most
            in need of birth control information, who more than all others <emph rend="italics"
                >should</emph> and <emph rend="italics">wish</emph> to have smaller families, in
            absolute ignorance of reliable information. No such restrictive laws exist in
                <place>England</place>, or in <place reg="Netherlands">Holland</place>,
                <place>Denmark</place>, <place>Norway</place>, <place>Sweden</place> or <place
                reg="Soviet Union">Russia</place>. Why should <org reg="United States Congress"
                >Congress</org>, on the basis of laws passed in 1873, continue to deny to American
            mothers the rights enjoyed by mothers in these countries?</p>
        <p>
            <org>The National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control</org>, of which I
            am the president, is fighting to change these laws. We want hospitals, clinics, public
            health agencies and doctors to be able to give parents harmless, safe and reliable birth
            control information. Only in this way can they have the number of children they want and
            are able to care for, can they properly space the arrival of their babies. Only in this
            way can they have Family Security.</p>
        <p> The Federal laws work tremendous hardship on the mothers of America. It is the poorest
            women who pay. They pay for their ignorance in ill health, in infant deaths, in maternal
            deaths. They pay for it in slums, in child labor, in unemployment. They pay by living in
            constant fear and anxiety, fear of the coming of children whom they have neither the
            strength nor means to bring up.</p>
        <p> The mothers of the poor, particularly the mothers in the millions of families on relief
            are the <emph rend="italics">forgotten women</emph>. They are too poor to have
            influence, too weak to rebel. They cry out to us for help. If you would help the
            forgotten woman, if you are in sympathy with the work I am doing, help me change the
            Federal law. We have at present two bills before Congress, which would amend these laws
            so that birth control clinics for the poor could be included in the government Public
            Health Program.</p>
        <p> We are preparing a petition to President <person rend="Roosevelt, Franklin D."
                >Roosevelt</person>, asking him to recommend to Congress the passage of these bills.
            Add your name to the thousands upon thousands who want to get rid of these obsolete
            laws. Help the mothers of America free themselves. </p>


    </docBody>
</doc>
