<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2003/06/09 SB</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2003/08/07 CH Index</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/26 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/08/09 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007/06/25/CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2001/03/11 CH Entered corrections suggested by Andy Carloff.</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-18 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1916-04-00">
            <supplied>Apr 1916</supplied>
        </docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>"The Woman Rebel" and The Fight for Birth Control</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp306320</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl> Records of the Joint Legislative Committee to Investigate Seditious Activities,
                New York State Archives</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title>, C16:1035</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="Woman Rebel, The " level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="Woman Rebel, the" level2="suppression of"/>
        <index level1="Woman Rebel, The" level2="legal case and"/>
        <index level1="working classes " level2="women and girls"/>
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Comstock Law"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="arrests"/>
        <index level1="obscenity"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, William" level2="arrest"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, William" level2="trial and imprisonment"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>"<title type="journal">The Woman Rebel</title>" and The Fight for Birth Control</head>
        <p>During fourteen years experience as a trained nurse, I found that a great percentage of
            women's diseases were due to ignorance of the means to prevent conception. I found that
            quackery was thriving on this ignorance, and that thousands of abortions were being
            performed each year-- principally upon the women of the working class. Since the laws
            deter reliable and expert surgeons from performing abortions, working women have always
            been thrown into the hands of the incompetent, with fatal results. The deaths from
            abortions mount very high.</p>
        <p>I found that physicians and nurses were dealing with these symptoms rather than their
            causes, and I decided to help remove the chief cause by imparting knowledge to prevent
            conception, in defiance of existing laws and their extreme penalty. I sent out a call to
            the proletarian women of <place reg="United States">America</place> to assist me in this
            work, and their answers came by the thousands. I started <title type="journal">The Woman
                Rebel</title> early in 1914. The first issue of the magazine was suppressed. Seven
            issues out of nine were suppressed, and although sent out as first-class mail, the
            editions were confiscated. The newspapers--even the most radical-- declined to give this
            official tyranny any publicity.</p>
        <p>In August, 1914, a Federal Grand Jury returned three indictments against me, based on
            articles in the March, May and July issues of <title type="journal">The Woman
                Rebel</title>. The articles branded as "obscene" merely discussed the question and
            contained no information how to prevent conception. But the authorities were anxious to
            forestall the distribution of this knowledge and knew that this could only be done by
            imprisoning me. I decided to avoid the imprisonment, at least until I had given out the
            information. One hundred thousand copies of a pamphlet, <title type="book">Family
                Limitation</title>, were prepared and distributed, and I sailed for
                <place>England</place>.</p>
        <p>I studied the question in England, <place reg="Netherlands">Holland</place>,
                <place>France</place> and <place>Spain</place>, and prepared three other pamphlets:
                <title type="book">English Methods of Birth Control</title>, <title type="book"
                >Dutch Methods of Birth Control</title>, and <title type="book">Magnetation Methods
                of Birth Control</title>.</p>
        <p>After these had been mailed to the United States, I returned to take up the fight with
            the authorities. The latter had, in the meantime, set a <person reg="Comstock, Anthony"
                >Comstock</person> trap for <person reg="Sanger, William">William Sanger</person>
            and railroaded him to jail for 30 days. Nevertheless they postponed my case time and
            again, although I was anxious to face the issue and get the decision of a jury. They
            noted the widespread agitation in favor of birth control. They saw that interest had
            been thoroughly aroused. Never had there been an issue that had so aroused the entire
            country. Letters at the rate of 40 to 50 a day poured in upon the authorities and
            educated them.</p>
        <p>Finally, it was decided by Federal Judge <person reg="Dayton, Alston G.">Dayton</person>,
            United States District Attorney <person reg="Marshall. H. Snowden">Marshall</person> and
            Assistant United States District Attorney <person reg="Content, Harold A."
                >Content</person> to acquit me, instead of allowing a jury to do it. This decision
            is fully as important a precedent for future work as the decision of a jury would have
            been. </p>
        <p>Hundreds of requests have been made to me to revive <title type="journal">The Woman
                Rebel</title>; but I feel that it has already accomplished its purpose--to arouse
            interest. Now more constructive work is needed, in meeting the people directly and
            interesting them in establishing free clinics in those sections where women are
            overburdened with large families.</p>
        <byline><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">MARGARET SANGER</person>, 163 Lexington Avenue,
                <place reg="New York, NY">New York, N.Y.</place></byline>
    </docBody>
</doc>
