<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Printed article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2003/06/30 SB</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2012/06/07 AW</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-04-10 CH clean regs</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-07 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1920-09-00">Sept 1920</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>London Birth Control Meetings</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp306621</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title>, Sept. 1920, pp. 7-8.</bibl>
			<bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Collected Documents Series</title>
				C16:144</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
			<name id="MARAN">Martin, Anna</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<index level1="birth control" level2="class-based"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="methods"/>
		<index level1="child welfare"/>
		<index level1="labor movement," level2="birth control and"/>
		<index level1="men" level2="birth control and"/>
		<index level1="motherhood"/>
		<index level1="physicians" level2="women"/>
		<index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="speaking tours" level3="1920 (U.K.)"/>
		<index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>LONDON BIRTH CONTROL MEETINGS</head>
		<p>On the night of June 29, I finished my <place reg="London, England">London</place>
			lectures for the time being. That meeting, the second under the auspices of the
				<org>Emily Davidson Club</org>, was perhaps the most thrilling and unusual of all
			because it was the first time practical preventive methods were explained and discussed
			publicly before an audience of both sexes. There were about sixty men and as many women
			present, the lecture having been advertised in a very small way and being given to
			compensate the men for having been turned away from a previous lecture given for women
			only.</p>
		<p>After I had discussed the theoretical and economic side of Birth Control a man of about
			thirty-five years, arose.</p>
		<p>"<q who="UNK">It's all very interesting and enlightening, what the lady speaker has told
				us</q>" he said, "<q who="UNK">but really I and others have come here on purpose to
				have her tell us what methods she advises us to use. Won't she tell us while we are
				here for that purpose?</q>"</p>
		<p>"<q who="UNK">Hear. Hear!</q>" cried part of the audience. "<q who="UNK">No! No!</q>"
			came from the others.</p>
		<p>"<q who="UNK">Let the men go out--let her talk to the women!</q>"</p>
		<p>"<q who="UNK">No, No!</q>" cried a man, "<q who="UNK">we have just as much right to know
				these things as the women!</q>"</p>
		<p>The men insistently demanded a vote upon the question. The chairman inquired if I were
			willing to address a mixed audience and I agreed, suggesting that those who did not wish
			to remain to hear the practical methods should depart while I continued the theoretical
			discussion. Only one couple left the room.</p>
		<p>The attitude of both men and women during the explanation of methods was one of ease,
			confidence and reverence for the subject which means so much in their everyday lives.
			Afterwards, six men came seeking advice on other problems, saying that if they had known
			Birth Control methods a few years earlier they would have been spared great unhappiness
			and would not now be carrying backbreaking burdens without the help of understanding
			spiritual advisers.</p>
		<p>Within less than six weeks I have given about twenty-two private lectures, reaching some
			twenty-five hundred women. All were working women, and all demanded and received
			information concerning the practical methods, which were discussed fully at each
			meeting.</p>
		<p>The subject is being discussed everywhere and information concerning contraceptives is
			spreading like wildfire among the workers. One can feel the increased and increasing
			interest. One indication is the requests that are pouring in for lectures before labor
			organizations and other bodies. If I accepted all these invitations, I should have to
			remain here at least a year, working constantly.</p>
		<p>The attitude toward Birth Control exhibited by various groups of people show some
			decidedly interesting contrasts. That of the working women may be described as
			"natural." They are <supplied resp="MSPP">vitally</supplied> interested and they demand
			the knowledge of Birth Control, receiving it eagerly. The professional social worker is
			more likely to suspend his or her common sense and exhibit a good deal of hypocrisy.
			This is especially true of the official Labor leaders and officials are prone to deny
			entirely the call to plain economic necessity of Birth Control. Many radicals, too,
			ignore this phase of the matter, especially the older ones, who are wedded to
			oft-repeated phrases. The younger people, however, are almost entirely convinced that
			there is much in the Birth Control movement and at least have their minds open to
			it.</p>
		<p> The fact that officialdom in labor circles and "social work" is strongly against the
			diminution of labor's misery is constantly shown by the arguments used in such groups
			against Birth Control. "<q who="UNK">Let 'em have all the children they can. It will
				bring on the revolution all the quicker</q>," said one spokesman of labor to me some
			weeks ago.</p>
		<p>"<q>Why do you fight for higher wages then</q>?" I asked, "<q>Why ask higher wages if you
				really want poverty and misery</q>?" </p>
		<p>He was silent at that, but he was forced to do some thinking just the same. On the other
			hand, the practical working man and the practical social worker are entirely in
			agreement with the practice of Birth Control and say so. But the official, the leader,
			turns a deaf ear to it.</p>
		<p>One of the <org reg="Bermondsey Settlment">groups</org> that is on the road to practical
			work on a very large scale is that under the direction of Mrs. <person
				reg="Martin, Anna">Anna Martin</person> at Rotherhithe. This is one of the most
			dilapidated and poverty-stricken districts of London. When, on June 22, I gave an
			informal address to Miss Martin's group there were present something over one hundred
			women from the neighborhood. I was surprised to learn that these women had small
			families--one or two, not more than three children. The explanation was that Dr. <person
				reg="Vickery, Alice">Alice Vickery</person> had visited the neighborhood some ten
			years previously and had instructed some of the intelligent women of the neighborhood in
			Birth Control methods. Some of the more prosperous of these women purchased the
			necessary contraceptives and furnished them to their poorer neighbors, who reimbursed
			them upon the installment plan. The result was smaller families and children growing up
			with more advantages, including better health.</p>
		<p>The benefits to the mothers were marked. These women were farther advanced than others
			who had been denied Birth Control information. They enjoyed a greater companionship with
			their husbands. They go to lectures; they have something of an intellectual life.</p>
		<p>Miss Martin is a magnificent example of courage and understanding. Her work reflects both
			in a tremendous degree.</p>
		<p>"<q who="MARAN">I must get the mothers early</q>," she said, in talking of the women of
			her neighborhood, "<q who="MARAN">If I do not get them soon after the birth of the first
				or second child, it is almost certain that I never will. When other babies come
				close together, they bring with them discouragement and lower standards of life, for
				both parents</q>."</p>
		<p>These women are well aware that family limitations enabled them to give their children a
			chance in life and to protect their own well being. There was in this group a frankness,
			during discussion of Birth Control methods, markedly absent from ll other groups that I
			have addressed in <place>England</place>. These women were self-reliant,
			self-respecting, and independent. They might have been spiritless drudges, mothers of
			huge, hopeless families, if it had not been for the work of Miss Martin and Dr.
			Vickery.</p>
		<p>One of the exceedingly interesting meetings was an "invitation" affair arranged by Mrs.
				<person reg="How-Martyn, Edith">Edith How Martin</person>, a widely known <org
				reg="Middlesex County Council">County Council</org> woman of <place
				reg="Middlesex, England">Middlesex</place> and Miss <person
				reg="Thompson, Louise M.">L. Thompson</person>. To this meeting came social workers,
			women physicians and the like. Many of the Labor women were unable to come because of
			the Labor Conference at <place reg="Scarborough, England">Scarborough</place>, which
			demanded their presence. The audience, as has often happened, was divided upon the
			question of contraceptives versus continence, except when procreation is desired and the
			chief advocate of the latter view was a woman physician, who in a strong speech declared
			that to be her method of Birth Control and who took exceptions to my address on the
			ground that I represented the "American view point," which she declared was that there
			is a high spiritual element in the sex relationship. "<q who="UNK">That idea will not go
				down in England</q>" she declared. Adjournment, taken when the meeting had run long
			past its time cut short a storm of protest against this view. It was not until later
			that I go the full significance of the meeting. Ten women wrote me saying that they can
			now see the futility of alleviative measures and asking if there is a place for them in
			the Birth Control movement. Others write saying that economic necessity keeps them in
			their present positions but that if they had means on which to live they would throw all
			of their strength into this cause!</p>
		<p>I am quite convinced that if there were sufficient money here to carry on a Birth Control
			campaign of wide proportions the women would rally to this cause until the suffrage
			fight would be far surpassed in intensity and enthusiasm and the results would be
			immensely more constructive and far reaching.</p>
		<p>On July 2, I was invited to speak before the <org
				reg="Conference on Maternity and Child Welfare">Conference on Maternity and Child
				welfare</org> at <place reg="Brighton, England">Brighton</place>, the invitation
			coming through Miss <person reg="March, Nora">Nora March</person>, editor of <title
				type="book">Racial Health</title>, by the good offices of Dr. <person
				reg="Prichard, Ira">Ira Prichard</person>. Although Birth Control was not being
			discussed when I arrived, a place was made for me under the head of Child Welfare to
			talk five minutes which the chairman afterward extended to ten.</p>
		<p>I had time to point out that there are three definite factors to be considered in a
			constructive campaign to aid the children of the nation and that these three factors had
			their roots deeply inbeded in other prevalent evils. First, the fear of pregnancy in the
			motherhood of the nation creates a condition of mind that must inevitable mean a child
			predisposed to a lack of health and courage. Second, this same fear in the mother leads
			to the use of drugs which poison the embryo at the beginning of life and induce in it a
			condition of ill health never entirely obliterated. Thirdly, frequent pregnancies cause
			the mother to bring forth weaklings, and that all these factors conspire to handicap the
			child from the very beginning of its existence. I emphasized the fact that unless the
			child welfare workers began to be thoroughly constructive and include Birth Control in
			their program, they were in a great degree wasting their efforts. They were beginning
			too late.</p>
		<p>The time was far too short, but so great was the interest in the subject of Birth Control
			that dozens crowded around me to ask questions and request literature.</p>
		<p>I go now to <place>Glasgow, Scotland</place> to spend two weeks. A meeting is planned for
			the <org reg="Glasgow Green">Green</org> on July 4, another the evening of the same day
			in a <org reg="Watson Street Hall">hall</org>. A short hour of a lecturer's time is not
			much in which to break down the prejudices of ages and communicate a new message. But
			the time is ripe and both men and women are eager. The interest quickens constantly. The
			Cause moves on.</p>
		<dateline>--London, <date value="1920-07-02">July 2nd</date></dateline>
	</docBody>
</doc>
