<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2003/07/29 SR</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/01 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/08/08 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/11/28 CH correct typos</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-01 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1921-12-28">28 Dec 1921</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Stop Perpetuating The Unfit by a National Policy on Limitation of
                Families</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp306688</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">New York American</title>, Dec. 28, 1921, 9.</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> C16:167.</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>This article was part of a "discussion" aroused by the November 1921 case of Anna
            Reynolds Cassidente, a Denver woman, who was brought before Juvenile Court because her
            five children were undernourished and her house was dirty. The judge suggested that
            rather than take the existing children away, Mrs. Cassidente be sterilized to prevent
            any more. The judge ruled that both parents had to agree to the procedure; while her
            husband, <person reg="Cassidente, Clyde">Clyde Cassidente</person>, was amenable, Mrs.
            Cassidente had refused. A brief editorial note preceded the article, identifying
            Sanger.</p>
        <index level1="American Birth Control League"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits and risks of"/>
       <index level1="mortality rates" level2="infant"/>
        <index level1="sterilization" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="&quot;unfit&quot; to reproduce" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="eugenics" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="enslavement of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">MARGARET SANGER</person>----Stop Perpetuating The
            Unfit by a National Policy on Limitation of Families</head>
        <p>In the case of Mrs. <person reg="Cassidente, Anna Reynolds ">Cassidente</person>, of
                <place reg="Denver, CO">Denver</place>, one must remember that such cases are to be
            looked upon as one views a war measure in a great and trying emergency. </p>
        <p>Such an operation as that suggested by the doctor is permanent birth control. There are
            thousands of women who, for serious reasons to health or life, have been compelled to
            undergo this operation, with results neither harmful nor disastrous to the woman. </p>
        <p>But these cases are rare compared to the millions of poor overworked women, mothers all,
            whose condition does not warrant so strenuous a measure as sterilization but whose lives
            are made miserable and wretched, because babies come too quickly after each other. There
            mothers need and desire knowledge of birth control.</p>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Better Children.</head>
            <p>Such knowledge does not prevent the coming of children when they are wanted, but it
                may be put into practice, to the result that a woman may have three or four
                children, give them care and attend to their health and welfare and bring this
                number to full maturity as citizens a country may be proud of rearing.</p>
            <p>The huge infant mortality rate is a symptom of the disease of an ignorant and forced
                maternity. Those who strive to reduce the number of deaths of infants, should first
                remove three factors, the first of which is the crude and harmful evil of resorting
                to drugs in the early stages of motherhood.</p>
            <p>Thousands of women in <place reg="United States">America</place> spend fabulous sums
                at drug shops for useless and injurious ingredients which poison the number and
                injure the infant at its very inception. Women who complain of sickly and weak
                infants are often reminded of the attempts made at foetecide and regret the harm
                done only too late.</p>
            <p>Such an infant is weakened at the start of life and may have so little power of
                resistance that it cannot survive early infancy. </p>
            <p>The second factor in infant mortality is the birth of infants coming so rapidly one
                after the other, that the mother has not time to recover her strength for to
                recuperate from the strain of the last birth, nor to gain strength for the coming of
                the next.</p>
            <p>Such a condition makes it imperative that the mother use up the vitality of the
                coming child in order to get through herself. In other words, she draws upon the
                capital of the child unborn, which weakens its resistance for the battle of life
                after birth.</p>
            <p>The third factor is the lack of time and attention and knowledge of the mother to
                expend on the child, making it a creature of chance, to grow up or not, according to
                the mercy of neighbors or charitable agencies.</p>
            <p>Birth control would save mothers, not only from undergoing the useless agony (year
                after year) of fruitless pregnancies, but also from the horrible spectacle of
                countless little coffins made necessary by a forced or involuntary maternity.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">No Magic Goal.</head>
            <p>There is no magic road to the goal of Birth Control. There is no magic method to be
                practiced. The methods advanced and taught in <place reg="Netherlands"
                    >Holland</place> in private clinics by doctors and nurses to poor mothers, are
                strictly individual, suitable not to everyone, but to the special woman concerned. </p>
            <p>The woman who has had two children may need different advice from that given to a
                mother who had given birth to eight or ten children. </p>
            <p>The woman who has had good medical care during her pregnancies and childbirth may
                need far different instruction to that given a woman who has not had that care. </p>
            <p>The methods most advised and insuring the greatest amount of safety cannot be used by
                an unmarried woman. All methods advised, require home conditions, some intelligence
                and a certain understanding of hygiene.</p>
            <p>The parents who desire to limit their families show intelligence and responsibility.
                They should be encouraged and assisted in every means at the command of science and
                the state. </p>
            <p>Such is the object of the <org>American Birth Control League</org> (104 Fifth avenue,
                    <place reg="New York, NY">New York City</place>, which aims to arouse interest
                among the American people to bring to birth a better quality in our race, as well as
                to establish clinics in all thickly populated districts where poor overburdened
                wretched mothers may be instructed in the methods of birth control.</p>
            <p>We need one generation of birth control to weed out the misfits, to breed
                self-reliant, intelligent, responsible individuals.</p>
            <p>Our immigration laws forbid the entrance into this country of paupers, insane,
                feeble-minded and diseased people from other lands. Why not extend the idea and
                discourage the bringing to birth these same types within our borders. Let us stop
                reproducing and perpetuation disease, insanity and ignorance. </p>
            <p>Stop these and other evils at their source by a national policy and education of
                birth control.</p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
