<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2001-11-02 MH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2002-08-22 KH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/02 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007-05-30 CH Oxygen cleanup</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-05 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1912-04-06">6 Apr 1912</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>The Boy Scout Movement</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp307878</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Il Proletario</title>, Apr. 6, 1912</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm </title> C16:21</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="ROOTH">Theodore Roosevelt</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
            <name id="BOSCO">Boys Scouts</name>
            <name id="POWBA">Powell, Baden</name>
            <name id="ED8">Edward VIII, (king of England)</name>
            <name id="KIRGE">Kirkpatrick, George</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
        <index level1="Boy Scouts"/>
        <index level1="capitalism"/>
        <index level1="working classes" level2="revolution and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>The Boy Scout Movement </head>
        <p>About five years ago an organization was started in <place>England</place> called
                "<org>The Boy Scouts</org>". It was originated by Mr. <person
                reg="Baden=Powell, Robert">Baden Powell</person> during the Boer War. It was very
            quickly imported to <place reg="United States">America</place> and seized upon most
            enthusiastically by America's grown up boy scout, <person reg="Roosevelt, Theodore"
                >Theodore Roosevelt</person>. </p>
        <p>"<q who="ROOTH">Delighted</q>" indeed was he to <supplied resp="MSPP">fasten</supplied>
            this military idea upon the American people, and together with the <org
                reg="Young Mens Christian Association ">Young Mens Christian Ass'n</org> and the
                <org reg="Young Mens Hebrew Association">Young Mens Hebrew Ass'n</org> they grasped
            this new <supplied resp="MSPP">prop</supplied>, which will in time of need, help to keep
            the Capitalist Class and private property a little longer standing.</p>
        <p>A great deal of opposition was met with in this country at first because mothers objected
            to military training given to their sons, but behold - this objection <supplied
                resp="MSPP">will</supplied> soon overcome, voices shouted from the house tops that
            this was "<q who="UNK"><gap reason="torn" extent="one word"/> its essence strictly
                non-military movement</q>", that the real idea <gap reason="torn" extent="one word"
            /> the organization is to develop <supplied resp="MSPP">the</supplied> individuality of
            the boy. One of the essential laws of the Boy Scouts <gap reason="torn"
                extent="one word"/> that he shall "<q who="BOSCO">show respect to those who are his
                superiors</q>". Now <gap reason="torn" extent="one word"/> to the individuality let
            us see just how they go about to develop <gap reason="torn " extent="one word"/> "<q
                who="BOSCO">To be a boy scout, a boy must learn to OBEY the orders of <supplied
                    resp="MSPP">the</supplied> patrol leader, scout master, and scout
                commissioner.</q>" </p>
        <p>He must learn to obey before <gap reason="torn " extent="one word"/> can command. He
            should so <supplied resp="MSPP">learn</supplied> to discipline and control <supplied
                resp="MSPP">himself</supplied> that he will have NO THOUGHT but to OBEY the Orders
            of this Officers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Baden Powell on a visit <gap reason="torn" extent="one word"/> this country in
            February still insisted that the whole object of the Organization is to develop "<q
                who="POWBA">Individual character and initiative</q>".</p>
        <p>Let us go on a little further <gap reason="torn" extent="one word"/> the by-laws, for far
            be it from us <gap reason="torn" extent="one word"/> judge without proof. "<q
                who="BOSCO">A scout <gap reason="torn" extent="one word"/> loyal to the King, to his
                Officers, to his County and to his <supplied resp="MSPP">Employers</supplied>. -
                THIS IS THE VERY <supplied resp="MSPP">ESSENCE</supplied> OF GOOD
            CITIZENSHIP</q>."</p>
        <p>And again:</p>
        <p>"<q who="BOSCO">A Scout obeys Orders to anyone placed in authority over him, must obey
                orders INSTANTLY <supplied resp="MSPP">and</supplied> WITHOUT QUESTION.</q>"</p>
        <p>These rules and by-laws should settle the question of the individuality any boy can
            develop in the Boy Scout Movement. Many parents against are appealed to through the camp
            life which the boy can lead. The boys themselves having only one glorious idea of
            freedom in the woods, pictures of running streams, lovely forests, tramping, running,
            playing, good companions, and a lot of good fun, all of which appeals to any healthy boy
            at this critical period of his development. Hundreds of boys answer to this call of
            out-door life just as thousands answer the call of the sea and enlist in the <org
                reg="United States Navy">Navy</org>, where in glowing colors trips in
                <place>China</place> and <place>Japan</place> and all Countries are viewed to them.
            To catch the young men in their "down and out" financial state, imagination does the
            rest and off they go to join the Navy. In Powell's own words he says: "<q who="POWBA">To
                seize the boys character in its red hot state of enthusiasm</q>." That has been the
            idea of the <org>Catholic Church</org> too, they understand the value of influence at
            this crucial age. How cowardly and base to take advantage of the undeveloped youth, to
            use him, to mold his life and actions for the benefit of their class: the Master Class.
            There is only one step from the boy scout to the <org reg="United States Army"
                >Army</org>. This has been foreseen and planned by all who support it, and it
            behooves all who are far sighted enough to see and understand the real significance of
            this movement, to attack it, to crush it and stamp it out for once and all. We should
            lay more stress on the underlying motive of this fiendish organization, and expose it.
            We are not doing our duty to the Working Class when we calmly sit by and watch this
            movement grow into an army. It has increased in United States in the last four years at
            a tremendous rate, it is increasing daily, and it is time for the working class to
            ACT.</p>
        <p>Wherever the Church is, they are organizing, there they find fertile soil. They are
            joining their forces for the final battle, and we are allowing them to do so without a
            murmur. There are over 40000 boys in this country being trained to scab on the working
            class, there are over 40,000 boys in this Country being trained to murder the Working
            Class. </p>
        <p>The following speaks for itself:</p>
        <p>"<q who="UNK">Accordingly - Employers of labor seeking trustworthy boys service will look
                first among scouts, knowing that they will find boys broken to discipline.</q>" </p>
        <p>And yet in the face of all these remarks and statement issued by Powell himself, they try
            to fool parents by saying it is a movement to develop ideas in a healthy mind. In the
            first annual report of the Boy Scout by Powell, he states: -</p>
        <p>"<q who="POWBA">Appreciation from a Chief Constable who states that the boy scouts in a
                town are worth 20 extra constables to him</q>". Should there still be a mother who
            doubts the real intention of the movement, let her read the message from <person
                reg="Edward VIII (England)">King Edward</person> to the boys at their first Annual
            parade.</p>
        <p>"<q who="ED8">Please assure the boys that the King takes great interest in them, and that
                if he should call upon them later in life, their sense of patriotic responsibility
                and happy discipline, which they are now acquiring as boys will enable them to do
                their duty as men, should any danger threaten the Empire</q>". The two words
            "patriotic responsibility" are plain enough for anyone to understand and don't let the
            "happy discipline" escape your notice. Think it over. The Capitalists have had much to
            contend with in the last few years in finding the two essentials, patriotism and
            discipline, fast dying out. They realize that the species which exhibit a trace of
            patriotism is almost extinct, and the growing youth does not love
            discipline--consequently they invent a new kind of discipline--a happy one--and with
            this they feed the scouts. </p>
        <p>Too well to do they realize that it is not the love of country which sends young men into
            the Army or Navy, but absolute necessity drives thousands of others into the factories.
            Too well they know this, and knowing they cannot instill patriotism into the man--they
            take a chance on the boy and take him before he begins to think--then they have for
            their motto "<q who="BOSCO">I do not think--I obey</q>". </p>
        <p>It is all the same to the Capitalist to what use they put the children of the workers -
            millions into human machines--and millions would they gladly put into the army to
            develop into human murderers.</p>
        <p>Parent, your duty is plain - develop in your child a CONTEMPT for soldiers in uniform: a
            contempt for anyone would train in the art of murder: a contempt for anyone who prances
            up and down monkey like at the orders of another. Teach him the words of <person
                reg="Kirkpatrick, George">George Kirkpatrick</person> who says "<q who="KIRGE">I
                refuse to kill my father, or my sisters, sweet heart, I refuse to kill any member of
                the working class and hide my blood stained hands in the folds of ANY FLAG.</q>"</p>
        <byline><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>.</byline>
    </docBody>
</doc>
