<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Autograph fiction">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014/06/11 MM</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014/11/21 EK clean regs and correct proof</prepDate><prepDate>2015-01-22 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1911-00-00">1911</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>Does Youth Win the Race?</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp309022</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
			<bibl><title type="mf">Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Collected Documents Series</title>, C16:1049</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name/>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">Sanger likely drafted this short story outline in 1911. <index
			level1="motherhood" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="marriage" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="racial/>ethnic references" level2="to Italians"/>
		<index level1="sexuality" level2="MS on"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>
			<title rend="underline">Does youth win the race</title>
		</head>
		<head type="sub">Beauty or Brains?</head>
		<p>Adoption of little Italian immigrant (slum) child by childless couple (show <place>Ellis
				Island</place> with incoming family of several children).</p>
		<p>Mother splendid type of American school teacher--big-brained &amp;
			unselfish--intellectual in all current activities.</p>
		<p>Her devotion &amp; intellect makes <add>weak</add> husband climb <del>for</del> step by
			step to highest position in his profession she studies &amp; suggests--he accepts &amp;
			gets benefit--daughter (adopted) gets same devotion.</p>
		<p>Mother tireless in training her in habits of neatness--but she only cares for
			style;--tireless in training her in habits of concentration--girl <emph rend="underline"
				>flippant</emph> and inconstant.</p>
		<p>The only quality which seems natural--real--is her voice inherited from Italian parentage
			far back in that land of sunshine</p>
		<p>Thus the mother trains--works night &amp; day to train voice of much beloved child.</p>
		<p>Husband dies--</p>
		<p>Mother spends entire fortune in helping daughter--who improves but little--good voice but
			lazy &amp; will not work to develop--</p>
		<p>Mother takes in <del>sewing</del> &amp; washing &amp; ironing <add>men's</add>silk shirts
			as a speciality--</p>
		<p>Meets <person reg="Neenan, George (fictional)">George</person><supplied resp="MSPP">Neenan</supplied>
			a poor but ambitious composer.</p>
		<p>He falls in love with mothers <gap reason="missing" extent="one word"/>
			<supplied resp="MSPP"><add>mental</add></supplied> and mother with him--</p>
		<p>Finds himself seeking her advice in all important questions. </p>
		<p>mp;hrough her advice he succeeds in a big composition &amp; wins great victory--</p>
		<p>Daughter comes home--</p>
		<p>Neenan falls in love with daughter--while still in love with the womans mind her big
			grasp on the world affairs--her deep understanding her psychic &amp; intentional
			qualities awe him--he needs them--but he loves Dorothy.</p>
		<p>He comes to live in their home (flat) to live in touch with the inspiration of
				<person>Helen</person> the Mother--</p>
		<p>He does not tell <person>Dora</person> he loves her--</p>
		<p>He tells Helen he can not love her as he would like to-- He is married &amp; can not get
			divorced.</p>
		<p>Helen wants to make him the greatest in the musical world-- She studies for him early
			&amp; late helps him to rise--and he does--</p>
		<p>Word came that his wife has passed away--he is now free to choose--</p>
		<p>He is torn between physical love for Dora and the ideal love of Helen--. One love which
			satisfies the cravings of the <add>body</add>. The other which lifts &amp; exalts the
			growth of the soul. Man being a physical creature--ages of physical cravings
			satisfied--the test too hard--</p>
		<p>He sees a young couple with a baby &amp; walks behind them &amp; hears their conversation
			of happiness &amp; joy in their mutual love &amp; he pictures their state of happiness
			&amp; home life--and torn to a frenzy by the new freedom and the joy which he knows can
			be his for the asking-- He rushes off to the theatre &amp; asks Dora to marry him.</p>
		<p>They marry--</p>
		<p>He fearing to lose Helens help--urges Dora to keep their marriage secret.</p>
		<p>A happier triangle could not be conceived of--</p>
		<p>He the adored of two women <del>is</del> has a complete life--beauty to fill his artistic
			&amp; physical eye and a clean, clear inspiring intelligence to urge him on to greater
			&amp; higher accomplishment.</p>
		<p>The great pain of <person reg="Helen (fictional)">Helen</person> is Doras lack of purpose, of character or stability &amp; she
			covers-up those shortcomings in every way.</p>
		<p>He feeds Doras vanity--</p>
		<p>Helen feeds his mind.</p>
		<p>She is content in the service of <del><gap reason="illegible" extent="one word"/>
			</del><add>helping</add>them to grow--</p>
		<p>From them she gets nothing both selfishly engrossed in their own vanities-- They let her
			serve on--while they make love behind her back.</p>
		<p>Such secrets must out--and after several months they inform Helen that they are to become
			the loving parents of a new born child.</p>
		<p>Helen <del><gap reason="illegible" extent="one word"/></del> receives this news
			quietly--without emotion.</p>
		<p>He fearing she has had a shock--talks quietly-- He tells her of his love for Dora from
			the moment he laid eyes upon her lovely face. The charm of her voice-- The lift of her
			adorable eyes-- The fascination of <emph rend="underline">her</emph> in all her gestures
			&amp; doings--his passion abject &amp; helpless before her as none before had come into
			his life. She listens gazes coldly into his face realizing how little he had her in his
			thoughts--what a fool she had been--to think he had. Helen turns to Dora--and says What
			have you to say <q>"<emph rend="underline">Babe</emph></q> Dora stops chewing gum long
			enough to wipe a tear away from her much powdered face &amp; says indifferently--oh I
			dont care mother--don't make a scene all over the place-- Its no bodys business who I
			marry-- So whats the matter with you?</p>
		<p>We can all live togerher just the same--wheres the tragedy--cant I marry &amp; have a
			baby like other folks without a funeral.</p>
		<p>Helen reviews in her mind the baby she took under her care the nights &amp; days watching
			&amp; caring. The confidences etc and then bursts into flame.</p>
		<p>Yes you have that right--you both have-- But you had no right to deceive--to
				<add>live</add> a life of lies to me--to each other. You, poor dear pretty
				child--<del>for</del> you I <del>can</del>
			<add>do</add>not blame--</p>
		<p>But you George Neenan--you are not a child. You are a man. Your marriage--your love for
			Dora does not hurt me--but I hate you for the faith you have robbed me of-- I hate you
			for exploiting my love of you--you knew I loved you. I <supplied resp="MSPP"
				>despise</supplied> you for climbing to fame upon a woman's Soul.</p>
		<p>And now I leave you to each other</p>
		<p>Neenan <del>&amp; Dora</del>, one year later in apartment with Dora, untidy unkept &amp;
			unhappy--quarreling a common habit-- She is still beautiful to look at--but he has
			missed the intellectual pillar of his successful career. He has gone down hill
			rapidly--both taken to drink her voice gone--his career <gap reason="torn"
				extent="one word"/>. They separate!</p>
		<p>Helen takes up social work &amp; becomes head organizer of great national campaign for
			women. Years (5) later--watches her go <add>proudly</add> past &amp; wonders-- For now
			he thinks only brains make for real &amp; lasting Beauty.</p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
