<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Letter">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-06-25 CH proofed </prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1916/04/--"/>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Letter to Mother Earth</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp309031</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Mother Earth</title><title type="article">A Letter from
                    Margaret Sanger</title>April, 1916, pp. 492-93</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm Edition</title> C1:132</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>

        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, William" level2="arrest, trial and imprisonment"/>
        <index level1="Goldman, Emma"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="arrests and imprisonment"/>
        <index level1="law breaking and direct action"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>A LETTER FROM <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">MARGARET SANGER</person></head>
        <p>THERE seems to be general dissatisfaction among the readers of <title type="journal"
                >MOTHER EARTH</title> over the result of my trial.</p>
        <p>Many of them have written me that the law remains unchanged. That any man or woman may
            still be rushed into prison, whose case may not be "dismissed."</p>
        <p>True-all too true.</p>
        <p>The Socialists have been telling us this for years. They have been telling us that
            "direct action" does not accomplish anything until the laws are changed.</p>
        <p>You have taken an interest in my trial. You have written letters to <person
                reg="Dayton, A.G.">Judge Dayton,</person>
            <person reg="Content, Harold A.">U.S. Dist. Attorney</person> and other officials
            requesting the dismissal of my case-You have pleaded the Cause of Birth Control thru
            thousands of letters to these officials-you have been heard-the authorities dismissed
            the case, as you requested-and now you are disappointed and "mad" at ME because they did
            it.</p>
        <p>I made no requests of the authorities: on the contrary I informed them, before the case
            was dismissed, that I should continue my work until working women in <place
                reg="The United States">America</place> should have the same freedom to get Birth
            Control knowledge as the women of wealth.</p>
        <p>I have tried to tell you that going into jail or staying out of it was of slight
            importance to me. My work-my Cause, is the cry of anguish which comes to me from the
            women of <place reg="United States, Southern">the Cotton Belt</place>-the cry of working
            women tortured with the dread of child bearing and begging for relief from it. I am free
            and have relieved nearly three hundred of these women in the past four weeks: to
            continue to do this work-via direct action-is my Cause.</p>
        <p><person reg="Sanger, William">William Sanger</person> went to jail-the law remained the
            same-I did not go to jail-you say the law remains the same. Then the Socialists must be
            right. Will <person reg="Goldman, Emma">Emma Goldman</person>'s trial change the law, or
            will it serve as William Sanger's and my case has served-as precedents only? Opinions
            expressed by several prominent members of the legal profession have been to the effect
            that the "dismissal" of my case by the <org reg="United States, Government of"
                >Government</org> is of far greater value as a precedent than an acquittal by a
            jury.</p>
        <p>Comrades-let's on with our work and stop quibbling.</p>
        <byline>M.H.S.</byline>


    </docBody>
</doc>
