<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2001-10-29 MH</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2002-08-22 KH</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2004/07/02 CH</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2004/08/13 CH</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2007-05-30 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-03-05 CH clean regs</prepDate><prepDate>2015-01-07 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1912-06-11">11 Jun 1912</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>Lawrence Defense Conference Active</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp320096</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="journal">New York Call</title>, June 11, 1912</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name/>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote>
		<index level1="labor movement" level2="Lawrence, MA Strike, 1912"/>
		<index level1="Socialist Party"/>
		<index level1="Industrial Workers of the World"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>LAWRENCE DEFENSE CONFERENCE ACTIVE</head>
		<head type="sub">To Start Big Open Air Campaign.<lb/>Will Distribute 20,000 Leaflets on
				<person reg="Ettor, Joseph">Ettor</person>-<person reg="Giovannitti, Arturo"
				>Giovannitti</person> Case.</head>
		<p>The <org>Lawrence Defense Conference</org> met Thursday, June 6, at the <org>Labor
				Temple</org>. <person reg="Bromberg, Sol">Sol Bromberg</person> was elected
			chairman. A motion that the Executive Committee of this conference be requested to meet
			every Thursday hereafter, also that they act immediately and make arrangements for open
			air meetings, was carried.</p>
		<p>The leaflet which the conference requested <person reg="Oppenheimer, Moses">Moses
				Oppenheimer</person> to write, covering the case of Ettor and Giovannitti, was read
			and accepted. The Executive Committee ordered 20,000 to be printed at once. </p>
		<p>A motion made and carried that the secretary write to the <org>Lawrence Defense Committee</org> at
				<place reg="Lawrence, MA">Lawrence</place> informing them of this conference and
			requesting them not to send subscription lists to various organizations in <place
				reg="New York, NY">New York City</place>, but to send lists to this conference.</p>
		<p>Delegates from the first <org reg="Socialist Party of America, Russian Branch">Russian
				Branch of the Socialist party</org>, also <org
				reg="Socialist Party of America, Branch 1">Branch 1, Socialist party</org>, were
			seated.</p>
		<p>Delegates for Local 179, <org reg="Industrial Workers of the World">I. W. W.</org>,
			reported that the local is making arrangements for a monster protest meeting, together
			with all affiliated unions.</p>
		<p>On Saturday, June 15, 3 p.m., there will be an open air meeting at <place>Union
				Square</place>. Speakers <person reg="Cassidy, Edward F.">Edward F.
			Cassidy</person>, <person reg="Boyd, Frederick Sumner">F. Sumner Boyd</person>, <person
				reg="Panken, Jacob">Jacob Panken</person>, <person reg="Coronel, Jean J.">Jean J.
				Coronel</person>, <person reg="Flynn, Thomas">Thomas Flynn</person> and <person
				reg="Breen, J.">J. Breen</person>. Meetings will be held at this place every
			Saturday afternoon until after the trial of Ettor and Giovannitti.</p>
		<p>On account of the party meeting on the same evening many delegates of the conference were
			not present. It is hoped that at the next regular meeting, June 20, all delegates will
			attend and other organizations which have not yet sent delegates to this conference are
			urged to do so. The time is drawing near for the trial, and there is much work to be
			done.</p>
		<p>Speak up, Comrades: get your organizations to send delegates here at the next meeting and
			let us all together make such a noise that the workers of the country will awaken to the
			outrageous crime committed against them before it is too late.</p>
		<byline><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret H. Sanger</person>, <lb/>Secretary.
		</byline>
	</docBody>
</doc>
