<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article ">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2003/06/10 RK</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2003/08/07 CH Index</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/08/09 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007/06/25 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/11/28 CH correct typos</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-01 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1916-06-09">09 June 1916</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Tell Girls Things They Should Know: Mrs. Sanger</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp320267</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">San Francisco Call &amp; Post</title>, June 9,1916.</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>First article in a two part series. The second article was "<xref from="320266.xml"
                    ><title type="journal">Prolific Child-Breeding Scored by Mrs.
                Sanger</title></xref>," June 10, 1916</p>
        <index level1="birth control clinics and leagues" level2="educational benetifts of"/>
        <index level1="marriage" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="sex education"/>
        <index level1="women and girls"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="sexuality and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="morality of"/>
        <index level1="working classes"/>
        <index level1="&quot;unfit&quot; to reproduce" level2="descriptions of"/>
        <index level1="mentally dieseased or disabled"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>TELL GIRLS THINGS THEY SHOULD KNOW: MRS. SANGER</head>
        <byline>By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">MARGARET SANGER</person></byline>
        <div>
            <p>The great industrial changes which have taken place within the last half century have
                brought with them a great and urgent need for sex education.</p>
            <p>In former days the women and girls were kept within the close confines of the home.
                Innocence was their charm, and ignorance was a virtue. There was no need that the
                girl should know anything of her body, of the marriage state, or of motherhood,
                until she was given over by her parents into the hands of her husband for
                instruction and care.</p>
            <p>Today, however, this is no longer sufficient. The girl of today begins her life at 14
                years to leave the home and the cloistered care of her parents to enter into the
                world's work. Never before has she worked so closely at the side of her brother, and
                never before has she had greater need for knowledge of her self, her physiology, her
                emotions and desires--in fact, a need to know herself throughout. Education is her
                only and principal weapon for her defense against downfall.</p>
            <p>Thousands of young girls are being caught in the meshes of modern life because of
                their ignorance of themselves. Ignorance of a girl's body is one of the strongest
                forces that sends her into unclean living: and all the curfew bells, the legislation
                and the suppression in the world will only strengthen this force instead of
                lessening it.</p>
            <p>From the fourteenth to the twenty-third year every girl passes through a budding
                period called the adolescent period. She finds herself suddenly changed from a
                little girl with her hair down her back, whose interests have been dolls and toys,
                into a different being, with new sensations, new dreams, new awakenings--all of
                which she does not understand.</p>
            <p>We hear our moralists and well-intentioned people criticise severely the young girl
                because she likes pretty ribbons, perfumes, gay colors and pretty clothes, and scold
                her incessantly for having such desires. But if we once realized that all of these
                desires are just as much a part of her developing nature at this particular period,
                and as legitimate for her development as playing with dolls was part of her nature a
                few years before, we would accept these whims as a passing phase of her life and
                help her to understand their insignificance.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub " rend="bold">MILLIONS UNABLE TO WED</head>
            <p>It is a well known fact that there are nearly 9,000,000 women in the <place
                    reg="United States">United States</place> today who are unable to
                marry. The cause of this is mainly that there are 9,000,000 men who do not receive a
                wage sufficient to support a family. This means that the majority of these 9,000,000
                women are living lives of sexual purity, while perhaps not more than 10 per cent of
                the vast majority of the male population are denying themselves sexually, for it is
                a known fact that the double standard of sex exists and is actively in force with
                the male population of this country. It also means that a great part of these women
                are denying themselves the beauty of conscious voluntary motherhood, while a
                possible husband is driven to the professional prostitute.</p>
            <p>One of the principal reasons that this condition exists is the lack of knowledge to
                control the size of one's family. If two young people had this knowledge they could
                live and work together until the time came to support a family. The birds in their
                mating prepare a nest for their little ones, and why should not young couples do the
                same?</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub " rend="bold">BLIND TO INSTRUCTION</head>
            <p>Our puritanical ideas and prejudices have made us blind to the needs of sex
                instruction and have left us unable to face squarely the responsibilities toward our
                young people and toward the mothers of the race. In our public schools we are taught
                physiology, it is true. But the human body has been taught to us only in the terms
                of a neuter gender, and the vital and important department of the body--the sex
                department--has been left untouched.</p>
            <p>We have been proud of erecting schools for the education of our children; we have
                erected lofty and magnificent churches for their religious instruction; but for
                their moral instruction, upon which depends their happiness and their welfare, we
                have erected nothing but the streets and the gutter.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub " rend="bold">TIME FOR CHANGE</head>
            <p>The time has come for universal change in this respect. Today we have grown to
                realize that we are a social being, with social instincts and desires. We have found
                it necessary, in order to protect ourselves against polluted streams and poisonous
                milk, drugs, etc., that we can not protect ourselves alone without also giving the
                same protection to our neighbor. And so it is with sex instruction. It is not
                sufficient that our individual boy or girl shall be instructed; it is also necessary
                to see that the associates and companions at school are likewise instructed, if our
                work is to have permanent results. The question is, where shall he or she go for
                this instruction. The library shelves are closed to this subject. The mother, who
                should be the proper person for such instruction, is as ignorant as the girl herself
                and unprepared to advise her, with the result that only companions, ignorant and
                misinformed, give wrong information, which does more harm than if it were let
                alone.</p>
            <p>Modern society's attitude toward the unmarried mother is a disgrace to civilization.
                We take upon ourselves the responsibility of keeping her in ignorance concerning
                motherhood, and then condemn her when, through ignorance, motherhood is thrust upon
                her. The great majority of young girls living in prostitution today tell us that
                their first step in this path was because they became unmarried mothers.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub " rend="bold">WITHOUT KNOWLEDGE</head>
            <p>In the face of these facts the unthinking people will tell us that knowledge to
                control birth will cause young girls to become immoral. I emphatically deny such
                assertion, for not 1 per cent of all of these women living lives of degradation have
                ever had knowledge to control birth. Rather do I believe that knowledge would have
                saved them from this unfortunate following. Statistics today tell us that over 50
                per cent of these girls have been found to be mentally defective, and though they
                have arrived at the age of 19 or 20 years with a matured physical development, we
                find them with the mind and the intelligence of a child of 9 or 10 years. Again we
                find that the great majority of the girls living in this life are members of large
                families, and have been early thrown upon the street as their playground, with
                ignorant companions as their moral instructors.</p>
            <p>Our institutions for these feeble-minded, as well as the insane, are full and
                overcrowded. Ten thousand feeble-minded girls taken from the streets of <place
                    reg="New York, NY">New York City</place> are clamoring at the doors of the
                charities to be taken in and protected from this degrading occupation. The reply
                comes that there is no room for them. Our modern institutions, homes for girls,
                insane asylums, feeble-minded homes, incurable hospitals, juvenile courts and
                foundling asylums are all monuments to reckless and careless breeding.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub " rend="bold">FASHION RACE SANELY</head>
            <p>The question is, "What shall we do about it?"</p>
            <p>The facts are that the development of the race has been unconscious. We have had no
                responsibility for its right course.</p>
            <p>Now, in the twentieth century, in the fullness of time, let us be children no longer.
                Let us fashion the human race with an intelligent consciousness and stand squarely
                to meet our responsibilities. </p>
            <p>Birth control leagues are being established throughout the United States for the
                purpose of educating the people on this subject. Reliable and prominent physicians
                will lecture, and have lectured, free of charge to those who desire to be informed
                here in <place reg="San Francisco, CA">San Francisco</place>.</p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
