<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014/06/19 MM encode and transcribe</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-12-19 CH proof tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-07 CH enter corrections</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1918-11-00"> Nov 1918</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>Birth Control--The Cure for War</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp320231</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title>, Nov. 1918,
				p. 12</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="ML">Malthusian League</name>
			<name id="MARHE">Marcuse, Herbert</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Much of this article is made of quotes from a
				<org>Malthusian League</org> report. </p>
		<index level1="Malthusian League"/>
		<index level1="World War I" level2="population"/>
		<index level1="Germany" level2="birth rate in"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="war and"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Birth Control--The Cure For War</head>
		<p>THE DEEPER THAT thinking minds look into the causes of the Great War,
			the more evident it is becoming that the chief cause of the
			cataclysmic struggle is high birth rates, particularly the high
			birth rate of <place>Germany</place>. High birth rates mean
			expansion of national boundaries, conquests, annexations,
			exploitation, and all the manifold oppressions of a militaristic and
			imperialistic policy. </p>
		<p>The soundness of the general policy laid down by Dr. <person
				reg="Millard, Charles Killick">C. Killick Millard</person>, the
			eminent British scientist and health official, whose notable address
			was quoted in the last issue of <title type="journal">THE BIRTH
				CONTROL REVIEW</title>, is strikingly exemplified in detail by
			conditions cited in the Fortieth Annual Report of the (British) <org
				reg="Malthusian League">Mathusian League</org> just issued. Dr.
			Millard laid down the principle that only worldwide birth control
			can preclude the possibility of another such race-wrecking conflict
			as we are now undergoing. The report brings to light certain facts
			which leaves no doubt as to the necessity of limiting population by
			those normal methods for which advocates of Birth Control contend. </p>
		<p>That these facts are beginning to take hold upon the public
			understanding is startingly evidenced by the doubling of the demand
			for the literature of the Malthusian League during the twelve months
			covered by the report. The horrors of war are bringing home to the
			English people the necessity of reducing the birth rate.</p>

		<p><q who="ML">"THE WAR HAS certainly stimulated interest in the
				population question and birth control"</q> says the report. <q
				who="ML">"First the public was impressed by the statements of
				the <person reg="Wilhelm II">Kasier</person>, <person
					reg="von Bernhardi, Friedrich">Von Bernhardi</person>,
					<person>Von Bulow </person>and others as to Germany's
				necessity for conquests in order to provide for its high birth
				rate, and next by the food difficulties and by the
				questionableness altogether, of bringing more children into the
				world at such a time. So the demands for our literature and for
				our free Practical leaflet began to increase rapidly. People
				were interested to learn how, since 1901, Germany's high birth
				rate had been falling with amazing speed, and how we had hoped
				that peace between us might continue a few years longer and
				become permanent.</q>
		</p>
		<q who="ML">
			<p>"In 1908 its birth rate had fallen below thirty per thousand per
				annum, and we hoped that Germany would soon enter into a
				peaceful alliance with <place>France</place>, <place
					reg="Great Britain">Britain</place> and America. Now we know
				that the preparations for war which Germany had made in its high
				birth rate years, had gone too far for this. But the fall of its
				birth rate since 1914 has been tremendous, and has aroused great
				indignation and alarm among its militarists.</p>
			<p>"The January issue of <title type="journal">Maternity and Child
					Welfare</title>, in an editorial article in favor of birth
				control, quote as follows from <person reg="Marcuse, Herbert"
					>Dr. Marcuse</person> who had discussed the subject with
				hundreds of sick German soldiers: <q who="MARHE">The large
					proportion of them do not wish to ever have children again.
					They said in effect that factory-food and cannon-food, all
					that kind of thing, has got to go, and only after our women
					have proclaimed a general birth strike will things be
					better.</q>
			</p>
			<q who="MARHE"><p>"It seems certain that Germany, though its
					birth-rate like ours will probably rise for a year or two
					after the war, will soon become a very low birth rate
					country. Unfortunately, <place reg="Soviet Union"
						>Russia</place> and the <place>Balkan States</place>
					will continue for some years to have high birth rates
					causing a high pressure of population which will still
					endanger the peace of <place>Europe</place>."</p></q>
		</q>
		<p>Still other "war problems" bring home the necessity of birth control.
				<q who="ML">"Many doctors and social workers"</q> says the
			report just quoted from, <q who="ML"> "expect a serious increase in
				prostitution and venereal disease after the war.</q></p>
		<q who="ML">
			<p>"<emph rend="italics">Our remedy for prostitution is to encourage
					early marriage by spreading the knowledge that couples can
					avoid having any more children than they are able to do
					justice to.</emph></p>
			<p>"There may be a period of terrible poverty and suffering after
				the war, and the fewer children born for a year or so, the
				shorter that period will be. The population of America,
					<place>Canada</place>, <place>Australia</place>and
					<place>New Zealand</place> continues, and will continue, to
				increase very rapidly, so Britain and France need not be in any
				hurry to raise their birth rates above the present level. In any
				case, the only way we can do something towards compensating for
				our losses in the war is to bring about a better distribution of
				children by upholding the Malthusian principle that people
				should not have more children than they can provide for."</p>
		</q>
		<p>THERE YET REMAINS the threat of an increase in the birth rate after
			the war and the intensification of the evils of poverty. Says the
			report:</p>
		<q who="ML">
			<p>"In the year or so after the war the birth rate will probably
				rise, alas, to about its 1914 figure of 23.6 per thousand. As
				there was still a large amount of poverty with this birth rate
				before the war, it would seem certain that there will be a
				greater amount with such a birth rate after the war.</p>
			<p>"Moreover, if there is such emigration of young workers to the
				Colonies it will increase the amount of poverty. So the birth
				rate will soon begin to fall again, and it will go on falling
				until poverty (i.e., insufficiency of the necessaries for good
				health) has disappeared. Those who look upon the falling birth
				rate as an evil and oppose it, only succeed in retarding the
				movement slightly; but hinder its spreading where it is most
				needed, namely, amongst the poor and the unfit. </p>
			<p>"We consider the falling birth rate to be a good thing, so to us
				the only question is--should the inevitable further decline of
				the birth rate be among the richer or among the poorer classes?
				We say that it should be among the poor and that advice on
				contraception, which they are generally so eager to get, should
				be freely given them. Birth control clinics, like those in
					<place reg="Netherlands">Holland</place>, should be
				established in every town, and doctors and nurses should also be
				called upon to give the information when needed. The <org
					reg="Dutch Nieuw Malthusiaansche Bond">Dutch Neo-Malthusian
					League</org>, which is officially recognized as a Society of
				Public Utility, enables poor people to get the information
				easily, and the improvement in the condition and physique of the
				nation has been extraordinary."</p>
		</q>

	</docBody>
</doc>
