<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014-06-10 CH transcribe</prepDate><prepDate>2014-12-18 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1916-10-00">Oct 1916</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>Schools and Teachers</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp320326</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="journal">The Modern School</title> Oct-Nov. 1916, pp. 114-118</bibl>

		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
			<name id="WARGE">Ward, George H.B.</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>This is the first article in a four-part series. For the remaining articles see "Portet
			and Ferrer," <xref from="320119.xml">Dec. 1916</xref>, <xref from="320120.xml">Jan.
				1917</xref>, and <xref from="320090.xml">Feb. 1917</xref>. For an additional series
			in the <title type="journal">Modern School</title>, see "<xref from="320328.xml">Modern Schools in Spain</xref>," June
			1918.</p>
		<index level1="Spain" level2="education in"/>
		<index level1="Spain" level2="political conditions in"/>
		<index level1="Spain" level2="Catholic Church in"/>
		<index level1="Spain"/>
		<index level1="Modern School Movement" level2="in Spain"/>
		<index level1="Portet, Lorenzo" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="Ferrer, Francisco" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="Catholic Church"/>
		<index level1="children" level2="education of"/>

	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>SCHOOLS AND TEACHERS.</head>
		<byline><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">MARGARET H. SANGER</person>.</byline>
		<p> The <org reg="Roman Catholic Church">Catholic Church</org>, wherever she puts her foot as a power, carries with her
			ignorance, superstition and the crime of illiteracy, but nowhere is she so directly
			responsible for these evils as in <place>Spain</place> today. If Spanish education, as
			some writers say, is seventy years behind that of <place>England</place>, then it is
			safe to say she is a hundred years behind that in <place reg="United States"
				>America</place> in efficiency, equipment, administration, numbers, and especially
			in freedom from religious influence.</p>
		<p>In official figures in 1908, there were 5212 private schools with 6000 teachers. Of these
			5000 were Catholic schools; 90 were Protestant schools and the reamining 120 were
			secular or lay schools. In the year 1910, it was found that over half the child
			population of <place reg="Madrid, Spain">Madrid</place> (the capital of Spain), 30,000
			children, did not attend school. Then what they are taught in this enlightened age seems
			a crime to civilization. The humdrum rote, and Catholic dogma, obligatory in all
			government schools, have Catholic inspection and Catholic supervision, which secures
			hundreds of positions for grafting politicians, who plunder upon the poor and docile
			school-teacher.</p>
		<p>The school-teacher in Spain is the joks of the nation. "<q who="UNK">He is hungrier than
				a school-master</q>" is a household proverb. The salary set aside for the
			school-teacher averages $200 a year. he works constantly twelve months in the year, so
			that his salary averages about $16. per month. But even this ridiculous sum he does not
			always get. There is so much graft and plunder. The University professor seldom gets
			more than $500. a year. No wonder the profession is despised and admited to be the most
			ill-paid and thankless of all professions as well as requiring the least intelligent
			equipment. Any skilled worker gets a better wage and is more certain of it than the
			school-master.</p>
		<p>There is abuse of office in educational departments. There are hundreds of instances
			where schools have been closed by <org reg="Spain, Government">Government</org> order
			and the officials continue to draw the teacher's salary and keep it. Out of nine hundred
			prisoners in one jail it was found that 85% were illiterate. One teacher of a prison did
			not teach the prisoners, because there was no suitable class-room! Nevertheless, he had
			drawn his salary for twenty-four years as a teacher in that prison.</p>
		<p>Everywhere are to be found graft and illiteracy, and always it can be traced to the power
			of the Church. In all the central streets of even the large cities can be seen the
			booths for the professional letter writer, who reads the letter received and answers it
			for the sum of ten or twenty cents. In small villages it is usually the priest who
			performs this office, but sometimes the school-master.</p>
		<p>The school-houses in Spain are, if possible, even a greater disgrace, than the
			wide-spread illiteracy. Such filthy, dingy ramshakle buildings can scarcely be classed
			as schools. Of those I visited not one had sunlight. Only a few had light other than the
			sky-light. There was no system of ventilation in any of them. I quote from <person
				reg="Ward, George H.B.">Ward</person>'s "<title type="book">Truth About
				Spain</title>" the following:-</p>
		<p>"<q who="WARGE">If the provision of public schools is lamentably deficient, the buildings
				themselves are a scandal. The public school is little better than a barn, appliances
				are rude and primitive, text-books and primers, cry aloud for a bonfire. Playgrounds
				are conspicuous by their absence, and children in large classes suffer from
				confinement in the close ill-ventilated, insanitary rooms. The schoolmaster is
				usually badly equipped for his task. Often semi-illiterate; often he adds tyranny to
				ignorance, and the child's school life is a martyrdom. As a result, children are
				soured and subdued in temperament, and mentally, if not physically, injured for the
				rest of their lives. The child reads badly, writes worse, and his arithmetic is a
				joke; he learns to recite a fable, apprehends the history of a dead people and the
				wonders of the Inquisition. The only part of his education that may be called
				efficient consists in the inculcation of Catholic rites and formulas, which are
				carefully instilled by the school-master who has sworn to protect the 'faith' within
				the school and who is vigilantly supervised by the parochial priest and diocesan
				inspector.</q>"</p>
		<p>This gives us some idea of the Herculean task which that beloved man <person
				reg="Ferrer, Francisco">Francisco Ferrer</person> set himself to do. When we see the
			obstacles which were in his path, can we, who find modern education difficult with none
			of these obstacles present, appreciate the vision and ideal which must have dominated
			his very being to undertake to establish modern education under these conditions?</p>
		<p>In July 1909 there were in <place reg="Barcelona, Spain">Barcelona</place> and surounding
			suburbs and other parts of Spain sixty Modern Schools endowed by Ferrer. At the time of
			Ferrer's arrest not only all the Modern Schools were closed, but most of the secular and
			Republican schools as well. Teachers were arrested and sent to into exile; all books and
			equipment were confiscated by the Government. It was two years before the authorities
			relinquished their hold upon the books and publications of the Modern School.</p>
		<p>This scattered the force of Ferrer's work for some time after his death. But gradually,
			one by one, the schools have again opened their doors, until to-day there are 50
			schools. If not all strictly Modern Schools, they all use text-books adopted by Ferrer,
			as well as many of the most advanced books published by <org>Escuela Moderna</org>.
			Beside these, there is in nearly every working class town at least one Republican
			school, which is kept up by the workers. In these also, many Ferrer text-books are used.
			One of the greatest difficulties is the terror in the teacher's heart of arrest, for it
			is ever the game of the authorities to imprison and exile republican and secular
			school-masters whom they hold accountable for the child's ideas. The schools are closed
			on the slightest pretext, and kept closed long enough to ruin any organization
			attempting independent education.</p>
		<p>The scarcity of teachers capable of teaching in advanced schools, the constant
			threatening persecution of teachers, have made the advancement of the Modern Schools in
			Spain a difficult task. On the slightest pretext they are pounced upon by vigilant
			grafters, and are met with threats to close their doors at another instance of "illegal
			proceedings". The most absurd charges are called "illegal". For instance, the boys and
			girls are not allowed to be in the same class room at the same time (infants from 3
			years to 10 years are usually the ages of attendance). Naturally the Modern Schools
			conduct their classes "mixed", but the teacher has to be on the alert to separate them
			on the announcement of an inspector. All such silly devices are there to exhaust the
			teacher's capabilities as well as to intimidate him.</p>
		<p>The greatest work which is being done in Spain today thru the Modern Schools, is being
			done not so directly thru the establishment of Modern Schools, as thru injecting into
			the secular and republican schools already established the text-books of Ferrer and his
			ideas. This has been wisely done by <person reg="Portet, Lorenzo">Lorenzo
				Portet</person>, Ferrer's successor, who has gone ahead with the publishing of
			advanced literature of a revolutionary character, aiming to publish educational matter
			so cheaply in Spain that all who read may afford to buy it.</p>
		<p>In this way far more has been done to carry out Ferrer's ideals of the Modern School than
			could otherwise, considering the appalling conditions of illiteracy, Catholic influence
			and prejudice, be accomplished. And not alone in Spain are these ideals spreading, for
			in <place>South America</place>, <place>Cuba</place> and the <place reg="Philippines"
				>Philippine Islands</place>, Modern Schools have been established and weekly demands
			of advanced literature come in large orders from these Spanish-speaking countries.</p>
		<p>All who know the ideals of Ferrer as represented in his teachings, will be interested to
			know something of the man he chose as his successor to carry out his ideas and to put
			into execution as near as possible the ideals he strove for. This man is Lorenzo Portet.
			He was entrusted with a life-work, a responsibility, which one can scarcely take
			lightly; he has been confronted with every barrier a tricky government could devise, but
			he has set his teeth in the grip and he will never let go, for high above the
			mountainside of Barcelonia towers that huge formidable prison of <org>Montjuich</org>.
			It stands there dark and threatening above the peace and beauty of the town below. At
			every turn the winding roads it can be seen like some weird fascinating horror which
			follows one about; within its walls have been committed some of the foulest deeds ever
			conceived by human mind. Within its walls was written to Portet, in the last hour of
			Francisco Ferrer's life, a trust to carry out his work. In its courtyard Ferrer the
			education, the idealist, the friend, was shot to death. The memory and the trust go
			together, and Lorenzo Portet cannot forget, neither he can fail.</p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
