<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Printed article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2003/09/02 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-11 CH clean errors</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1939-08-05">5 Aug 1939</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Birth Control and Marriage</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp320558</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Liberty</title>, Aug. 5, 1939, 19.</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger</person>'s essay was written in response to a
            statement made by <person reg="Gandhi, Mohandas">Mohandas K. Gandhi</person> included in
            the same issue of <title>Liberty</title>.</p>
        <index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
        <index level1="birth control methods" level2="continence"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="and marriage"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>BIRTH CONTROL and MARRIAGE</head>
        <head type="sub">Here is an American woman's answer–the woman who all her life has fought
            for our right to limit our offspring.</head>
        <byline>BY MARGARET SANGER<lb/>READING TIME 3 MINUTES 55 SECONDS</byline>
        <p>Yes: it is quite true that the rising generations are beginning to discredit and discount
            those prejudices voiced by the elders which too often have been accepted as traditional
            "wisdom."</p>
        <p>They are being born into a world of confusion and chaos. They are confronted on all sides
            by misery, poverty, insecurity, crime. Dictators whip up class hatred, race hatreds,
            national hatreds among their slaves, most of whom were born of men and women close to
            the starvation point, and themselves were undernourished children. It has been well said
            that starving men are always angry men. Even more menacing to the established order is a
            generation of undernourished children. Such a background becomes the soil out of which
            dictators emerge. Is it any wonder therefore that the younger generation can no longer
            revere the wisdom of those who have permitted international chaos to become
            worldwide?</p>

        <p>We advocate birth control by means of contraception, not to encourage reckless sex
            gratification but to place in the hands of young and responsible married couples a
            scientific instrument by means of which they may fulfill their duties to their children.
            To their children already born and to those to come.</p>

        <p>We advocate intelligent control of the procreative faculties in the very same manner that
            all intelligent and civilized persons control all the physiological functions of the
            human body--in the interests of health, hygiene, and the development of higher purposes
            and uses.</p>

        <p>The legitimate use of contraception implies foresight and co-operation. Instead of being
            in any sense a secret vice, it is the extreme opposite from heedless sex
            gratification.</p>

        <p>Birth control is synonymous with discipline, foresight, the conquest of heedless, selfish
            impulses, and the channeling of one of the most imperative forces of all nature to the
            common good--to the best interests of the individual, the community at large, and the
            ultimate destiny of the human race.</p>

        <p>Intelligently utilized, the instrument of contraception has brought freedom to the lives
            of thousands. It has removed fear from married love. It has and shall continue to reduce
            the maternal death rate among mothers too ill and feeble to bear the burden of a long
            series of undesired pregnancies. It is saving the lives of many infants and children,
            because it is giving them more "vital space" in which to grow and to be properly fed.
            Remember that the ranks of crime are recruited mainly from the high-birth-rate groups. </p>

        <p>Mr. <person reg="Gandhi, Mohandas K.">Ghandi</person>, if I understand him, advocates
            birth control by the method of abstinence. This indeed is an argument that can appeal
            only to the aged. It is based upon an obsolete conception of the marriage relationship.
            I see no idealism in such a policy. To limit the marital relation to exclusively
            procreative purpose would debase the noblest and most idealistic human relationship to
            the level of stock-breeding. It would send humanity back along the road from which it
            has so painfully emerged. It would place such narrow limitations upon the marriage
            relationship as to generate untold misery, unhappiness, and discord upon parents, and
            their unhappiness must automatically be reflected in the lives of their children. </p>

        <p>Mr. Ghandi has fought long and fearlessly for the emancipation of the women of
                <place>India</place>, and I would be the first to recognize the nobility of his
            consecration to human freedom.</p>

        <p>But, with all due respect and reverence, one may ask of what value such freedom can be,
            if women are denied the primary and fundamental freedom of their own bodies, if they are
            denied the right to decide if, when, and under what conditions they are to assume the
            responsibility of motherhood? To advocate the freedom of women, yet to withhold the
            knowledge of contraception, is to indulge in idle rhetoric.</p>

        <p>India has practiced little birth control. In no other country (with the possible
            exception of <place>China</place>, another high-birth-rate territory) have women been so
            heedlessly sacrificed to the Juggernaut of futile childbearing. In no other country has
            so great a proportion of mankind been debased to a level lower than the beasts.</p>

        <p>Contrast the status of women and children among those groups, states, and countries where
            scientific contraception has been accepted and legitimatized. Birth may be spaced out
            according to the strength and desires of mother and father. Families can be planned; and
            racial progress may be controlled in the very manner traffic is controlled on our
            highways.</p>

        <p>Birth control is a problem that is bound up with civilization itself. It is the
            instrument whereby mankind can master the imperious forces of his internal nature, as
            today he is mastering those of the external world. </p>
        <trailer>THE END</trailer>
    </docBody>
</doc>
