<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Printed Article">
<mepHeader>
<prepDate>2003/07/21, 2003/07/28 SR</prepDate>
<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger an Thomas Webster Edgar</docAuthor>
<docDate value="1923-03">Mar 1923</docDate>
<docTitle>
<titlePart>The Physician and Birth Control</titlePart>
</docTitle>
<idno>msp320596</idno>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl><title>The Medical Times</title>, Mar. 1923, 73-74, 77.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
<respStmt>
<resp/>
<name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
<name id="INMBC5">International Neo-Malthusian and Birth Control Conference, 5th (1922)</name>
<name id="JOUBR">British Medical Journal</name>
<name id="YAWNS">N. S. Yawger</name>
<name id="DRYGE">George Drysdale</name>
</respStmt>
</mepHeader>
<headNote resp="MSPP">For a reprint of this article, see <title>MSM</title> C16:189. <index
level1="birth control" level2="history of"/>
<index level1="birth control" level2="international"/>
<index level1="physicians" level2="birth control and"/>
<index level1="war" level2="overpopulation and"/>
<index level1="World War I" level2="population and"/></headNote>
<docBody>
<head>The Physician and Birth Control</head>
<byline>Thomas Webster Edgar, M.D., and Margaret Sanger</byline>
<head type="sub">Foreword.</head>
<epigraph>
<p><q>Due to my great interest in birth control, legitimately sponsored and properly advocated, I
have collaborated with <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person> in presenting this
article. My interest in the subject is purely humanitarian.</q> -- <person reg="Edgar, Thomas W."
>Thomas W. Edgar</person>. </p>
</epigraph>
<p>Although it is only in the last few years that the doctrine of Birth Control has assumed the
proportions of a definitely crystallized world movement, its history is ancient. This history began
with the first crude efforts to control and direct the human reproduction. This custom of
infanticide, a custom practiced in certain portions of the globe even today, was the first crude and
barbarous expression of a dim realization that instinct must in some way be made to subserve
intelligent adaptation. The next step toward conscious control of population was the practice of
abortion. It is unnecessary here to go into the history of this cruel and barbarous practice.
Physicians even today are brought sufficiently into contact with the dangers and the frightful cost
of this emergency measure, which still remains, among large sections of the world's population, the
only method of control over the great overwhelming power of the procreative instincts. Birth
Control, as it is understood by all intelligent students today, means the substitution of scientific
contraception of a sanitary and harmless nature for the costly, cruel and often fatal customs of
infanticide and abortion. </p>
<p>The World War has concentrated interest in and thrown new light on the complex problems of
population, of racial conflicts, as well as upon the qualitative analysis of human intelligence. A
large and distinguished body of social and economic thinkers are coming to realize that the complex
economic and political problems which confront human society today are organically bound up with the
question of Birth Control. But in thus emphasizing the larger aspects of this program, we should
never forget that actual progress is impossible without the cooperation and the guidance of, the
scientist and the physician. </p>
<p>The program for Birth Control parallels recent developments in the sphere of medicine. In the war
against disease and epidemic, prevention and sanitation are now recognized as the only adequate
weapons. Undoubtedly for many years to come the majority of physicians and surgeons must direct
their energies to individual cases of disease. But because this is their task, a task requiring a
vast fund of fortitude and patience, it would be an error to suppose that the role of the physician
in society should be limited to the care and cure of the diseased and ailing. His is a vastly more
important role. His sphere is by no means limited to the mere amelioration of human suffering; it
embraces the whole of life, health as well as disease. Individual and racial health, as every day we
are coming more intensely to realize, has its own laws and structure--laws as complex, as deeply
rooted, and as worthy of investigation as those of disease. In our more superficially humanitarian
efforts we have perhaps not realized until very recently, that the prevention of disease is
dependent upon broadly based programs of social hygiene and racial prophylaxis. When laymen, as well
as physicians, awaken to the fact that disease is not a matter of chance occurrence, but is closely
related to every manifestation of life, the pivotal importance of the physician to every human
being, in health as in illness, will be recognized. The day is not far distant let us hope, when the
doctor, armed with the intimate knowledge of every phase of the human constitution, and standing
with the calm authority of far-seeing vision, may be acclaimed, rather than the priest, the
politician or the warrior, as the only true leader competent to show suffering humanity the path out
of its vale of tears. For today only to the physician is afforded a view of man as a biological
organism. If the physician be possessed of the "divine curiosity" of Science, he comes to the
realization that the greatest menace to the health of humanity is found not in those dire epidemic
of infectious or contagious diseases that may cut down whole communities, calamitous as these seem.
The direct menaces is to be found in the heritable maladies and defects which are handed down to
generation after generation, and manifest themselves in myriad forms. Thus syphilis allies itself
with feeble-mindedness. And mental defect, wearing the mask of delinquency, pauperism, prostitution
and crime, renders almost impossible the Herculean task of attaining racial health. Our poorhouses,
our prisons, our asylums for the feeble-minded, all have a common <emph rend="italics">
biological</emph> root. Crime is not merely a matter of law. It has a physiological history. A
faulty heredity, a defective germ plasm, a biological or physiological imperfection of the nervous
and endocrine system--these lie at the root of most of our social and racial problems.</p>
<p>It has been the realization of these truths that has enlisted most of the physicians and
scientists of other countries who have challenged conservative opinion by bravely championing the
cause of Birth Control. This movement is by means of propaganda of extremists who are seeking to
tell physicians and doctors their duty. On the contrary, from the earliest days of the
Neo-Malthusian agitation it has been inspired and directed by physicians who had the clear vision
that enabled them to look beyond the special individual case to the underlying significance. In
<place>England</place> those valiant pioneer Doctors <person reg="Drysdale, George">George</person>
and <person>Charles R. Drysdale</person> fought for years against the momentum of Victorian opinion.
In <place reg="the Netherlands">Holland</place>, where the First Birth Control Clinic in the world
was opened in <place reg="Amsterdam, the Netherlands">Amsterdam </place>in 1881, it has been mainly
due to the efforts of two physicians, Dr. <person reg="Jacobs, Aletta">Aletta Jacobs</person> and
Dr. <person reg="Rutgers, Johannes">J. Rutgers</person> that we have that splendid example of what
the practice of Birth Control and the establishment of clinics under the direction of trained
specialists may accomplish for a nation.</p>
<p>At the present moment, <place>England</place> offers a brilliant illustration of the interest of
physicians in the problem of Birth Control. The sensational address on "<title type="book">Married
Love</title>" of <person reg="Dawson, Lord Bertram Edward">Lord Dawson</person>, the <person
reg="George V (England)">King</person>'s physician, at the <org>Lambeth Conference of the Bishop of
the Church of England</org>, in which he defended the practice of Birth Control, is one outstanding
instance. At the <org>Fifth International Congress on Birth Control</org> held in <place
reg="London, England">London</place>last summer, the Contraceptive Section, held for doctors and
medical students only, under the presidency of Dr. <person reg="Haire, Norman">Norman
Haire</person>, illustrated the growing adherence of British physicians to the movement. It was
attended by no less than 164 medical men and women, including Lord Dawson and Sir <person
reg="Lane, William Arbuthnot">Arbuthnot Lane</person>, who, with the exception of only three
dissentients, passed this resolution:</p>
<p>"<q who="INMBC5">That this meeting of the medical members of the <title>Fifth International
Neo-Malthusian and Birth control Conference</title> wishes to point out that Birth control by
hygienic contraceptive devices is absolutely distinct from abortion in its physiological, legal and
moral aspects. It further records its opinion that there is no evidence that the best contraceptive
methods are injurious to health or conducive to sterility.</q>"</p>
<p>Similarly, the Medical Section, held under the presidency of Dr. <person
reg="Millard, C. Killick">C. Killick Millard</person>, unanimously passed the following resolution: </p>
<p>"<q who="INMBC5"> That this meeting of the Fifth International Neo-Malthusian and Birth Control
Conference, consisting chiefly of members of the British medial profession, considers that it is of
the greatest importance that the provisions of hygienic Birth Control instruction should become part
of the recognized duty of the medical profession, and that such instruction should especially be
given at all hospitals and public health centres to which the poorest classes and those suffering
from hereditary disease or defectiveness apply for help.</q>"</p>
<p>Previous to the Conference, Dr. Millard had sent a questionnaire to the leading members of the
British medical profession. From their replies, Dr. Millard reported, it could no longer be claimed
that the medical profession in <place>Great Britain</place> condemned contraceptive methods; but he
made a strong plea that the profession should concentrate its attention upon this important subject,
because, if it continued to be silent, it committed to laymen the solution of problems which are
legitimately within the sphere of its activity. Two of the leading medical journals of Great
Britain, the <title type="journal">Lancet</title> and the <title type="journal">British Medical
Journal</title>, devoted much space to the conference, especially the contraceptive and medical
aspects. The British Medical Journal notes: "<q who="JOUBR">. . .It was interesting to observe the
way in which people who were sharply divided on other subjects found a common meeting place in Birth
Control. The matter was pressed to the same conclusion from the point of view of the Socialist and
the individualist, the nationalist and the internationalist. . . .</q>" The <title type="journal"
>Lancet</title> reported the speeches of Lord Dawson, Sir Arbuthnot Lane, and other men eminent in
the medical profession. </p>
<p>But it has not been in the Western world alone that physicians have pioneered the way for
hygienic Birth Control. In <place>Japan</place>, Dr. <person reg="Ukita, Kezutami">Kezutami
Ukita</person>, a decade or so ago, courageously advocated Birth Control, in the face of the most
powerful militarists of the island empire. Dr. <person reg="Kaji, Tokojiro">Tokijiro Kaji</person>,
returning from <place>Germany</place> and Holland where he had undertaken a technical study of
contraception, devised appropriate methods for the Japanese. He established a free clinic in <place
reg="Tokyo, Japan">Tokio</place> and finally opened the <org>People's Hospital</org>, for the
benefit of women of the poorer classes. Only last year the <org reg="">Japanese Birth Control
Association</org> was organized, with Dr. Kaji as one of the four founders.</p>
<p>It would be unfair not to record here the strong support given to the Birth Control Movement in
the United States by individual physicians. The scientific and medical magazines often contain
papers of the greatest importance upon this question, and papers are read in the various societies
that bear pertinently upon Birth Control. Unfortunately the physician too often confines his remarks
to his colleagues, and the significant truths of his experiences are seldom conveyed to the general
public. Thus, Dr. <person reg="Yawger, N. S.">N. S. Yawger</person> read a compelling paper before
the <org>Philadelphia Neurological Society</org> (Foot note: January 27, 1922, <title><reg> ew York
Medical Journal</reg>N. Y. Med. Jour.</title>, Vol. CXVI, No. 6, p. 334), dealing with an epileptic
and her sixteen children, a study "<q who="YAWNS"> of a family that was rendered distressingly poor
through the circumstances of a blind father, and of an epileptic mother who scouted race suicide by
living up to sixteen pregnancies, who clung to all these maternal burdens save one--the tenth
conception miscarried--but who still ran true to a total of sixteen, by reason of her first effort
having brought forth twins.</q> Despite the fact that there was no evidence of syphilis that the
diseases and defects of the unfortunate children do not appear especially to have developed upon a
leutic basis--only three of the children appeared to have escaped the hereditary blight. Dr. Yawger
concludes that "<q who="YAWNS"> a small volume could be written upon the disorders which will
develop among the early descendants of this ill-fated family.</q>" Such studies are of the greatest
value not merely to the medical profession, but to all who have the health of the nation and the
race at heart--and where else, we may ask, is true patriotism to be found? In the matter of breeding
out disease and breeding in health, prophylaxis, as a distinguished authority asserts, is ninety per
cent. of the cure. Until the medical profession, not merely at home but in all countries in the
world, and the laity under the leadership of medical science, realize these fundamental and
unchanging truths, we cannot hope to make any progress toward the eradication of those monstrous
biological diseases, the full terror of whose blight we can only realize when we study them through
a succession of generations, when we study them genetically instead of in the individual
patient.</p>
<p>The profession of medicine stands upon the threshold of a new era in the social organism. The
physician today is in possession of truths of the most vital importance to the community; and it is
his duty, as a member of one of the noblest, if not the noblest of all professions, to co-operate to
the full extent of his ability with Science in enlightening the public concerning those necessary
<emph rend="italics"> biological</emph> laws which we must observe or perish.</p>
<p>In the past, medicine has too often been looked down upon as a plodding prosaic and uninteresting
profession, secondary in importance to that of the Church, the law, or politics. "<q who="DRYGE">
How can the voice of the physician be heard</q>," exclaimed George Drysdale, "<q who="DRYGE">if he
can urge only the feeble motives of expediency, while the moralist and the clergyman have at their
command the armory of duty and religion, with the array of eternal rewards and punishments, to
enforce reverence for their precepts?</q>" </p>
<p>It is because the Birth Control Movement is the only organized current of thought in the world
today that emphasizes the basic and fundamental place of the physician in the community that we urge
upon all members of the profession the immediate study of this problem in all its aspects. Mere
agreement with or assent to the doctrine is not enough. The immediate need of the country is
technical study and experimentation, and the presentation of the results to all parents and
parents-to-be. The destiny of the United States cannot be founded.</p>
<trailer>320West82ndStreet.</trailer>
</docBody>
</doc>
