<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Unpublished statement">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-05-02 JK initial tags</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1947-01-07">07 Jan 1947</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Biographical Note on India</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp320874</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Sripati Chandrasekhar Papers, Ward M. Canady Center for Special Collections,
                University of Toledo.</bibl>
            <bibl><title>OhUT:1</title></bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>No final version of this statement found.</p>
        <index level1="Gandhi, Mohandas K."/>
        <index level1="India" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="population policies of"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="overpopulation and"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="women in"/><index level1="India" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="birth control clinics and leagues in"/><index
            level1="conferences" level2="All India Women's Conference" level3="1935-36 (10th)"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="birth control movement in"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>I meet <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger.</person></head>

        <dateline>
            <date value="1947-01-07 "/>7th January 1947</dateline>
        <p><person reg="Mayo, Katherine">Katherine Mayo</person>’s book was, I am ashamed to
            confess, was my first introduction to <place>India</place>. I was so shocked on reading
            it that I wanted to visit India as well as startled about visiting India. That book
            later I found to be full of half truths and all the statistics she gave was so bad that
            I wonder where she got them from. Perhaps the British gave them to her. </p>
        <p> In fact her book kept me away from India for a long time though from the point of view
            of my work I wanted to visit India very badly. </p>
        <p>
            <person reg="Nehru, Jawaharlal">Nehru</person> is like <person reg="Shih, Hu">Hu
                Shih</person>. Nehru is perhaps the greatest leader <place>Asia</place> has today. </p>
        <p> To me India and her people are the kindest and gentlest people I have ever seen. </p>
        <p> I visited India in 1936 and 1939.</p>
        <p>I attended the <org>All-India Women's Conference</org> and realized that Indian women
            were brilliant. There are some women whom no women in any part of the world who can
            excel. The Indian Women Conference is better than the <org reg="League of Women Voters"
                >American league of Women Voters</org> or the<org> American Association of
                University Women</org> or for that any other womens organization in any part of the
            world. Unlike women in some parts of the world I found the Indian women most honest and
            sincere. They had no preconceived notions or any inhibitions. They had courage and
            forthright honesty. </p>

        <p>At the Conference three Catholic European women missionaries in India wanted to walk out
            of the conference. Her <person reg="Bayi, Setu Parvati">Highness the Maharani of <person
                    reg="Travancore, India">Travancore</person></person> was upset but the Birth
            Control Resolution was passed and the Catholic women who never married and never
            understood walked out. </p>
        <p>
            <person reg="Lester, Muriel">Muriel Lester</person> close to <person
                reg="Gandhi, Mohandas K.">Gandhi</person> was opposed to Birth Control just because
            Gandhi was opposed to it. </p>
        <p>Met Gandhi at <place reg="Wardha, India">Wardha</place>. Went for walks with him early
            morning at punctually 6 a.m. We did not discuss Birth Control at these walks because we
            did not have a secretary and Gandhi wanted every word to be taken down when they
            discussed Birth Control so that there may not be understanding and misquotation. </p>
        <p>When I first met him I was surprised how homely he was but after an hour when we began to
            talk about various things I realized what an illuminated soul he was-- something you
            might call spiritualism he has. </p>
        <p>Sir <person reg="Ramesam, Vepa">Vepa Ramesam</person>’s meeting in <place
                reg="Madras, India">Madras</place> and how he conducted the meeting. India’s
            population problem and the way out. No one knows the Indian people like the Indian
            leaders and advice and introduction on this question has to come from accredited and
            popular Indian leaders. </p>
        <p>I wish Indian leaders would stimulate Indian scientists in the labs to work out and
            perfect a simple contraceptive device that the Indian women can use easily. Indian
            women’s economic standards cannot let them go to clinics or doctors and use expensive
            imported contraceptives. If India can do this for her women she will be not only helping
            herself but the whole world. There are no new methods apart from what we had in 1916--
            the pessary. There is nothing dramatically new that we can use even for our own American
            women beyond the and below the medical fee line. </p>
        <p> Wanted biomedical research. </p>
        <p> I do know that some Indian women can stand on a par with some of the ablest statesmen of
            the world. </p>
        <p>I send my regards to Gandhi. I cannot forget my memorable visit at Wardha, I am just
            hoping that he has changed his mind. India like all other countries to advance the
            finest in her cannot be bogged down by poverty and to be anchored by the masses who can
            contribute to the general advancement but use up the resources of their generation.
            Every nation has the same anchorages and the way out is to stop perpetually their own
            misery and the ignorance of the numbers. </p>
        <p>I also think that India is one of the great nations of the future. Even when she becomes
            industrialized and powerful I hope she can hold to those ancient qualities of gentleness
            and kindness that I saw all over India during my travels. </p>
        <p> I met Nehru in <place reg="London, England">London</place> in 1936. He was very friendly
            and cooperative. he is one of the great minds of the modern world. He and Hu Shih will
            leave their mark over and beyond the war generals who are so much in the news these
            days. What Nehru says and does will I think live in the minds of men for a long time. I
            think he represents the total negation of what <person reg="Kipling, Rudyard"
                >Kipling</person> sang about. he is perhaps one of the few great minds who
            understands both the East and the West.</p>

        <p><place>Russia</place> devised the method of injecting the woman once every six months and
            rendering them temporarily sterile. Didn’t really work out though. I was told in Russia
            it was working with Russian women at that time. I brought the formula but it failed. </p>
        <p>Shall be glad to donate some money if some Indian biochemist would like to pursue
            research in evolving a simple foolproof and indigenous contraceptive for Indian women. </p>

        <p><org reg="Birth Control Federation of America">Birth Control Federation</org> 17 West
            16th Street, <place reg="New York, NY">New York City</place>
        </p>

        <p>Mrs. Margaret Sanger Slee </p>
        <p>2318 East Elm Street</p>
        <p><place reg="Tucson, AZ">Tucson, Arizona</place>, <place reg="United States"
            >USA</place></p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
