<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/06/07 CE</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/06/20 CE</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-18 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1958-00-00">1958</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Birth Control, 1957</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp320987</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="book">Britannica Book of the Year</title>(1958), pp.105-106.</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="WF">Watumull Foundation</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>For other articles in the <title type="book">Britannica Book of the
                Year</title> series, see <xref from="320976.xml"><title type="article">Birth
                    Control, 1944</title></xref>; <xref from="320980.xml"><title type="article"
                    >Birth Control, 1946</title></xref>; <xref from="320979.xml"><title
                    type="article">Birth Control, 1947</title></xref>; <xref from="321981.xml"
                    ><title type="article">Birth Control, 1948</title>, 1949</xref>;<xref
                from="320981.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control, 1949</title></xref>; <xref
                from="321981.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control, 1950</title></xref>; <xref
                from="320983.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control, 1951</title></xref>; <xref
                from="320984.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control, 1952</title></xref>; <xref
                from="321984.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control, 1953</title></xref>; <xref
                from="320985.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control, 1954</title></xref>; <xref
                from="320986.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control, 1955</title></xref>; <xref
                from="none.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control, 1956</title></xref>; <xref
                from="320988.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control, 1958</title>.</xref></p>
        <index level1="Asia" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Africa" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to" level3="international"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="international"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="international conferences on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="research"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="international"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="suppression of"/>
        <index level1="Europe" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="France" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="New York City" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="population growth" level2="natural resources and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Birth Control.</head>
        <p>The problems of population growth and the need for control through widespread family
            planning programs were increasingly recognized during 1957. At a <org
                reg="Lambeth Conference">conference of the bishops</org> of the <org>Church of
                    <place>England</place></org> at Lambeth palace, the control of rising population
            was realistically appraised. At a meeting of the <org>International Rice
                commission</org> in <place reg="Lucknow, India">Lucknow, India</place>, the <person
                reg="Sen, Binay Ranjan">director-general</person> of the <org>United Nations Food
                and Agricultural organization</org> announced that production of food grains was
            hardly keeping pace with the population growth and a great part of the world was in want
            and hunger. In <place reg="New York, NY">New York</place>, speakers at a meeting of the
                <org>American Association for the Advancement of Science</org> declared that
            explosive population growth might soon threaten even the <place>United States</place>
            standard of living.</p>
        <p>Throughout <place>Africa</place> a widened interest in controlling numbers through birth
            control was evidenced by the spread of private family planning work, aided by partial
            government support. The <org>South African National Council for Maternal and Family
                Welfare</org> had since 1935 steadily provided birth control services for the lowest
            income group, irrespective or race or creed. The council received an annual grant of
            £1,000 from the government health department.</p>
        <p>In <place>France</place>, where birth control has been forbidden by law since 1920, a new
            organization, the <org reg="Association Maternit&eacute; Heureuse">Happy Motherhood
                association</org>, announced plans for an intensive social and psychological study
            of current French attitudes toward birth control and related subjects. The group also
            hoped to establish counseling centres, modeled after those of the <org
                reg="National Marriage Guidance Council">Marriage Guidance council</org> in <place
                reg="Great Britain">Britain</place>, where French couples could go for marital
            advice.</p>
        <p>The <org reg="Family Planning Association of Singapore"><place>Singapore</place> Family
                Planning association</org> pressed for bigger government grants and received an
            increase from $28,335 to $33,333. Plans for the year included six new clinics and
            expansion of home visiting services. In <place>Poland</place>, where the first birth
            control clinic opened in <place reg="Warsaw, Poland">Warsaw</place> in 1931 under
            auspices of the <org>Workmen’s Association for Social Services</org>, advice on setting
            up family planning clinics was sought and received from the <org>International Planned
                Parenthood federation</org>.</p>
        <p>The <org>Watumull foundation</org> of the U.S. offered, during the year, an award for the
            first “<q who="WF">ideal, universally acceptable contraceptive developed in India within
                three years</q>.” An independent, nine-member committee was set up to test and
            evaluate contraceptives submitted. At the same time, efforts were continued in the
            search for a reliable oral contraceptive at the <org>Central Drug Research
                institute</org> in Lucknow, in collaboration with the <org>Indian Council of Medical
                Research</org> and the <org><place reg="Calcutta, India">Calcutta</place>
                Bacteriological institute</org>.</p>
        <p>Numerous family planning conferences took place in various parts of the world in 1957,
            including the first <org reg="All-Japan Conference on Family Planning, 1st">all-Japan
                Conference on Family Planning</org> in <place reg="Tokyo, Japan">Tokyo</place> with
            more than 1,500 participants and the third <org>all-India Conference on Family
                Planning</org> in Calcutta in January, where six-day sessions assessed “National
            Development Programs and Family Planning.” Delegates from all part of
                <place>Europe</place>, the <place>near east</place> and Africa gathered in <place
                reg="West Berlin, Federal Republic of Germany">West Berlin</place> in October for
            the International Planned Parenthood federation’s regional conference. Discussions
            centered on the moral, physical and psychological foundations for healthy family
            life.</p>
        <p>A group of clergymen, medical men and social scientists participated in a symposium at
            the <org>Planned Parenthood Federation of America</org>’s 37th annual meeting in New
            York City in October. Discussion on the medical, moral and social implications of new
            contraceptives included reports on preliminary tests of new birth control methods. The
            symposium’s consensus was that some of the newer contraceptive methods were about to
            leave the experimental stage and enter into wide clinical use; other methods, however,
            were still too new to be completely evaluated. The featured speaker at the annual
            meeting was <person reg="Adams, Grantley Herbert">Sir Grantley Herbert Adams</person>,
            first premier of <place>Barbados</place>, who told an audience of 800 that
            underdeveloped countries needed assistance from the scientists and governments of more
            advanced nations if they were to cope effectively with explosive population growth.</p>
        <p>During the year the American federation established biological research and social
            research committees to guide and coordinate work in research in human reproduction. The
            Planned Parenthood Federation of America also became a member of the sponsoring and
            participating organizations of the <org>National Citizens Committee</org> for the
                <org>United Nations</org>
            <org>World Health organization</org>.</p>
        <byline>(<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">M.SR.</person>)</byline>
    </docBody>
</doc>
