<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/05/31 CH began encoding/transcription</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/06/01 CH finished initial encoding/transcription</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2013/05/07 CH title cleanup</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-07-03 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1947-00-00">1947</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Birth Control, 1946</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp320980</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="book">Britannica Book of the Year</title> (1947), pp. 119-20</bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="ORRJO">Orr, John Boyd</name>
            <name id="ICPWR">International Congress on Population in Relation to World
                Resources</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>For other articles in the <title type="book">Britannica Book of the
                Year</title> series, see <xref from="320980.xml"><title type="article">Birth
                    Control, 1946</title></xref>; <xref from="320979.xml"><title type="article"
                    >Birth Control, 1947</title>
            </xref>; <xref from="321981.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control,
                1948</title></xref>;<xref from="320981.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control,
                    1949</title></xref>; <xref from="321981.xml"><title>Birth Control, 1950</title>
            </xref>; <xref from="320983.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control,
                1951</title></xref>; <xref from="320984.xml"><title>Birth Control,
                1952</title></xref>; <xref from="321984.xml"><title>Birth Control,
                1953</title></xref>; <xref from="320985.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control,
                    1954</title></xref>; <xref from="320986.xml"><title type="article">Birth
                    Control, 1955</title></xref>; <xref from="none.xml"><title type="article">Birth
                    Control, 1956</title></xref>; <xref from="320987.xml"><title type="article"
                    >Birth Control, 1957</title></xref>; <xref from="320988.xml"><title
                    type="article">Birth Control, 1958</title></xref></p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues" level3="in US"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Massachusetts"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="research"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="American"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="international"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="opposition to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="international conferences on"/>
        <index level1="Planned Parenthood Federation of America"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="religion and"/>
        <index level1="physicians" level2="birth control and"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Birth Control</head>
        <div>
            <p>The first comprehensive program on research in human reproduction was bugun during
                1948. Nine studies were started on factors governing fertility control and problems
                of infertility in as many institutions throughout the country. They were recommeded
                by the <org reg="National Research Council Committee on Human Reproduction">National
                    Research council's Committee on Human Reproduction</org> to the board of the
                    <org>National Committee on Maternal Health</org>; funds were raised mainly by
                the <org>Planned Parenthood Federation of America</org>, one of the three
                collaborating organizations. The dearth of scientific work in fertility control
                resulted in numerous applications for study of fields other than conception
                control.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Population.--</head>
            <p>The <org>International Congress on Population and World Resources in Relation to the
                    Family</org>, held in <place>Cheltenham, England</place>, was an indication of
                the rising interest among scientists and the lay public in world population
                problems. Sir <person reg="Orr, John Boyd">John Orr</person>, former director of the
                    <org reg="United Nations Food and Agriculture Organization">World Food and
                    Agricultural</org> organization told the congress, "<q who="ORRJO">If we cannot
                    solve the problem of world resources in this century, we are heading for the
                    greatest catastrophe in history. . . hungry people do not die quietly; and why
                    should they?</q>" Representatives from more than 20 countries participated. They
                were leaders in three fields: scientific and social inquiry, biological and medical
                research, and organizational activity in the promotion of planned parenthood. A
                provisional international committee was established with headquarters in <place
                    reg="London, England">London</place>. Its purpose was "<q who="ICPWR">to promote
                    research and education for the furthering of human welfare through planned
                    parenthood and progressive sex education.</q>" Members were the national Planned
                Parenthood organizations of <org><place reg="Family Planning Association">Great
                        Britain</place></org>, the <org
                    reg="Nederlandse Vereniging voor Sexuele Hervorming"
                    ><place>Netherlands</place></org>, <org><place
                        reg="Riksförbundet för sexuell upplysning">Sweden</place></org>, and the
                    <place>United States</place>, the only four nations where such agencies
                existed.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Magazine Poll.--</head>
            <p>A poll of more than 3,000,000 women was conducted by the <title type="journal"
                    >Woman's Home Companion</title>. Three-fifths favored making birth-control
                information available to all adults, and 97% of those polled approved birth control
                measures for use by married women.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Committee on Clinic Studies.--</head>
            <p>A demonstration to evaluate the practical efficiency of simple existing contraceptive
                methods was developed in order to broaden the use of conception control in public
                health. The need for such as study was indicated by the small percentage
                (approximately 5%) of patients attending pre- and postnatal public health clinics
                receiving conception-control information.</p>
            <p>It was found after an investigation by <person reg="Kling, L. E. ">L. E.
                    Kling</person>, federation medical director, of clinics in
                    <place>Florida</place>, <place>Mississippi</place>, <place reg="North Carolina"
                    >North</place> and <place>South Carolina</place>, <place>Virginia</place>,
                    <place>West Virginia</place>, <place>Georgia</place> and <place>Alabama</place>
                that staffs were too overworked to give time to fitting and instructing patients.
                Many patients did not know this service was available, since neither the public
                health nurse nor health educator mentioned or encouraged it.</p>
            <p>A <org reg="Planned Parenthood Federation of America, Committee on Clinic Studies"
                    >committee on clinic studies</org> was appointed by the federation's <org
                    reg="Planned Parenthood Federation of America, Medical Committee">Medical
                    Executive committee</org>. It was given the support of private physicians who
                agreed on the need to encourage practical application of planned parenthood in
                public health.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"><place>Massachusetts</place> Birth-Control Referendum.--</head>
            <p>A birth-control referendum on the question of allowing physicians to prescribe
                contraceptives to married women whose health or life, in the judgement of the
                physician, required it, was defeated by 200,000 votes in the 1948 Massachusetts
                election.</p>
            <p>The measure, which aimed to place contraceptive advice in the hands of the medical
                profession, was endorsed by a majority of resident members of the <org>Massachusetts
                    Medical society</org> and by more than 1,000 Protestant and Jewish clergymen.
                Four thousand volunteers in 300 local communities campaigned to repeal the state
                law.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Organization.--</head>
            <p>The Planned Parenthood federation was in 1948 the national agency and clearinghouse
                for 15 state leagues and 166 local committees. The total number of birth-control
                clinics stood at 557. These services were in 242 public health clinics, 62 hospital
                clinics, 210 extramural clinics and 43 referral services. Of the 58 fertility
                clinics in the U. S. listed with the federation, 13 were under Planned Parenthood
                direction.</p>
        </div>
        <byline>(<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">M. Sr.</person>)</byline>
    </docBody>
</doc>
