<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-01-06 CH transcribed and encoded</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1916-05-16">16 May 1926</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Speech to the Women of Indianapolis</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp321957</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Birth Control Expounded Here</title><title type="journal"
					>Indianapolis Star</title>, May 16, 1916, p. 5.</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="IS">Indianapolis Star</name>
			<name id="BIB">Bible</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>Sanger delivered this speech during the <org>National Conference of Charities and
				Correction</org>, held at the <org>Claypool Hotel</org> in <place
				reg="Indianapolis, IN">Indianapolis</place>. program. </p>
		<index level1="abortion" level2="illegal"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="class-based"/>
		<index level1="mortality rates" level2="infant"/>
		<index level1="mortality rate" level2="maternal"/>
		<index level1="motherhood" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="poverty" level2="family size and"/>
		<index level1="prostitution"/>
		<index level1="race suicide"/>
		<index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="speaking tour, 1916 (U.S.)"/>
		<index level1="women" level2="employment of"/>
		<index level1="women" level2="freedom and rights of"/>
		<index level1="women" level2="health of"/>
		<index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
		<index level1="working classes" level2="birth control and"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Birth Control Expounded Here</head>
		<head type="sub">Indianpolis Women Flock to Hear Mrs. Margaret Sanger and Hiss Opponents to
			Practice at End of Meeting</head>
		<div type="section">
			<q who="US">
				<p>It would seem that many Indianapolis women are in favor of birth control, as
					advocated by Mrs. Margaret Sanger, of <place reg="New York, NY">New
					York</place>, judging from the way they hooted, hissed and ridiculed with
					penetrating feminine giggles the efforts of a few scattered "antis" who
					endeavored to make themselves heard at the close of Mrs. Sanger's lecture
					yesterday afternoon.</p>
				<p>It was a vast crowd of women, with a few men scattered here and there, that
					thronged into the assembly room at the Claypool Hotel to hear Mrs. Sanger. They
					filled every seat and all the aisles; they rested on window sills and on tables
					and sat on the floor. Some of them may have been there merely out of curiosity
					to hear Mrs. Sanger, who has been arrested for spreading her propaganda of
					advocating that the ban of medical secrecy shall be lifted in regard to
					disseminating information that will enable a woman to determine the number of
					children she shall bear. Every woman in the audience, however, listened with
					breathless interest while Mrs. Sanger told of the history of the movement, and
					of what it would mean to the working women, especially if the law would consent
					to their becoming possessed of necessary information.</p>
			</q>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">Distinct from Conference</head>
			<q who="IS">
				<p>The address of Mrs. Sanger was not under the auspices of the National Conference
					of Charities and Correction, and was not on the official program of meetings or
					papers of the conference, but a large number of the delegates and visitors to
					the big meetings head the talk.</p>
			</q>
			<p>"There is all this talk about race suicide." <q who="IS">said Mrs. Sanger.</q> "I say
				the race ought to commit suicide unless it can take care of its children better. We
				know that <person reg="Roosevelt, Theodore">Theodore Roosevelt</person> goes up and
				down the country urging women to have large families and he is neither arrested nor
				molested--yet I am persecuted for urging small families for people of the poorest
				class who can not afford to have a great number of children. If it is wrong to tell
				young women how they may have small families, how much worse it would seem to be to
				urge them to have large families.</p>
			<p>"Every year there are 250,000 illegal operations performed in this country, with the
				deaths of 50,000 mothers as a result; every year 300,000 babies die of poverty and
				neglect--yet we prevent the parents from gaining that knowledge of how to prevent
				300,000 more babies, who can not be taken care of to come into the world only to die
				of poverty and neglect.</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">For Working Women</head>
			<p>"The working women want this knowledge as well as the wealthier women, who already
				are possessed of it to a certain extent, for while the physicians are most religious
				in obeying the law in forbidding them to impart this knowledge in the case of the
				poor women, they seem willing to give it to women of a higher class. One of the
				arguments against birth control is that it would tend to lower the standards of
				women's morals--but the guarding of women's morals is nothing but an age-old cloak
				to keep her in bondage. The time has come to stop quibbling. When education for
				women was first begun it had this same opposition and on the same grounds--but
				education has not impaired women's moral standards and we would find that a knowlege
				of birth control would not impair them.</p>
			<p>"The insane asylums and feebel-minded insitututes are huge monuments to reckless
				breeding. It is a fact that a great percentage of prostitutes come from families of
				eight or nine children, who were unable to care for the children once they had
				brought them into the world In the large cities the birth rate of the wealthy
				districts is about one-third of that of the poorer districts, and my experience has
				been taht a women living on a wage of $10 a week does not desire a large family;
				when she has three or four children, she is in constant terror that another may
				come, and when the laws forbid her to be given knowledge on how to prevent this, she
				is forced into the hands of quacks and midwives. When the practice of performing
				certain operations was put under the ban of the law and the church its alternate
				evil, the foundling asylum, immediately sprang up.</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">Clinics in Holland</head>
			<p>"In <place>New Zealand</place> and <place reg="Netherlands">Holland</place>, where
				they have clinics where women may obtain information regarding birth control,
				prostitution is practically unknown. There, when a new baby comes, it is like an
				automobile or a grand piano, something that families do not have unless they want
				it, and can afford to have it and take care of it. In <place reg="United States"
					>America</place> we have the best of foundations for establishing these clinics,
				especially in the industrial and agricultural districts, where women could come for
				instruction from nurses. Where the poor continue to breed it invariably leads to
				greatly increased mortality, and is 'up to' the scientists and doctors to direct the
				great wave in favor of teaching birth control</p>
			<q who="IS">
				<p>When the lecture was ended and a general discussion was announced by <person
						reg="Blossom, Frederick A.">Frederick A. Blossom</person> of <place
						reg="Cleveland, OH">Cleveland</place> who managed the meeting and presided
					over it. Dr. <person reg="Graham, Hannah M.">Hannah M. Graham</person> was the
					first one to speak. Dr. Graham wished to know, first, where the country would
					have been had <person reg="Lincoln, Nancy Hanks">Abraham Lincoln's
						mother</person> been an advocate of birth control, and, secondly, how the
					advocates of birth control reconciled their beliefs with the line in the
						<title>Bible</title> that says "<q who="BIB">Suffer the little children to
						come to us.</q>" </p>
			</q>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">Chorus of Hisses</head>
			<p><q who="IS">There was a wild chorus of hisses and laughs, and when the tumult was
					stilled, the answer was made that </q>"The kingdome of heaven today is full of
				little children that have suffered to come unto you, and as for <person
					reg="Lincoln, Abraham">Abraham Lincoln</person>--there was only one of him."</p>
			<p>
				<q who="IS">Up rose another opponent and asked how about the passage in the Bible
					where the <name type="deity">Lord</name> told <person
						reg="Adam (Biblical figure)">Adam</person> to go forth and replenish, the
					reply to this was that Adam had the whole earth to himself.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="IS">Each answer in favor of the birth control brought forth loud and
					prolonged appluause and each question that indicated that the questioner in any
					way was opposed to it brought forth a storm of hisses and laughs. In the midset
					of this excitement, slips were passed about the audience requesting that all
					women interested in forming a league for the furthering of the movement should
					sign, and hundreds of women busily affixed their names to the little slips of
					paper.</q>
			</p>
		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
