<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014/04/11 VS initial tagging</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-22 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1928-09-14">14 Sept 1928</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Statement on Maternal Mortality</supplied></titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp321979</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">New York Woman Hopes to Curb Mortality Among
				Mothers</title>, <title type="journal">Portsmouth Herald</title>, Sept. 14, 1928, p.
				9 </bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="PH">Portsmouth Herald</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<index level1="American Birth Control League"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits and risks"/>
		<index level1="birth control movement" level2="history of"/>
		<index level1="mortality rates" level2="maternal"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>NEW YORK WOMAN HOPES TO CURB MORTALITY AMONG MOTHERS</head>
		<q who="PH">
			<p><dateline><place reg="New York, NY">New York</place>.--</dateline> An intensive study
				of methods of reducing the morality among mothers as a result of childbirth will be
				undertaken by Mrs. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>, founder
				and president of the <org>American Birth Control League</org> and one of the
				foremost advocates of scientifically applied birth control in the world. Maternal
				mortality is greater in <place reg="United States">this country</place>, Mrs. Sanger
				said, than any other country in the civilized world, except <place>Chile</place>.
			</p>
		</q>
		<p> “Statistics on the subject of maternal mortality are of doubtful values,” <q who="PH"
				>Mrs. Sanger declared in a statement given out last night,</q> “but the record shows
			that in 1925, 647 mothers died of every 100,000 live births.” </p>
		<q who="PH">
			<p> She charged that work to lower the death rate of mothers in childbirth had been
				ineffective in the last ten years and advocated proper birth control as the solution
				of the problem. </p>
		</q>
		<p> “In 1926,” <q who="PH">said Mrs. Sanger,</q> “656 mothers in every 100,000 gave their
			lives. Since there has been no decline in these figures, which include only about 76
			percent of the total population of the United States. </p>
		<p> “I have been interested in this problem since 1914, and it was my interest in this
			particular aspect of the situation that led to the beginnings of a birth-control
			movement. I feel now that the time has come when I can turn over to the others the
			organization, legislative and educational features of active birth-control work. </p>
		<p> “As I have long wished to do, I will devote myself to a scientific study of the causes
			and cures of this terrific sacrifice of the lives of child-bearing women. I feel
			confident that a serious study will lead to a scientific demonstration of the fact that
			maternal mortality can be reduced by the application of birth-control knowledge. </p>
		<p> “Infant mortality in the United States has been appreciably lowered in the last ten
			years, but nothing of consequence has been accomplished in lowering the death-rate of
			mothers.</p>
		<p> “I am preparing to spend a period of from three to five years in the collection of
			material, in sociological investigation and in gathering facts generally pertinent to
			the situation. In this work I will have the aid and cooperation of some of the foremost
			authorities in the world.”</p>
		<q who="PH">
			<p> Mrs. Sanger tendered her resignation as president of the League, which she founded,
				in order to devote herself wholly to this phase of the work. </p>
		</q>
	</docBody>
</doc>
