<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article ">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-02-26 JK initial tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-02-28 CH proof tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-05 JK corrected tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-11-14 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1923-04-08">08 Apr 1923</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Apostle of Birth Control Sees Cause Gaining
                Here</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp321972</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Apostle of Birth Control Sees Cause
                    Gaining Here</title>, <title type="journal">New York
                    Times</title>, Apr. 8, 1923, p. XII</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="SANTZ">Sang, Tzi</name>
            <name id="LUSE">Lu, Set</name>
            <name id="CHI">Chinese</name>
            <name id="MALTH">Malthus, Thomas Robert</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="birth control" level2="neo-Malthusian arguments for"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="speaking tours"
            level3="1922 (China)"/>
        <index level1="China" level2="overpopulation and"/>
        <index level1="China" level2="population policies of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="in New York"/>
        <index level1="China" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="England" level2="MS on"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Apostle of Birth Control Sees Cause Gaining Here</head>
        <head type="sub">Hearing in Albany on Bill to Legalize Practice a
            Milestone in Long Fight of <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret
                Sanger</person>-- Even <place reg="China">China
            </place>Awakening to Need of Selective Methods, She Says.</head>
        <byline>by Margaret SangerPresident<org> American Birth Control
                League</org></byline>

        <p>After ten years of incessant agitation and activity the
            much-discussed question of birth control has invaded the legislative
            halls of <place reg="Albany, NY">Albany</place>. A bill intended to
            amend existing laws so that <place>New York</place> physicians may
            be authorized to disseminate contraceptive advice has been
            introduced. There will be a hearing on that matter in the <org
                reg="New York State Assembly">Assembly Chamber</org> on April
            10. If enacted, we may hope for the beginning of a new era of social
            welfare and racial hygiene. But whatever the outcome, this bill
            means that birth control is no longer looked upon, even in the
            judicial and legislative field, as a topic obscene and indecent,”
            worthy only of ribald jest and suggestive leer.</p>
        <p>No other great problem affecting the welfare of nation and race has
            been more misinterpreted and misunderstood, even by Americans who
            consider themselves well informed. Advocates of this doctrine do not
            beg for mere assent or approval. They ask for investigation and
            understanding, as the initial step toward support and adherence to
            their doctrines.</p>
        <p> Much of the opposition to birth control has had its source among
            clergymen and other professional moralists. This ecclesiastic
            opposition is amazing in view of the fact that the “onlie true
            begetter” of the whole birth control movement, <person
                reg="Malthus, Thomas Robert">Robert Malthus</person>, was
            himself a clergyman of the <org reg="Church of England">Church of
                England.</org> He advocated <q who="MALTH">prudential
                checks</q>" on the grounds of austere morality. Our clerical
            opponents also ignore the fact that many of the most noted champions
            of birth control today are clergymen. The most noteworthy example is
            that of the distinguished Dean of <org reg="St. Paul's Cathedral"
                >St. Paul’s</org>, <place reg="London, England">London</place>,
                <person reg="Inge, William Ralph">William Ralph Inge</person>. </p>
        <p>There is a confusion in the public mind concerning the origin of the
            present movement, which must be distinguished from the so-called
            Neo-Malthusian movement of <place reg="Great Britain">Great
                Britain</place> and the <place reg="Europe">Continent</place>.
            The <org reg="Malthusian League">Neo-Malthusian League</org> was the
            direct outcome of the celebrated trial in London in 1877 of <person
                reg="Bradlaugh, Charles">Charles Bradlaugh </person>and
                Mrs.<person reg="Besant, Annie">Annie Besant</person>, who had
            frankly admitted distributing among the English poor thousands upon
            thousands of copies of the pamphlet of a <place reg="Boston, MA"
                >Boston</place> physician, Dr. <person reg="Knowlton, Charles"
                >Knowlton</person>, entitled “<title type="book">Fruits of
                Philosophy</title>,” originally published in this country in
            1833. The <org>Neo-Malthusian League</org>, sponsored by those
            valiant pioneers, <person reg="Drysdale, Charles R.">Charles </person>
            and <person reg="Drysdale, George">George Drysdale</person> and Dr.
                <person reg="Vickery, Alice">Alice Vickery</person>, soon spread
            to all countries of the continent, and its doctrines were put into
            practice in <place reg="Netherlands">Holland</place>, where
            fifty-three birth control clinics, approved by the <org
                reg="Government of the Netherlands">Dutch Government</org>, have
            been conducted with great success for forty years. </p>
        <p>The birth control movement, which has now absorbed the earlier
            Neo-Malthusian movement, originated right here in <place
                reg="New York, NY">New York</place> just a decade ago. While the
            Neo-Malthusians based their propaganda on the broad general basis of
            Malthus’s theory of population, the expression “birth control” was
            devised in my little paper of advance feminism, <title
                type="journal">The Woman Rebel</title>, as one of the
            fundamental rights of the emancipation of working women. The
            response to this idea of birth control was so immediate and so
            overwhelming that a league was formed-- the first birth control
            league in the world. </p>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Why She Took Up Task.</head>
            <p>With all the flame-like ardor of pioneers we did not at first
                realize the full scope of this fundamental discovery. At that
                time I knew nothing of Malthus, nothing of the courageous and
                desperate battle waged by the Drysdales in <place reg="England"
                    >England</place>, <person reg="Rutgers, Johannes"
                    >Rutgers</person> in Holland, of <person
                    reg="Giroud, Gabriel"> G. Hardy </person>and <person
                    reg="Robin, Paul">Paul Robin</person> in <place reg="France"
                    >France</place>, for this century-old doctrine. I was merely
                thinking of the poor mothers of congested districts of the East
                Side who had so poignantly begged me for relief, in order that
                the children they had already brought into the world might have
                a chance to grow into strong and stalwart Americans. It was
                almost impossible to believe that the dissemination of knowledge
                easily available to the intelligent and thoughtful parents of
                the well-to-do-classes was actually a criminal act, proscribed
                not only by State laws but by Federal as well.</p>
            <p>My paper was suppressed. I was arrested and indicted by the <org
                    reg="United States Post Office">Federal authorities</org>.
                But owing to the vigorous protests of the public and an appeal
                sent by a number of distinguished English writers and thinkers,
                the case against me was finally abandoned. Meanwhile “birth
                control” became the slogan of the idea and not only spread
                through the American press from coast to coast, but immediately
                gained currency in <place>Great Britain</place>. Succinctly and with telling
                brevity and precision “birth control” summed up our whole
                philosophy. Birth control is not contraception indiscriminately
                and thoughtlessly practiced. It means the release and
                cultivation of the better racial elements in our society, and
                the gradual suppression, elimination and eventual extirpation of
                defective stocks-those human weeds which threaten the blooming
                of the finest flowers of American civilization. </p>
            <p>In our efforts to effect the repeal of the existing laws which
                declare the use of contraceptive methods indecent and obscene,
                birth control advocated have been forced to battle every inch of
                the way. To get the matter before the Legislature of New York my
                path has led completely around the earth. Our effort has been to
                enlist the support of the best minds of every country, an object
                we have achieved even beyond our fondest expectations.</p>
            <p>The backbone of the birth control movement has been from the time
                Malthus first published his epoch-making <title type="book"
                    >“Principles of Population”</title> essentially Anglo-Saxon.
                    <person reg="Mill, John Stuart">John Stuart Mill</person>,
                    <person reg="Place, Francis">Francis Place,</person>
                <person reg="Arnold, Matthew">Matthew Arnold</person>, <person
                    reg="Huxley, Thomas">Thomas Huxley</person> and our own
                    <person reg="Jefferson, Thomas"> Thomas
                    Jefferson</person>,<person reg="Madison, James"> James
                    Madison</person>, <person reg="Emerson, Ralph Waldo">Ralph
                    Waldo Emerson</person> and <person
                    reg="Ingersoll, Robert G.">Robert G. Ingersoll</person>
                spoke openly in favor of control of the population. Today such
                thinkers and writers as <person reg="Wells, H. G.">H.G.
                    Wells</person>, <person reg="Cox, Harold">Harold
                    Cox</person> (editor of <title type="journal">The Edinburgh
                    Review</title>), <person reg="Bennett, Arnold">Arnold
                    Bennett</person>, Dean Inge, <person reg="Archer, William"
                    >William Archer</person>, <person reg="Ellis, Havelock"
                    >Havelock Ellis,</person>
                <person reg="Murray, Gilbert">Gilbert Murray</person>, <person
                    reg="Russell, Bertram">Bertram Russell</person>, <person
                    reg="Keynes, John Maynard">John Maynard Keynes</person>
                (editor of <title type="journal">The Nation</title>), and
                    <person reg="Dawson, Bertrand">Lord Dawson</person>, one of
                the <person reg="George V of England">King</person>’s
                physicians, and innumerable others in Great Britain speak openly
                and valiantly for birth control.</p>
            <p>It is not without significance that since the inauguration of our
                agitation in 1913 there has been an immense recrudescence of
                interest in the persistent problem of population; and a number
                of new efforts, notably that of <person
                    reg="Carr-Saunders, Alexander Morris">A.M.
                    Carr-Saunders</person>, to reinterpret the thesis so
                brilliantly advanced by that obscure clergyman, Malthus. </p>
            <p>Most gratifying to the battle-scarred propagandist for birth
                control has been the awakening of the Orient.
                    <place>China</place> and <place>Japan</place> for ages have
                been the notoriously overpopulated countries of the earth, the
                high birth rate, as always, accompanied by a high death rate, a
                high infant mortality rate and even acceptance of the widespread
                practice of infanticide. Famine, pestilence and flood have been
                the only checks to overpopulation in China, and these have been
                regarded even as a blessing by the yellow races. “<foreign
                    rend="CHI">Yang to meng ping</foreign>” is a well known
                exclamation in China-- “<q who="UNK">Many men, life cheap!</q>” </p>
            <p>Following my sojourn in China last year, the <title
                    type="journal">Ladies’ Journal of China</title>, the most
                influential women’s publication there, devoted a special edition
                of more than one hundred pages to the problem of birth control.
                In this paper <person reg="Sang, Tzi">Tzi Sang</person> wrote:
                    <q who="SANTZ">“Since Mrs. Sanger’s visit public opinion has
                    been greatly influenced, and I understand that some
                    educators are planning to propagate the doctrine in the
                    interior so that our women will no longer be mere machines
                    for breeding children. When the majority of our people know
                    the benefits of birth control and believe that it is the
                    remedy for plague, famine and war in China, then we can
                    adopt the method of asking doctors to pass on their
                    knowledge to women poor in health.”</q>
            </p>
            <p><person reg="Lu, Set">Set Lu</person>, another writer in the same
                paper, points out that <q who="LUSE">“if we study the actual
                    situation in China we find that unconsciously the Chinese
                    have attempted to practice birth control in a different way.
                    Do we not throw away our babies?”</q> frankly asks this
                writer of his compatriots. His answer is interesting: “<q
                    who="LUSE">Savages practice infanticide, but civilized
                    people use scientific methods of prevention. Herein lies the
                    difference between a barbarous and a civilized people. No
                    wonder that our civilization fails to make any noticeable
                    advance</q>.”</p>
            <p>Both in Japan and China, as a result of my visit, and especially
                as the effect of the attempt upon the part of the <org>Imperial
                    Japanese Government</org> to suppress birth control and to
                shut its door in my face, the subject of birth control has
                aroused the deepest and most widespread interest among all
                classes.In both these great Oriental empires the roots of a
                permanent birth control movement have struck deep in popular
                interest, and undoubtedly will exert a great influence toward
                bringing down the alarmingly high birth rates to the level of
                those of Western civilization. The importance, the immediate
                necessity of an autonomous control of the birth rate by the
                races of the Orient is by no one more emphatically stated than
                by that eloquent and picturesque writer and traveler, <person
                    reg="Bland, J. O. P.">J. O. P. Bland.</person>
            </p>
            <p>Since the first birth control clinic established in this country
                was raided by the <org reg="New York City Police Department">New
                    York Police</org> in <place reg="Brooklyn, NY"
                    >Brownsville</place>, some years ago, and its founders
                sentenced to jail as petty miscreants, the whole current of
                opinion has advanced, not merely in this country but throughout
                the world. The results of the intelligence tests, the menace of
                indiscriminate immigration, the fertility of the unfit and the
                increasing burden upon the healthful and vigorous members of
                American society of the delinquent and dependent classes,
                together with the growing danger of the abnormal fecundity of
                the feeble-minded, all emphasize the necessity of
                clear-sightedness and courageously facing the problem and the
                possibilities of birth control as a practical and feasible
                weapon against national and racial decadence.</p>
            <p>With the invasion of the <org reg="New York State Legislature">New York Legislature</org>
                exponents of this challenging doctrine may well congratulate
                themselves that they have won another victory against their
                opponents. Whatever the outcome of the hearing on April 10,
                birth control in any event will have compelled serious attention
                from our legislators. If we can convince the Assemblymen and
                State Senators that this is a matter which concerns not merely a
                group of "well-meaning” feminists, but is organically bound up
                with the biological welfare of the whole community, we shall
                consider that our efforts have not been entirely in vain. </p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
