<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article ">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014/02/26 JK</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-03-13 CH proof tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-03-26 JK correct tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-12-16 CH correct and enter tags</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="/1920-02-00/ ">Feb. 1920</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>Birth Control the Key to International Peace and Security
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp321974</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="journal">The Birth Control Review</title> Feb.
				1920, pp. 3-4</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="GOSGE">Goschen, George</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">Unsigned editorial believed to be written by Margaret
		Sanger. <index level1="Europe" level2="birth control in"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="peace and"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="international"/>
		<index level1="birth control movement"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Editorial Comment</head>
		<head type="sub">Birth Control the Key to International Peace and
			Security</head>

		<p>MOST INTELLIGENT people who have given the population problem any
			thought at all now acknowledge the world’s crying need for Birth
			Control. The few who still remain unconvinced could not remain so if
			they visited the European countries which are suffering most acutely
			from the consequences of the war. Had the war succeeded in jolting
			Europe out of its old ways of thinking and feeling, had it smashed
			up its old romantic and sentimental ideals, had I awakened men and
			women to the values of human life and human standards, it might
			after all have justified itself. If it had taught people the
			insanity of that hideous waste of human life, the danger of petty
			chauvinistic quarrels, and awakened them to the absolute need of
			international co-operation, it would not have been in vain. Instead,
			it seems to me after my months in <place>Central Europe</place> and
				<place>Great Britain</place>, the old reactionary and sinister
			forces are the first in the field to throw dust in the eyes of the
			awakened and disillusioned victims of the great disaster. In the
			face of wholesale starvation and disease, the militarists and the
			imperialists are still crying aloud for more babies. This despite
			the cruel fact that the children who have already been brought into
			the world by starving parents, are too weak, too undernourished to
			stand, even to hold up their heads. These are to become the torch
			bearers of the human race! The great duty of those of us who are
			convinced of the necessity of the intelligence, and therefore of the
			high morality of Birth Control, is to awaken and mobilize the
			intelligence of the whole world about this problem.</p>
		<p> WE HAVE PASSED the initial stage of controversy, of attack and
			discussion, of breaking the taboo of silence. The war which swept
			aside the old pruriencies concerning sex, has emphasized and
			accentuated the problem of population--showing it for those who have
			unprejudiced eyes to see-- in the problems thrust every day before
			our eyes by the news papers, pleas to save the starving children of
			Central Europe, appeals to aid the thirty million starving Chinese,
			questions of immigration and exclusion, the thousand “neediest
			cases,” reports on the increase of heritable disease and the
			congenitally feeble minded, plagues and pestilence bred and
			propagated in this overcrowded world, the effort of the <org>Roman
				Catholic Church</org> to stop, upon the basis of its traditional
			dogma, the rising and inevitable practice of Birth Control, the
			organization of huge international charities and philanthropies,
			through which the people of the less crowded and more prosperous
			nations are encouraged to pay for and palliate the inevitable
			disasters that follow blind and reckless breeding. More and more the
			whole world is looking to the people of <place reg="United States"
				>America </place>for financial support, for food, for the
			expression of our traditional generosity.</p>
		<p>In facing all these complex problems, let us attempt first and always
			to seek the intelligent solution. Let us be generous, certainly! Let
			us minister to the needs of the afflicted and the disinherited, but
			in so doing, there is no need of wallowing in pathos and
			sentimentality. Let us remember that generosity does not preclude
			intelligence. We must not merely give, we must also guide.</p>
		<p> To be creative, to be constructive, international charity faces the
			important duty, not primarily of relieving the sufferings of the
			afflicted, the starving and the diseased, but of preventing
			permanently the recurrence of conditions which have brought about
			social or economic disaster. Charity or philanthropy which does not
			seek to uproot the radical causes of social disaster, misery and
			starvation is negative and not worth of support. </p>
		<p>WHETHER WE LIKE it or not, the consequences of the war has thrust
			internationalism upon us. Our “<q who="GOSGE">splendid
			isolation</q>” is a myth. We have been shaken out of our slumber of
			complacency into an acute realization of a finely enmeshed tangle of
			interdependencies, inter-relationships, and tightly knotted
			antagonisms. Today we are confronted with an internationalism of
			petty hatreds, of disasters, of starvation, of industrial
			bankruptcy. Among nations as among smaller communities the
			irresponsible and the helpless become the burden of the self
			supporting and the self reliant, a fact sufficiently and
			emphatically thrust upon us every day of our lives.</p>
		<p> How then is it possible to disentangle this disordered skein of
			international affairs? How, out of all the international chaos and
			disease produced by national hatred, is it possible to sow the
			fruitful seed of the internationalism of peace and security?</p>
		<p> The internationalism of peace and security and progress, to be
			enduring, to be a vital growing and fruitful principle, to be
			effective, cannot be based on the conferences of politicians and
			self appointed “statesmen” who meet and discuss the limitation of
			armaments, who strive to gloss over deeply rooted antagonisms and
			disguised policies of imperialism. Nor can it be brought about by
			the establishment of a “world court” which refuses to recognize the
			most deeply rooted instincts and habits of the human race.</p>
		<p> No, the new internationalism can only come as the out growth of a
			dynamic, living, functional practice, which penetrates into the very
			lives and habits of the human race, and which gradually but
			progressively lessens and obliterates the cause of wars and social
			catastrophes. If seriously we aim for world peace, we must
			discourage over population and over crowding, with its attendant
			train of disease, epidemic and plague. By diminishing overcrowding,
			much of the incentive for emigration will disappear, and with the
			lessening of emigration and immigration, we shall have taken an
			important step in stabilizing and increasing the power of organized
			labor. </p>
		<p>THE PRACTICE OF Birth Control is this dynamic living principle which
			not only relieves the conditions of over crowding for the
			individual, but also for the race. It is the crying need in over
			populated countries like <place>Japan</place> and
				<place>China</place> and elsewhere, as the statistics of
			infantile mortality, infanticide and abortion tragically indicate.
			Only the great reactionary forces of tradition and exploitation and
			ignorance oppose its practice.</p>
		<p> Our own immediate duty then, is to mobilize the forces of
			intelligence and true statesmanship in all countries, to establish
			“spheres of influence,” to awaken the consciousness and the
			conscience of all serious minded people to this great world problem,
			and to unite with the rapidly growing movements in other lands.</p>
		<p> Our outlook is more promising than it has ever been. The causes of
			the present international chaos are becoming more and more evident,
			and to ever increasing numbers of people. Once we begin to grasp the
			factors of our great problem of international peace and security, we
			may assure ourselves that we shall be brave enough and courageous
			enough not to rest until we have solved it. </p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
