<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published statement">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2013-10-23 EK Initial Tag</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014/03/30 EK clean regs + proof corrections </prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-07 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1913-12-00">Dec 1913</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Statement on Women and
				Capitalism</supplied></titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp321986</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="journal">The Conservator</title>Dec. 1913, p. 145</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name/>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>This statement was published in <title type="journal">The Conservator</title>, a radical
			literary monthly edited by <person reg="Traubel, Horace">Horace Traubel</person>.</p>
		<index level1="capitalism"/>
		<index level1="women's rights"/>
		<index level1="prostitution"/>
		<index level1="venereal disease"/>
		<index level1="sex education"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<p>It is impossible to separate the ignorance of parents, prostitution, venereal diseases,
			or the silence of the medical profession, from the great economic question that the
			world is facing today. It is here ever before us, and the more we look into the
			so-called evils of the day the more we realize that the whole structure of present-day
			society is built upon a rotten and decaying foundation. Until capitalism is swept away,
			there is no hope for young girls to live a beautiful life during their girlhood. There
			is no hope for boys or girls to build up strong and sturdy bodies. There is no hope that
			a woman can live in the family relation and have children without sacrificing every
			vestige of individual development. There is no hope that prostitution will cease as long
			as there is hunger. There is no hope for a strong race as long as venereal diseases
			exist. And they will exist until women rise in one big sisterhood to fight this
			capitalist society which compels a woman to serve as a sex implement for man's use.
			Education is necessary—-education is the need of the people. For this will soon enable
			one to see that knowledge alone does not suffice, but that it is only through economic
			security that the man and the woman will emerge in a future civilization.</p>
		<byline>MARGARET SANGER</byline>
	</docBody>
</doc>
