<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2011/05/06 CH Initials</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-03-18 clean regs and errors</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-22 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1927-05-02">2 May 1927</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<title type="article">Foreword to <title type="book">Sex Problems in
					India</title></title>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp321952</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>N. S. Phadke, <title type="book">Sex Problems in India</title> (<place
					reg="Bombay, India">Bombay</place>, 1929), v-vii</bibl>

		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name/>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<index level1="eugenics" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="India" level2="birth control in"/>
		<index level1="marriage" level2="reforms"/>
		<index level1="unfit to reproduce" level2="MS on"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>FOREWORD</head>
		<p>In this book, "<title type="book">Sex Problems in India</title>," Prof. <person
				reg="Phadke, Narayan Sitaram">Phadke</person> treats the various problems in the
			light of modern practical science. His chapter on "<title type="article">The Vindication
				of Birth Control</title>" is especially sound and clearly stated.</p>
		<p>The plea the author makes for <title type="article">Eugenic Marriages</title> is the plea
			of the far-sighted patriot, whose desire is that the country of his allegiance shall
			grow strong on sound biological principles.</p>
		<p>There is knowledge in the world to-day, which, if placed at the disposal of the people
			for their guidance, would help to eliminate some of the most persistent social evils of
			this country. Many of these evils keep cropping up generation after generation, while
			efforts to deal with them, especially in <place>Europe</place> and <place
				reg="United States">America</place>, are mainly palliative. I refer to infant
			mortality, child labour, maternal mortality, and other problems arising out of the
			increasing hordes of inert, unfit multitudes being born into the world each year.</p>
		<p>In the western countries where the effort to solve such problems by legislative methods
			has practically failed, we have had to resort to a large expenditure to keep alive those
			very types whose multiplication causes dysgenic conditions. Our hospitals, as well as
			institutiions for the feeble-minded and insane, are overcrowded. The cost of maintaining
			these institutions casts a tremendous burden upon the normal person. This lessens the
			ability of the healthy normal classes to rear larger families, with the conseqence that
			the birth rate is of so differential a character it constitutes a problem and in some
			countries it has become an alarming factor. The future of western civilization is
			threatened by this stupendous error.</p>
		<p>This is only one angle of the social side of birth control. There is another which is
			also treated by the author in a masterly fashion: that of the individual woman. He asks
			that marriage shall be based on love and affection. That it shall be consumated only
			after maturity. That children shall be born to parents only when there is that
			development of the body and mind which modern students of psychology claim is necessary
			for the parents as well as essential to the well-being of the child born.</p>
		<p>A country cannot keep pace in the world today when its population is bowed down by large
			families, misery and poverty.</p>
		<p>A nation ignoring the researches advanced by modern science, relentlessly holding to
			customs outworn and proven inadequare, cannot claim equal recognition with those
			countries which have left behind them outworn dogma and mediaeval superstitions.</p>
		<p>The <title type="book">Sex Problems in India</title> are doubtless much the same
			fundamentally as the problems of other countries. But in the occident an effort is being
			made to solve such problems fearlessly and honestly.</p>
		<p>Prof. Phadke has undertaken this task for <place>India</place>. I heartily recommend his
			book to those who are seeking guidance along these lines.</p>
		<closer><dateline><place reg="Geneva, Switzerland">GENEVA</place>, <date value="1927-05-02"
					>2nd May, 1927</date>.</dateline>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">MARGARET SANGER</person>.</closer>

	</docBody>
</doc>
