<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Essay">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2013/12/18 JK encoded</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1933">1933</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Birth Control</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp321976</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Social Work Yearbook Vol. 2 1933 NY Russell Sage
                Foundation</bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="PHRC">Public Health Relations Committee</name>
            <name id="CCAR">Central Conference of American Rabbis</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">This contains both the 1929 and 1933 version of
        Margaret Sanger's <title>Birth Control</title> essay. <index
            level1="birth control" level2="birth control leagues"/><index
            level1="birth control" level2="birth control leagues"
            level3="Birth Control League of New York"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="birth control leagues"
            level3="National Birth Control League"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation"
            level3="New York "/><index level1="birth control"
            level2="clinics and leagues"/><index level1="Catholic Church"/>
        <index level1="Catholic Church" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="conferences"
            level2="White House Conference on Child health and Protection"
            level3="1930"/><index
            level1="National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control"
            /><index level1="United States" level2="public health programs"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Birth Control 1929</head>

        <p> The general aim of the birth control movement is to legitimatize the
            practice of contraception through scientific and hygienic methods,
            and to educate the adult public as to its advantages from the
            personal and social points of view. International in scope, the
            movement has been known under a number of names; in the <place
                reg="England">British Empire</place> as “neo-malthusianism”; in
                <place>France</place> as “conscious generation”; and
            occasionally as “voluntary parenthood.”</p>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">History and Present Status </head>
            <p>In English-speaking countries the present movement derives from
                    <person reg="Malthus, Thomas">Malthus</person>. In the
                second edition of his famous <title>Essay on Population</title>,
                published in 1803, the English clergyman first enunciated his
                law of the pressure of population upon the means of subsistence.
                The only solution he suggested for overpopulation was the
                practice of celibacy and late marriage. In 1826 Dr. <person
                    reg="Knowlton, Charles">Charles Knowlton</person>, a
                    <place>Boston</place> physician, was prosecuted for
                publishing a small book, <title>The Fruits of
                Philosophy</title>, advocating mechanical and chemical methods
                of contraception. In 1876-1877 <person reg="Bradlaugh, Charles"
                    >Charles Bradlaugh</person> and Mrs. <person
                    reg="Besant, Annie"> Annie Besant </person>were prosecuted
                and convicted for distributing that book among the working
                classes of Great Britain. Their conviction led to the foundation
                of the Malthusian League in 1878 by Dr. <person
                    reg="Drysdale, Charles">Charles Drysdale</person> and his
                wife, Dr. <person reg="Vickery Drysdale, Alice">Alice Vickery
                    Drysdale</person>. A Dutch League was founded in 1881. The
                neo-malthusians differed from Malthus in advocating
                contraception to prevent overpopulation and to reduce the birth
                rate. The period between 1914 and 1921 in the United States was
                one of militant agitation and widespread publicity, partly as a
                result of several convictions of persons active in the movement
                for challenging federal and state laws. In <place> New York
                    City</place> in 1914 <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Mrs.
                    Margaret Sanger </person>began to advocate contraception on
                feministic and libertarian grounds, coining at that time the
                term “birth control.” The interest awakened in the whole
                question of contraception resulted in 1921 in the foundation of
                the <org>American Birth Control League</org> and of the
                    <org>Voluntary Parenthood League</org>; also in the
                publication of a monthly periodical, the <title>Birth Control
                    Review</title>, edited by Mrs. Sanger. The two organizations
                were subsequently combined under the name of the former.
                Activities of the second period of the American movement, from
                1921 to 1925, included the organization of local leagues, the
                education of public opinion, and campaigns for the amendment of
                statutes which class the practice of contraception with
                obscenity and criminal abortion. During the third period, 1925
                to the present, advocates of birth control have concentrated
                upon the establishment of clinics and research bureaus, and upon
                enlisting th interest and activities of physicians, biologists,
                biochemists, and social scientists generally. Results of these
                efforts are seen in the fact that no less than 55 clinics and
                bureaus are now operating legitimately in the United States
                (covering 23 cities and 13 states), dispensing contraceptive
                information to all persons legally permitted to receive it. In
                    <place>New York </place>State it is given to married people
                for the cure or prevention of disease. In <place>California
                </place>there are 12 clinics; there is one each in
                    <place>Baltimore</place>, <place>Cincinnati</place>,
                    <place>Cleveland,</place>
                <place>Denver,</place>
                <place>Detroit,</place>
                <place>Newark</place>, <place>New Haven</place>, and
                    <place>Philadelphia</place>; there are six in
                    <place>Chicago</place>; and <place>New York City</place> has
                eight in hospitals and one operating independently. In addition,
                a branch for colored women has recently been established in the
                    <place>Harlem</place> section of New York City by the <org
                    reg="Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau">Clinical
                    Research Bureau</org>. The year 1929 was marked by the
                establishment of 27 new clinics. The successful operation of
                such clinics and research bureaus, under medical direction,
                makes possible the scientific analysis of individual cases, and
                also statistical studies. Through the latter material is being
                developed for the replacement of untested theory with impartial
                analysis. Social agencies are beginning to cooperate with such
                clinics. Owing to the widespread change in public opinion,
                physicians are more willing to give advice in private practice.
                Over 10,000 of them have expressed willingness to do so. The
                birth control movement is exerting a noticeable influence upon
                eugenics and giving a new direction to programs for
                race-betterment; it has resulted in renewed consideration of the
                problem of the legal sterilization of the unfit; and has
                influenced programs for the control of dependent, delinquent,
                and defective groups in society. It has been given consideration
                by many social agencies seeking to decrease maternal and infant
                mortality rates, particularly by the Committee on Maternal
                Health of New York City. Financial support of the birth control
                movement has been from independent and anonymous sources, with
                the exception of temporary support from the Brush Foundation of
                Cleveland. During 1929 a study of 10,000 case was made by the
                Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau, and a study of fertility
                and sterility by the Committee on Maternal Health. Legislation,
                1929. No laws on the subject were passed during the year. Bills
                to amend the laws which prohibit contraceptive instruction were
                defeated in New York and Connecticut. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head> Birth Control 1933 </head>
            <p>The general aim of the birth control movement is to legalize the
                practice of contraception through scientific and hygienic
                methods, and to educate the public to its advantages as a health
                and economic expedient. Though the movement had its origin in
                England, it was in 1914 in New York City that Mrs. Margaret
                Sanger first coined the term “birth control” and challenged the
                federal laws by advocating birth control on feministic and
                economic grounds. There followed in 1917 the publication of the
                    <title>Birth Control Review</title>, the formation of the
                Voluntary Parenthood League in 1919, and the organization in
                1921 of the American Birth Control League. The period from 1914
                to 1921 was one of agitation, education, organization, and
                legislation. The National Committee on Maternal Health,
                organized in 1923, has for its purpose the scientific
                investigation of contraception, sterilization, and the general
                problems of sterility and fertility from the point of view of
                the practice of medicine and public health. In 1923 also the
                Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau was established in New
                York City. That Bureau-- with which a large number of social and
                welfare agencies and hospitals are cooperating has instructed
                over 31,000 women since its organization. The first 10,000 case
                histories, under a grant from the Bureau of Social Hygiene, have
                been analyzed by a committee of specialists and the results are
                to be made available at a later date.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Legislative Campaigns, and Birth Control
                Clinics</head>
            <p>While efforts are being constantly made for needed legislation in
                the several states, the attention of leaders in the field has
                recently been centered more particularly upon obtaining federal
                legislation. For this purpose the <org>National Committee on
                    Federal Legislation for Birth Control</org> was organized in
                1929. Federal laws forbidding the distribution of contraceptive
                information affect the use of the mails and common carriers, and
                impose a penalty of $5,000, or imprisonment for five years or
                both, on anyone who is convicted of a violation. In many states
                a physician may give oral contraceptive information to his
                patients, but scientific literature on the subject, or medical
                supplies for the purpose, cannot be legally sent to him through
                the United States mails, nor can he knowingly receive them
                without violating the law. Amendments to remedy this situation
                are now pending in Congress. At the present time not less than
                100 so-called birth control clinics- through some of them,
                located in hospitals, are not generally known as such- are
                operating legally in the United States (covering 43 cities in 17
                states). They are all places where contraceptive information may
                be obtained, but only under conditions within the limitation of
                the laws of each particular state. In New York State, for
                example, information can be given for the “cure or prevention of
                disease,” but not for economic reasons. In the Harlem section of
                New York City, through a grant from the <org>Julius Rosenwald
                    Fund</org>, a branch clinic for colored women has been
                established as a part of the work of the Birth Control Clinical
                Research Bureau. A comprehensive study of the work and location
                of birth control clinics in different cities is contained in
                Seventy Birth Control Clinics (infra cit.), issued in 1930. The
                latest information as to the location of such clinics may be
                obtained from the National Committee on Maternal Health.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">The Movement Endorsed and Opposed</head>
            <p>In recent years public opinion has been rapidly growing in favor
                of medically supervised instruction on birth control, as
                evidenced by the support and endorsements given by medical and
                other groups since 1930. Conspicuous among the former were the
                    <org>Public Health Relations Committee</org> of the <org>New
                    York Academy of Medicine</org>. Its recommendations, adopted
                in 1931, included the following statement: <q who="PHRC">“A
                    movement should be begun to include, in the curriculum of
                    medical schools, instruction in modern contraceptive
                    measures and in the indications therefor. The hospital
                    clinics should likewise be asked to offer similar
                    instruction to practicing physicians.” </q>At the White
                House Conference on Child Health and Protection in 1930 a
                similar recommendation was made by the Sub-committee of the
                    <org>Section on Obstetric Teaching and Education of
                    Physicians, Nurses, Midwives, Social Workers, and
                    Laity</org>. Many religious groups have recently made public
                statement favorable to the birth control movement, at least to
                the extent of recognizing that existing laws should be modified
                which prevent physicians from imparting information concerning
                the use of contraceptives to those entitled to receive it. Among
                the groups which have issued such statements are the following:
                the <org> Committee on Marriage and the Home of the Federal
                    Council of the Churches of Christ in America</org>;
                    <org>General Council of the Congregational and Christian
                    Churches</org>;<org> New York East Conference</org>,
                    <org>Methodist Episcopal Church; Universalist General
                    Convention</org>; and numerous political, lay, and social
                welfare organizations. In addition, the <org>Central Conference
                    of American Rabbis </org>in 1929 urged <q who="CCAR">“the
                    recognition of the importance of the control of parenthood
                    as one of the methods of coping with social problems”</q>;
                and the <org>American Unitarian Association</org> in 1930
                recommended that its constituents consider the subject “to the
                end that they may support all reasonable efforts in their
                communities for the promotion of the birth control movement.”
                For the text of the statements by the specified organizations
                see Information Service (infra cit.) and <org>The Gospel and the
                    Family and Youth</org> (General Council of the
                Congregational and Christian Churches), 1931. In July, 1930, the
                    <org>English Ministry of Health</org> issued a memorandum
                stating that in response to a widespread responsible demand,
                public health authorities would be authorized to give birth
                control information in the maternal and infant welfare centers
                of which there are several thousand throughout the British
                Isles. This announcement was preceded by a favorable, though
                guarded, pronouncement by the House of Lords, the <org>Lambeth
                    Conference of Bishops</org>, and the <org>British Medical
                    Society</org>. The principal organized opposition to the
                movement comes from the Roman Catholic Church, and since the
                publication of the Encyclical Letter of Pope Pius XI, <title>On
                    Christian Marriage</title>, 1931, many Catholic
                organizations- including the National Council of Catholic Men,
                the <org>International Federation of Catholic Alumni</org>, and
                the <org>National Council of Catholic Women</org>- have
                registered formal protests against the passage of birth control
                legislation. It is safe to say that all Catholic organizations
                are similarly opposed. <org>The United Lutheran Church of
                    America,</org>
                <org>Evangelical Lutheran Augusta Synod</org>, <org>Lord’s Day
                    Alliance,</org> and a small number of local religious
                denominations are also reported as opposed to the pending birth
                control legislation. </p>
        </div>

    </docBody>
</doc>
