<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2013/12/18 JK</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-11-10 CH clean regs</prepDate><prepDate>2014-12-18 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1920-02-00">Feb 1920</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>Light for Mexico and South America</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp321973</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="journal">The Birth Control Review</title>, Feb. 1920, p. 15. </bibl>

		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>This unsigned article was likely written by Margaret Sanger.</p>
		<index level1="Latin America" level2="birth control in"/>
		<index level1="Mexico" level2="descriptions of"/>
		<index level1="infant mortality"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Light for Mexico and <place>South America</place></head>

		<p>ONE OF THE recent important developments in the Birth Control movement is that which is
			manifesting itself vigorously in <place>Latin America</place>. Every mail brings us,
			from some country to the south of us, letters of encouragement. These letters give
			evidence of the fact that independent thinkers have recognized the necessity of woman's
			freedom as the first step in solving the problems with which the masses are confronted.
				<person reg="Unknown">One man</person> who has been active in behalf of Birth
			Control in South America writes from a city in <place>Colombia</place> "<q who="UNK"
				>Every day that passes away I realize more and more what a great help Birth Control
				is going to be in the near future. Here in this poor country they need more of that
				help than any other. People of the lower class here live like pigs. They used to
				have from six to eighteen children and almost all died before being three years old.
				If you could look at the statistics in this country you would see that the mortality
				of children under three years old is awfully high. I saw a report stating that the
				births in one week had been 128 and the infant mortality 122 among the poor people.
				This is terrible, <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Mrs. Sanger</person>, and I wish I
				could use all my power, money and knowledge to help those poor women of this beloved
				but unhappy country of mine.</q>"</p>
		<p>A birth control group in Colombia is also planning to translate <title type="journal">THE
				BIRTH CONTROL REVIEW</title> into Spanish for the benefit of the native population
			of all Latin American Countries. It is needless to say that all available information
			concerning contraceptive methods has already been translated and is in circulation. A
			group headed by a <person reg="Unknown">North American woman</person> in <place
				reg="Buenos Aires, Argentina">Buenas Ayres</place> has its branch of the movement
			well under way. Literature is being distributed and a general interest is being aroused.
			Coming nearer home, there is also a lively movement in Mexico, with headquarters in the
				<place reg="Mexico City, Mexico">capital city</place> of the republic. In that
			country, one of the most familiar sights is that of beggar women, mothers of from nine
			to sixteen children, clustered about the doors of the church, to claim the charity of
			the worshipper and to divide their gains with the church itself. To offset this misery,
			the Birth Control group have translated the literature of the movement into the native
			language and have distributed it widely. Although the church is opposed to this activity
			and spares no pains to prohibit it, the present <org reg="Mexico, Government of"
				>government of <place>Mexico</place></org> has been liberal enough to refuse to
			prosecute these workers for humanity. The women of Mexico are moving on toward their
			freedom. One of the important recent events in the City of Mexico was a feminist
			conference, which was widely asserting their rights, it will not be long until they
			claim the fundamental right of controlling their own productive functions. A new day is
			dawning for the women of the world and the women of Latin America are claiming their
			right to the light.</p>


	</docBody>
</doc>
