<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article ">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2007/10/22 CH initial prep</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2008/01/08 CH correct type</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/11/30 CH Correct typo</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-01 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1921-01-30">30 Jan 1921</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Modern Motherhood and Child Slavery</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp400200</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Long Beach Press</title>, Jan. 30, 1921</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>This article was introduced by an editorial note: "Margaret Sanger is the author of a
            number of books and has for many years been identified with the science of eugenics in
            this country and England. She had two fine boys now in college and a home life such as
            we like to think of as typical of the best in America. </p>
        <index level1="child labor"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="socio-economic benefits of"/>
        <index level1="labor movement"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="maternal feelings"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Modern Motherhood and Child Slavery</head>
        <byline>By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">MARGARET SANGER</person></byline>
        <p>Child labor is a most grievous blot on civilization. Those who have looked carefully into
            the problem know that is one of the cruelest of all modern social evils and that when
            the full accounting is made, one of the most far-reaching in its blighting effects.</p>
        <p>For many years, various agencies have fought hard to awaken the people of the
                <place>United States</place> to the evils and perils of permitting children to work.
            Chief among these agencies today is the national child labor committee which with heroic
            persistence and unflagging faith has sought to abolish this curse. This powerful group,
            always on guard, unceasing in its aggressive efforts, commanding a great following has
            been leading the battle for humanity since 1904. Despite its utmost efforts, however,
            there are in the United States today, according to its own authoritative estimate, some
            2,500,000 child workers whose lives are being spent unprofitably, wastefully, cruelly,
            upon industry. And these millions represent just so much racial energy taken from future
            generations. And many of them are to become the mentally, physically and spiritually
            incompetent parents of weaklings, who will carry on the impoverished family strains for
            many generations.</p>
        <p>Child labor can never be wiped out by legislation. The roots of this evil weed strike
            deeper than the statutes. They spring from the disregard of natural and spiritual laws
            -- they draw their sustenance from over-population. </p>
        <p>How narrow, how pitifully puny has become motherhood against its chains? The modern
            motherhood enfolds one or two adoring children of its own blood, and cherishes, protects
            and loves them. It does not reach out to all children. When motherhood is a high
            privilege not a sordid, slavish requirement, it will encircle all. Its deep, passionate
            intensity will overflow the limits of blood relationship. Its beauty will shine upon
            all, for its beauty is of the soul, whose power of enfoldment is unbounded. </p>
        <p>While there is surplus population, under the present social and industrial order, there
            will be child labor. As long as homes are crowded beyond the sustaining power of the
            father's wages, children will go to work. </p>
        <p>It is high time that everyone in the United States awakened to the gravity of the
            situation.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
