<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2001-11-12 MH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2002-08-27 KH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/03/11 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/26 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007-05-31 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-05 CH cleaning regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1914-04-00">Apr 1914</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>How It Works</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp420067</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">The Woman Rebel</title>, Vol. 1, No. 2, Apr. 1914, 13</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Collected Documents Series</title>
                C16:0527</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
        <index level1="labor movement"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>HOW IT WORKS!</head>
        <p>How much longer will the working class be led to slaughter by the legal defense
            bunko!</p>
        <p><person reg="Tannenbaum, Frank">Frank Tannenbaum</person> did not want legal defense, but
            was persuaded to for the cause--to promote propaganda.</p>
        <p>When the workers resort to legal defense and choose a lawyer who represents them in
            spirit--in ideas--he is considered insolent--he must be taught a lesson--and the
            prisoner is the victim who gets the limit.</p>
        <p>Tannenbaum got the limit. What right had he to retain an insolent lawyer who refused to
            bow the head and bend the knee. It's up to the <person reg="Wadhams, William H."
                >judge</person> to teach this young lawyer a lesson. <person reg="Sheffield, Justus"
                >Sheffield</person> learned it. If only the workers could learn it too. It is
            impossible for a lawyer to represent the worker in the spirit of the worker. Let the
            worker defend himself. He gets the limit either way.</p>
        <p>Do away with petitions, protests and apologies. Let us cease accepting the pennies of the
            toilers for legal defense, and let us consciously enter the fight, accepting the
            results.</p>
        <p>Such action by the workers, uncompromising and revolutionary, would make not only the
            strongest propaganda but bring about the ideal we strive for.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
