<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">

    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/03/26 VS initial tagging</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docAuthor>Gardner Bradford</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1993-02-26">26 February, 1936</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>If I Were Baby Dictator of the United States</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp420078</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">If I Were Baby Dictator of the United States</title>
                <title type="journal">Los Angeles Times</title></bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="BRAGA">Bradford, Gardner</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><person reg="Bradford, Gardner">Gardner Bradford</person> of the Los
        Angeles Times interviews Margaret Sanger, asking her how she would implement birth control
        if she had total authority over the United States. <index level1="abortion" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="American opinion on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="physical justifications for"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="medical community and"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="population growth and"/>
        <index level1="children" level2="rights of"/>
        <index level1="immigration" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="men" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
        <index level1="men" level2="sexual fulfillment of"/>
        <index level1="mentally disabled and diseased" level2="fertility of"/>
        <index level1="population growth" level2="regulation of"/>
        <index level1="poverty" level2="family size and"/>
        <index level1="sex education" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="&quot;unfit&quot; to reproduce" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="health of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>If I Were Baby Dictator of the <place>United States</place></head>
        <byline>"I'd put a stop," she declares, "to the having of 'Depression Babies;' they are
            going to give us a Mad Generation!" - a frank interview with the "mother" of Birth
            Control</byline>
        <div>
            <q who="BRAGA"><p> “Just what would you do if you were appointed Dictator of Motherhood
                    for the United States? – a sort of <person reg="Mussolini, Benito"
                        >Mussolini</person> of Maternity, with absolute power to act?”</p></q>
            <q who="BRAGA"><p>
                    <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>, mother of birth control
                    – and several children – gasped. Obviously it was not the temerity of the
                    question that troubled her, but the supposition of so much power! Martyr
                    crusaders seldom picture themselves as despots. Prison doors are always closer
                    than are those to throne rooms and Margaret Sanger, during her long battle to
                    regulate the biological urge, has smilingly jeopardized her liberty to champion
                    an idea.</p></q>
            <q who="BRAGA"><p> I had pictured this world-renowned exponent of birth control as a
                    raw-boned, hard-faced, domineering Amazon – a <person reg="Nation, Carrie"
                        >Carrie Nation</person> barging about the country with a scalpel instead of
                    a hatchet. It was pleasantly disconcerting to find her small, slender and soft
                    spoken. One does not look for dynamite in baby blue frocks.</p></q>
            <p> “If I were a dictator,” <q who="BRAGA">mused Margaret Sanger,</q> “I would –”</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> What She Would Order</head>
            <p> “First – Place greater responsibility upon social service workers, charities and all
                those having medical contact with the people and create a nationwide system of
                physical, mental and moral reports which would afford the government and every
                community a basis for intelligent action.</p>
            <p> “Second – Appoint a commission of three or five in every community to decide if
                couples should have progeny and determine when sterilization, isolation or free-will
                abstinence should be enforced.</p>
            <p> “Third – I might grant pensions to those denied the right to have children, as a
                recognition of their contribution toward race betterment, just as we grant pensions
                to citizens who serve their country in other ways. The commission would also conduct
                educational campaigns to establish what sterilization and isolation really are and
                emphasize that the former is not a punishment, does not unsex the subject and causes
                no change beyond the elimination of parenthood.</p>
            <p> “Fourth – Put the responsibility upon every mother to reduce maternity mortality. In
                the United States, two women die every single hour of the day and night from
                childbirth, the highest maternity death rate in the world. Any woman with
                tuberculosis, heart disease, goiter or kidney trouble, must be protected. I would
                compel them to take measures to correct their health.</p>
            <p> “Fifth – I would make parenthood a privilege. They would have to work for it.</p>
            <p> “Sixth – Economics would be a factor. A man’s earning potentialities, not his actual
                income at the time of the union, would be considered. I believe in birth control,
                not birth limitation, except in certain cases. From the moment of marriage there
                would be a periodical check-up to make sure that the birth rate and financial
                standing were proportionate.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> No More Child Beating</head>
            <p> “Seventh – Treatment of children is important. Many parents prove they are unfit to
                have them. Parents who beat their children ‘because they have the right to’ would
                not be allowed to have any more.</p>
            <p> “Eighth – Certificates for parenthood issued with the marriage license, would be
                compulsory. To obtain them both man and woman would undergo physical, mental and
                moral tests; family medical and mental history would be recorded and financial
                ability to rear children. There would be a black list and a white one. Those on the
                white list, bearing no children, would be privileged to adopt some. No child should
                be in an institution.</p>
            <p> “Ninth – And then I would resign, for I believe in a co-operative education, not
                dictatorship!”</p>
            <q who="BRAGA"><p> Yes, Margaret Sanger would resign. There is nothing of the militant
                    crusader about her. Her method is to disarm her opponents rather than fight them
                    and she relies upon education and common sense for her ultimate success.</p></q>
            <p>
                <q who="BRAGA">Right now, if she could be a dictator for a single hour, she would
                    declare moratorium on depression babies.</q> “Worried mothers,” <q who="BRAGA"
                    >she declares,</q> “starved, overworked, scared and devitalized, are bringing
                into the world a new moron, a mentally deficient, subnormal child who is forming the
                nucleus of a mad generation. No one can tell just what these children will be like
                when they grow up or what form their abnormality will take.</p>
            <p> “Dr. <person reg="Schlapp, Max">Max Schlapp</person>, the psychiatrist, examined
                10,000 children born in one year on American soil of immigrant parents just arrived
                in this country. Three thousand of these, disclosed to have been born in an
                atmosphere of unemployment, homesickness and anxiety, were mentally under par. In no
                instance was there bad inheritance. They were the new menace to the survival of the
                race – the Depression Baby.”</p>
            <q who="BRAGA"><p> “It would be a simple matter to let them die,” I suggested, striving
                    to be helpful.</p></q>
            <p> “Oh, no!” <q who="BRAGA">Mrs. Sanger remonstrated earnestly.</q> “We must regard
                imperfect babies as our mistakes – to be carried and cared for. But we must make
                sure that they, in their turn, do not have children. After all, the whole thing
                centers upon sterilization. When people learn what it really is, our first great
                stride toward betterment and preservation of the human race will have been
                taken.”</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Modern Methods</head>
            <p> “If people only would comprehend that modern sterilization isn’t the mutilation of
                olden times! It doesn’t unsex or kill the biological urge. It does not destroy sex
                life and is frequently a restorer of mental and physical health. Dr. <person
                    reg="Hare, Norman">Norman Hare</person> of <place reg="London, England"
                    >London</place> cured thirty epileptics by that method.</p>
            <p> “The disheartening thing is that if every person in America known to have a
                transmissible disease were sterilized today, it would still take five generations to
                eradicate the damage already done.</p>
            <p> “Nowadays,” <q who="BRAGA">continued Mrs. Sanger, who, by the way, is a trained
                    nurse and medical graduate,</q> “X-rays have largely replaced other methods and
                there is in process of development a sperma-toxin which will prevent childbirth by
                the same principles manifested by vaccination in the control of diseases once deemed
                incurable. Other new serums promise to give children to hitherto barren
                couples.”</p>
            <q who="BRAGA"><p> I suggested, by way of deserting serums for a more tangible topic,
                    that the younger generation of today, especially college girls, evince a
                    stronger tendency toward race suicide than promiscuous progeny. Would they not,
                    in course of time, make birth control and obsolete problem?</p></q>
            <p> “You forget,” <q who="BRAGA">Mrs. Sanger pointed out,</q> “that birth control is a
                matter of selectivity, not limitation. If a couple can produce twenty healthy
                children and raise and educate them properly, that is wonderful. On the contrary,
                the woman who lack the biological urge, who prefer poodles to children – and these
                college co-eds with non-maternal instincts – are nothing but deadwood in the
                progress of the race; a form of parasitic moron who will die out, having done
                neither harm nor good.”</p>
            <q who="BRAGA"><p> Civilization, Mrs. Sanger believes, is the main menace to the future
                    well-being of mankind. It seems to have disturbed the balance of the biological
                    urge, or, in other words, complicated the desire to mate.</p></q>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Answering the Urge</head>
            <p> “You see,” <q who="BRAGA">she explains,</q> “human desire was first for food, then
                for mating. Love, as we know it, is something comparatively new, just a few thousand
                years old. Love has made the mating instinct lose its surety – love, law and
                civilization. The genuine biological urge, love at first sight, is seldom
                consummated, due to the barriers erected by civilization. We’d have better babies if
                men, feeling the true biological urge, immediately took possession of the women who
                inspired it.”</p>
            <q who="BRAGA"><p> “You mean smack ‘em with a club? Cave-man stuff?”</p></q>
            <p> “Exactly!” <q who="BRAGA">(Understand, she was speaking biologically only.)</q></p>
            <p> “But the trouble is with the age, not the individual,” <q who="BRAGA">added Mrs.
                    Sanger, hastening from cave men into safer channels.</q> “The greatest menace to
                the future generations lies in the fact that the modern nerve forces have been
                depleted by the rush and noise and worry of our own creating. Our energy capital is
                used up.</p>
            <p> “Another complication civilization has contributed to our biological life is the
                marriage of convenience or opportunity. From the reproduction angle, almost all of
                these marriages are misfits. They lack what poets call the ‘divine spark’ and the
                medical profession terms the ‘biological urge.’”</p>
            <q who="BRAGA"><p> “Then how about these people who have eight or ten children and who
                    are usually of the so-called ‘undesirable class’?” I wanted to know. “Doesn’t
                    the fact that they are so prolific indicate that they are perfect
                mates?”</p></q>
            <p> “Usually,” <q who="BRAGA">came the answer,</q> “it is because the urge ceases to be
                an urge and becomes a habit! Sometimes there is a chemical affinity that makes for
                an abundance of progeny. Science, you know, has discovered that we have positive and
                negative sides, governed by too much or too little acidity or alkaline reactions.
                Now science gives children, through the use of serums, as well as prevents
                them.”</p>
            <q who="BRAGA"><p> “Doesn’t that automatically make the doctors the birth control
                    dictators of tomorrow?” I demanded.</p></q>
            <p> “You mustn’t forget the biological urge. Next to life itself, it is the oldest most
                enduring and most unruly element in our existence. It may make a servant of science,
                but never a master.”</p>
            <p>
                <q who="BRAGA"><person reg="Slee, James Noah H.">Mrs. Sanger’s husband</person> used
                    to be at the helm of the Three-In-One oil concern but retired to become the
                    manager of his wife’s crusade. She denied that he had to take a lot of joshing
                    on account of the nature of her work, but was, on the contrary, greatly
                    interested in it and an invaluable aid to the cause.</q> “And he pays bills
                beautifully!” <q who="BRAGA">she exclaimed with enthusiasm.</q></p>
            <p> “It’s my boys, now in college, who must endure a lot of bantering from their
                classmates, but they don’t mind. What is more, they believe in my work and are
                excellent missionaries in a very important field. My <person reg="Sanger, Stuart"
                    >oldest boy</person> became quite interested in a charming girl not so very long
                ago and it looked as though it might be serious. He insisted that he undergo all the
                physical, mental, and pathological tests I have laid down as an essential part of
                birth control, but it seems that the young lady balked at the idea. And so they
                drifted apart.</p>
            <p> “I find that college men are very responsive to the birth control idea. The majority
                take pride in the belief that they CAN successfully meet the requirements and would
                regard a parenthood certificate as a badge of merit, even though they expected to
                remain bachelors.</p>
            <p> “The average college girl, on the contrary, seems to shun examinations of any kind.
                The majority apparently cling to the old idea that love, to be true, must also be
                blind and ask no questions. This attitude is not confined to colleges, however. In
                all walks of life, the majority of men take the suggestion of an examination as a
                challenge and woman as an insult. But the women who DO take the trouble to
                understand birth control are invariably its strongest supporters.”</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> “Larger Than Eugenics”</head>
            <q who="BRAGA"><p> Is there such a thing as an ideal birth control couple? Apparently
                    not, for the scope of the idea is far wider than mere eugenics. The mating of
                    two “perfect specimens” seldom proves to be an ideal union.</p></q>
            <q who="BRAGA"><p> Margaret Sanger’s birth control crusade, it is well to remember, is
                    by no means confined to lecturing and the dispensing of educational propaganda,
                    although, just at present, the big fight is so to amend the laws of the land
                    that medical information pertinent to birth control may be sent through the
                    mails.</p></q>
            <q who="BRAGA"><p> But in New York she has a big <org
                        reg="Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau">birth control clinic</org>
                    which she hopes will be the model for countless other throughout the country.
                    Here, through advice, education, medical and physical help, she practices what
                    she preaches. She tells me that up to the present time more than 32,000 women
                    have been helped.</p></q>
            <p> “When I first embarked on my work,” <q who="BRAGA">she smiles reminiscently,</q> “it
                created something of a sensation. I was the target for high praise and scathing
                denunciation. Little by little, a nation-wide hysteria was dissipated by cold facts
                and common sense, backed by science.</p>
            <p> “Depression has proved a marvelous boost for the birth control idea, although the
                new adherents are mainly interested in it from the economical angle. Taxpayers have
                grown tired of supporting indigents with whole flocks of children. While this
                economy wave is merely one phase of the work, it may result in legislation that will
                facilitate the main objective of birth control – which is the betterment and
                perpetuation of the human race.”</p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
