<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2001-11-13 MH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2002-08-29 KH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/07 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007-05-31 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-05 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1914-05-00">May 1914</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>The Ban</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp420008</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">The Woman Rebel</title>, Vol. 1, No. 3, May 1914, 24</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Collected Documents Series</title> C16:0538</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
      <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Comstock Laws"
      <index level1="Woman Rebel, The"/>
      <index level1="censorship"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>THE BAN</head>
        <p><title type="journal">The Woman Rebel</title> is not going to be suppressed by the <org
                reg="United States Post Office">Post Office</org> until it has accomplished the work
            which it has undertaken.</p>
        <p>Unthinkingly many comrades have fallen into Postmaster <person reg="Morgan, Edward M."
                >Morgan</person>'s trap, laid for the downfall of the <title type="journal">Woman
                Rebel</title>, and have refused to subscribe, thinking the paper will be suppressed
            again and they will not receive their copy.</p>
        <p>It is true, friends--this may happen many times. As no one has yet ever decided what
            "obscenity" is, one is always liable to prosecution under this clause. I make no promise
            of being good nor framing my language so scientifically technical that only those with
            medical training can understand it. But I do promise I shall live up to the aim as
            expressed in the first issue. The subscriber who is willing to back up this fight and
            take a chance shall get the paper--SOMEWAY.</p>
        <p>Those who will not subscribe because of the above-mentioned reason, to all purposes
            unknowingly and unintentionally have lined up with the Post Office officials who are
            trying to suppress the paper, for it is only by financial and moral support that the
                <title type="journal">Woman Rebel</title> can exist.</p>
        <p>The Post Office cannot suppress this paper. Only you can do this!</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
