<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/06/22 CE</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/08/18 EK</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011-11-21 CH correct typo</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-30 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1926-03-26">26 Mar. 1926</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Comment at the Sixth International Neo-Malthusian and Birth Control
                Conference</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp420075</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
            <bibl>Library of Congress Microfilm 122:148-149</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="PEARA">Pearl, Raymond</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Sanger made the following remarks during the on the "<title
                type="article">Differential Birth Rate</title>" at the <org
                reg="International Neo-Malthusian and Birth Control Conference, 6th">Sixth
                International Neo-Malthusian and Birth Control Conference</org> in <place
                reg="New York, NY">New York City</place>. Papers read at that session include:
                <person reg="Sumner, Francis Bertody">Francis B. Sumner's</person>
            <title type="article">"Is Volunary Control of the Human Population an Idle
                Dream?"</title>, <person reg="Wilcox, Walter">Walter Wilcox,</person>
            <title type="article">"Decreasing the birth Rate in the United States"</title>, <person
                reg="Huntington, Ellsworth">Ellsworth Huntington</person>, <title type="article"
                >"The Effect of Overpopulation on Chinese Character"</title>, <person
                reg="Bissell, Malcolm">Malcolm Bissell,</person><title type="title">"Some Neglected
                Aspects of the Population Problem"</title>, <person reg="Bland, J.O.P.">J.O.P.
                Bland,</person>
            <title>"Race Suicide Fallacy"</title>, and <person reg="Dunlop, Binnie">Binnie
                Dunlop</person>, <title type="article">"Small Families and Willing Work"</title>.
            For the text of these papers, see LCM 122:105.</p>
        <index level1="American Birth Control League"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="religion and"/>
        <index level1="Catholic Church" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="conferences"
            level2="International Neo-Malthusian and birth Control Conference" level3="1925 (6th)"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Federal"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="State"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="medical community and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="doctor's only laws"/>
        <index level1="Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau"/>
        <index level1="working classes" level2="birth control and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <p><person reg="Pearl, Raymond">CHAIRMAN PEARL</person>: <q who="PEARA">If there is no
                further discussion, I would like to ask <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Mrs.
                    Sanger</person> to say a few words</q>. (Applause) </p>
        <p>MRS. SANGER: I would just like to make a point on Prof. Sumner's paper. He spoke of the
            Catholics. I want to say that our information from our <org
                reg="Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau">Clinical Research Department</org> shows that as far
            as the desire to have information to restrict or control the family runs at 33 per cent
            of the people who come to us are Protestants and 32 per cent Catholics, 31 per cent
            Jewish. So it seems to me that there is not quite the fear of alarm; that these women
            have just the same desires, the same economic standards that they want to uphold in the
            Catholic families as Jewish and Protestant.</p>
        <p>I think as we have our facts there that it will dissolve any theory that the Catholics
            are going to out-number the others, if they so desire and will restrict their families
            in the face of opposition and in face of the laws that are here. It seems to me when we
            get to them the freedom we are trying to get, especially the restrictions out of the
            way, there will be absolutely no reason why they should not go along even better than
            they are.</p>
        <p>There was also a point raised about the Federal and State Laws. I want to point out that
            the reason the <org>American Birth Control League</org> has not gone in for Federal
            Legislation is because of our experience and our knowledge of the facts. The question of
            practical contraception still is in the almost experimental state and we believe we can
            get far better results if we confine our work to state restrictions, or rather state
            legislatures, where we will have the benefit of the doctor or the members of the medical
            profession in personal contact in giving personal advice to the individual. We believe
            that the medical profession should give the proper information, and that the average
            physician would not use the mails to prescribe to a patient. We believe that that
            personal contact and personal instruction is going to give us far better results than
            the best kind of a book that could be written.</p>
        <p>We know both sides. We know pamphlets have been written. There was one out some years
            ago. I have never felt, even with thousands of them, that they were going to be as
            effective as the individual instruction to the woman herself. The more we get on with
            this work in our Research Department, we are positive that is the right attitude.</p>
        <p>Many of these women we are trying to reach cannot read at all. We know to follow even the
            plainest sort of instructions that it would be difficult for her. She comes to us and
            she is tired, and she is weary, and she can’t understand what she reads, and we can
            instruct her and examine her, as our physician does, and teach her. It only takes a few
            minutes for her to learn what to do, while a whole book could be written and she would
            not know what to do. We contend we are going to get better results by having personal
            instruction.</p>
        <p>There is no question but what the Federal Law needs to be changed. We certainly come up
            against it when we want scientific information. Still, I think the laws we want changed
            in the Federal way need to go along consistently with the policy of the American Birth
            Control League. We think they should be changed at the present for the medical
            profession.</p>
        <p>On the other hand people say, “What are you bothering about the medical profession for
            when they don’t stand for you?” The principle is the same and we are going to fight for
            it. We say we are going to make the public clamor at the doors of the medical profession
            until they take up this work and do it for us. (Applause)</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
