<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2001-12-10 MH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/20 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007-05-31 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-05 CH cleaning regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1914-08-00">Aug 1914</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>
                <supplied resp="MSPP">Short Pieces from page 48 of the August 1914 <title>Woman
                        Rebel</title></supplied>
            </titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp420056</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">The Woman Rebel</title>, Vol. 1, No. 6, Aug.
                1914,48</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Collected Documents Series</title> C16:562</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp id="MSPP">MSPP</resp>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
        <index level1="radicals" level2="suppression and deportation of"/>
        <index level1="socialism" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="socialism" level2="in Germany"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <div type="section">
            <head>MORE JUSTICE!</head>
            <p>Imprisoned Comrades of the working class have been saved again and again from the
                clutches of the monster Capitalism, but from the turn the trials have taken in the
                    <person reg="Rangel, Jesus M.">Rangel</person>-<person reg="Cline, Charles"
                    >Cline</person> case those of us on the outside will have to awaken to our
                consciousness and act without delay if those boys are to be saved.</p>
            <p>Fourteen of our boys have been in jail in <place>Texas</place> for more than a year,
                several of them have been tried and have received the following sentences: <person
                    reg="Gonzales, J.">J. Gonzales</person>, 99 years; <person
                    reg="Vasquez, Leonardo">L. Vasquez </person>who has been sentenced to serve
                fifteen years, appealed his case and the decision was reversed by the <org>Texas
                    Court of Appeals</org>, AND TEN MORE YEARS WERE ADDED TO HIS SENTENCE.</p>
            <p>How is this for Justice for the workers? <person reg="Serrato, J. A.">J. A.
                    Serrato</person>, 25 years; <person>L. Gonzales</person>, 6 years; and <person
                    reg="Martinez, M. P.">M. P. Martinez</person>, 12 years. What Rangel, Cline and
                the other boys not yet tried will get one can almost predict, unless SOMETHING
                DEFINITE and SPECIFIC is acted upon at once.</p>
            <p>Get into communication at once with <person reg="Cravello, Victor">Victor
                    Cravello</person>, Room 108,<place reg="Los Angles, CA"> Los Angeles,
                    Cal.</place>, and save these boys.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head>WHERE IS YOUR POWER NOW?</head>
            <p>What is wrong with <place>Germany</place>'s four or five million Socialists?</p>
            <p>The answer is plain. Germany represents Autocracy and Imperialism. No matter how
                strong the Socialist movement may be in Germany, it has proved its shallowness and
                weakness in the present crisis. German Socialists ought to learn that Socialism
                under an Imperialistic Monarchy is a farce--a parody of the Revolutionary movement.
                Small wonder, then, that our feelings and sympathies must be with the French who
                have always labored champions of human liberty.</p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
