<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2001-11-12 MH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2002-08-27 KH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/03/11 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007-05-31 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-05 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1914-04-00">April, 1914</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Self Preservation</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp420044</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">The Woman Rebel</title>, Vol. 1, No. 2, April 1914,
                16</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Collected Documents Series</title> C16:0530</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
        <index level1="working class" level2="revolution and"/>
        <index level1="labor movement"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>SELF PRESERVATION</head>
        <p>In all living creatures there are strong instincts. One of the strongest, which has
            predominated throughout the evolutionary process of man, is the instinct of
            self-preservation. Man is the victorious species, through the action and strength of
            this instinct. The history of mankind is the history of classes. Between the two classes
            of to-day the question is which class shows in the strongest way, the instinct of
            self-defense.</p>
        <p>At <place>Union Square</place>, <place reg="New York, NY">New York</place>, Saturday, April 4th there
            came men and women who had spent their adult lives on the firing line of the class war.
            They came, scenting, feeling, knowing that brutal treatment awaited them. They came
            fearlessly, yet they came weaponless and unarmed. What has happened to the workers that
            they have lost the greatest principle of all life--self defense?</p>
        <p>Throughout the United States there have been brutal demonstrations by the police against
            the workers. In <place reg="San Francisco, CA">San Francisco</place>, <place
                reg="Sacramento, CA">Sacramento</place>,<place reg="Cleveland, OH"
            >Cleveland</place>, <place reg="Chicago, IL">Chicago</place>, New York have occurred
            most outrageous beatings and clubbings, broken heads, and maimed bodies--always by the
            police. The <org reg="Industrial Workers of the World">I. W. W.</org> boys and the
            anarchists are not so unsophisticated that they look for justice or freedom; they have
            been too long on the firing line to expect it and yet they continue to hope!</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
