<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2001-12-05 MH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2002-08-29 KH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/20 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007-05-31 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011-11-02 EH correct transcriptions and index</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-26 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1914-07-00">July 1914</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Are Preventive Means Injurious?</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp420026</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">The Woman Rebel</title>, Vol. 1, No. 5, July 1914, 40</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> C16:554</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits and risks of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="class-based"/>
        <index level1="Comstock, Anthony"/>
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Comstock Laws"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="morality of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>ARE PREVENTIVE MEANS INJURIOUS?</head>
        <p>It is often asked by those interested in the control of offspring whether the use of
            preventive means does not injure the health. According to investigations carried on
            among physicians in <place reg="Paris, France">Paris</place>, the families who average
            about two children each and who have practiced and used preventative means have
            certainly not found the means harmful.</p>
        <p>The people of each country have found means of prevention differing from those used in
            other countries. The people in this country shall soon demand such knowledge just as
            they do preventive medicine and anti-toxins, and open discussion of these means. To-day
            the women and men of the middle and upper classes certainly use preventives, the death
            rate among them is proportionately small. It is the working class who do not use these
            means that fill the hospitals of the country as well as the grave-yards.</p>
        <p>There is greater harm being done today where women, only half and poorly informed, use
            strong solutions, which are often injurious to the delicate membranous linings of the
            generative organs.</p>
        <p>There are, however, harmless preventives, which, when used, have a temporary effect, and
            when the woman later desires a child she will be in condition to have one.</p>
        <p>These are the sane measures to be advanced; and the stupidity of <person
                reg="Anthony Comstock">Comstock</person> as well as the
                "morality" of the <org reg="United States Post Office">Post
                Office </org>censors, shall never prevent your knowing these preventive means or in
            passing on this knowledge to your shop mate; for every time you place such information
            into the hands of your fellow-workers, you are building the foundation of a clean and
            intelligent society.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
