<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2001-11-30 MH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2002-08-29 KH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/19 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/11/09 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007-05-31 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011-10-06 EK corrections and index</prepDate><prepDate>2014-03-26 CH clearn regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1914-07-00">July 1914</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Tragedy</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp420032</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">The Woman Rebel</title>, Vol. 1, No. 5, July 1914, p. 33</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> C16:547</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
        <index level1="direct action" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="anarchism and anarchists"/>
        <index level1="anarchism and anarchists" level2="violence and"/>
        <index level1="labor movement" level2="radical"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>TRAGEDY</head>
        <p>Even if dynamite were to serve no other purpose than to call forth the spirit of
            revolutionary solidarity and loyalty, it would prove its great value. For this
            expression of solidarity and loyalty and of complete defiance to the morality of the
            masters, in a time of distress and defeat and death, is the most certain sign of that
            strength and courage which are the first essentials to victory. On July 4th, three
            revolutionists, <person reg="Caron, Arthur">Caron</person>, <person reg="Berg, Charles"
                >Berg</person> and <person reg="Hanson, Carl">Hanson</person>, were killed by the
            explosion of dynamite--sacrificed because of their willingness to risk life for their
            convictions. This tragedy created a wonderful spirit of loyalty and solidarity among
            their comrades. It ought to have awakened the same spirit among all those who advocate
            the overthrow of the present system--at least among those agitators and leaders who urge
            direct and revolutionary tactics against the master class.</p>
        <p>But instead we have witnessed a far greater tragedy than the death of our comrades. That
            event in itself bespoke courage, determination, conviction, a spirit of
            defiance--unfortunately, unusual qualities. The real tragedy has been the cowardice and
            the poisonous respectability expressed in the apologies of those adepts in that glib and
            oily art to speak and purpose not--those agitators and leaders who howl about solidarity
            among the workers, only to whitewash themselves with respectability when an episode
            occurs which actually offers an opportunity for the expression of such a spirit of
            solidarity. Instead of this expected defiance of conventional morality and standards,
            they have given nothing more than involved, shamefaced explanations and apologies
            actioned which do more to discredit the organizations they represent than any number of
            bombs or ill-advised acts of violence.</p>
        <p>Explanations and apologies, like patriotism, are the cloaks of cowards, not the reactions
            of strong men.</p>
        <p>It is time to learn to accept and exult in every act of revolt against oppression, to
            encourage and create in ourselves that spirit of rebellion which shall lead us to
            understand and look at the social situation without flinching or quavering or running to
            cover when any crisis arises. Not until we do create this spirit will the revolutionists
            ever be feared or even respected in <place reg="United States"
                >America</place>.</p>
        <p>We are all talking revolution and direct action, solidarity and freedom. If we are not
            willing to back every word that we utter publicly by determined action, we will never
            accomplish anything except to render ourselves ridiculous.</p>
        <p>Solidarity is a means, not an end. It will unite the working class against its oppressors
            not at a single catastrophe at some dim and distant future date, but only as we
            individually incorporate it. We must Live Solidarity, not merely talk it. Even if we
            disagree regarding the social value of the act of revolt, we must accept it and acclaim
            it for the spirit and the motive in back of it. Never repudiate or apologize for the
            comrade who, by an act of revolt has given the best evidence of loyalty to his class, of
            his SOLIDARITY.</p>
        <p>If the so-called revolutionary labor movement must justify its actions at the bar of the
            very public opinion and morality that have created and sustained laws against labor, it
            is a wishywashy, milk-and-watery, weakneed movement at best. If it cannot accept as
            possible and inevitable and valuable among its ranks such men as Berg, Caron and
            Hanson--if, in short, it is not moving in the direction of REVOLUTION, it is time for us
            to build up a movement that is.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
