<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2001-11-13 MH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2002-08-29 KH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/03/11 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/26 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007-05-30 CH Oxygen cleanup</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-05 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1914-04-00">Apr 1914</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Conventions</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp420050</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">The Woman Rebel</title>, Vol. 1, No. 2, Apr 1914, 11</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Collected Documents Series</title> C16:0525</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
        <index level1="marriage"/>
        <index level1="free love"/>
        <index level1="feminism and feminists" level2="MS on"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>CONVENTIONS</head>
        <p>When women-feminists, radicals, calling themselves free-women, arrive at a place in life
            where they are compelled to face and defy conventions, they seldom do it. Go over a list
            of your acquaintances and see how few of them have been big enough or brave enough to
            live up to their principles or ideals. They will tell you that marriage really means
            nothing to them, that they recognize it is an institution which is nothing but forced
            prostitution upon the woman, they agree that only a union of two people based upon love
            should justify a continuous union, that the marriage license had nothing to do with
            love, that it is the marriage law which divides the female sex into moral and immoral
            women (whereas men have no such standards) they agree to these ideas, yet when the time
            comes for them to live up to these ideas, to give expression to their love without
            marriage, they have no back-bone, they whitewash their conscience by stating that they
            care so little for conventions; so little for the marriage license, that--they get
            married. There is the father and mother, and the dear aunt Laura, why should we hurt
            those poor dears, by doing something of which they do not approve? Every new adjustment
            of social relations is painful, someone is likely to object to the adjustment, yet does
            that justify one in not living up to the highest and best in one? No! To ignore
            conventions is not sufficient. That passive, non-resistant attitude does not build
            character. The fighting, aggressive, militant spirit of the English suffragette will
            create a womanhood in <place>England</place> which will put the American Suffragist to
            shame. It is effort which builds. It is effort which creates. It is effort which
            accomplishes, not always the results which it seeks, but the ultimate result of all
            struggle, the development of the individual, of the personality, of the freewoman.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
