<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2001-11-13 MH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2002-08-29 KH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2003-07-28 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/07 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007-05-31 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-05 CH correct regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1914-05-00">May 1914</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Cannibals</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp420013</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">The Woman Rebel</title>, May 1914, 17.</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Collected Documents Series</title>
                C16:0531</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
        <index level1="socialism"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>CANNIBALS</head>
        <p>Compared with the diseased, perverted, hypocritical ghouls of American "civilization,"
            cannibals strike you as simple, healthy people who live in an earthly
                <place>Utopia</place>. If they feed and fatten upon the charred flesh of human
            beings, cannibals at least do not hide behind the sickening smirk of the Church and the
                <org reg="Young Men's Christian Association">Y. M. C. A.</org> They are open, frank,
            and straightforward in their search for food. They eat their victims outright. They do
            not use the charred skulls and skeletons of women and children as the foundation of
            institutions that will hide the cries and shrieks of the tortured, or attempt to kill
            the nauseating stench of their bloody breath by vomiting forth the perfumed hypocrisies
            of the <org>Baptist Church</org>--words of peace on earth and goodwill toward men.</p>
        <p>Cannibals are not so cowardly that they must employ Maxim guns in the wholesale slaughter
            of men, women and children. They do not employ starving sneaks to burn the evidence of
            their nightmarish appetites, or fear themselves to look upon the disemboweled and
            dismembered corpses of the men, women and children who are sacrificed to promote great
            works of charity and philanthropy.</p>
        <p>Cannibals, you see, are uncivilized, primitive folk, low in the scale of human
            intelligence. Their tastes are not so fastidious, so refined, so Christian, as those of
            our great American coal operators, who have subsidized the State of
                <place>Colorado</place>, and treat the <person reg="Wilson, Woodrow">President of
                the United States</person> as an office boy--these leering, bloody hyenas of the
            human race who smear themselves with the stinking honey of Charity to attract those foul
            flies of religion who spread pollution throughout the land.</p>
        <p>Have we workers been inoculated with this foul pollution of the spirit, this poison that
            is being spread by the Young Men's and <org>Young Women's Christian Association</org>s
            and by those churches which are subsidized by the murderous masters of <place
                reg="United States">America</place>?</p>
        <p>Certainly we have if we do not boycott the Baptist Church and its allies, those
            "Christian Associations," that are subsidized by the <person reg="Rockefeller Family"
                >Rockefellers</person> and other criminals in order to kill the spirit of the
            workers of America.</p>
        <p>Certainly we have been if we remain silent or inactive in the campaign against the poison
            of the "religion" that is weakening and killing the spirit of the American workers.</p>
        <p>Workingwomen! Keep away from the Y. W. C. A. as you would from a pesthouse. It is based
            upon the slavery and torture of the workers of America, upon the bodies of toilers who
            have been killed in the mines and factories, and upon the bodies of those who have
            protested against being so murdered--shot down by Maxim guns and burned up with <org>Standard
            Oil</org>. These substantial buildings have been built by those Christians who riddled the
            bodies of women and children with bullets when they attempted to escape from a burning
            pit to a place of safety. It is they who are conferring favors upon you, in order to rob
            you of your freedom.</p>
        <p>They want to inculcate in you the stupid spirit of submission to their mastery. They want
            to feed you upon the vapid innocuities of religion. They want to make you keep books
            with their <name type="deity">God</name>. They want to keep you in stupid ignorance of
            your own body, so that you, too, will some day be forced to breed children who can
            perform their horrible wholesale murders for them--who will shoot down all men and women
            and children who may dare question their mastery and their tyranny. They will force you
            to breed the cowards who murder those who are willing to die for freedom rather than to
            live in slavery.</p>
        <p>But remember <place reg="Ludlow, CO">Ludlow</place>! Remember the men and women and
            children who were sacrificed in order that <person reg="Rockefeller, John D., Jr.">John
                D. Rockefeller, Jr.</person>, might continue his noble career of charity and
            philanthropy as a supporter of the Christian faith.</p>
        <p>Steer clear of those brothels of the Spirit and morgues of Freedom!</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
