<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2001-11-12 MH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2002-08-27 KH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/03/11 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/26 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007-05-30 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-05 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1914-04-00">Apr 1914</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Amusement</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp420052</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">The Woman Rebel</title>, Vol. 1, No. 2, Apr. 1914, 11</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Collected Documents Series</title> C16:0525</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
        <index level1="woman suffrage" level2="working women and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>AMUSEMENT</head>
        <p>The attitude of those fashionable ladies who are working for the suffrage "cause" has
            been revealed in a letter written to one of the daily papers by a bewildered
            suffragist--who happens to be a working woman. How deeply the American suffragists
            concern themselves with the wrongs and the problems of the millions of women workers is
            strikingly shown in these lines from "a working suffragist's" letter:</p>
        <p>"<q who="UNK">Here the leader is a fighter, I am assured. This appeals to me, warms me
                up, makes me feel that here things other than leaders' speeches may happen--but I
                find that working-women are not encouraged, since they have no money to give, no
                time to work. Then the rich women, the women who hold meetings in expensive hotels
                for other rich women--I wonder, can they teach me anything, and I find they can--a
                holy horror of them and their unspeakable patronage of the worker of any
            grade.</q>"</p>
        <p>"<q who="UNK">They talk about us, they pity us, they talk for the papers about us, they
                take up a collection for us."</q></p>
        <p>"<q who="UNK">Gold bags clatter, the mass of furs and feathers heaves--they tremble with
                the thought of the great things they are going to do for us, the workers, and the
                collection amounts to $35, not enough to buy one hat as handsome as the one the
                presiding genius is wearing. Poor workers, your hope is not to be realized here.
                They are not in earnest, they are amusing themselves; they are enjoying a new
                sensation which you, your needs, your struggles and your hopes provide. How does it
                affect me and thousands like me?</q>"</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
