<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2001-12-10 MH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/20 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007-05-31 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/03/11 CH entered corrections suggested by Andy Carloff</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-12 CH clean errors and regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1914-09-00">Sep-Oct 1914</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>A Little Lesson</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp420035</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">The Woman Rebel</title>, Vol. 1, No. 7, Sept.-Oct. 1914, 53</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title>, C16:567</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits and risks"/>
        <index level1="family size"/>
        <index level1="race suicide"/>
        <index level1="family size"/>
        <index level1="physicians" level2="birth control and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>A LITTLE LESSON</head>
        <head type="sub">FOR THOSE WHO OUGHT TO KNOW BETTER</head>
        <p>Query.--What is Birth Control?</p>
        <p>Answer.--A Science which teaches that poverty and social evils can be greatly reduced by
            encouraging people to have small families.</p>
        <p>Q.--Why should people only have small families?</p>
        <p>A.--(1) In order to be able to feed, clothe, house and educate their children
            properly;<lb/>(2) In order to preserve the mother's health, strength and
            happiness;<lb/>(3) In order to avoid overcrowding the labour market and keeping down
            wages by competition.</p>
        <p>Q.--How can people limit their families?</p>
        <p>A.--In two ways. One is by ceasing to live a natural mated life. The other is to employ
            the means which have been discovered for avoiding having children without giving up the
            sex-life.</p>
        <p>Q.--Is it not wrong to use artificial means for avoiding having children?</p>
        <p>A.--It is not wrong provided that no means are employed which would injure the parents or
            any child which is once on the way.</p>
        <p>Q.--Are not artificial methods of restricting families bad for the health?</p>
        <p>A.--It used to be thought so. But within the last few years it has become clear that
            there is not justification for this belief.</p>
        <p>Here are some facts:-</p>
        <p>(a) Doctors nearly all have small families nowadays.<lb/>(b) the Presidents of the <org
                reg="British Medical Society">British Association</org> and of the <org>American
                Medical Association</org> have both spoken in favor of family limitation.<lb/>(c) In
            1911 the <org>Hungarian Medical Senate</org> gave a judgment in favor of permitting the
            use of preventive means.</p>
        <p>(d) Wherever small families have become the rule the health of the nation has improved;
            and it is not improved when families have remained large.</p>
        <p>Q.--Does not family limitation mean race suicide?</p>
        <p>A.--No, it does not. Large families mean race slaughter, because so many mouths cannot be
            fed, and large numbers parish.</p>
        <p>Q.--Would not a knowledge of preventive means encourage young people in immorality?</p>
        <p>A.--Perhaps it might if it were taught to very young people without warning them properly
            in other ways and warning them of the terrible risk of disease. But if young people are
            told that they can marry because there is no need of having children before they can
            support them, and if they are given the knowledge when they marry, it will improve
            morality by taking them away from temptation.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
