<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2001-11-13 MH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2002-08-29 KH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/07 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007-05-31 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011-03-11 CH Entered corrections suggested by Andy Carloff.</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/03/13 EK clean regs</prepDate>

        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1914-05-00">May 1914</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Motherhood--Or Destruction</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp420012</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Woman Rebel, The</title>, Vol. 1, No. 3, May 1914, 22</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> C16:0536</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="WEBJC">Webster, John Clarence</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
        <index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="freedom and rights of"/>
        <index level1="sex and sexuality" level2="MS on"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>MOTHERHOOD--OR DESTRUCTION</head>
        <p>"<q who="WEBJC">The attainment of high intellectual culture in the academies, normal
                schools and colleges is very commonly found to be at the expense of reproductive
                energy,</q>" says <person>Webster, John Clarence</person>, M. D., Professor in the
            University of <place reg="Edinburgh, Scotland">Edinburgh</place>. He points out that the
            New England States furnish us with the most striking proof of these facts. Further he
            states that when women are sure that they will not be mothers, then allow them to
            achieve all greatness, "<q who="WEBJC">throw open all doors to them and let them destroy
                themselves in the service of mankind.</q>"</p>
        <p>There is no doubt that Dr. Webster has struck a very true note in the progress of
            mankind. But why he isolates the woman in this regard I cannot see, for it is a well
            recognized fact that the sexual impulse can be guided, directed and used in various
            ways, in men as well as in women.</p>
        <p>It is said that when a certain amount of energy is used in brain development, there will
            be less of this energy for the sexual function during that particular period. Certainly
            the reproductive energy is used in self development, but that does not signify that the
            reproductive function or ability is destroyed. The energy is transferred to other
            creative processes, perhaps even to a greater extent in men than in women.</p>
        <p>It may be that the sexual desire is not so frequent among women of intellectual
            attainments and pursuits but there is a possibility that there exists a finer and
            greater intensity in the fulfilment of the desire. Is this, then, Dr. Webster's meaning
            of her destruction?</p>
        <p>Perhaps out of woman's contact with the advance movements of the world there will in time
            arise a more honest and courageous womanhood, devoid of petty shames, which shall be
            able and willing to contribute to science intelligently the deepest complexities of
            woman's emotional nature. Then can there be some conclusion arrived at of the antagonism
            between the sexual and intellectual functions. The book of the woman is yet to be
            written and it remains for the <emph rend="bold">woman</emph> to do it who is able and
            brave enough to strip herself clean to the soul; to know herself and let herself be
            known.</p>
        <p>Dr. Webster has yet to learn that motherhood is not the sole agent in woman's salvation.
            Woman's experiences must be many and varied, but above all she must assume control over
            her own body that she alone shall decide her needs and if motherhood is among them--let
            her accept it, but if not--then let her reject it at any cost. If this be "destroying
            themselves in the service of mankind" then Dr. Webster must make the most of it.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
