<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2001-11-13 MH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2002-08-27 KH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/03/11 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007-05-30 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-05 CH correcting regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1914-04-00">Apr 1914</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Two Sisters</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp420053</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">The Woman Rebel</title>, Vol. 1, No. 2, Apr. 1914 ,
                11</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Collected Documents Series</title> C16:0525</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
        <index level1="women" level2="freedom and rights of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>TWO SISTERS</head>
        <div type="section">
            <p>Two sisters--daughters of a policeman--only two years apart in age; one worked six
                years in one place for six dollars a week; was content and happy, day in and day
                out, year in and year out, until the end of six years she received eight
                dollars--she was content, obedient and happy, giving no trouble--the other, two
                years her junior, was never satisfied--could not get along with her boss--often out
                of work--had strong desires--consequently stole things she wanted--and lands in the
                House of Correction.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <p>Progress depends on the individual with strong desires--on the individual who is not
                satisfied. Woman's freedom depends on the woman with strong desires, who is not
                content with anything less than her complete emancipation. But she will fight and
                continue to fight and not sit with folded hands and be satisfied with half-way
                measures. The junior daughter was by far in my estimation a superior individual to
                the slave, the "job-minded" sister.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <p>The tragedy of this little story is not the slave, who is happy to work for six years
                for $6 a week to enrich a master.</p>
            <p>Not the prostitute who sells her body for the "good things of life" but Society, in
                its stupidity and ignorance which refuses to recognize in the one, an individuality,
                but instead sends her to an institution especially equipped by brute creatures to
                break that splendid spirit; to degrade the girl; to humiliate her.</p>
            <p>The Reformatory establishes laws to make of her a sneak, a coward and a traitor to
                her class and aims to reform her by means of a scrubbing brush and a club.</p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
