<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-03-05 JK initial tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-14 CH proof tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-26 JK correct tags</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1936-02-20">20 Feb 1936</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">The Case for Birth
                    Control</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421089</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Birth Control Case</title>, <title
                    type="journal">South China Morning Post</title>, Feb. 21,
                1936.</bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="SCMP">South China Morning Post</name>
            <name id="SHAGE"> Shaw, George Bernard </name>
            <name id="INGWI">Inge, William Ralph</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger</person> spoke
        at the <place reg="Hong Kong, China">Hong Kong </place><org
            reg="Hong Kong Hotel Roof Garden">Hotel Roof Garden</org> on Feb.
        19, 1936. <person reg="Nixon, W.C.W.">W.C.W. Nixon</person> presided and
            <person reg="How-Martyn, Edith">Edith How-Martyn</person> also made
        a speech. <index level1="birth control" level2="in India"/><index
            level1="birth control" level2="international"/><index
            level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="economic benefits and risks of"
            /><index level1="birth control" level2="socio-economic benefits of"
            /><index level1="birth control" level2="in China"/><index
            level1="Asia" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Asia" level2="overpopulation and"/><index level1="women"
            level2="freedom and rights of"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="health of"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"
            /><index level1="overpopulation" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="overpopulation" level2="threat to peace as"/>
        <index level1="parenthood"/><index level1="population growth"
            level2="regulation of"/>
        <index level1="population growth" level2="standard of living and"
        /></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Birth Control Case</head>
        <head type="sub">Mrs. Margaret Sanger's Seven Principal Points</head>
        <head type="sub">Too-Large Families Deprecated</head>

        <div>
            <head type="sub">Mrs. Sanger’s Address</head>

            <p>
                <q who="SCMP">Mrs. Sanger said that she believed that birth
                    control had struck not only the West but also the East, as a
                    whole. There was no other subject of equal importance.
                        <person reg="Shaw, George Bernard">George Bernard
                        Shaw</person> had said that it was </q>“<q who="SHAGE"
                    >the most revolutionary idea of this century</q>” and
                    <person reg="Inge, William Ralph">Dean Inge</person> had
                agreed that birth control “<q who="INGWI">had come and come to
                    stay</q>.” <person reg="Dawson, Bertrand">Lord Dawson of
                    Penn </person>went before the Anglican Bishops some years
                ago and, in closing his address, said that if they would not
                open their eyes and ears, they would have to close their jaws.
                One had to look at the subject with a broad mind. Birth control
                did not disturb life but was a means of limiting the family. it
                was the key note in a new social awakening. Some people would
                ask why control the birth rate, and others would say that there
                was an unlimited space in the world for everybody. </p>
            <q who="SCMP">
                <p> Mrs. Sanger said that she would deny these statements.
                    Nature in the past had used wars, floods, pestilence and
                    famine to maintain the balance in every community and in
                    every nation. At the present day it was either an increase
                    of death rate or a decrease of birth rate, and one could not
                    have it both ways. The situation in modern times was further
                    aggravated by the fact that immigration had been entirely
                    suspended in every country with the possible exception of
                        <place>South America</place>. If there was no control in
                    birth rate, the situation as it now exists would be further
                    aggravated. </p>
                <p> It was unfair to tax the normal and healthy in order to keep
                    the ill-equipped and defective ones. Yet, at the present
                    moment this very thing was tolerated. Without some control
                    over the ill-equipped and defective, the situation at the
                    present time could not be reconciled. </p>
                <p> Mrs. Sanger drew the attention of those present to the
                    countries where birth control was practiced and had been
                    practiced for some ten years or so past, and compare them
                    with the countries where such was not the case. In
                        <place>France</place>, <place>England</place>,<place>
                        Germany</place>, <place>Finland</place>,
                        <place>Denmark</place>, and the <place reg="Scandinavia"
                        >Scandinavian countries</place> the power of fertility
                    had been under control. There were fewer children born but
                    thy were given much better opportunities to grow to full
                    maturity and were born into conditions that were a great
                    deal more favorable than otherwise would be the case. By
                    birth control, families had children at spaced intervals
                    which gave the women a chance to recuperate fully between
                    each pregnancy, with a consequence betterment in the
                    standard of health, and there were no horrors of abortion.
                    Mothers were able to develop any talent that they might
                    possess, and those in professions were able to get back to
                    work. Families, on the whole, were spiritually, mentally,
                    and physically bettered. </p></q>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Consideration </head>
            <q who="SCMP">
                <p> A race would not die out. it was not selfish to have a
                    smaller family, rather it was the reverse. It clearly
                    demonstrated that consideration was being given to the
                    children born or to go even further, to the children yet
                    unborn. In the other national groups where there were very
                    large families, with the horrors of too frequent pregnancy,
                    the health of the mother was inevitably impaired while the
                    hopelessness of the situation had adverse effects on the
                    fathers. Every social evil of to-day is to be found in this
                    group. In an effort to do away with these evils, legislative
                    methods had been adopted generation after generation. The
                        <place reg="United States">United States of
                        America</place> had tried to do away with child labor.
                    many of those present, Mrs. Sanger said were under the
                    illusion that child labor had been dispensed with totally by
                    the mere stroke of the President’s pen. She assured all that
                    this was not the case. Child labor did in fact still exist,
                    and was existing at the present moment in America. Millions
                    of children under the age of 14 years still toil, but now
                    worked in family groups whereby the father was getting paid
                    for what his children did. As long as parents who could not
                    support two or three children were encouraged to bring 10,
                    12, or 14 children into the world, there would always be
                    child labor. </p></q>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Unemployment </head>
            <q who="SCMP">
                <p> Speaking of unemployment Mrs. Sanger said that the labor
                    saving devices had increased during the past 20 years with
                    amazing rapidity. A machine could make more electric bulbs
                    in one hour than 2,000 men without machinery. America would
                    always carry the load of unemployment unless machinery was
                    scrapped, and the country resorted to adult male labor.
                    Personally, she thought that America would never resort to
                    this method as a solution to the present day problem. Birth
                    control was, however, one solution. Birth control had been
                    at work and where it had worked, it had done well. It had
                    reduced maternal and infantile mortality and raised the
                    standard of living. There were about seven important reasons
                    why birth control should be practiced. <list>
                        <item>(1) A man or woman with a transmissible disease
                            should have no children. If birth control failed in
                            respect of this type of people, then Mrs. Sanger
                            strongly recommended sterilization. </item>
                        <item> (2) Women who have temporary diseases, such as
                            tuberculosis, disease of the heart or kidneys,
                            should be protected not only from child birth, but
                            pregnancy until cured. </item>
                        <item>(3) Parents who although healthy, yet give birth
                            to children that are abnormal (deaf, blind, etc.)
                            should be encouraged not to have any more children. </item>
                        <item> (4) Women, especially those of the working class
                            with a low income, should have their children spaced
                            at least three years. </item>
                        <item>(5) Economy. It was socially immoral for parents
                            to have 10 ir 12 children when they could not afford
                            to take care of two. The responsibility would fall
                            on the elder child who would have to work and toil
                            all day to look after and care for his or her
                            younger brothers and sisters. </item>
                        <item>(6) Adolescence, which was the period between 14
                            and 23 years for boys, and 12 and 22 for girls.
                            While marriage during the latter part of adolescence
                            might be useful and beneficial, postponement of
                            parenthood was most essential. </item>
                        <item>(7) Adjustment to marriage. Young people should be
                            encouraged to wait and keep the period of adjustment
                            after marriage.</item>
                    </list></p></q>

        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> No Injurious Effects</head>

            <p>
                <q who="SCMP">Mrs. Sanger went on to deal with three means of
                    controlling the birth rate, namely the raising of the age of
                    marriage such as has taken place in <place>India</place> and
                    the <place reg="Asia">Far East</place>; sterilization, which
                    did not imply desexing of male or female; (in 24 States in
                    America sterilization was at present taking place); chemical
                    and mechanical means of contraception, and this was where
                    mot of the argument arose. In America there were over 125
                    clinics and from the experience gained it was positive that
                    no injurious effects were suffered. Concluding Mrs. Sanger
                    said that birth control had reduced abortion and divorces.
                    Her great aim was to have these methods of birth control in
                    the hands of public health authorities, where proper
                    instruction was made available to each individual. They had
                    the means and methods for nearly every condition now-a-days,
                    and they were not expensive.</q>
            </p>
            <p>“We hope that we are bringing a message of hope that may be
                fulfilled in China. We want our young people to think of their
                bodies as holy temples,” said Mrs. Sanger, in conclusion. </p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
