<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="(Published article) ">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/04/09 VS initial tagging</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="(1934-07-10) ">10 July, 1934</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Statements on Birth Control and Peace</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421078</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Dagens Nyheter</title></bibl>
            <bibl><title>LCM 20:169</title></bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="DAGEN">Dagens Nyhter</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">This is an exerpt from a translation of an article of a Swedish newspaper,
            <title type="journal">Dagens Nyheter</title>. <index level1="birth control"
            level2="access to" level3="international"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="war and"/>
        <index level1="conferences"
            level2="International Neo-Malthusian and Birth Control Conference" level3="1922 (5th)"/>
        <index level1="war" level2="causes of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="and war"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Fewer Children the Best Front Against War</head>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> U.S.A. Has the Greatest Percentage of Deaths in Childbirth</head>
            <p> “For five minutes my proposal concerning a change in <place reg="United States"
                    >U.S.A.</place>’s sixty-year old <name reg="United States Penal Code">Birth
                    Control Law</name> was actually elevated to law,” <q who="DAGEN">related Mrs.
                        <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>, known over the
                    whole world as the foremost pioneer for Birth Control, and now on a visit to
                        <place reg="Stockholm, Sweden">Stockholm</place>.</q> “But afterwards an
                elderly gentleman in the <org reg="United States Senate">Senate</org> woke up and
                protested, and so the work of many years for a change in this vital problem was
                stopped for the time being. But next year it will go through.”</p>
            <q who="DAGEN"><p> Mrs. Sanger, who is traveling in <place>Europe</place> with the
                    intention of starting an international movement for organized Birth Control, and
                    has no arrived in Stockholm, is a lady with a gallant and tumultuous past. And
                    that she did little on her own part to avoid the storms one can see immediately
                    in her red Irish hair and clear blue American eyes. She has been called
                    America’s most slandered woman, and that is quite correct. To begin a campaign
                    for legalized birth control twenty-five years ago in American must have been a
                    task with many risks. Between 1921, when she called together the first <org
                        reg="First American Birth Control Conference">Birth Control Conference</org>
                    in America, and now, when her proposition became law, if only for five minutes,
                    lie many defeats and many personal persecutions, but also many glorious
                    victories. Her first step on the way to which her experience as a child in a
                    large and poor family drove her was an article in her own paper, “<title
                        type="journal">The Woman Rebel</title>,” which was followed immediately by a
                    commitment. She eluded the action by escaping to <place>England</place>, and
                    when, a year later she returned to the United States, such a strong European
                    opinion stood back of her that the authorities found it advisable to forget the
                    little incident of by-gone days. Nevertheless, since then she has served a
                    month’s imprisonment. </p></q>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Birth Control the Only Way to Peace</head>
            <p> “To me it was quite clear,” <q who="DAGEN">she declares,</q> “that now since all the
                countries have closed their boundaries to other nations the only solution to the
                problem of peace is control of population. If you do not choose this method, there
                is only one other, a lowering of the standard of living. And the end is that women
                become the slaves of militarism, that the countries need colonies, the colonies new
                soldiers for their defense, and so on, in one vicious circle.</p>
            <p> “In America, as I said, the law on this question is 60 years old and has never been
                changed. As a consequence of this we have the highest percentage of deaths in
                childbirth in the whole world. Thanks to the somewhat varying laws of the different
                states we have finally come so far that we have nearly 140 more or less officially
                tolerated clinics for birth control information, of which one is mine, and in my
                work I have had occasion to help 50,000 women. But much still needs to be done, and
                that is why I am making this trip. I shall go to <place reg="Soviet Union"
                    >Russia</place> to study their organizations for women and how they solve the
                problem home - work. But before this I shall meet with some of my friends here in
                order to talk with them and form a group to continue work. From <place>India</place>
                an inquiry has also come asking I will come there and take part in a congress which
                represents 11 million women. And, as I said, the next time my proposed law
                concerning permission from doctors and other medical scientists to render positive
                enlightenment regarding Birth Control comes up, I believe it will be difficult to
                count the minutes of its duration.”</p>
            <q who="DAGEN"><p> Wednesday, at one o’clock at Moseback there will be a meeting between
                    Mrs. Sanger and Swedish doctors and others who are interested.</p></q>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
