<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="(Published Interview) ">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/31/01 YG initial encoding</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/02/07 CH proof tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/02/07 YG correct tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-11-10 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1936-02-05">05 Feb 1936</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Interview with the<title type="journal">Rangoon Gazette</title></titlePart>
        </docTitle>

        <idno>msp421091</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">"Dr. Sanger in Rangoon: Leader of Birth Control
                    Movement,"</title>
                <title type="journal">Rangoon Gazette</title>, 5 Feb 1936.</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="RG">Rangoon Gazette</name>
            <name id="CRAFR">Crane,Frederikc</name>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">The first of two interviews published in the <title type="journal">Rangoon
            Gazette</title> For the second interview see <xref from="421092.xml">February 6,
            1936</xref>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to" level3="international"/>
        <index level1="Gandhi, Mahatma"/>
        <index level1="conferences"
            level2="International Neo-Malthusian and birth Control Conference" level3="1925 (6th)"/>
        <index level1="birth control movement" level2="history of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Dr. Sanger in Rangoon</head>
        <head type="sub">Leader of Birth Control Movement</head>
        <div>
            <p>
                <q who="RG"> Dr. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>,
                    internationally recognized as the leader of the birth control movement, arrived
                    in <place reg="Rangoon, Burma">Rangoon</place>yesterday from
                        <place>India</place>. This is Dr. Sanger’s first visit to India, although
                    she has already visited almost every other country in the world.</q>
            </p>
            <p>“Parenthood when it is responsible can be a noble trust, a proud commission, an
                honored assignment- but this can be accomplished only by taking it out of the sphere
                of accident and placing it in the sphere of conscious responsibility. We can then
                trust that every child will be a wanted child, born to its rightful heritage of
                love, care and comfort.” <q who="RG">This is Dr. Sanger's message to <place
                        reg="Burma">Burma</place>as it has been to every country she has visited,
                    since she began her crusade for birth control twenty-one years ago.</q></p>
            <p><q who="RG">Dr. Sanger herself is surprised at the fruitful results of her visit to
                    India. She spoke at the <org reg="All-India Women's Conference">All-India
                        Women's Conference</org>'s annual meeting at <place reg="Travancore, India"
                        >Travancore</place>at the end of December. As a result a resolution was
                    passed to ask the municipalities and hospitals in India to give free advice
                    concerning birth control and the spacing of children. There were eight-five for
                    the resolution and twenty-four against.</q></p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Meets <person reg="Gandhi, Mohandas K.">Mr. Gandhi</person></head>
            <p>“Just prior to my departure for <place reg="Burma">Burma</place>, I had an
                interview--a rather prolonged interview, it lasted two days-- with Mr. Gandhi,” <q
                    who="RG">Dr. Sanger said to a Rangoon Gazette reporter. </q>“I was his guest and
                had a very receptive and hospitable visit. We discussed the regulating of the size
                of the family among the poorer families, for the well-to-do are already aware of the
                various methods and have the means to practice them. The children of the poor only
                come into this world to die off in large numbers. Mr. Gandhi agreed that there
                should be regulation of families, but we differed as to methods to achieve this. He
                was of the opinion that the correct method was continence. I opposed him, and said
                that, although this might be practicable in small groups who could sublimate their
                energies, it was not for the greater masses in their humdrum every day existence. I
                put forward my arguments to support my statement against continence and said that I
                thought birth control was much more scientific, less injurious and more conducive to
                the happiness of the whole family.”</p>
            <p><q who="RG">Dr. Sanger will leave tomorrow for <place reg="Singapore"
                        >Singapore</place>. She hopes to meet medical men in Rangoon and, if
                    possible, to organize a meeting.</q>
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"><q who="RG">A Romantic Career</q></head>
            <p><q who="RG">Mrs. Sanger has had a career which without exaggeration has been
                    romantic. She was born in <place reg="Corning, NY">a small factory town in
                            <place reg="New York">New York State</place>.</place> Of Irish
                    parentage, she was the sixth in a family of eleven children. On her mother’s
                    side she is related to the famous translator of <person reg="Khayyam, Omar">Omar
                        Kheyyani</person>, <person reg="Fitzgerald, Edward">Edward
                        Fitzgerald</person>; her <person reg="Higgins, Michael Hennessy"
                        >father</person> was a Civil War veteran, a liberal, and a
                philosopher.</q></p>

            <p><q who="RG">The American fight for birth control was launched by Margaret Sanger in
                    1914 when she invented the phrase “birth control,” launched the “<title
                        type="journal">Woman Rebel</title>” magazine, and founded <org
                        reg="Birth Control League of America">the first birth control organization
                        in America</org>.</q></p>
            <p><q who="RG">The “<title type="journal">Woman Rebel</title>” was suppressed, and Mrs.
                    Sanger was indicted by the <org reg="United States Government">Federal
                        Government</org>. Between her indictment and appearance for trial, she
                    studied in <place reg="England">England</place> and <place reg="Netherlands"
                        >Holland</place>, grounding herself in the social and economic aspects of
                    the question and learning methods in the birth control clinics of Holland. In
                    England her case aroused such sympathy that a letter in her behalf was addressed
                    to <person reg="Wilson, Woodrow">President Wilson</person>President Wilson by
                        <person reg="Bennett, Arnold">Arnold Bennett</person>, <person
                        reg="Murray, Gilbert">Gilbert Murray</person>, <person reg="Wells, H.G."
                        >H.G. Wells</person>, and other prominent people. When she returned home for
                    trial, protests poured in to the <person reg="Clayton, Henry Delamar"
                        >judge</person> and to the President, and in the face of this support, the
                    case was dropped.</q></p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"><q who="RG">Opens Clinic </q></head>
            <p>
                <q who="RG">Her next move was to test the New York State law by opening a clinic in
                    the slum section of <place reg="Brooklyn, NY">Brooklyn</place>in 1916. As a
                    trained nurse she saw the misery caused by too frequent pregnancies among the
                    poor and resolved to help the mothers of <place reg="United States"
                        >America</place> obtain safe, harmless birth control information. After ten
                    days the clinic was raided by the police, Mrs. Sanger was convicted and spent a
                    month in jail, but on appeal a judicial opinion was handed down permitting
                    doctors to give contraceptive advice </q><q who="CRAF"> “for the cure or
                    prevention of disease.” </q>
            </p>
            <p><q who="RG">Taking advantage of this decision, Mrs. Sanger opened the <org>Birth
                        Control Clinical Research Bureau</org> in <place reg="New York, NY">New York
                        City</place> in 1923. This clinic, the oldest in America and the largest in
                    the world, has been operating ever since and serves as a teaching centre for
                    clinics throughout the country. </q></p>
            <p><q who="RG">In the spring of 1929 this clinic, too, was raided but the protests of
                    physicians, lawyers, and an outraged public made it quickly apparent that a
                    mistake had been made. Mrs. Sanger received an official apology and the court
                    decision fully exonerated the clinic physicians.</q></p>
            <p><q who="RG">Meanwhile Mrs. Sanger was developing the national and international
                    aspects of the subject. In 1921 she organized the <org
                        reg="First American Birth Control Conference">First American Birth Control
                        Conference</org>, held in New York. The meeting was attended by men and
                    women prominent in medicine and the social sciences and their participation and
                    offers to help the cause did much to establish the movement.</q>
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">World Tour</head>
            <p><q who="RG">The following year Mrs. Sanger made a world tour, speaking in <place
                        reg="China">China</place>, <place reg="Japan">Japan</place>, and <place
                        reg="Hawaii">Hawaii</place>. Great impetus was given to birth control in the
                        <place reg="Asia">Orient</place>through this visit.</q></p>
            <p><q who="RG">An <org
                        reg="International Neo-Malthusian and Birth Control Conference, Sixth (New York)"
                        >International Birth Control Conference</org> was held in New York under her
                    leadership in 1925, and two years later she was instrumental in calling together
                    the <org reg="World Population Conference, 1927, Geneva"> World Population
                        Conference in Geneva</org>. </q></p>
            <p><q who="RG">Resigning the presidency of the <org reg="American Birth Control League">
                        American Birth Control League</org>, which she had founded, Margaret Sanger
                    organized the <org
                        reg="National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control"> National
                        Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control</org> in 1929,to secure
                    the amendment of the federal laws which forbid the sending of contraceptive
                    information or supplies by mail or common carrier. Realizing that these federal
                    laws must be amended of birth control information is to be given by clinics and
                    hospitals to the poor who need it most, the Committee was organized for a
                    nation-wide educational campaign. Its membership includes leading
                    public-spirited men and women - doctors, teachers, ministers, welfare workers,
                    nurses, editors, economists, and home-makers. It comprises many thousands of
                    individuals who have given their personal endorsement to the birth control
                    movement and the legislative aims of the Committee. </q></p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Campaign to Amend Laws</head>
            <p><q who="RG">Actively aiding in the campaign to amend the federal laws is an imposing
                    list of medical, social, educational, religious, and political organizations.
                    The success of Mrs. Sanger’s work during the last five years may be measured in
                    part by the number and kinds of groups which have passed resolutions in support
                    of her efforts to amend the federal laws. Outstanding among these are the <org
                        reg="Federal Council of
                        Churches of Christ in America"
                        >Federal Council of Churches of Christ in America</org>, regional
                    conferences of the <org reg="Methodist Episcopal Church">Methodist Episcopal
                        Church</org>, the <org
                        reg="General Convention of the House of Bishops and House of Deputies of the Protestant
                    Episcopal Church"
                        >General Convention of the House of Bishops and House of Deputies of the
                        Protestant Episcopal Church</org>, state medical societies and state public
                    health associations, state Conferences of Social Work, <org
                        reg="League of Women Voters">Leagues of Women Voters</org>, <org
                        reg="Parents and Teachers Association">Parents and Teachers
                        Associations</org>, and, during the last year, the <org>General Federation
                        of Women’s Clubs</org> composed of 2,000,000 members and the <org>American
                        Association of University Women</org>, representing 450,000 college women.
                </q></p>
            <p><q who="RG">Bills have been introduced into each <org reg="United States Congress"
                        >Congress</org> since 1930 and hearings, with attendant publicity, have been
                    held. </q></p>
            <p><q who="RG">A happy recognition of Mrs. Sanger’s services was given by the
                        <org>American Women’s Association</org> which in 1931 presented to her its
                    medal for distinguished achievement. During this year her autobiography, <title
                        type="book">“My Fight for Birth Control</title>,” was published. Mrs. Sanger
                    is also the author of <title type="book">“Motherhood in Bondage </title>,”
                        <title type="book">“Happiness in Marriage</title>,” <title type="book"
                        >“Woman and the New Race </title>,” <title type="book">“The Pivot of
                        Civilization </title>.” She founded the <title type="journal">“Birth Control
                        Review”</title> and was its editor for eleven years.</q>
            </p>
            <p><q who="RG">Among her major activities during the least few years are the
                    organization of the <org>American Conference on Birth Control and National
                        Recovery</org>, held in <place reg="Washington, DC">Washington</place> in
                    January, 1934, the introduction of bills now pending in Congress and the gradual
                    enlightenment of the National Committee through regional and state chairmen.
                </q></p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
