<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/02/21 YG</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/02/27 CH proof</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/03/07 YG correct</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1917-03-06">6 Mar 1917</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Remarks on Release From Prison</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421007</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">MRS. SANGER FLAYS MISS DAVIS'S PLANS</title>,
                <title type="journal">New York Times</title>,Mar 7, 1917, p. 13</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="NYT">New York Times</name>
        </respStmt><name id="DAVKA">Davis, Katherine B.</name>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">summary of Sanger's statement on her release from the
        <org>Queens County Penitentiary</org> after serving a thirty day sentence for opening the <org>Brownsville Clinic.</org> <index
            level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="arrests"/>
        <index level1="Brownsville Clinic" level2="arrests and trial"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head><person reg="Sanger, Margaret>MRS. SANGER</person> FLAYS <person reg="Davis, Katherine B.">MISS DAVIS</person>'S PLANS</head>
        <head type="sub">Birth Control Crusader, Her Imprisonment Ended, Brings Jail Women’s
            Plaint.</head>
        <head type="sub">INMATES “LEARN TO HATE”</head>
        <head type="sub">Will Deliver Her Message to <org>Miss Davis’s Club</org>-- Resists All Attempts to
            Take Her Fingerprints.</head>
        <div>
            <p>
                <q who="NYT">Mrs. Margaret Sanger, her term of thirty days’ imprisonment
                    over, left the <org>Queens County Jail</org> yesterday bringing with her what she calls a
                </q>“message in trust”<q who="NYT">for the women of New York from the women of the jail. This
                    message has nothing to do with birth control, advocacy of which sent Mrs. Sanger
                    to jail, but, according to Mrs. Sanger, charges of studied cruelty heartlessness
                    in the treatment of the jail’s population. Throughout the message occurs
                    frequently the name of Katherine B. Davis, former Commissioner of Correction and
                    now Chairman of the Parole Board.</q>
            </p>

            <p>
                <q who="NYT">Mrs. Sanger says she has determined to deliver her message
                    at the meeting next Tuesday of the <org>Women’s City Club</org>, which she has been invited
                    to address and of which Miss Davis is an officer. Miss Davis may not be present,
                    but Mrs. Sanger hopes she will. Miss Davis was out of town yesterday, and so an
                    outline of the charges which Mrs. Sanger will make in her public address could
                    not be submitted to her.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
                <q who="NYT"> Mrs. Sanger, however, says she does not intend to make any
                    campaign against Miss Davis. She merely regards herself, she explained
                    yesterday, as the spokesman of the inmates of the Queens County Jail --</q> “poor
                    girls” <q who="NYT">Mrs. Sanger calls them. </q>
            </p>
        </div>
       
            <head type="sub">An Atmosphere of Resentment</head>
        <div>
            <p>“It is not of physical conditions that the girls complained,” <q who="New York Times">
                   said Mrs. Sanger, in her home, 246 West Fourteenth Street, after an
                    enthusiastic crowd of her friends and sympathizers had met her at the jail and
                    carried her off to a luncheon, at the <org>Hotel Lafayette</org>, in celebration of her
                    freedom.</q> “It is not of these conditions, though certainly they are
                sufficiently bad. It is the attitude adopted towards the girls, the atmosphere in
                which they are compelled to live. </p>
            <p>“These are such that every inmate of the jail learns to hate Miss Davis with a
                bitterness and a depth of resentment that one would scarcely believe possible. Do
                you know that she cannot enter the men’s mess hall. She has tried on one or two
                occasions and each time has been greeted with cries of ‘Get out. Get out.’ A keeper
                told me that, and he told me that Miss Davis got out, too. </p>
            <p>The girls complain that Miss Davis delights in the exercise of authority that amounts
                to tyranny. For instance, one girl learned that her family, her child and her
                mother, had been made destitute by her imprisonment, which had deprived them of her
                support. She pleaded with Miss Davis to release her. Her sentence was an
                indeterminate one and its length was entirely at the pleasure of Miss Davis. Miss
                Davis laughed at her request and then the girl begged at least to be told about how
                long she must remain in jail so that she might, if it were possible, make
                arrangements to tide over matters until her release. </p>
            <p><q who="DAVKA">“‘That’s one of the beauties of the system-- that you don’t know,’ </q>Miss Davis
                replied.</p>
            <p>“The poor girl told me the whole story. Another begged that her parents be not
                informed of her plight, and she told me that Miss Davis replied: <q who="DAVKA">“‘Ha! Ha! You
                    should have thought of that before you got in here.’ </q></p></div>
            
        <head type="sub">In Contrast with <org reg="Sing Sing Correctional Facility">Sing Sing.</org></head>
            <div>
            <p>“It was Miss Davis who put up a fine mesh screen in the visiting room so that an
                inmate can see her callers only through a veil so fine that their features are
                scarcely distinguishable. Yet in Sing Sing a convict may receive visitors in a
                comfortable room, where both may be at their ease. Miss Davis removed the knives and
                forks and crockery and replaced them with tin and agate ware. She did not replace
                the knives and forks at all, so that now, if you are unfortunate enough to be an
                inmate, you may tear your meat apart, when you get it, with your fingers. Miss Davis
                has taken away privileges that the inmates fought for years to obtain. Her idea of
                prison management and of reform for prisoners seem to be a discipline so harsh and
                unfeeling that every decent emotion of her victim is killed by it.” </p>
            <p>
                <q who="NYT">Mrs. Sanger said another girl, heartbroken, had told her how
                    a member of the <org reg="New York State Division of Parole">Parole Board</org> had gone to the trouble of a long journey into 
                    <place>Connecticut</place>
                    to tell the girl’s mother the whole history of her case; how she had been
                    convicted of theft and how she was in jail. Recently, the girl had told Mrs.
                    Sanger, word reached her of her mother’s illness, brought on by this news, for
                    the girl had always been enabled to keep from her parents all knowledge of her
                    wrongdoings. </q>
            </p>
            <p>
                <q who="NYT">Little of her own experience in jail would find a place in
                    her address, Mrs. Sanger said, for she had a not unpleasant time, all things
                    considered. Shortage of material had kept the authorities from putting her in
                    the sewing squad, and so all she had to do was care for her cell. <person reg="McCann, John">John McCann,</person>
                    the Warden, and <person reg="Whittaker, Mary">Matron Whittaker</person>, she said, were kindly, humane persons, who
                    made the duties of their offices as little unpleasant to the inmates as
                    possible. </q>
            </p>
            <p>“I ought to say that of them,” <q who="New York Times">said Mrs. Sanger,</q> “for
                other prisoners told me that they were the rare exception. But even they would not
                permit me to lecture to the girls. I offered to talk on any subject, but they said
                it was impossible. Just think! And those girls had practically nothing to do. There
                is no provision to educate the prisoners, so that an opportunity for real reform
                work is lost.” </p>
            <p>
                <q who="NYT">Mrs. Sanger’s only real trouble while a prisoner arose over
                    her refusal to be fingerprinted. Throughout her stay in jail Warden McCann tried
                    to get her to submit, and finally on Monday night two keepers tried to force her
                    to submit. They apologized for the necessity of using force, but they persisted,
                    and for more than an hour they tried to force Mrs. Sanger’s fingers on to the
                    pad. </q>
            </p>
            <p>“I was bruised and exhausted,” <q who="New York Times">said Mrs. Sanger,</q> “though
                they tried to be as gentle as they could, and at last they went to ask McCann if
                they should persist. He told them to do so, but after more resistence they abandoned
                the attempt. I cautioned them that they had no right to lay hands on me.” </p></div>
          
            <head type="sub">Warm Greetings from Sympathizers.</head>
        <div>
            <p><q who="NYT">Discussion over this kept Mrs. Sanger in jail an hour and a half longer, while some
                forty persons were waiting for her outside. Meantime <person reg="Marion, Kitty">Miss Kitty Marion</person>, an English
                militant suffragette, stood in the prison courtyard and sang suffragette words to
                the air of <title type="song">“The Marseillaise</title>,” the inmates joining in the chorus from the windows. </q></p>
            <p><q who="NYT">A testimonial dinner will be given to Mrs. Sanger and <person reg="Byrne, Ethel Higgins">her sister</person> 
                at <org>Terrace Garden</org>
                March 16. She says she will make a lecture tour of the <place reg="United States">States</place> between <place reg="New York, NY">New York</place>
                and <place reg="Chicago, IL">Chicago</place>. </q></p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
