<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="(Published article) ">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/04/04 VS initial tagging</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="(1936-01-17) ">17 Jan, 1936</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Sanger's Speech in Central College Bengalore</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421086</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>The Hindu</title></bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="HINDU">The Hindu</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">Sanger gave a speech on "Birth Control to the South Indian Science
        Association at the Central College in Bangalore, India. Sastra Vaidya Pravine, and S. Subba
        Rao presided. A summary was published as "Birth Control," The Hindu, Jan. 18, 1936. <index
            level1="birth control" level2="international"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="birth control in"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Birth Control</head>
        <byline>Mrs. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger</person>'s Address at <place
                reg="Bangalore, India">Bangalore</place></byline>
        <dateline>Jan. 16 <date value="1936-01-16 "/>Bangalore<place/></dateline>
        <p> “To you in <place>India</place> who have given to the world marvelous temples that have
            been built by your great men in the past and handed on to use (westerners) to admire-
            and we do admire them- the time is now come to make another kind of temple, the ‘human
            temple’ and the ‘human body.’ Let us begin to make our bodies fit and perfect
            instruments to house that soul that we may summon to take its place in the mystery of
            human beings.”</p>
        <p><supplied resp="MSPP"> [Parts of this article that were not related to Margaret Sanger
                were omitted]</supplied></p>
        <q who="HINDU"><p> Mrs. Margaret Sanger said that birth control was the key-not of a new
                moral and spiritual awakening. It was not only a health or economic expedient. It
                was a moral and social principle. That principle was interlocked with the spiritual
                advancement of nations and with the race as well. </p></q>
        <q who="HINDU"><p> Many British Bishops and clergymen, Mrs. Sanger said, had been pleading
                for some time past that the members of the Christian faith should come forth and
                lead the movement so that it might be a constructive force in civilization and not
                to close their eyes and ears to its human appeal. </p></q>
    </docBody>
</doc>
