<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2013/12/04 JK encoded</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-08-21 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1932-11-15">15 Nov 1932</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Speech to Penn State Forum</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421052</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Margaret Sanger Addresses Forum</title>, <title
                    type="journal">Penn State Collegian</title>, Nov. 18, 1932, 1 </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="PSC">Penn State Collegian</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Sanger's speech was not found, but two articles in the Penn State
            Collegian, "<title type="article">Margaret Sanger Addresses Forum</title>," and "<title
                type="article">Solve Europe's Problem or War Will Result, Sanger Says</title>."
                <title type="journal">Penn State Collegian</title>, Nov. 18,1932, included
            excerpts</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="class-based"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="and war"/>
        <index level1="Italy" level2="overpopulation and"/>
        <index level1="Europe" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="consequences on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="American"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person> Addresses Forum</head>
        <head type="sub">Speaker at First Meeting Cites Definite Reason for Birth Control
            Practice</head>
        <p>“Birth control is not a panacea for all the social and economic ills in the world but at
            least it is the most important immediate help which can be applied as a solution the
            present problems of millions of men and women here and now,” <q who="PSC">Mrs. Margaret
                Sanger said at the opening Forum of the year in the Auditorium Tuesday night.
                Contraception, she believes, should be used in the case of communicable diseases,
                where the mother is physically weak and incapable of bearing children, and where
                parents produce sub-normal offspring. The practice is also valuable in the spacing
                of children in a family, protecting adolescent married couples from having children
                too soon, and also in the case of poverty stricken parents.</q> “Birth control will
            give women a chance to develop and to express themselves; it will, above all, mean
            happier marriages,” Mrs. Sanger stated. “Instead of the customary single child in
            families of higher classes, and ten or eleven in the poorer classes, birth control will
            usher in a new era of families with three or four children. This will constitute the
            American family of the future,” the speaker believes. <q who="PSC">Mrs. Sanger left the
                    <place reg="Penn State University">College</place> yesterday afternoon. In
                addition to her open lecture, she addressed a women’s club meeting Tuesday
                night.</q> “<place>Europe</place>’s over-population problem is sizzling now; in five
            or six years something is going to explode!” “Already <place>Italy</place> has its eye
            on several choice pieces of territory. And when its congested mass of humanity is so
            much in excess that it reaches the brim and overflows, we shall have a war.” <q
                who="PSC">She paused and then added crisply,</q> “This is as inevitable as was the
            outbreak in 1914.” “Population must be controlled. Unless it is limited or some system
            of distribution worked out the nations of the world might just as well throw all their
            peace treaties to the winds,” Mrs. Sanger said. “Peace will never be achieved until this
            problem is solved; that’s why the birth control question has become not only of family
            importance but of international significance.” “Fortunately, statesmen are beginning to
            acquire some concept of the importance of the ever-populated plight of many countries.”
            “They must have some outlets for these increasing internal numbers, and they’re
            resorting to invasion to find them,” she said. “After all, no matter how hard we fight,
            birth control will come. It’s just a matter of how soon.” </p>


    </docBody>
</doc>
