<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Interview">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2013/11/13 JK encoded</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-08-21 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-12-15 CH proof and enter tags</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1917-04-21">
            <supplied resp="MSPP">21 Apr 1917</supplied>
        </docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>
                <supplied resp="MSPP">Chicago Interview</supplied>
            </titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421005</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">"Birth Control Clinic Here, Sanger Plan</title>,"<title
                    type="journal">Chicago Daily Tribune</title>, Apr. 22, 1917, 9. </bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="CDT">Chicago Daily Tribune</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>After her release from prison for the Brownsvlle Clinic, Sanger announced plans to make
            Chicago the national headquarters for birth control movement. </p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues" level3="in US"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="in Chicago"/>
        <index level1="jails and imprisonment"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <div>
            <head>Birth Control Clinic Here, Sanger Plan </head>
            <head type="sub"> Leader May Make Chicago Headquarters for Movement. </head>

            <p>
                <q who="CDT">Mrs. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>, birth
                    control advocate, who recently spent thirty days in a <place reg="New York, NY">New York</place>
                    jail for disseminating forbidden literature, is seriously considering
                    establishing a birth control clinic in the stockyard district and making <place
                        reg="Chicago, IL">Chicago</place> the national headquarters for the birth
                    control propaganda throughout the <place>United States</place>. She arrived here
                    yesterday and found already 200 letters from Chicagoans asking for the
                    information which she is ready to give. </q> “Chicago, it seems, more than any
                other city wants this information,” said Mrs. Sanger. “The deeply appealing human
                need expressed in these letters is one of the most touching things I have ever
                known. And there are so many letters. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Chicago the Logical Place. </head>

            <p> “I feel that Chicago is the logical headquarters because Chicago is the most
                democratic city I know, and this is distinctly a democratic movement. There is a
                great opposition to having New York the center, for birth control is considered a
                pink tea movement there, since so many society women have ‘taken it up.’ The people
                naturally do not want it to be placed in the hands of women with lorgnettes, who
                will make it an affair of class and will ask so many questions before they are
                willing to give out the information that it will be too late to do any good.” <q
                    who="CDT"> Mrs. Sanger, herself the mother of two boys, considers birth control
                    the only real propaganda for patriotism and preparedness. </q></p>
        </div>

        <div>
            <head type="sub">Stock-Taking in Nation.</head>
            <p> “If conscription goes through,” she said, “We shall have a stock-taking of our
                national fitness, and get some statistics which will be rather startling, I fancy.
                How long will it be before we realize the necessity for bearing only those children
                who can properly be supported, instead of continuing as we are now doing, producing
                families of degenerates, who are of no use to themselves or any one else. If people
                will only realize that I do not preach abortion they would accept the idea, I am
                sure . “This distinction is to be the subject of my Sunday afternoon lecture.” <q
                    who="CDT"> In addition to this afternoon’s lecture at the Strand theater there
                    will be another talk in the evening, and a lecture on Tuesday afternoon, which
                    both men and women will attend. <person reg="Bemis, Anna">Mrs. Edward Bemis
                    </person> of 4818 Sheridan Road will introduce Mrs. Sanger.</q></p>
        </div>

    </docBody>
</doc>
