<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Interview">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/02/07 YG</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/02/11 CH proof tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-11-11 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1936-02-14">14 Feb 1936</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Interview with <title type="journal">Singapore Straits
                Times</title></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421087</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">"Continence or Science in Birth Control"</title>, <title
                    type="journal">the Singapore Straits Times</title>, Feb. 14, 1936, p.12</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="SST">Singapore Strait Times</name>
            <name id="TAGRA">Tagore, Rabindranath</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="Asia" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="war" level2="overpopulation and"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="birth control in"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>CONTINENCE OR SCIENCE IN BIRTH CONTROL</head>
        <head type="sub"><person reg="Gandhi, Mohandas K.">Gandhi's</person> Views Conflict with
                <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Mrs. Sanger's</person></head>
        <head type="sub">ADVICE TO <place reg="British Malaya">MALAYA</place>ON PRESSURE OF
            POPULATIONS</head>
        <div>
            <q who="SST">
                <p>Standing room only on <place reg="Singapore">Singapore Island</place> will result
                    if the birth rate and Indian and Chinese migration continue as at present.</p>
                <p>Continence between married people is difficult enough anywhere, and certainly far
                    too difficult in <place>India</place>.</p>
                <p>Birth control will succeed in the East. </p>
                <p>Present day national aggression is a result of uncontrolled birth rates.</p>
                <p>These are some of the views expressed by Mrs. Margaret Sanger, the world famous
                    authority on birth control, when she arrived in Singapore in the <name
                        type="boat">Corfu</name>yesterday.</p></q>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">“Women Will Be With Me”</head>
            <p><q who="SST"> Mrs. Sanger, who has been visiting India, and is going on to
                        <place>China</place>, said that unless something was done to check
                    uncontrolled births, Malaya would have the same population problem as India,
                    China, and <place>Japan</place>. </q>“Under the crushing pressure of
                populations, the Eastern countries will go back to barbarism,” she said. </p>
            <p><q who="SST">If birth control was not introduced scientifically in Malaya, Mrs.
                    Sanger said, Malayans would have to lower their standard of living. The
                    important step of establishing scientific birth control should be taken by the
                    public health authorities because it was an essential part of public health
                    work. </q></p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Continence or Science?</head>
            <p><q who="SST">Mrs. Sanger disclosed to the <title type="journal">Straits Times</title>
                    her recent discussion with Gandhi on birth control in India. She said that
                    Gandhi had made more occasions than ever before.</q></p>
            <p>"Gandhi agreed with me that the population of India must be controlled,” Mrs. Sanger
                said.“He also though that the women must do the job, and that families should be
                regulated according to income and health. </p>
            <p>“We disagreed however, on the methods of birth control. </p>
            <p>“I wanted to base birth control on medical science, Gandhi wanted continence. </p>
            <p>“Continence between married people is difficult enough anywhere and certainly far too
                difficult in India. </p>
            <p>“Gandhi’s idea was that the women would co-operate and resist the attentions of the
                men. I could not share that view. </p>
            <p>“Gandhi told me he was a practical idealist. I told him that I was a practical
                scientist.”</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Gandhi and Divorce</head>
            <p><q who="SST"> Mrs. Sanger said that she had asked Gandhi what he considered was a
                    practical solution, knowing that all Indian women were less equipped
                    economically and socially to go out into the world. He had replied that Indian
                    women could have divorce laws. </q></p>
            <p>“I told him that this all sounded rather chaotic to me,” she said. “I claimed that
                the Indian men would be on my side. </p>
            <p>“We have yet to find out whether the women will be on Gandhi’s side.”</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Religion, Ignorance, Inertia</head>
            <p><q who="SST"> Mrs. Sanger said that Indian women were aroused to the importance of
                    birth control. There were only two things that could be done to relieve India’s
                    population crisis--let the people die by withdrawing safeguards against cholera
                    and smallpox epidemics, or lower the birth rate. Surely the second course would
                    be preferable to the nation. </q></p>
            <p><q who="SST"> The population of India had increased by 34 millions in the last 10
                    years. At that rate the population would be doubled in 40 years. If something
                    was not done immediately the nation would return to barbarism. </q></p>
            <p><q who="SST">Religion, ignorance and inertia were the three reasons for this.
                </q></p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Control in China</head>
            <p><q who="SST">Mrs. Sanger thinks that the campaign for birth control will eventually
                    succeed in the East. It would take 10 years to get it started, however.</q></p>
            <p><q who="SST">When she goes to China, Mrs. Sanger hopes to establish more birth
                    control centers, and to arrange for proper health instruction for the men and
                    women of China.</q></p>
            <p><q who="SST">Mrs. Sanger gave a lecture to members of <org
                        reg="Young Women's Christian Association">the Y.W.C.A.</org> at Raffles Quay
                    this morning. </q></p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">“A Cause of Aggression.”</head>
            <head type="sub">Uncontrolled Birth-Rate</head>
            <head type="sub">Mrs. Sanger’s Views</head>
            <p><q who="SST">Referring to appeals by <person reg="Mussolini, Benito"
                        >Mussolini</person> and <person reg="Hitler, Adolf">Hitler</person> for more
                    children, Mrs. Margaret Sanger, the authority on birth control, who arrived in
                    Singapore yesterday, said that when a nation with a small area had a high
                    birth-rate and overpopulation, it means one of three things:</q></p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <p rend="blockquote"><q who="SST">Lowering the standard of living, which led to
                    revolution and civil war; Scientific control of the birth-rate, or Extension
                    into a neighbor’s territory </q></p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <p><q who="SST"><place reg="Italy">Italy</place> and <place reg="Germany"
                        >Germany</place>, the two countries in the West with high birth-rates and
                    over-population were contemplating expansion into other nation’s territories. In
                    the East, India and China had lowered their standard of living. Japan was
                    apparently contemplating the same solution as Italy and Germany. </q></p>
            <p><q who="SST">An uncontrolled birth-rate was, therefore, a cause of
                aggression.</q></p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">India’s Tragedy</head>
            <p><q who="SST">Mrs. Sanger said that in India the population had increased by 34
                    millions in the last 10 years. At this rate the present population of India
                    would be doubled in about 40 years, which would create an impossible position.
                    There was no accommodation for extra population. </q></p>
            <p><q who="SST">On top of this, the death rate was decreasing. Many lives that were
                    previously lost by cholera, small-pox and bad food and water were being saved by
                    modern hygiene. </q></p>
            <p><q who="SST">The maternal welfare centres had also saved the lives of many mothers
                    and babies in the last seven years. </q></p>
            <p><q who="SST">Mrs. Sanger said that scientific birth control methods were gradually
                    spreading from the West to the East. </q></p>
            <p><q who="SST">Born of Irish-American parents in <place reg="Corning, NY">Corning, New
                        York</place>, it was the conditions Mrs. Sanger met as a nurse among the
                    East Side poor in <place reg="New York, NY">New York City</place> that drove her
                    to dedicate her life to securing for women the right to scientific birth control
                    information.</q></p>
            <p><q who="SST">She has carried her message throughout the length and breadth of the
                        <place reg="United States">United States</place>, to <place reg="Canada"
                        >Canada</place>, <place reg="England">England</place>, <place
                        reg="Soviet Union">Russia</place>, China, and Japan. She has organized birth
                    control leagues, clinics, and conferences, national and international.
                    Denounced, persecuted, and jailed, she never wavered, and today she is
                    recognized as the world leader of the birth control movement. </q></p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Biological Revolutionary</head>
            <p><q who="SST"><person reg="Shaw, George Bernard">Bernard Shaw</person> has called
                    birth control the most revolutionary discovery of the past century. <person
                        reg="Wells, H.G.">H. G. Wells</person> says that Margaret Sanger is the
                    greatest biological revolutionary the world has ever known. </q></p>
            <p><q who="SST">In <place reg="United States">America</place>, through the <org>National
                        Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control</org>, of which she is
                    president, she is attempting to secure amendments to the Federal laws which
                    prohibit the sending of contraceptive information and supplies through the
                    mails, by express, or other common carriers. </q></p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Letter from <person reg="Tagra">Tagore</person></head>
            <p><q who="SST">Mrs. Sanger said that leaders of thought in India were supporting her in
                    the movement for scientific birth control. As evidence of this she had just
                    received the following letter from <person reg="Tagore, Rabindranath"
                        >Rabindranath Tagore</person>, the great Indian poet:</q></p>
            <p><q who="TAGRA">“Dear Margaret Sanger-- I am of opinion that the birth control
                    movement is a great movement not only because it will save women from enforced
                    and undesirable maternity, but because it will help the cause of peace by
                    lessening the number of surplus population of a country, scrambling for food and
                    space outside its own rightful limits.”</q></p>
        </div>
    </docBody>

</doc>
