<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published statement">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/03/07 YG initial tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-14 CH proof tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-26 JK correct tags</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1936-05-14">14 May 1946</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Statement on the American Medical
                    Association</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421082</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Regulation of Families Seen as
                    Possibility</title>, <title type="journal">Jefferson City
                    Post-Tribune</title>, May 14, 1936</bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="JCPT">Jefferson City Post-Tribune</name>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">This is a summary of <person reg="Sanger, Margaret"
            >Sanger</person>'s press conference in <place>Washington, DC</place>
        on May 14, 1936, published in the <place reg="Jefferson City, MO"
            >Jefferson City</place> Post-Tribune as "Regulations of Family Seen
        as Possibility" 5/14/36 p. 2 <index level1="birth control"
            level2="medical community and"/>
        <index level1="American Medical Association"/>
        <index level1="birth control methods" level2="rice-based"/>
    </headNote>

    <docBody>
        <head>REGULATION OF FAMILIES SEEN AS POSSIBILITY</head>
        <head type="sub"><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret
            Sanger</person>, Birth Control Advocate, Reports Discovery That Will
            Simplify Problem</head>
        <dateline>May 14, 1936 <date value="1936-05-14"/>
            <place/></dateline>
        <div>
            <q who="JCPT"><p>Mrs. Margaret Sanger returned from a tour of
                        <place>Asia</place> today with a new formula for
                    regulating the size of families for 25 cents a year.</p>
                <p>Mrs. Sanger hopes the formula eventually will be the answer
                    to present bans against disseminating birth control
                    information.</p>
                <p>It may also, she said, be “the answer to the social workers’
                    prayers,” and to refusal of the <org>American Medical
                        Association</org> to help change the laws. </p></q>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Keeps Formula Secret</head>
            <p> “I have tried for 20 years to corral people into their doctors’
                offices to learn about birth control because as a trained nurse
                I have always believed that birth control is individual and that
                each woman should consult her physician on her own needs,” <q
                    who="JCPT">Mrs.Sanger Said.</q></p>
            <p><q who="JCPT">If the doctors refuse to see that present laws
                    force people to consult “bootleggers” of birth control
                    information then they must expect people to go elsewhere,
                    Mrs. Sanger said.</q></p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Assails A.M.A.</head>
            <p>“The doctors who made that report possibly have adequate
                information for their private practice,” she said. “Their
                patients can get advice and equipment. They probably have not
                seen enough of the poor in hospitals. If the medical profession
                had met its responsibilities in this respect, the A.M.A.
                committee could not complain that the educated class is not
                producing itself while the poorer classes are over-producing. </p>
            <p> When the A.M.A. committee says there is no evidence that present
                laws, federal or state, have interfered with “any medical advice
                which a physician has felt called upon to furnish his patients,”
                they should remember that within two years, two doctors and two
                nurses in the New York birth control clinic were arrested, and
                that last week in Washington, the scientific contraceptive
                exhibit of the <org>District of Columbia Medical
                    Association</org> was stopped," Mrs. Sanger said. </p>

        </div>




    </docBody>
</doc>
