<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="(Published Speech) ">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/04/04 YG</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="(1935-01-07) ">07 Jan 1935</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>The Birth Control Movement</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421099</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="speech">"Birth Control"</title>
                <title type="journal">Justice</title></bibl>
            <bibl><title>MSM</title></bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="J">Justice</name>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="birth control" level2="morality of"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="overpopulation and"/>
        <index level1="Gandhi, Mohandas K."/> 
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>"Birth Control"</head>
        <head type="sub">Mrs. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>'s Lecture At <place reg="Adyar, India">Adyar</place></head>
        <div>
            <p><q who="J">Mrs. Margaret Sanger, delivered an address on “the
            birth control movement,” at Adyar on Tuesday afternoon. </q></p>
            <p><q who="J">Mrs. Sanger defined birth control as </q>“the conscious control
                of the birth rate by means that prevent the conception of life.”
                    <q who="J">Birth control did not mean the taking of life
                    even in its most latent germ state, but the prevention of
                    the union of germ and sperm. Control did not mean a birth
                    rate falling below a standard necessary to preserve a
                    healthy and prosperous nation, but the regulation of the
                    number of children in any given family to that which could
                    be properly educated and given the care due to every child.
                    Mrs. Sanger averred that in many of the birth control
                    clinics childless couples are given special consideration in
                    an endeavor to solve also this unhappy situation.</q> </p>
                <p>“To me,” <q who="J">said Mrs. Sanger</q>, “the word ‘conscious’ is one of
                the most important things in the whole movement. No longer shall
                the race be brought into being through the recklessness or the
                abandonment of the movement, but the child shall come
                considered, planned for, wanted, and loved. It is the right of
                every child to come as in invited guest.” </p>
                <p><q who="J">Mrs. Sanger also
                    referred to the sufferings of the poor who in sickness,
                    disease, and poverty, still went on bringing unwanted
                    children into squalid misery. She revealed the gripping fear
                    of women who faced unwanted pregnancies. Always, she said,
                    birth control had been known and practiced by the educated
                    classes but the information had not been at the disposal of
                    the poor. She traced the history of the practice of
                    infanticide and showed that coincident with the knowledge of
                    abortion, this practice disappeared, and in the lecturer’s
                    opinion, the tremendous evils of widespread abortion
                    existent at the present time would not be done away with
                    until birth control information was available to those who
                    needed it. </q></p>
            <p> <q who="J">She then dealt with the two great objections to
                    the idea of birth control: First, that it might be injurious
                    to woman. Second, that it would be conducive to an increase
                    of immorality. Answering the former objection, she quoted
                    statistics from <place>Holland</place>where such information had been
                    disseminated for over 44 years. The infant and maternal
                    mortality rate had been greatly lowered and conditions in
                    family life much improved. </q></p>
        </div>

        <div>
            <head type="sub">Question of Immorality</head>
            <p><q who="J">Discussing the question of an increase of immorality, Mrs. Sanger
                said: </q>“I refuse to accept the theory that morality or immorality
                comes from outside forces. It is an individual matter. One might
                as well say the automobile, good roads, good hotels, etc. are
                causes of immorality as birth control.” <q who="J">She boldly declared: </q>
                "If two people are going to be illicit and immoral, they have a
                right only to injure themselves-not bring an innocent child into
                a world which at present has no place for the illegitimate
                child.” </p>
            <p><q who="J">All authorities at the present time, were agreed that
                birth control was a necessity. In an interview with <person reg="Gandhi, Mohandas">Mahatma
                Gandhi</person>, Mrs. Sanger stated he quite agreed with her as to the
                necessity of women being freed from this bondage. Mr. Gandhi
                believed that continence was the only answer and that women
                should resist men to enforce it. Mrs. Sanger expressed herself
                in utter sympathy with the idea of continence though doubting
                the feasibility of resistence. However, she did not believe
                continence was a practical solution for those who are not yet
                evolved sufficiently to sublimate te sex urge through creative
                mental or artistic activity. She cited instances where much harm
                was done through enforced continence in the case of the less
                spiritually cultured people. </q></p>
                <p>“The whole relationship of parents
                and children, of husband and wife, changes with birth control
                knowledge was available and the husband’s economic fears are
                removed,” <q who="J">concluded Mrs. Sanger. </q>"Husband and wife become
                friends, pals; mothers have freedom to know and help their
                children. I believe birth control is the key-note of our social
                awakening and interlocked with the spiritual advances of the
                women of the race. Our physical sight came to us in the
                evolution of the race and so education became possible. I
                believe that our spiritual sight will come to us as we move
                upwards and onwards into that current of life where we become
                conscious of our acts and responsibilities, and most of all of
                that greatest responsibility of passing on the gift of life. Let
                us see that it is passed on in a body fir and perfect as an
                instrument for the service of the soul that we may summon to
                take its place in the mystery of natural being.”</p>
        </div>


    </docBody>
</doc>
