<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech ">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-04-09 JK initial tags</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1935-11-01 ">01 Nov 1935</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Statement on Happy
                    Marriages</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421081</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Secrets of Happy Marriage</title><title
                    type="journal">Times of India</title>, Nov. 12, 1935, p.
                6.</bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="ToI">Times of India</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">This is an excerpt from an interview with the <title
            type="journal">Times of India</title>, published as "<title
            type="journal">Secrets of Happy Marriage</title>," <title
            type="journal">Times of India</title>, Nov. 12, 1935, p.6. <index
            level1="birth control clinics and leagues" level2="in India"/><index
            level1="India" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="population policies of"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="overpopulation and"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="women in"/><index level1="India"
            level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="birth control movement in"/><index
            level1="All-India Women's Conference"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Secrets of Happy Marriage</head>
        <head type="sub">Mrs. M. Sanger on Birth Control</head>

        <dateline>
            <date value="/----/-11-01"/>November 1, <place reg="London, England"
                >London</place></dateline>
        <q who="ToI">
            <p>To tell the world some secrets of a happy marriage is the object
                of the tour of thousands of miles, which is being made by Mrs.
                Margaret Sanger, President of the <org>Birth Control
                    International Information Centre</org>, one of the best
                known women of <place reg="United States">America</place>. She
                will be the guest of the <person reg="Ali, Shareefah Hamid"
                    >chairman</person> of the <org>All-India Women’s
                    Conference</org>. </p>
            <p>She told your correspondent why it is often wise to marry early -
                at 18 or 19. She believes that the only child is a tragedy,
                especially for the child. An interval of three years between
                each child she found ideal.</p></q>
        <p> “It is best if young people are encouraged to marry early, but to
            take time before they being to have children,” she said. “In the
            first place they should get acquainted with the plan of that
            adjustment, which is so important in a marriage. I am quite certain
            of one thing - these early marriages and the adjustment period will
            reduce the enormous number of divorces in America. I wonder if
            economists have never realised the good thing young marriages are
            for industry. They mean more suited furniture bought, more radio
            sets and baby-carriages etc.”</p>
        <q who="ToI">
            <p> She added that she was not going to <place>India </place>to
                persuade everyone to have a small family, but rather to convince
                the people of the desirability of having families of the right
                size and of the right quality.</p>
            <p> She argues that, although birth control may not solve population
                problems, it does contribute to the health, happiness and mental
                poise of an individual and families.</p></q>
    </docBody>
</doc>
