<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="(Published article) ">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/04/09 VS initial tagging</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="(1929-12-14) ">14 December, 1929</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Lecture to Cleveland City Club</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421077</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Cleveland Plain-Dealer</title></bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="CDP">Cleveland Plain-Dealer</name>
            <name id="WITPE">Witt, Peter</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
            <name id="THOJO">Thomas, John J.</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">No draft version found. <index level1="birth control"
            level2="distribution of information about"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="economic benefits and risks of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="physical justifications for"/>
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Federal"/>
        <index level1="family size" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="&quot;feeble-minded&quot; persons" level2="allowed to reproduce"/>
        <index level1="Great Depression"/>
        <index level1="mentally disabled and diseased" level2="birth control and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>City Club Stirred By Mrs. Sanger</head>
        <byline>Questions Fly Fast: Vote of Confidence Urged, but Fails.</byline>
        <div>
            <q who="CPD"><p> Mrs. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>’s lecture
                    on birth control at the <org reg="City Club of Cleveland">City Club</org>
                    yesterday so moved an Episcopal minister, Rev. <person reg="Hauck, Franklin E."
                        >Franklin E. Hauck</person> of <place reg="Bellevue, OH">Bellevue,
                        O.</place>, a club member, that he submitted a motion that the club indorse
                    Mrs. Sanger’s program for revision of the federal statutes to make legal the
                    distribution of information on birth control. </p></q>
            <p>
                <q who="CPD">Dr. <person reg="Thomas, John J.">J. J. Thomas</person>, president of
                    the club, said the motion would not come to a vote and went on with the question
                    and answer session which followed the lecture. Another club member, however,
                    shouted that those present should at least vote that</q> “<q who="UNK">it is the
                    sense of the club that Mrs. Sanger’s program should be adopted</q>.”</p>
            <p>
                <q who="CPD">Dr. Thomas said</q> “<q who="THOJO">No!</q>” <q who="CPD">and banged
                    his gavel</q>. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> 85,000,000 Child Minds</head>
            <q who="CPD"><p> Mrs. Sanger, in opening her lecture, said that, according to available
                    statistics, 85,000,000 of the 105,000,000 people in the <place>United
                        States</place> have the mentality of a fifteen-year-old child. There are
                    45,000,000 feeble-minded persons in the country, she said, and the upper group
                    capable of raising and properly caring for intelligent children numbers only
                    30,000,000. </p></q>
            <q who="CPD"><p> She argued that the feeble minded and those who compose the lower group
                    should be compelled to practice birth control, and that in some cases an
                    operation to prevent conception should be resorted to. </p></q>
            <p> “<q who="UNK">Do you think that we have progressed far enough in the science of
                    psychology so that the official body which would pass on who should have
                    children and who should not, according to your theories, knows enough to say who
                    is feeble minded and who is not?</q>”<q who="CPD"> a questioner asked</q>. </p>
            <p> “<q who="WITPE">How do you know that there are 45,000,000 feeble minded?</q>” <q
                    who="CPD">Peter Witt shouted</q>. “<q who="WITPE">Is that the vote <person
                        reg="Hoover, Herbert">Hoover</person> got in <place>North
                    Carolina</place>?</q>”</p>
            <p> “I’m not sure there are 45,000,000 people in North Carolina,” <q who="CPD">Mrs.
                    Sanger replied</q>,” However, all my figures are contained in a report made by
                Prof. <person reg="Myers, William Starr">William Starr Meyer</person> of
                    <org>Princeton University</org>. I think they’re correct, but if you have any
                fault to find with them, consult the professor.” </p>
            <p> “<q who="UNK">Do you think that the 85,000,000 you spoke of should submit to an
                    operation?</q>” <q who="CPD">another questioner asked</q>. </p>
            <p>
                <q who="CPD">Mrs. Sanger said</q>, “No.”</p>
            <p> “Birth control,” <q who="CPD">Mrs. Sanger said,</q> “means that children come into
                the world from choice and not by chance. She described it as “the keynote of a new
                social and moral awakening.”</p>
            <p> “Population can be controlled either by increasing the death rate or decreasing the
                birth rate,” <q who="CPD">she said.</q> “In the past population has been controlled
                by the former means. Now, with progress in surgery and the exercise of humanitarian
                principles, the death rate is being decreased. Yet population must be
                controlled-that is a necessity recognized by all students. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Economic Reasons</head>
            <p> “In the first place, there are economic reasons. Why should the 20,000,000 who are
                physically and mentally capable and who compose the upper group assume the burden of
                supporting the oftentimes mentally deficient offspring of the lower group? </p>
            <p> “If a mother is not physically fit to bear a child and the father is economically
                unable to support it, why should such a couple be permitted to have eight or ten
                children? Many of these children are death-doomed anyway. </p>
            <p> “In the lower group, there is no correlation between income and children. Thus, we
                have slums, ignorance, disease and child labor. We spend billions yearly to care for
                the poor families in the lower group. Why not get at the heart of things and spend a
                good deal less money wisely? </p>
            <p> “<name reg="United States Penal Code">Federal law</name>, passed 53 years ago,
                prohibits use of the mails to disseminate information on birth control, but federal
                law does not interfere with the practices of animal breeding in which only the
                wholesome stock is permitted to increase. </p>
            <p> “On the other hand, federal law limits the number of aliens into the country. They
                must be physically and morally sound and must have a certain amount of capital so
                that they will not become public charges. </p>
            <p> “Why shouldn’t the same principles apply in the rearing of families?</p>
            <p> “We are working to disseminate knowledge to prevent families having children where
                they don’t want them-- where the children might be mentally deficient or sub-normal
                or where there is no support for them. </p>
            <p> “We believe that children should not come except at spaces of two to three years and
                that the young wife between 18 and 22 should not have children until she has passed
                the adolescent stage. Also a young couple should have at least two years to adjust
                themselves to each other and establish a harmonious home.”</p>
            <q who="CPD"><p> Dissemination of knowledge, she said, would have no effect on morals. A
                    man chooses his course of action no more wisely when he is in ignorance.
                </p></q>
            <p>
                <q who="CPD">In reference to determining the feeble minded in a community, Dr.
                    Thomas asked if Mrs. Sanger meant the <org reg="Cleveland City Council">City
                        Council</org> should be the determining group. She said,</q> “no.”</p>
            <q who="CPD"><p> Another questioner asked if the practice of birth control in poor
                    families might not result in “geniuses not being born” since statistics indicate
                    that the sixth or eight child in many cases is a genius. </p></q>
            <p> “<person reg="Caruso, Enrico">Caruso</person> was a genius-- he had a freak throat,
                a really abnormal throat,” <q who="CPD">Mrs. Sanger replied.</q> “Anyway, are we
                going to develop geniuses in that way? How do we know how many geniuses we have in
                any community today who have never been developed because they haven’t the economic
                chance?”</p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
