<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-02-13 JC encoding</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person>Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1924-06-00">June 1924</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>MARGARET SANGER'S OWN CORNER</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp421010</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title>Birth Control Review</title>, June 1924, pg. 181</bibl>

		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="BCR">Birth Control Review</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>Under this column name, the <title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title> published
			letters written to Margaret Sanger with occasional commentary. For others in this series
			see Margaret Sanger's Own Corner, <xref from="421032.xml">Jan. 1924</xref>, <xref
				from="421033.xml">Feb. 1924</xref>, <xref from="301463.xml">Mar. 1924</xref>, and
				<xref from="421034.xml">Apr. 1924</xref>
			<xref from="421009.xml">May 1924</xref>.</p>
		<index level1="abortion" level2="birth control and"/>
		<index level1="abortion" level2="health risks"/>
		<index level1="abortion" level2="MS on"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>MARGARET SANGER'S OWN CORNER</head>


		<p><q who="BCR"><emph rend="italics">A Correspondent writes</emph> "Do you think it is wrong
				to bring myself around when I am not yet three months overtime?</q></p>
		<p><emph rend="italics">Answer</emph> When you use the term "bring myself around," you are
			referring to abortion. I believe that repeated abortions, however early they are brought
			on, have a very bad effect on a woman's health. I do not advise it even by skilled
			hands, unless it has been recommended by your physician. I strongly advise you against
			taking drugs for any such purpose. Drugs are frequently useless and always injurious.
			They injure the mother and if they fail of their purpose, as they often do, they are apt
			to injure the child. The practice of abortion gets you nowhere, for pregnancy comes
			again more easily after abortion than before, and it becomes necessary to go through it
			all again. Abortion is not the right means of controlling the size of your family. One
			of the strong reasons for urging Birth Control is that the scientific prevention of
			conception makes abortion unnecessary, and will thus do away with this evil thing.</p>
		<p>M S</p>
		<p/>
	</docBody>
</doc>
