<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-01-08 CH transcribe and encode</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-21 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Martin, M. J.">M. J. Martin</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1924-02-00">Feb 1924</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>Margaret Sanger's Own Corner</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp421033</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title>, Feb. 1924, p. 43</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="BCR">Birth Control Review</name>
			<name id="MARMJ">Martin, M. J.</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>Under this column name, the <title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title> published
			letters written to Margaret Sanger with occasional commentary. For others in this series
			see Margaret Sanger's Own Corner, <xref from="421032.xml">Jan. 1924</xref>, <xref
				from="301463.xml">Mar. 1924</xref>, <xref from="421034.xml">Apr. 1924</xref>
			<xref from="421009.xml">May 1924</xref>, and <xref from="421010.xml">June
			1924</xref>.</p>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="morality of"/>
		<index level1="birth control” level2=”opposition to"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="neo-Malthusian arguments for"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="religion and"/>
		<index level1="food supply"/>
		<index level1="population growth" level2="natural resources and"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Margaret Sanger's Own Corner</head>
		<div type="section">
			<p rend="italics">
				<q who="BCR">This time we give in full the letter of our correspondent along with
					our answer to it.</q>
			</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<q who="MARMJ"><salute>Dear Madam,</salute></q>
			<p><q who="MARMJ">Pardon me for trespassing on your time but I feel so strongly in the
					matter of birth control that it is impressed deeply into my heart and soul. * *
					*</q></p>
			<p><q who="MARMJ">In one of your circulars, it is stated that the present social
					condition is carried on by beginning at the wrong end, that is, we are taking
					care of the unfortunates when we ought to prevent such unfortunates from coming
					into the world. You claim that we are forced to go to vast expense for all kinds
					of eleemosynary and penal institutions for those who ought never to have been
					allowed to come into being. It appears to me that the advocates of birth control
					are the ones who are working from the wrong end.</q></p>
			<p><q who="MARMJ">Some scientist whose name I can not recall said that if properly
					cultivated the state of <place>Texas</place> could raise sufficient food for the
					whole world. Another in speaking of the financial state of
						<place>Germany</place> said that if that country were rightly managed they
					could pay off the whole indemnity and grow rich at the same time. These may be
					foolish estimates but we all know that agriculure and all our resources have
					barely given a small sample of what there is stored away for man's use just
					below the surface of the earth.</q></p>
			<p><q who="MARMJ">Further than this, look at the vast sums of money spent in
					foolishness, sin and crime-- Candy, chewing gum, tobacco and alcohol. Then we
					ought to consider the wasted money in the great banquests and balls of the elite
					in all the large cities. Also we may observe the fabulous sums spent for basket
					ball, base ball, and foot ball.</q>
			</p>
			<p><q who="MARMJ">Most of the above enumerations will be upheld by many good people but
					the fact remains that these things do not contribute in any way to the
					upbuilding of a righteous nation, and they do not lessen the tendency of the
					human heart to rush into folly and transgression. If a portion of this wealth
					were employed in caring for those who come into the world under adverse
					circumstances much good could be done. Then more than all the above combined is
					spent for war and war materials. It appears to me that it would be far better
					for us to expend our energies in educating people to use their surplus means in
					charitable work rather than in educating them how to prevent the increase of
					population.</q></p>
			<p><q who="MARMJ">I will refrain from giving instances of astounding immorality among
					students in high schools, colleges and universities, as you have undoubtedly
					learned of these sad occurrences from the public journals and court records. And
					then the question arises before every thinking person, what would be the
					condition in these institutions, if the young people were posted on methods of
					prevention, for we surely can not imagine that these measures which are given to
					the married can be kept secret from the single.</q></p>
			<p><q who="MARMJ">If it were possible, we might put the question to ourselves as to what
					we would think if some legislative politicians or enthusiastic reformers had
					prevented our birth and thus deprived us of immortal life. It seems to me to be
					a great sin to prevent the coming into existence of a soul destined to
					everlasting life. The Father above gave man this wonderful power of peopling
					heaven and it appears to me that any tampering with this incomprehensible gift
					will be fraught with unknown dangers and poignant sorry.</q></p>
			<p><q who="MARMJ">The veiled object of the control of births is to allow perfect freedom
					in the exercise of our animal natures with no fear of the consequences. The
					passions that the Father designed us to curb so as to develop the soul are to be
					given free rein, and we are to enjoy to the full our lower propensities without
					let or hindrance. Not that this power of procreation is necessarily a low
					propoensity, but the overindulgence makes both man and woman fall below the
					beasts of the field, and what should be the culmination and crown of perfect
					human love is made but the groveling of hideous and brutal lust.</q></p>
			<p><q who="MARMJ">I hope that you will not consider this as in any manner personal but
					simply a very brief essay for all who are studying this extremely serious
					subject. I am nearing the close of a somewhat long and eventful life, and I do
					not wish to say or do anything to cause grief or unrest, but if possbile, I want
					to assist my fellow travelers to find that straight and narrow path, and point
					them to the <person reg="Jesus Christ">Man of Galilee</person> and show them
					that belief in Him as <name type="deity">God</name> manifest in the flesh
					constitutes the only Door opening into the glory-land where we may see the
					Saviour face to face.</q></p>
			<q who="MARMJ"><signed>M J MARTIN</signed></q>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<p>In his letter Dr Martin summarizes the objections commonly brought against Birth
				Control. It can hardly be said, however, that he fairly meets a single one of the
				many arguments that can be brought in its support.</p>
			<p>1 In his second paragraph he hints that the resources of the world are equal to any
				increase of population. In reply, we can quote <person reg="East, Edward Murray"
					>Professor East</person>, the best authority on food production and agricultural
				possibilities in the world. In "<title type="book"><rs
						reg="Mankind at the Crossroads">Mankind at the Crossways</rs></title>" (p
				153) Professor East attributes to "an editorial in the <title type="journal">N Y
					Tribune</title>" the remark quoted by Dr Martin concerning Texas, and adds "It
				is extraordinary, it is even somewhat amusing, that there should be persons without
				the slightest knowledge of the trend of population or the possibilities of
				agriculture, who will write thus, but it is also serious." It is serious when a man
				so earnest and sincere as Dr Martin is taken in by such assertions. Professor East
				sets a maximum population of 5,200 millions as the limit of the world's capacity to
				feed, and adds that at the present rate of increase, this limit would be reached in
				little over a century. Surely it is time to consider the population questions
				seriously when children now being born may live to see the world so crowded that
				there will be room for no further expansion. </p>
			<p>2 The vast sums of money spent on foolish or unecessary things, such as chewing gum
				or candy cannot greatly affect the problems of population. They represent part of
				the energy of people, but chewing gum and candy are not inheritable diseases, and
				the habits do not affect the coming generation. As for basket ball, base ball and
				other games, these should be considered as part of the health activities of our
				young people. They certainly do contriubute to the welfare of the nation, and the
				building up of clean and healthy bodies and minds in the manhood of the country.</p>
			<p>Dr Martin is distressed at the waste of war, but does not realize that it is now
				pretty generally agreed that there is no more potent cause of war than the pressure
				of over-population.</p>
			<p>The old objection that knowledge must be kept from the people lest they abuse it for
				evil purposes, applied equally to the knowledge of reading and writing, as it does
				to a knowledge of the functioning of sex, and of methods of encouraging or checking
				reproduction. <place reg="United States">America</place> settled that point when the
				nation accepted universal education as the groundwork of her existence. </p>
			<p>Is it a sin to prevent the coming into existence of a soul destined for eternal life?
				Our opponents have never answered that question. If they assert that it is a sin,
				they should condemn celibacy, for any cause whatever, they should also condemn
				abstinence, and they should approve--or consistently should approve, illegitimacy,
				polygamy or any other sexual conduct that would result in more births. Does Dr
				Martin really believe that it is a sin and accept the consequences of such a belief?
				If not, how has he the right to decide that the soul may be prevented from being
				born by celibacy but not by Birth Conrol, especially as in many cases Birth Control
				may be inspired by higher and more unselfish motives than actuate the bachelor.</p>
			<p>The objects of the Birth Control movement are not veiled. We desire to remove fear of
				consequences as a motive for what is falsely called a "moral" conduct. True morality
				was never the result of fear. We assert this openly and with pride. Why should our
				sex powers, the powers wherein man comes nearest to the Divine, be denominated in
				our "animal nature." Please explain. </p>
			<closer>M S</closer>
		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
