<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="(Published article) ">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/04/04 VS initial tagging</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="(1934-12-04) ">4 Dec., 1934</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Interview with the El Paso Herald Post</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421060</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>El Paso Herald</title></bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="HERALD">El Paso Herald</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">Sanger gives an interview with the El Paso Herald, explaining the need for
        sterilization laws and education for students about birth contrl. <index
            level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"
            level3="negative consequences of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="in California"/>
        <index level1="sterilization" level2="benefits and risks of"/>
        <index level1="sterilization" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="sterilization" level2="in United State"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Sterilization Laws Are Emergency War Measures, Mrs. Sanger Says</head>
        <div>
            <p>
                <q who="HERALD">The sterilization law is an absolute emergency war measure against
                    conditions which we have no other way to fight, believes Mrs. Margaret Sanger,
                    who will be known in history as the first woman to fight fearlessly and
                    intelligently for birth control.</q>
            </p>
            <p> “I think California has the best law on sterilization and one that has been working
                over a period of five years,” <q who="HERALD">she said.</q> “It is one that can be
                followed with the greatest security for anyone who has fears of being taken
                advantage of. It goes hand in hand with an educational campaign for those who should
                be and are to be sterilized. Results are that there are more demands in California
                for sterilization by persons who are made to realize the benefit and why they should
                be, than can be met. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Future Debt</head>
            <p> “We have long substituted philanthropy and charity for recognition of evil to
                society. Now the demand for more and more charity has increased incompetency and
                piled up staggering debt future generations will have to pay, because of our
                short-sightedness in not following up laws which have been passed.”</p>
            <p>
                <q who="HERALD">The evil from parole of incompetents from prisons and institutions
                    is another question which people should take a stand against, Mrs. Sanger
                    believes</q>. </p>
            <p> “In most cases the officials are glad to get the inmates out of prisons or
                institutions, when the disease has been abated. Generally, those persons leave a
                child at home,” <q who="HERALD">she said.</q> “The institution takes no precaution
                against the increase of those persons’ progeny. </p>
            <p> “Sterilization is the only way to protect society from persons who have not the
                moral responsibility to practice birth control.”</p>
            <p>
                <q who="HERALD">The knowledge of sterilization has made a great change in the
                    acceptance of it, Mrs. Sanger maintains.</q>
            </p>
            <p> “It used to be thought the operation injured the individual. It is known now that
                the operation is a minor one with the man and though a larger one with the woman
                does not in any way affect the vital functions,” <q who="HERALD">she said.</q>
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Promiscuity </head>
            <p> “Certainly, they know more than their grandparents knew,” <q who="HERALD">she
                    said.</q> “But whether promiscuity and birth control are practiced generally
                among young people is a debatable one,” <q who="HERALD">she said.</q> “I believe
                when we find such conditions in one locality we are inclined to put the stamp on the
                country as a whole. I think when young people may have a smattering of knowledge and
                act and talk wisely, we jump to conclusions in assuming they know more than they do. </p>
            <p> “However, there are certain young girls in circles of the so-called better families
                who are accepted with the others today, whereas yesterday they ran in ‘separate
                herds’ and were known as ‘hussies’.” </p>
            <p>
                <q who="HERALD">An encouraging phase in the matter of birth control education is the
                    general information that is</q> "learned in the study of science and hygiene in
                schools today,” <q who="HERALD">Mrs. Sanger believes.</q>
            </p>
            <p> “You can’t teach boys and girls the danger of social diseases without giving a
                general idea of the ways to combat it,” <q who="HERALD">she said.</q>
            </p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
