<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="(Published article) ">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/04/11 VS initial tagging</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="(1929-11-15) ">15 November, 1929</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Buffalo Clinic Talk Suggests Plans for Clinic in Buffalo</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421036</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Buffalo Courier-Express</title></bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="BCE">Buffalo Courier-Express</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">Sanger was in Buffalo, NY on November 14, 1929 and had a meeting at Susan
        Fiske Rumsey's House. <index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="civilization and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="economic benefits and risks of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="population and"/>
        <index level1="birth control clinics and leagues" level2="in US"/>
        <index level1="Comstock, Anthony"/>
        <index level1="&quot;feeble-minded&quot; persons" level2="allowed to reproduce"/>
        <index level1="mentally disabled and diseased" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="overpopulation" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="population control" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="public health programs"/>
        <index level1="working classes" level2="living conditions of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Suggests Plans for Clinic in Buffalo</head>
        <byline>Interest shown; Mrs. Margaret Sanger tells of work of <org
                reg="National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control">legislation
                committee</org></byline>
        <q who="BCE"><p>
                <place reg="Buffalo, NY">Buffalo</place> will probably have a birth control clinic
                modeled after that in <place reg="New York, NY">New York City</place>, of which Mrs.
                    <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person> is the director. Great
                interest in the project was evinced yesterday afternoon following the talk given by
                Mrs. Sanger at the home of Mrs. <person reg="Rumsey, Margaret R.">Dexter P.
                    Rumsey</person> in <place>Delaware</place> avenue on the work of the committee
                for federal legislation on birth control, and Mrs. Sanger gave suggestions for the
                formation of such a clinic. She advised first the formation of a medical committee
                with a lay committee to sanction the work, and she estimated that $5,000 a year
                would cover the expense of the clinic. </p></q>
        <p>
            <q who="BCE">Mrs. Sanger, who has been called</q> “the stormy petrel of the birth
            control movement,” <q who="BCE">and who is famous for her conviction that the growth of
                the population should be legally controlled fairly covered the case for the birth
                control movement in this country.</q>
        </p>
        <q who="BCE"><p> At present she is working for a change in <name
                    reg="United States Penal Code">a law</name> passed by <org
                    reg="United States Congress">Congress</org> 56 years ago by which birth control
                information is classed with “obscene writings,” and can not be sent through the
                mails. </p></q>
        <p> “That well-meaning man, <person reg="Comstock, Anthony">Anthony Comstock</person>,
            backed the bill when it was passed, and I believe that if Comstock himself saw the sum
            total of misery and horror that law has caused he would wish to have it changed,”<q
                who="BCE"> Mrs. Sanger declared.</q>
        </p>
        <p> “Populations have always been controlled,” <q who="BCE">Mrs. Sanger said.</q> “In the
            earliest days they were controlled by the methods of nature, pestilence, famine, and
            war; later unwanted children were killed off or abandoned. Now we know that these
            methods are not the methods of civilization. </p>
        <p> “We hope that we’re through with wars. We’re doing everything to keep the unfit alive,
            and our civilization is seriously threatened. How far are we going to allow the unfit to
            increase, the insane to return to their homes on parole, with no protection to society
            against their bringing into the world demanded offspring? From these ranks we’re
            recruiting the future generations. </p>
        <p> “How philanthropic we are, and, to a certain extent what miserable results we are
            getting! Nine billions spent on diseased, defective, delinquent, and criminal! If we
            could use those nine billions on normal, fit children we could surpass anything <place
                reg="Rome, Italy">Rome</place> or <place>Greece</place> ever dreamed of.”</p>
        <p>
            <q who="BCE"> Mrs. Sanger pointed out that 90 percent of children who die in the first
                year of life die from causes due to poverty and neglect; she pointed out that,</q>
            “we are getting particular about the kind of people we are letting into <place
                reg="United States">this country</place>; the government has recognized that there
            must be a selective quota. </p>
        <p> “There is one class of people that has been controlling the size of the family, and
            there you see your best people today. In the other group you see every social problem
            entrenched, with all its hopelessness of life, inertia, and feeble-mindedness.</p>
        <p> “The better class of people will never be able to have larger families, and keep up
            their standards of living until you take the support of the other crowd off their
            backs.”</p>
        <q who="BCE"><p> Mrs. Sanger said that, while birth control clinics are legal under the
                state law, and may give instruction for the cure or prevention of disease, it is,
                under the federal law, illegal to send the address of the clinic through the mails.
            </p></q>
        <q who="BCE"><p> Among those who attended the lecture where Mrs. <person
                    reg="Gurney, Evelyn">Charles Gurney</person>, Mrs. <person reg="Hill, Dorothy"
                    >Ernest Hill</person>, Mrs. <person reg="Warren, Clara S.">William C.
                    Warren</person>, Mrs. <person reg="Schoellkopf, Virginia P.">Alfred
                    Schoellkopf</person>, Mrs. <person reg="Irwin, Jennie">Dudley Irwin</person>,
                Mrs. <person reg="Burgard, Jane">Henry P. Burgard</person>, Mrs. McGee Wyckoff, Mrs.
                    <person reg="Bass, Grace H.">Lyman Bass</person>, Mrs. <person
                    reg="Satterfield, Rachel P.">John Satterfield</person>, Mrs. <person
                    reg="White, Anna L. D.">Seymour White</person>, Mrs. <person reg="Smith, Mary"
                    >Carlton Smith</person>, Miss <person reg="Love, Maria">Maria Love</person>,
                Mrs. <person reg="Visqer't Hooft, Frans">Franz Vissert Hooft</person>. </p></q>
        <q who="BCE"><p> On the committee were: </p></q>
        <q who="BCE"><p> Mrs. <person reg="Burgard, Dorothy">Henry O. Burgard</person>, 3d, Mrs.
                    <person reg="Clement, Constance">Harold T. Clement</person>, Mrs. <person
                    reg="Cooke, Frances Wilcex">Thomas F. Cooke</person>, Mrs. <person
                    reg="Dann, Clara L.">Jesse C. Dann</person>, Jr., Mrs. Emile F. Dupant, Mrs.
                    <person reg="Dunbar, Anna G.">Davis T. Dunbar</person>, Mrs. <person
                    reg="Deans, Harriet V. B.">J. Sterling Deans</person>, Mrs. <person
                    reg="Evans, Margaret">James C. Evans</person>, Mrs. <person reg="Evans, Jane"
                    >John G. Evans</person>, Miss <person reg="Fisher, Opal">Opal Fisher</person>,
                Mrs. <person reg="Franchot, Harriet M.">Edward E. Franchot</person>, Mrs. <person
                    reg="Galt, Malrose G.">Alexander Galt</person>, Miss <person
                    reg="Gane, Marguerite">Marguerite Gane</person>, Mrs. <person
                    reg="Gardner, Sarah">Lawrence H. Gardner</person>, Mrs. <person
                    reg="Goodyear, Dorothy K.">Frank H. Goodyear</person>, Mrs. <person
                    reg="Gaylord, Kathering">Bradley J. Gaylord</person>, Mrs. Nelson M. Grayes,
                Mrs. <person reg="Gratwick, Dotha Dart">Frederick C. Gratwick</person>, Dr. Frances
                Hollingshead, Mrs. <person reg="Hedstrom, Katherine W.">Arthur E. Hedstrom</person>,
                Mrs. <person reg="Hill, Elizabeth H.">Ernest M. Hill</person>, Mrs. <person
                    reg="Hoyt, Esther">William B. Hoyt</person>, Mrs. <person
                    reg="Ingham, Florence L.">James R. Ingham</person>, Mrs. <person
                    reg="Knox, Esther B.">Seymour H. Knox, Jr.</person>, Mrs. <person
                    reg="McKenna, Katherine B.">Edmund B. McKenna</person>, Mrs. <person
                    reg="Noye, Florence">Richard K. Noye</person>, Mrs. <person
                    reg="Plimpton, Mary Wilcox">George F. Plimpton</person>, Mrs. H. Ten Eyck Perry,
                Mrs. <person reg="Rumsey, Margaret">Dexter P. Rumsey</person>, Mrs. <person
                    reg="Robins, Louisa W.">Thomas Robins</person>, Jr., Mrs. <person
                    reg="Schoeltkopf, Emily">Alfred H. Schoellkopf</person>, Mrs. <person
                    reg="Sawyer, Esther Hoyt">Ansley W. Sawyer</person>, Mrs. <person
                    reg="Spaulding, Marion P.">S. V. R. Spaulding</person>, Mrs. <person
                    reg="Schoallkopf, Emily R.">William Schoellkopf</person>, Mrs. <person
                    reg="Streeter, Gertrude">Daniel W. Streeter</person>, Mrs. <person
                    reg="Sidway, Amelia R.">Frank St. John Sidway</person>, Mrs. <person
                    reg="Taylor, Cecilia">Reginald B. Taylor</person>, Mrs. <person
                    reg="Vanderwall, Wilma">Wilma Vanderwall</person>, Mrs. <person
                    reg="Wickwire, Ruth">Ward W. Wickwire</person>, Miss <person
                    reg="Wiener, Cecil B.">Cecil B. Wiener</person>, Mrs. <person
                    reg="Warren, Clara S.">William C. Warren</person>. </p></q>
    </docBody>
</doc>
