<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2013/12/11 JK encoded</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-10 EK clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1935-05-17">
            <supplied resp="MSPP">17 May 1935</supplied>
        </docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>
                <supplied resp="MSPP">Speech at the First Baptist Church, Richmond VA</supplied>
            </titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421071</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Richmond Times-Dispatch</title>, May 5, 1933</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="SANMA">Sanger, Margaret</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p><person>Sanger's</person> scheduled lecture at the <org>Medical College of
            Virginia</org>'s Egyptian Building was forced to move to the <org>First Baptist
                Church</org> because of an overflow crowd.<person reg="Wampler, Fred J."> Dr. Fred
                J. Wampler </person>presided.</p>
        <index level1="Catholic Church" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="morality of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="MS on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits and risks"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="continence"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="sterilization"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>1,500 Attend Birth Control Lecture Here</head>
        <head type="sub">Margaret Sanger Delivers Arguments for Dissemination of Such
            Information</head>
        <head type="sub">Cites 7 Reasons</head>
        <head type="sub">Hails Practice as Sign of New Moral Existence</head>
        <p><q who="RTD">While the <org reg="United States government">Federal Government</org> will
                give you a truck load of information on how to raise pigs and chickens, they will
                give you give years in <place reg="Atlanta, GA">Atlanta</place> and a fine of $5,000
                if you even tell anybody, through the mail, about birth control clinics operating
                legally in <place>Virginia</place>, Mrs. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret
                    Sanger</person>, founder of the modern birth control movement, told a large
                audience here last night in protesting against what she said was discrimination
                against mothers and children. Mrs. Sanger set forth many arguments why birth control
                information should be made readily accessible, but gave no information on how to
                accomplish such control. Summarizing the case, Mrs. Sanger gave seven reasons why
                birth control should be practiced. They were: 1. By parents who have transmittable
                disease. 2. In case of women who have tuberculosis, heart disease or some temporary
                ailment. 3. Where parents, though normal themselves apparently, already have brought
                into the world abnormal and defective children. 4. Adolescents. Early marriage, she
                said, was desirable, but the young should not become parents. The girls should be 22
                years old, the boys 23 for complete development. 5. For the purpose of spacing
                children so there will be two or three years between births. 6. The economic side of
                the question; the father’s earning power. It is unfair, she argued, for parents to
                have children they can do nothing for or for older children to have to stunt their
                youth working to feed their brothers and sisters, “<q>their parents’ children.</q>” 7. What
                she said was the necessity for young people after marriage to postpone at least two
                years after marriage the having of any children because they need the time for
                mental and spiritual adjustment. Premature parents, she said, found it harder in
                modern times to get along . Therefore contraceptive information should be available
                to young married people because individuals should be able to say what size their
                families should be. Birth control, Mrs. Sanger said, can be accomplished in three
                ways, one, continence or celibacy, the method approved by the <org>Catholic
                    Church</org>. This method, however, should not be forced on most people as
                religious dogma, particularly, she said, because psychiatrists have found continence
                was not good for most people. The second method was through sterilization by radium
                or x-ray, a method approved by Virginia and thirteen other States for epileptics and
                other persons who would transmit their physical and mental handicaps to children.
                The third was by chemical or mechanical contraceptives, the description of which now
                is classed by Federal law as “<q>obscenity.</q>” She stressed the advantages of small
                families– the longer school terms possible; better nourishment, and less
                overcrowding, low wages and unemployables. Birth control information, she found was
                generally denied the poor even when accessible to more prosperous people. “<q who="SANMA">No
            matter what laws we may make or what we may do, there will always be some kind of child
            labor in large families,</q>” she said, telling of 3-year-olds seen in
                    <place>Colorado</place> and <place>California</place> beet fields. Only
                    <place>Chile</place> has a worse maternal mortality rate than this country,
                although in 1929 we spent nine billions on maternal and child health. About 22,000
                mothers a year die of preventable causes usually resulting from pregnancy and more than 200,000 infants die as a result of poverty and neglect. “<q who="SANMA">They will not attack the problem at the root,</q>” she said. “<q who="SANMA">Children should have passports to give every child a sound body and mind. Our immigration laws forbid idiots, imbeciles, feeble-minded persons, epileptics, psychopathic and insane or diseased persons, prostitutes and so on. Why should the same types come in through the birthrate?</q>"
</p>
 </docBody>
</doc>

