<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="(Published article) ">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/04/09 VS initial tagging</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="(1936-01-14) ">14 January, 1936</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Summary and quotes published as "Calicut Speech," in The Hindu, Jan. 18,
                1936</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421085</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>The Hindu</title></bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="HINDU">The Hindu</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">Sanger spoke at a public meeting in Paran Square, Calicut, India on Jan.
        14, 1936; a summary was published in <title type="journal">The Hindu</title>. <index
            level1="India" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="overpopulation and"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="seaking tours" level3="1935-1936 (India)"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Address at Calicut</head>
        <byline>(From our Correspondent)</byline>
        <dateline>Jan. 15<date value="1936-01-15"/> Calicut<place/></dateline>
        <div>
            <q who="HINDU"><p> The need for adopting birth-control methods in the interests of
                    humanity at large was stressed by Mrs. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret
                        Sanger</person>, addressing a well-attended public meeting held at the
                        <place>Paran Square</place>, last evening, under the presidentship of Dr.
                        <person reg="Mugaseth, Kobad Dhunjibhai">Mugaseth</person>. </p></q>
            <q who="HINDU"><p> The President extended a hearty welcome to Mrs. Sanger on behalf of
                    the citizens of Calicut and said that Mrs. Sanger was doing propaganda for the
                    last so many years on the need for adopting birth-control methods. They were
                    glad to have her among them that day and hear her views on the subject. </p></q>
            <q who="HINDU"><p> Mrs. Sanger, in the course of her speech, said that the main reason
                    for the controversy about the subject was due to the fact that most of those who
                    were opposed to it had misunderstood it. After working for a number of years
                    among the people in a slum district of <place reg="New York, NY">New
                        York</place>, she came to the conclusion that in the interests of their
                    womanhood and country, It was necessary to adopt birth-control methods. She
                    firmly believed that if people knew the sufferings of the women at the time of
                    child birth, they would do everything possible to help them to gain the
                    knowledge of birth-control and make them healthy women. Though the work was in
                    progress for the last 21 years, no law had been changed and there was the same
                    opposition, intolerance, or bigotry, in all countries, denying the women the
                    chance of gaining knowledge which would free them from sickness, poverty, etc.
                    Birth-control meant conscious control of the birth-rate by preventing
                    conception. After explaining the harm that was being done to the country and
                    families by frequent births, she dealt at length on the methods fo rechecking
                    frequent pregnancy. </p></q>
        </div>



        <div>
            <p><supplied resp="MSPP"> The following clipping reports from the same event, but an
                    unknown newspaper.</supplied></p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Mrs. M. Sanger on Birth Control </head>
            <p> (From our own Correspondent)</p>
            <p>
                <place reg="Calicut, India">Calicut</place>, Jan. 15. </p>
            <q who="HINDU"><p> Mrs. Margaret Sanger, of the <org
                        reg="Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau">International Information
                        Centre on Birth Control</org>, addressed a large gathering, yesterday
                    evening, on birth control, at the Paran Square. Dr. Kh. D. Mugaseth presided.
                </p></q>
            <q who="HINDU"><p> Dr. Mugaseth, introduced the speaker. </p></q>
            <p>
                <q who="HINDU">Mrs. Sanger referred to the condemnation of the birth control
                    propaganda and said that <person reg="Stevenson, Robert Louis">Robert Louis
                        Stevenson</person> had said</q> “Condemnation is misunderstanding.” <q
                    who="HINDU">It was not fit to condemn a thing before its various aspects had
                    been studied.</q>
            </p>
            <q who="HINDU"><p> Proceeding Mrs. Sanger said that what birth control meant was the
                    control of birth rate and the number of births could be lowered either by
                    prevention of birth, or control over birth rate by conscious individual control.
                    In the process of preventing birth they were not in any way taking away life. In
                    preventing birth there was no interference with life and for that they had to be
                    single or unmarried in life. </p></q>
            <q who="HINDU"><p> In controlling birth they had to use their intelligence to suit their
                    needs. To be conscious of their acts and responsibilities necessarily involved
                    that they should be free from the animal kingdom, which was impossible in the
                    majority of cases. </p></q>
            <q who="HINDU"><p> She emphasized the need for bringing the population under control.
                    She could not imagine what the population of <place>India</place> would be after
                    hundred years if allowed to go on unchecked. <place>Italy</place> had a large
                    population within the last few decades and 25 per cent of their surplus
                    population within the last few decades and 25 per cent of her surplus population
                    had to emigrate to <place reg="United States">America</place>. </p></q>
            <q who="HINDU"><p> She knew that in India the marriage-able age had been raised but that
                    was not enough. Men and women should be allowed to marry only after they had
                    reached adolescence, that is, at the age of 23. </p></q>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
