<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech ">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-04-02 JK initial tags</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1936-01-06">06 Jan 1936</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Birth
                Control</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421094</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">"Mrs. Sanger on Birth Control"</title>,
                    <title type="journal">The Hindu</title>, Jan. 7,
                1936.</bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="TH">The Hindu</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger</person>
            spoke at the <place reg="Madras, India">Madras</place>
            <org reg="Young Men's Christian Association">Y.M.C.A.</org>
            Auditorium on Jan. 6, 1936, with <person reg="Ramesam, Vepa">Sir
                Vepa Ramesam</person> presiding. A summary was published as
                "<title type="article">Mrs. Sanger on Birth Control</title>,"
                <title type="journal">The Hindu</title>, Jan. 7, 1936.</p>
        <index level1="birth control"/><index level1="birth control"
            level2="in India"/><index
            level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="MS on"/><index
            level1="birth control clinics and leagues" level2="in India"/><index
            level1="India" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="population policies of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Mrs. Sanger on Birth Control </head>
        <head type="sub">“Absolutely in Accordance with Nature”</head>
        <dateline><date value="/----/-01-07"/> Jan. 7, <place
                reg="Madras, India">Madras</place></dateline>
        <q who="TH">
            <p>Mrs. Margaret Sanger delivered a lecture on “Birth Control,” last
                evening, at the Y. M. C. A. Auditorium. Sir Vepa Ramesam
                presided. </p>
            <p>Mrs. Sanger said that she found that in Madras, a great deal of
                propaganda had been done on the subject and she congratulated
                them on the way in which they had developed their organization.
                The movement was now at a stage when it must be properly guided.
                She would address them on the social significance of the
                movement. </p>
            <p>Birth control, she said, was the conscious control of the birth
                rate by application of natural means. It did not mean
                destruction of life. Birth control would lead to a new moral
                awakening. It was important for the creation of international
                peace. International peace would not be lasting until nations
                were truly contented and had solved the population problems. The
                conflict between nations could ultimately be traced to the
                population problem. There was no use resorting to palliatives to
                remedy the ills found in the land. The permanent cure lay in
                tackling the problem of population. No man had any right to pass
                on to the world an unwanted child.</p>
            <p>Birth control did not mean, the lecturer continued, the
                limitation of families, but it meant proper control of
                population. The aim of the movement was to bring about a new
                race, a new kind of people consciously conceived. </p>
            <p>Proceeding, Mrs. Sanger stated that there were three methods of
                controlling the population. The first method was continence,
                which was advocated by Mr. <person reg="Gandhi, Mahatma"
                    >Gandhi</person>. It had been claimed to be the best and the
                safest. She was not sure if it was the best. It might be the
                safest but not the best for all people. It was not a method that
                could generally be applied and in all ages. The second method
                was sterilization and in this mater they were in the hands of
                specialists. The third method was the adoption of chemical and
                mechanical means of contraception. If for adopting chemical and
                mechanical means, they should have proper guidance, each
                individual case should be examined separately, and it was for
                that purpose that they should have numerous clinics all over the
                country. </p>
            <p>It had been stated that birth-control was against nature.
                Self-preservation was the first law of nature and birth control
                was absolutely in accord with nature. Knowledge was power it was
                the duty of all to make it a power for good. They had no right
                to withhold information which would do the greatest amount of
                good to the greatest number, simply because some persons would
                misuse it. </p>
            <p>The <person reg="Ramesam, Vepa">Chairman</person> asked the
                members of the audience to read the valuable books on the
                subject published by the lecturer and come to their own
                conclusions. He said that in his opinion Mrs. Sanger was the
                greatest woman of the world, and the greatest benefactor to
                humanity. </p>
            <p>The meeting then terminated. </p></q>
    </docBody>
</doc>
