<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Interview">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2013/12/11 JK encoded</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/04/10 EK</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1933-11-22"><supplied resp="MSPP">22 Nov.
                1933</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Interview with the <title type="newspaper">Daily
                    Oklahoman</title></supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421069</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="newspaper">Daily Oklahoman</title> 11/23/1933 p. 7</bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="SANMA">Sanger, Margaret</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">From "<q>Advocate of Birth Control Praises Congressmen's
        Work,</q>" <title type="newspaper">Daily Oklahoman</title> Nov. 23, 1933, p. 7 
        <index level1="birth control" level2="mainstreaming of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="goals and strategies"/>    
        <index level1="birth control" level2="politicians and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Advocate of Birth Control Praises Congressmen's Work</head>
        <head type="sub">Visitor Here Says Representatives Do As People Back
            Home Wish. </head>
        <p> “<q who="SANMA">It has been my observation that <place>Oklahoma</place> congressmen
            follow the dictates of their people back home. The fact that they
            even know what the desire of the people is becomes remarkable in
            itself, because those from the so-called ‘older sections’ don’t even
            know who their constituents are,</q>” declared <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger</person>. "<q>On
                birth control, Mrs. Sanger’s study shows Oklahoma is "<q>rather
                    indifferent</q>."
                "<q who="SANMA">But you are going to see a change. Birth control is
the one issue left this generation of youths, who have had everything done for them</q>." </p>
             <p> "<q who="SANMA">They settled woman’s suffrage for them, changed this law and that and with prohibition repeal voted, only
            the bewhiskered law against disseminating of birth control information on the statute books for 60 years, remains for them.</q>" </p> 
                <p> “<q who="SANMA">My correspondence from Oklahoma is interesting in that it shows the
            farm women, those in poorer circumstances, are becoming slowly
            interested and are apt to take a hand.</q>" </p> 
            <p> “<q who="SANMA">We worry about the farmer who is worrying about a crop failure and give him relief– yet the
            greatest worry, and none can challenge this statement, of the farm
            woman is pregnancy.</q>" <p>“<q who="SANMA">We aid the unemployed, realize that hundreds of
            thousands of them will never find work, will always be poor– and yet
            more and more children are being born into exactly those
            circumstances, with no more hope for them than the doomed of today,</q>”
            she declared. “<q who="SANMA">All I ask is an understanding. That is all I want to
            do in this visit. Getting a clear understanding will do much more
            than attempting to force any doctrines.</q>” </p>


    </docBody>
</doc>
