<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="(Published article) ">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/04/11 VS initial tagging</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="(1935-09-17) ">17 September, 1935</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Statement at the national Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth
                Control</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421065</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>New York World Telegram</title></bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="NYWT">New York World Telegram</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="Mussolini, Benito" level2="policy of"/>
        <index level1="Africa" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Italy" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="overpopulation and"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="population policies of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Dictators Seen as Nearsighted By Mrs. Sanger</head>
        <byline>They Fail to Realize That Big Population Problesm Are the Cause of War, She
            Says.</byline>
        <byline>Forced <place>Ethiopia</place> Crisis</byline>
        <byline>Birth Control by Immunization on Way - To Establish Clinics in
            <place>India</place>.</byline>
        <dateline>September 17, 1935 <date value="1935-09-17 "/><place/></dateline>
        <div>
            <p> “Dictators have no use for birth control because they are near-sighted,” <q
                    who="NYWT">said <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person> today,
                    shaking her roan colored hair.</q> “They seem to realize that constantly
                increasing populations are potentially the strongest cause of war.” </p>
            <q who="NYWT"><p> Mrs. Sanger, vivacious and good-humored after 21 years of fighting for
                    the spreading of knowledge about birth control, today accepted an invitation
                    from the <org>All India Women’s Conference</org> and plans to sail next month to
                    establish clinics and bureaus in India. </p></q>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Real Basis for War. </head>
            <p> “As a result of unlimited increase in population in <place>Italy</place>,” <q
                    who="NYWT">said Mrs. Sanger,</q> “<person reg="Mussolini, Benito"
                    >Mussolini</person> is eager to gain new colonial territory in
                    <place>Africa</place> for his overflow. That’s the real basis for the Ethiopian
                situation.”</p>
            <q who="NYWT"><p> Mrs. Sanger told her plans at the office of the <org>National
                        Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control</org>. </p></q>
            <p> “We’re getting ahead fast,” <q who="NYWT">she said.</q> “In the future, and not very
                far into the future either, birth control will be effective through immunization. It
                will run for a half year depending on the dosage, just as small pox is staved off.
                But we still have a long way to go. “ </p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> India’s Population Jumped. </head>
            <p> “The population of India jumped from 318,000,000 in 1921 to 352,000,000 in 1931. And
                they still kill girl babies and many widows still commit suicide on their husband’s
                funeral pyres. What is to become of poor India? Well, I’ll see about that.”</p>
            <q who="NYWT"><p> Mrs. Sanger disclosed that records of the <org
                        reg="Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau">New York clinic</org> show that
                    of the thousands of persons who asked for birth control guidance there had been
                    only two per cent of failure for technical reasons and five percent for human
                    reasons in the system taught. </p></q>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
