<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="(Published Article) ">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/11/04 YG</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="(1935-08-20) ">20 Aug 1935</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Statement on Archbishop John Gregory Murray's Dictate</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421066</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>New York Herald Tribune</title></bibl>
            <bibl><title>MSM</title></bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="NYHT">New York Herald Tribune</name>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <xref from="421928.xml">For a related statement, see "Statement on Archbishop John Gregory
            Murray," Aug. 19, 1935</xref>
        <index level1="Catholic Church"/>
        <index level1="Catholic Church" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="Catholic Church" level2="freedom of speech and"/>
        <index level1="Catholic Church" level2="MS on"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Mrs. Sanger</person>Corrects Birth Control Critic</head>
        <head type="sub">Term Has Nothing to Do With Abortion, She Says in Reply to
            <person reg="Murray, John Gregory">Archbishop</person></head>
        <head type="sub">Defends Contraception</head>
        <head type="sub">Remarks One Cannot Kill What Does Not Exist</head>
        <p><q who="NYHT">Mrs. Margaret Sanger, birth control leader, drew a sharp distinction between abortion
            an[d] contraception in replying today to the edict of <person>Archbishop John Gregory Murray</person> of
            <place reg="Minnesota, St. Paul">St. Paul</place>directing Roman Catholics under his jurisdiction to hold aloof from all
            organizations advocating birth control. The archbishop likened birth control advocates
            to the “<person reg="Dillinger, John Herbert">Dillinger</person>mob,” saying that both were organized for murder.</q></p>
        <p> “Personal opinions matter little,” <q who="NYHT">Mrs. Sanger said in her statement today, </q>“however
            much one may regret the ignorance and misinformation behind them. But when such opinions
            appear in the public press and create confusion and misunderstanding, it becomes a
            public duty to challenge them. </p>
        <p>“The crux of the matter is that abortion is one thing and
            birth control is something totally different. Abortion destroys life. It kills the
            unborn child. It is a terrible and tragic thwarting of nature and one which takes its
            toll in ill health, in sterility and in women’s lives. Birth control, as the medical
            term contraception implies, prevents contraception. You cannot destroy what does not
            exist. You cannot use birth control and abortion as interchangeable terms. To do so is
            to misrepresent the facts.” </p>
        <p><q who="NYHT">Birth control is one of the chief ways in which abortions
            and the maternal deaths resulting from them can be checked, she insisted.</q></p>
        
        <p/>
    </docBody>
</doc>
