<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="(Published article) ">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/04/11 Initial tagging</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="(1929-04-30) ">30 April, 1929</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Illinois Birth Control League Talk</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421037</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Waterloo Evening Courier; Billings Gazette</title></bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="BG">Billings Gazette</name>
            <name id="WEC">Waterloo Evening Courier</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">Speech before the Illinois Birth Control League of the Chicago Women's
        Club - 04/30/1929. <index level1="birth control" level2="in Chicago"/>
        <index level1="birth control clinics and leagues"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="maternal"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Plans New Drive for Birth Control</head>
        <dateline>April 30 <date value="1929-04-30 "/> Chicago<place/></dateline>
        <div>
            <q who="WEC"><p> Mrs. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person> in a talk
                    today before the <org>Illinois Birth Control league</org> of the <org>Chicago
                        Woman’s club</org> here, will open a campaign for extension of birth control
                    clinics and a more lenient attitude toward dissemination of information. </p>
                <p> Before leaving <place reg="Chicago, IL">the city</place>, she said, she will
                    devote time to active organization work, and plans to carry her campaign to the
                    Pacific coast. </p>
                <p> Her activities came as an aftermath of the police raid and arrests are her <org
                        reg="Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau">New York clinic</org>. </p></q>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head>Mrs. Sanger Says Forces Are Gaining</head>
            <byline>Three-Year Interval Between Children Is Among Recommendations of Body</byline>
            <q who="BG"><p> Crime, overpopulation, and disease would be checked by scientific birth
                    control, Mrs. Margaret Sanger noted birth control advocate, said here Tuesday.
                </p></q>
            <q who="BG"><p> Mrs. Sanger opened her midwestern campaign for amendment of the <name
                        reg="United States Penal Code">federal laws</name> prohibiting the spread of
                    contraceptive information with a speech before the Illinois Birth Control league
                    and representatives of the <org>Brush Foundation for the Study of Birth
                        Control</org> at <place reg="Cleveland, OH">Cleveland</place>. </p></q>
            <p> “In the five years we have been conducting clinics in <place>New York</place>,” <q
                    who="BG">she said,</q> “we have cared for 13,000 women and we know we have saved
                90 percent of them from death.”</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Cites Alleged Good</head>
            <p> “We have reduced maternal and infant mortality by insisting on a three-year interval
                between children, and thus relieved the crowding of homes.” </p>
            <q who="BG"><p> Mrs. Sanger denounced the prosecution of Mrs. <person
                        reg="Dennett, Mary Ware">Mary Ware Dennett</person>, grandmother-author of a
                    sex book, who was fined $300 by a New York judge. </p></q>
            <p> “All New York is indignant about Mrs. Dennett’s trial,” <q who="BG">she
                    declared.</q> “Her pamphlet has been used by religious organizations for 10
                years. <org>The Union Theological seminary</org>, the <org>Young Woman’s Christian
                    association</org> and the <org>Young Men’s Christian association</org> have been
                using it as textbook.”</p>
            <q who="BG"><p> Mrs. Sanger plans to organize a committee of 1,000 here to work for
                    amendment of the federal penal code provisions in regard to birth control.
                </p></q>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Sees Progress</head>
            <p> “Chicago has five birth control clinics and will eventually be a greater field for
                our work than New York,” <q who="BG">she predicted.</q> “This city, with its large
                population of mixed nationalities, needs scientific birth control.</p>
            <p> “Under the present penal code even a reputable doctor may not legally furnish
                information or advice on this important matter. In 10 years, however, the government
                will be organizing birth control clinics as an essential part of the program of
                material and infant welfare.” </p>
        </div>

    </docBody>
</doc>
