<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/02/26 JK initial tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-13 CH proof tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-26 JK correct tags</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1932-01-21 ">21 Jan. 1932</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Sanger's Speech to the Rochester
                    Council of Jewish Women</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421045</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Scientific Information on Birth Control
                    Advocated by Mrs. Sanger</title>, <title type="journal"
                    >Rochester Democrats Chronicle</title> Jan. 20, 1932, p.
                13-16</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="RDC">Rochester Democrats Chronicle</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger</person>
        delivered an address to the <org reg="Rochester Council of Jewish Women"
            > Council of Jewish Women</org> at the <org>Temple of B'rith
            Kodesh</org> on Jan. 20 1932 in <place reg="Rochester, NY">Rochester
            NY</place>. <index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/><index
            level1="birth control" level2="in New York"/><index
            level1="birth control" level2="international"/><index
            level1="birth rate" level2="population growth and"/><index
            level1="poverty" level2="family size and"/><index
            level1="United States" level2="overpopulation in"/><index
            level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="New York "/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head> Scientific Information on Birth Control Advocated by Mrs.
            Sanger</head>
        <head type="sub">Sees Issue Keynote of New Social and Moral
            Awakening-Absence of Knowledge Increases Mortality Rate Among
            Mothers, She Declares </head>
        <q who="RDC"><p>A plea to give the women compelled to use the public
                clinic the scientific information available to her more
                fortunate sister who can afford to consult the private physician
                was made yesterday by Mrs. Margaret Sanger, internationally
                known advocate of birth control. </p>
            <p>Mrs. Sanger spoke to a capacity audience of several hundred women
                in Temple B'rith Kodesh Temple under the sponsorship of the
                Council of Jewish Women. Three men braved the feminine audience
                to hear Mrs. Sanger, and a stenographer made a complete report
                of her speech. </p></q>
        <p> “Birth control is the keynote of a new social and moral awakening,”
            Mrs. Sanger said. “It is the conscious control of the birth rate by
            means that prevent the conception of human life. All the great
            social problems are entrenched in the homes of the poor. Maternal
            and infant mortality, disease, child labor have their sad relation
            to poverty. I have seen mothers bowed and bent, carrying the triple
            burden of a job, a house, and maternity. They had to resign
            themselves to many children or resort to terrible drugs and poisons.
            The crimes of abortions are at our door for not permitting these
            women to have scientific information.” </p>
        <q who="RDC"><p>Mrs. Sanger declared that the absence of knowledge had
                been responsible for the high mortality rate among mothers,
                especially where such disorders as heart or kidney disease, or
                tuberculosis made child bearing equivalent to a death sentence
                for the mother. Poverty and maternal exhaustion play their role
                in the statistics of 200,000 children who die annually in the
                United States before they reach their first birthday, she said.
                Child labor laws will be ineffectual until adjustments can be
                made so that the older children do not have to go out at 14
                years of age to support the young brood. </p>
            <p>Population also has its relation to war, Mrs. Sanger pointed out,
                indicating <place>Japan</place> and <place>Italy</place> as
                evidences of this. </p></q>
        <p> “Japan has a population of sixty-five million in an area no larger
            than <place>California</place>,” she said. “The <place>United
                States</place>, <place>Australia</place>, and <place>
                Canada</place> have closed their doors to Japanese immigration.
            The population has just gone on growing until now it explodes in
            war. <place> Manchuria </place>is vast with oil and coal resources
            and good railroads. Japan has taken it unlawfully and menaces the
            peace of the world, but it would take the whole world to put her out
            of Manchuria. I think she’s never going to be put out. </p>
        <p>"Italy, too, is increasing her population. A woman who does not have
            a child every two years is required to report to the health bureau
            and give an explanation. Italy, it seems, would breed humans like
            animals. The Italian population will undoubtedly overflow the
            national frontiers into<place> France</place>.” </p>
        <q who="RDC"><p> Mrs. Sanger challenged her audience to lead the fight
                to amend the federal laws regarding birth control and permit the
                dissemination of information under the direction of physicians,
                both in public lectures clinics, and through the mails. </p>
            <p> She listed seven important reasons for birth control. In cases
                of transmissible disease, parenthood should be avoided. Women
                suffering from temporary ailments which are curable out to be
                put off motherhood until their health is improved. Parents who
                have had a sub-normal child have no right to bring other
                children into the world. Children should be spaced nearly three
                years apart to permit the mother to regain her health, except
                where unusually healthy parents desire two children to be closer
                in age. </p>
            <p>It may be all right to marry in adolescence but it is better to
                put off parenthood until that period is over, Mrs. Sanger
                believes. Economic reasons should enter into the consideration
                of when to have children, she believes. Wise young people wait
                for a period of at least two years after marriage before having
                children, she said. </p></q>
    </docBody>
</doc>
