<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="(Published Article) ">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/04/04 YG</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="(1934-07-10) ">10 July 1934</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Statement on Birth Control and Law in the <place>United States</place></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421079</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Svenska Dagbladet</title></bibl>
            <bibl><title>MSM</title></bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="SD">Svenska Dagbladet</name>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">Sanger gave a press conference in <place reg="Stockholm, Sweden">Stockholm</place>on July
        10, 1934. The comments were published in Svenska Dagbladet, a
        conservative newspaper. Text comes from a contemporary translation in
        the Margaret Sanger Papers. <index
            level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Federal"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>The Irish Woman Who Helped the American Woman</head>
        <head type="sub">Birth Control Lawful in the <place reg="United States">U.S.A.</place> - For Five
            Minutes</head>
        <div>
            <p><q who="SD">Mrs. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>from <place reg="United States">America</place>, 
                one of Birth Control’s most
                zealous champions, the pioneer for improving the condition of
                American mothers and wives, is at present visiting in <place>Stockholm</place>
                before she continues a few days hence her study trip to <place reg="U.S.S.R.">Russia</place>.
                About a decade ago Mrs. Sanger opened the first Birth Control
                Clinic in America. This was then possible by the revised law in
                this respect in <place>New York</place>State. One desired objective for the
                entire United States for which Mrs. Sanger is working is the
                passage of the so-called Birth Control Bill. </q></p>
            <p><q who="SD">This proposed law,
                which permits the dissemination of knowledge concerning birth
                control and methods of prevention through doctors, pharmacists
                and controlled clinics, lately came before the Senate. It went
                through - but only for five minutes. After this period one of
                the voters woke up - parenthesis, a representative of the
                <org>Catholic Church</org> - and protested. Thus, Birth Control fell
                through that time. But Mrs. Sanger does not despair.</q></p>
            <p>“Next year the law will pass,” <q who="SD">said Mrs. Sanger optimistically, when late
                Monday evening after an excursion to <place reg="Skansen, Sweden">Skansen</place> she placed herself
                at our disposal for an interview. </q>“We have worked for twenty
                years with faith and loyalty and some time our effort must bear
                fruit.”</p>
            <p>“The present law was introduced sixty years ago and
                nothing in it has been changed since that time. We are no
                striving to change it for the sake of the poor and burdened
                mother. If we have effective birth control,” <q who="SD">Mrs. Sanger
                continued optimistically,</q> “abortion will be unnecessary. What we
                wish to give mothers is a breathing space, so to speak, to give
                them at least a couple of years between each child. That can
                scarcely be too much to ask.” <q who="SD">In this connection Mrs. Sanger
                asserted tha tthe highest mortality figures among mothers occurs
                in the <place reg="United States">U.S.</place></q></p>
            <p>“A couple of weeks ago,” <q who="SD">Mrs. Sanger stated further,</q>
                “a law was introduced in <place>England</place>according to which doctors and
                clinics not only have the right but are obliged to enlighten
                women who consult them concerning the existence of methods of
                protection and their use.” </p>
            <p><q who="SD">Mrs. Sanger also developed her
                viewpoint on the subject of birth control in connection with the
                world’s peace problem. </q></p>
            <p>“We all know how the countries have
                closed their doors to each other, how emigration and immigration
                have diminished or been made impossible. If a people with a
                great increase of population are denied the possibility of
                immigrating, the standard of living goes down and the country
                must embark upon an effective control of birth. Birth Control
                is, I believe, a fundamental measure against the over-population
                and war between countries, and the women especially should all
                support this measure warmly and heartily.” </p>
            <p><q who="SD">The aim of Mrs.
                Sanger’s visit to Russia via our land is to study general health
                conditions and problems connected therewith, such as the
                capacity of women in different countries to combine home and
                work, etc. The East Indian women meet in a congress this year
                and naturally Mrs. Sanger has been asked to attend. </q></p>
            <p><q who="SD">Mrs. Sanger
                is a simple and sweet woman with a friendly smile about her wise
                mouth. One senses nothing about her of the suffrage woman and
                dictator, and yet as such a one must she still be regarded. Mrs.
                Sanger was born of Irish parents but came to American rather
                early where as a nurse in <place reg="New York, NY">New York City</place>she obtained an insight
                into the distressing lives of the working women. It was sympathy
                with her suffering sisters and the wish to lessen their burden
                which later dictated her actions. She contrived by and by, after
                a various number of reverses, among other a sojourn in prison,
                to bring about a <org>Birth Control Congress</org>in America, and a few
                years later she was present as a source of inspiration at the
                World Population Conference in <place reg="Geneva, Switzerland">Geneva</place>. Assiduous studies of
                European conditions had, on her part, preceded this conference.
                At the present time Mrs. Sanger is the director of a Birth
                Control Clinic in New York. It was the first of its kind but
                since then, hundreds have been established in imitation of it.</q></p>
               <p><q who="SD"><org>The Women's Club</org> in <place reg="Stockholm, Sweden">Stockholm</place>has planned a luncheon at 
                   <place reg="Moseback, Sweden">Moseback</place> on Wednesday for the American visitor. </q></p>

        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
