<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Speech ">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-02-26 JK</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-02-28 CH proof tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-11-13 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1933/05/17">17 May 1933</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Interview with <title
                        type="journal">Richmond News
                Leader</title></supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421062</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article"> Predicts Clinics on Birth Control Soon
                    in Virginia </title>, <title type="journal">The Richmond
                    News Leader</title>, May 17, 1933, pp. 1 and 22.</bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="RNL">The Richmond News Leader</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>This is a summary of an interview <person
                reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger</person> gave before speaking at
            the Egyptian Building at the <org>Medical College of Virginia</org>
            in <place reg="Richmond, VA">Richmond </place></p>
        <index level1="birth control movement" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="Catholic Church" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="sex education" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="in Virginia"/>
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Mississippi"
        /></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Predicts Clinics on Birth Control Soon in <place reg="VA"
                >Virginia</place></head>
        <head type="sub">Mrs. Margaret Sanger Gives Views on Subject as She
            Arrives for Lecture.</head>

        <p><q who="RNL">Present economic conditions and unemployment coupled
                with the fact that the loss of private fortunes will throw the
                major burden of philanthropic work on county, state and federal
                governments, will make birth control clinics throughout the
                country a necessity, believes Mrs. Margaret Sanger, pioneer
                birth control advocate, who arrived in Richmond earlier today to
                give a public lecture in the Egyptian building of the medical
                college tonight.</q>
        </p>
        <p>“It will not be long,” said Mrs. Sanger, “before federal and state
            governments will come face to face not only with the waste of life
            caused by the fact that birth control information is not legalized,
            but by the increasing burden on the taxpayer to maintain the
            unfortunate and often malformed children which are the result of
            lack of information on the subject.</p>
        <p>“Virginia, which is one of the most progressive states in the <place
                reg="United States">Union</place> in her wonderful eugenic laws,
            and which has accomplished a remarkable achievement in increasing
            her birthrate while decreasing the death rate, will undoubtably I
            believe shortly establish birth control clinics in her borders.” </p>
        <p><q who="RNL">Only one state in the Union, <place reg="MS"
                    >Mississippi</place>, will not legally allow a physician to
                give out information on the subject, she declared.</q> “All the
            other states have some leeway in the matter.” </p>
        <p>"The great need is for the federal birth control laws to be so
            amended that information may be sent through the mails or sent by
            public carriers,” she declared.</p>
        <p><q who="RNL">At present birth control information is undoubtedly
                widely disseminated throughout the country, and there are more
                than 135 legally established clinics. However, all the
                literature and supplies are literally “<emph rend="italics"
                    >bootlegged</emph>” into the states under existing federal
                laws.</q>
        </p>
        <p>“Birth control belongs with science, preventive medicine, public
            relief and public health work. It should be treated with dignity and
            taken out of the class of things which is practiced only
            surreptitiously,” she announced. </p>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Benefits General Welfare.</head>
            <p>“Where clinics have been established, prosperity has increased,
                the death rate, particularly as regards infant mortality, has
                been cut, and general conditions have been bettered.” </p>
            <p>“The Catholics block our plans wherever they can,” she said.
                “However in placed where public sentiment is firmly established
                they can do little. Moreover sentiment among Catholic women I
                find is changing in favor of birth control, and many individuals
                in the church are seeking information on the subject.” </p>
            <p><q who="RNL">The action of the <org>Virginia Federation of
                        Labor</org>, Mrs. Sanger pronounced one of the most
                    progressive things they could have done.</q>
            </p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
