<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/24/01 YG initial encoding</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-01-29 CH proof</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1931-11-09">09 Nov 1931</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Speech at the San Antonio Open Forum</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421063</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">600 Folk attend Sanger lecture</title>, <title
                    type="journal">San Antonio Express</title>, November 10, 1931 </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">Summary of Sanger's talk at the San Antonio Municipal Auditorium to the
        Open Forum. Over 600 were in attendance. <index level1="birth control" level2="religion and"
            /><index level1="birth control" level2="morality of"/>
        <index level1="abortion" level2="birth control vs."/>
        <index level1="&quot;unfit&quot; to reproduce" level2="social burden of"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>600 FOLK ATTEND SANGER LECTURE</head>
        <head type="sub">Birth Control Advocate Defends Belief Before Sparse Audience</head>
        <div>
            <p>
                <q who="SAE"><place reg="San Antonio, TX">San Antonio</place>either has matured and
                    unchangeable ideas about birth control, or else they are not interested, judging
                    from the small crowd that turned out Monday night to hear the world’s foremost
                    exponent of the practice, <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret
                        Sanger</person>, speak at <org reg="San Antonio Municipal Auditorium">the
                        Municipal Auditorium</org>.</q></p>
            <p><person reg="Lang, Sylvan">Sylvan Lang</person>, president of <org
                    reg="San Antonio Open Forum">the Open Forum</org>, presided at the meeting
                opening with the invitation for everyone to come on down and take one of the
                orchestra seats advertised at $1 each. At that time there some 200 of these seats
                occupied. When the galleries and the back rows had accepted his invitation, the
                crowd number about 600 persons. The gross proceeds of the house were said to be
                about $400.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Mother of Two Sons</head>
            <p><q who="SAE">The middle-aged, silver haired exponent of “conscious control of the
                    birth rate,” is herself the mother of two sons. She became a convert to the cult
                    of which she is now credited with being the founder, while a nurse in the slums
                    of <place reg="New York, NY">New York City</place>.</q></p>
            <p><q who="SAE">She said the <org>Church of England</org> had some time ago gone on
                    record favoring in principle the things she encouraged, and made the prediction
                    that in a short time the churches of the United States would do likewise. When
                    her lecture here was recently announced, her theme was denounced in a pastoral
                    letter mailed out by the Most Rev. Arthur J. Drossaerts, Catholic Archbishop of
                    San Antonio, and members of that faith were exhorted to remain away from the
                    lecture and not be misled by her pleadings.</q></p>
            <p><q who="SAE">However, a large and influential group of churches in the United States
                    are now aligned with her program, Mrs. Sanger said, and she expressed the belief
                    that their united endorsement was reasonably sure.</q></p>
            <p>“Conscious birth control,” she said, “is the keynote of a new social order; it is no
                more to be stopped that the tides of the ocean.”</p>
            <p><q who="SAE">The practices she advocates no more destroy human life as charged by her
                    critics than does mere celibacy, she said. Her church critics, according to her,
                    center their attacks on her on the grounds that to do as she advises means
                    destroying a human life.</q></p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Denies Life Destroyed</head>
            <p>“If my views prevail, there is no more human life destroyed than there is when a man
                or woman chooses to remain single and apart from the marriage relation,” she
                said.</p>
            <p><q who="SAE">Modern civilization, she said, is menaced by the </q> “hordes of unfit,”
                    <q who="SAE">and mentally deficient, and parents before bringing into the world
                    children should well consider and ponder the responsibility which they owe as
                    parents. It is a right and a privilege which they owe to their children, she
                    said.</q></p>
            <p><q who="SAE">She closed with a plea for a liberalization of postal laws which will
                    permit sending through the mail advice and instructions to women on how to
                    achieve the results she advocates.</q></p>
            <p><q who="SAE">She appeared under the auspices of the San Antonio Open Forum which
                    always disavows the opinions expressed by its speakers, according to a routine
                    announcement of the president, Sylvan Lang, made preceding her talk.</q></p>
        </div>


    </docBody>
</doc>
