<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="(Published Speech) ">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>1934/12/07 YG</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="(1934-12-07) ">07 Dec 1934</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Family Security</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421061</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>El Paso Herald Post</title></bibl>
            <bibl><title>MSM</title></bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="HP">El Paso Herald Post</name>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">Add text if needed. <index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="American opinion on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="economic benefits and risks of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Family Security</head>
        <head type="sub">Says Men More Interested In Birth Control Program</head>
        <head type="sub"><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Mrs. Margaret Sanger</person>, Nationally Known Advocate, Urges Clinic in <place reg="El Paso, Texas">El Paso</place></head>
        <div>
            <p><q who="HP">Men, in organized groups, have taken a greater interest in birth control than women
                in the same status, it was declared today by Mrs. Margaret Sanger, nationally known
                birth control advocate, who spoke at the <org reg="Altrusa Club">Altrusa Club</org>luncheon on “Family
                Security.”</q></p>
            <p>“Men seem to realize its social importance with reference to relief and
                unemployment,” <q who="HP">Mrs. Sanger said.</q> “Women are interested as individuals but after they
                find out information, they are through being interested.” </p>
        </div>
      
           <div><head type="sub">Population Great</head> </div>
        
    <div>
            <p><q who="HP">Statistics showing the decline of the birth rate doesn’t mean anything,
                    because the population is greater, Mrs. Sanger said.</q></p>
            <p>“Remember, there was a 17-million population increase from 1920 to 1930,” <q who="HP">she
                said.</q></p>
            <p><q who="HP">She quoted 1932 statistics given at the <org>American Conference on Birth
                Control and National Recovery</org> in <place reg="Washington, D.C.">Washington</place>by <person reg="Sydenstricker, Edgar">Edgar Sydenstricker</person>.</q></p>
            <p>“The average annual birth rate in families on relief was 53 per cent
                    higher than in those not on relief,” <q who="HP">she said.</q> “The birth rate in families which
                    were receiving relief in 1932 was 210 as against 137 in families which were not
                    receiving relief, a survey in four cities revealed."</p>
            <p><q who="HP">Mrs. Sanger does not blame the families on relief, but the authorities
                    and organizations in every community, she said.</q></p>
            <p>“They won’t take a stand to enable these people to get the information they should
                have,” <q who="HP">she said.</q></p>
        
    </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Blames Representative</head>
        </div>

        <div>
            <p><q who="HP">She also blames <person reg="Sumners, Hatton">Rep. Hatton Sumners</person>, chairman of the <org reg="House Judiciary Committee">House Judiciary
                committee</org>, for keeping the Birth Control Bill in the committee last
                year.</q></p>
            <p>“<person reg="Ashurst, Henry Fountain">Senator Ashurst</person> of <place reg="Phoenix, Arizona">Phoenix</place>, 
                chairman of <org reg="The Senate Judiciary Committee">Judiciary of the Senate</org>, allowed the bill to
                reach the <org reg="United States Senate">senate</org>,” <q who="HP">she said.</q></p>
            <p><q who="HP">Mrs. Sanger expects a fight against establishing a birth control clinic
                    in <place reg="Dallas, Texas">Dallas</place>, <person reg="Sumner, Hatton William">Representative Sumner</person>’s home. 
                She will go to <place reg="Ft. Worth, Texas">Ft. Worth</place>and Dallas
                    after leaving here.</q></p>
            <p>“But I believe the people in Dallas will put up a good fight for the clinic,”<q
                    who="HP">she said</q> “Such a clinic was established in six weeks’ time in
               <place reg="Tucson, Arizona">Tucson</place>.”</p>
            <p>“A business man paid a year’s rent for a cottage as headquarters. Co-operation is
                being given by the <org reg="Pima County Medical Society">County Medical society</org> and welfare agencies.”</p>
            <p><q who="HP">Mrs. Sanger will confer with a group of El Paso men and women this
                    afternoon on the establishment of a clinic here.</q></p>
        </div>

        <div>
            <head type="sub">Mrs. Sanger Meets at Luncheon with El Paso Doctors.</head>
        </div>

        <div>
            <p><q who="HP">Conscious control of the birth rate was stressed as the most important factor aimed
                for by the <org reg="Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control">National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control</org>, Mrs. Sanger
                said at the <org reg="Altrusa International">Altrusa Club</org> luncheon yesterday.</q></p>
            <p>“We control everything nowadays except the most important thing of all,” <q who="HP">she said</q>.
                “We control our tempers, our appetites, our currency. But we allow the increase of
                children who cannot be given a chance at life, in homes which can not afford them,
                do not want them. And we carry the burden in our social program.”</p>
            <p><q who="HP">No intelligence is being shown in the relief work, in any work for charity when
                children of unfit parents, or poverty-stricken parents are brought into the world in
                an increasing number, Mrs. Sanger pointed out.</q></p>
            <p>“It is like trying to cure the cancer by burning it on top,” <q who="HP">she said.</q></p>
            <p><q who="HP">The average cost to maintain a person through the birth control clinic would be $2 a
                year, Mrs. Sanger said.</q></p>
            <p>“Would you like to have knowledge?”<q who="HP"> is the question asked women at clinics.</q></p>
            <p>“It is taking the information out of the pornographic class and giving it out from
                scientific centers which take care of the individual needs of the women,”<q who="HP"> Mrs.
                    Sanger said.</q></p>
            <p><q who="HP">She said that 51,000 women had been taken care of in her own New York Clinic, for
                which she served 30 days in jail.</q></p>
            <p>“I never spent a better 30 days in my life,”<q who="HP">she said.</q></p>
            <p><q who="HP">In advocating young couples’ waiting two years after marriage to have children, Mrs.
                Sanger said:</q></p>
            <p>“We have got to make more of marriage. We have never had the development of the
                woman. The boy never knows the girl as a woman. He knows her as a girl and next as
                mother of children.</p>
            <p>“The wife never knows herself as a woman. She never gets the spiritual and mental
                development which should be hers between girlhood and motherhood.”</p>
            <p>“There are 47 states with conflicting laws on birth control,” <q who="HP">Mrs. Sanger said.
                <place>California</place>bootlegs her supplies to take care of her 14 clinics under her own law,
                she said.</q></p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
