<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/03/07 JK initial tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-13 CH proof tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-26 JK correct tags</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1936-12-26">12 Dec 1936</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Margaret Sanger's Statement on the
                    Court of Appeals decision.</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421102</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
                <title type="journal">Los Angeles Times</title>,<title
                    type="article">Educational Program to be Launched
                    Here</title>, Dec. 26, 1936, P. A6.</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="LAT">Los Angeles Times</name>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">Statement published in the <org>Los Angeles Times</org>. <index
            level1="birth control" level2="legalization of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="legal cases"
            level3="U.S. v. One Book Entitled 'Contraception'"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>EDUCATIONAL PROGRAM TO BE LAUNCHED HERE</head>
        <head type="sub">Birth Control Leader Tells Plan Progress</head>
        <p><q who="LAT">Just back from a tour of the Western States, <person
                    reg="Smith, Gladys Delancey">Miss Gladys Delancey
                    Smith</person> , regional director of the <org>National
                    Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control</org>,
                will direct attention to an educational program.</q></p>
        <p><q who="LAT">In receipt of communication from <person
                    reg="Sanger, Margaret">Mrs. Margaret Sanger</person>,
                president and founder of the national committee, Miss Smith is
                jubilant. The Sanger letter states:</q></p>
        <p>“The greatest legal victory in the birth control movement was just
            won when the <org>United States Circuit Court of Appeals for the
                Second Circuit</org> unanimously upheld <person
                reg="Moscowitz, Grover">Judge Moscowitz</person>'s decision
            liberating the medical profession, hospitals and other health
            agencies from legal restrictions. </p>
        <p>“We are proceeding on two fronts, judicial and legislative, and this
            decision has established our claim so clearly that there is now no
            need for us to ask <org reg="United States Congres">Congress</org>
            for further legislation regarding the rights of the medical
            profession.</p>
        <p>“This victory is due in large measure to the pressure of public
            opinion, as clearly shown not only by the millions who have endorsed
            our Federal work but also by the recent poll of the <org>Institute
                of Public Opinion.”</org>
        </p>
        <p><q who="LAT">That it is the duty of licensed physicians to aid in the
                committee's educational program is the belief of Mrs. Sanger who
                has established headquarters here at 350 South Figueroa Street,
                Studio D, with Miss Smith in charge. Plans are being perfected
                by Miss Smith for the formal reception and entertainment of
                    <person reg="Kato, Shidzue Ishimoto">Baronness
                    Ishimoto</person> of Japan, who will arrive here January 25.
                She is known as the "Margaret Sanger" of Japan.</q></p>
        <p/>
    </docBody>
</doc>
