<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="(Published article) ">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/04/09 VS initial tagging</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="(1936-12-29) ">29 December, 1936</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Statement on the Confernce on Contraceptive Research and Clinical
                Practice</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421101</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>New York Times</title></bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="TIMES">New York Times</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">The New York Times reposted a statement Sanger made on the opening of the
        Conference in New York at the Hotel Roosevelt. For Sanger's complete opening speech, see
            <xref from="101798.xml">Address to the Conference on Contraceptive Research and Clinical
            Practice</xref>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="medical community and"/>
        <index level1="Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau"/>
        <index level1="birth control clinics and leagues" level2="research benefits of"/>
        <index level1="birth control methods" level2="efficacy of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Birth Control Aid Received By 56,000</head>
        <byline>Mrs. Sanger Reports Clinical Work Nearly 100% Effective, but Urges Wider Scope. Says
            Millions Need Help.</byline>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> She Asks Further Assistance of Science to Reduce Costs- New Researches
                Revealed. </head>
            <q who="TIMES"><p> Clinical birth control methods are approaching 100 per cent success;
                    but cheaper, easier and equally harmless means must be found to help the
                    millions to whom present methods are economically or geographically unavailable,
                    Mrs. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>, director of the
                        <org>Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau</org>, declared yesterday.
                </p></q>
        </div>
        <div>
            <p>
                <supplied resp="MSPP">Part of this section has been omitted.</supplied></p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Bureau’s Work Reviewed</head>
            <p> “The outstanding achievement of this bureau,” <q who="TIMES">Mrs. Sanger said</q>,
                “has been to inform, teach, instruct and give contraceptive advice to more than
                56,000 women who voluntarily appealed to us for this advice. The records of these
                women may truly be looked upon as a veritable human laboratory for research and
                correlations. </p>
            <p> “We have been fortunate in enlisting the cooperation of competent physicians and
                have amassed a wealth of incontrovertible evidence supporting the feasability and
                desirability of contraceptive practice. The evidence seems to be on our side, for in
                all the studies we have made we find, when our teachings are followed and adhered
                to, there is the record of 96.4 to 97 per cent success. </p>
            <p> “The birth-control movement has arrived at a stage in its development where it
                definitely can help that part of the population accessible to hospitals, doctors or
                in the health services where properly qualified doctors are available, but we must
                go further and supply the demand of women in the submerged sections who are
                clamoring for cheap and effective means to control the size of the family. </p>
            <p> “We must have methods that are cheaper, easier to apply and as harmless as those
                which we now use have proven to be. The scientist must come to our aid. We want his
                cooperation, his wisdom, his impersonal courage and vision.”</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Praises Recent Court Verdict</head>
            <p>
                <q who="TIMES">Mrs. Sanger praised a <name
                        reg="United States v. One Package of Japanese Pessaries">recent
                        decision</name> of the <org>United States Circuit Court of Appeals</org>,
                    which held that</q> “the Federal statutes were not designed to obstruct the
                circulation of articles which may be intelligently employed by conscientious
                physicians for the purpose of saving life and promoting well-being.” </p>
            <p> “In our effort to clear away this legal rubbish,” <q who="TIMES">Mrs. Sanger
                    added</q>, “we have uncovered many obstacles, but we cannot go much farther,
                either onward or upward, without the help of the scientific mind.” </p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <p>
                <supplied resp="MSPP">Part of this section has been omitted</supplied></p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
