<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="(Published/Draft/Speech/Article) ">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/04/09 VS initial tagging</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="(1935-11-26) ">26 November, 1935</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Birth Control in India</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421100</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>The Times of India</title></bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="TIMES">The Times of India</name>
            <name id="MISJE">Mistri, Jerbanoo E.</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">Sanger spoke to the Society for the Study and Promotion of Family Hygiene
        at the Sir Cowasji Jehangir Hall in Bombay on Nov. 26, 1936. This summary was published as
        "Birth Control Part of Civilization," The Times of India, Nov. 27, 1936; for rough hand
        written notes, see MSM S71:760. <index level1="birth control" level2="access to"
            level3="international"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="civilization and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="international conferences on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="propaganda and publicity"/>
        <index level1="birth control methods"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="population growth and"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="population growth" level2="regulation of"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="seaking tours" level3="1935-1936 (India)"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Birth Control Part of Civilization</head>
        <byline>Modern Problem</byline>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Mrs. Sanger On Need For Propaganda</head>
            <q who="TIMES"><p> A large audience, in which women were well represented, heard Mrs.
                        <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>, the American birth
                    control expert, at the <org>Sir Cowasji Jehangir Hall</org>, <place
                        reg="Bombay, India">Bombay</place>, on Tuesday night. She explained
                    convincingly the need for the propagation of knowledge of birth control in
                        <place>India</place>. </p></q>
            <q who="TIMES"><p> The meeting was organised by the <org>Society for the Study and
                        Promotion of Family Hygiene</org>, and was preisded over by Lt.-Col. <person
                        reg="Sokhey, Sahib Singh">S.S. Sokhey</person> in the unavoidable absence of
                    the <person reg="Nariman, Khurshed Framji">Mayor</person>. Those present
                    included Sir <person reg="Dehlavi, Ali Muhammad Khan">A.M.K. Dehlavi</person>,
                    President of the <org>Bombay Legislative Council</org>; Sir <person
                        reg="Mehta, Chunilal B.">Chunilal</person> and Lady <person
                        reg="Mehta, Tapibai">Mehta</person>, Sir <person reg="Choksey, Nusserwanji"
                        >Nusserwanji Choksey</person>, Lt.-Col. <person reg="Shah, Jelal M.">Jelal
                        Shah</person>, Mrs. <person reg="How-Martyn, Edith">Edith
                        How-Martyn</person>, Mrs. <person>Kania</person>, Mr. And Mrs. <person
                        reg="Mehta, I. N.">I.N. Mehta</person>, Mrs. <person
                        reg="Talyarkhan, Frene S.">F.S. Talyarkhan</person>, Mrs.
                        <person>Judah</person>, Mr. <person reg="Sen, K. C.">K.C. Sen</person>, Dr.
                        <person reg="Mehta, Jivraj Narayan">Jivraj Mehta</person>, Dr. Mrs. <person
                        reg="Sukhtankar, Malini B.">Malini Sukhtankar</person> and <person
                        reg="Bole, Rao Bahadur S. K.">Rao Bahadur S.K. Bole</person>.</p></q>
            <q who="TIMES"><p> Mrs. Sanger said that the hour for birth control had struck not only
                    in the west but throughout the entire world. It was the most revolutionary idea
                    of the twentieth century, and it had become a part of their civilisation. It was
                    impossible to ignore it.</p></q>
            <q who="TIMES"><p> Since the beginning of human society there had always existed some
                    method to control population. Nature’s way of keeping down population lay in
                    famines, floods, pestilences and other calamities, but the methods adopted now
                    were quite different. There were two ways of controlling population: to increase
                    the death rate and lower the birth rate, or to emigrate. Thanks to the national
                    policies followed by the countries of the world, emigration had become an
                    impossibility, except to the underpopulated regions of South America. The only
                    alternative therefore was to increase the death-rate and decrease the
                    birth-rate. </p></q>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Nature’s Process Hindered</head>
            <q who="TIMES"><p> There were, however, factors operation in the world which hindered
                    nature’s way of controlling population. The growth of humanitarianism, with its
                    organised charities, philanthropic institutions and movements was interfering
                    with Nature’s process of elimination of the undesirable and unfit types of
                    people, who were being maintained at the expense of society. The existence of
                    such a class of people was a danger to civilisation, as they were using up the
                    energy and resources of the world, without in any way adding to them.</p></q>
            <q who="TIMES"><p> She said the two greatest problems of present day civilisation were
                    pressure of population upon its means of subsistence, and the reconciliation of
                    humanitarian ideals with projects to improve the race.</p></q>
            <q who="TIMES"><p> Mrs. Sanger declared that each child, before it was born, had a right
                    to be assured of a decent standard of existence. It was the duty of parents to
                    ascertain whether they could give a fair condition of existence to the child.
                    Even nations subjected the entry of other peoples into the territories to severe
                    tests. </p></q>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Handicaps to Knowledge</head>
            <q who="TIMES"><p> The lecturer then contrasted large and small families, and observed
                    that much of the misery noticed in large family groups could be avoided if
                    people had a proper knowledge of the means of controlling a family’s numbers.
                    The greatest handicaps in the way of carrying knowledge to the people were their
                    prejudice, ignorance and financial inability to acquire such knowledge.</p></q>
            <q who="TIMES"><p> The lecturer said a period of two to four years should be allowed
                    between each childbirth. No man or woman should undertake the duty of parenthood
                    before they had passed the period of adolescence. No more children should be
                    brought into the world than parents were economically able to take care of.
                    There must be a period of adjustment after marriage during which the man might
                    know the woman as a woman and not as a child-bearing machine.</p></q>
            <q who="TIMES"><p> Discussing modern methods of birth control, Mrs. Sanger said the
                    first, which had the approval of all religions, was continence or celibacy.
                    That, however, was possible only to a few and could not be forced on others. The
                    second method was sterilisation of the unfit. A third method was the chemical
                    process. That had to be employed according to the special needs of
                    individuals.</p></q>
            <q who="TIMES"><p> Mrs. Sanger advocated the opening of clinics where men and women
                    could get proper knowledge and materials for birth control. She urged the women
                    of <place>India</place> to take a special interest in that respect.</p></q>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> New Race Evolving</head>
            <p>
                <q who="TIMES">She concluded.</q> “We believe there is evolving in this world,
                through experiment, a new race. We believe that birth control and eugenic ideas are
                the corner-stones of this new structure.”</p>
            <q who="TIMES"><p> Sir Nusserwanji Choksey, proposing a vote of thanks to the speaker,
                    asserted that birth control was a matter of vital importance to India.</p></q>
            <q who="TIMES"><p> Dr. <person reg="Erulkar, Abraham Solomon">A.S. Erulkar</person>,
                    while thanking Mrs. Sanger, said that he did not agree with her that continence
                    was a method of birth control. As a doctor it was his view that continence in a
                    normal person was not only impossible but positively undesirable.</p></q>
            <p>
                <q who="TIMES">Dr. Miss <person reg="Mistri, Jerbanoo E.">Jerbanoo E.
                        Mistri</person> seconding the vote of thanks, stated that medical women in
                    Bombay thought that self-control was the best and most reliable means of birth
                    control, but that being an ideal artificial birth control was a case of</q>
                <q who="MISJE">“needs must.”</q>
                <q who="TIMES">They did not approve it, however, to the extent of enabling married
                    people to shirk the responsibilities of marriage. She declared that advice on
                    birth control should be given by only qualified doctors and to married women
                    only and that, too, on medical grounds.</q></p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
