<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/05/02 YG</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1923-01-23">23 Jan 1923 </docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Statement on Pronatalist Dictatorships</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421956</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Planned Parenthood Federation Reports a Successful
                    Year</title></bibl>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Chicago Defender</title></bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="CD">Chicago Defender</name>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">Portions of this article, dealing with <org
            reg="Planned Parenthood Federation of America">Planned Parenthood</org>'s activities in
        1942, have not been transcribed. <index level1="birth control" level2="civilization and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="history of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="international"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="morality of"/>
    </headNote>

    <docBody>
        <head>PLANNED PARENTHOOD FEDERATION REPORTS A SUCCESSFUL YEAR.</head>
        <p>How do you fit ‘Birth Control’ into a world in which dictators are clamoring for more and
            more and yet more people?</p>
        <p><q id="CD">In answer to this question, <person>Margaret Sanger</person>, pioneer of
                ‘birth control,’ replied: </q> I can only answer momentum must now derive its power
            from some other source than arousing sympathy. The present insensitivity is due to a
            horror of hovering peril. Man will be swept away and destroyed but when the battered
            hulls of the various ships of state will emerge into calmer seas, a lesson may have been
            learned, perhaps, whereby these vessels may be made more seaworthy.</p>
        <p>To have helped carry the cause thus far has been at times strenuous but I have never
            considered it a sacrifice. Every conscious hour, night and day, in any city, in any
            country, has brought its compensations. My life has been joyous and exulting and full
            because it has touched profoundly millions of other lives. it is ever a privilege to be
            a part of something unquestionably proved of value, something so fundamentally right.
            Battles over impiety, heresy, blasphemy, obscenity, have been fought, temporarily lost
            and finally won. Science whittles away at suchs obstructions little by little. In
            January 1937 in that same <place>Town Hall</place>, where fifteen years before I had
            been forbidden to speak, and whence I had been hauled into court, I was honored with a
            MEDAL.</p>
        <p><person reg="Buck, Pearl S.">Pearl Buck</person>said on one occasion, ‘The cause conquers
            because YOUTH is for you. I have lived in <place>China</place>so long, and know what it
            is to wait until the OLD ONES DIE and the young can do what is necessary to be
            done.’”</p>
        <p/>
    </docBody>
</doc>
