<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-04-15 JK initial tag</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1935-08-16">16 Aug 1935</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Statement on Archbishop John
                    Gregory Murray</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421928</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">"Birth Control Leader Hits at
                    Archbishop"</title>, <title type="journal">Washington
                    Herald</title>, Aug. 16, 1935.</bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="WH">Washington Herald</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>For a related statement, <xref from="421066.xml"
                >Statement on <person reg="Murray, John Gregory">Archbishop John
                    Gregory Murray</person>, Aug. 19, 1935.</xref>
        </p><index
            level1="National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control"
            /><index level1="Catholic Church" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="Catholic Church" level2="birth control and"/><index
            level1="birth control movement"/><index
            level1="American Medical Association"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Birth Control Leader Hits at Archbishop</head>

        <dateline>
            <date value="/----/-08-16"/>Aug. 16, <place reg="Washington, D.C."
                >Washington</place></dateline>
        <p><q who="WH">A bitter attack on <person reg="Murray, John Gregory"
                    >Archbishop Murray’s</person> order that clergy in the <org
                    reg="Archdiocese of St. Paul">St. Paul archdiocese</org>
                announce at August 18 masses that communicants may not retain
                membership in birth control organizations was made here today by
                    <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person> of
                the <org> National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth
                    Control.</org></q></p>
        <p> “If Catholic prelates follow the example of Archbishop John Gregory
            Murray,” she asserted, “Catholics will have to withdraw completely
            and irrevocably from civic, public and professional life.” </p>
        <p>“Catholics,” said Mrs. Sanger, “will soon have to emigrate from
            America to some less enlightened country.”</p>
        <p> “Every Catholic physician who is a member of the <org
                reg="American Gynecological and Obstetrical Society">American
                Gynecological society</org>, the <org
                reg="American Neurological Association">American Neurological
                society</org> and the obstetrical section of the <org>American
                Medical Association</org> will have to sever his connection with
            these professional groups, (if Catholic prelates follow Archbishop
            Murray’s lead) for they indorse the principles of birth control,”
            she charged.</p>
        <p>
            <q who="WH">Defending the Americanism of the birth control movement,
                Mrs. Sanger asserted it originated in this country.</q></p>
        <p>“But the anti-birth control movement,” she charged, “takes its orders
            from <place reg="Vatican City, Italy">Rome</place>. When these
            orders call for the repudiation of the findings of science, for
            attempts to impose the will of minorities on majority groups, and
            for withdrawal from activity in community life, it is time to
            inquire which line of conduct is the more truly American.” </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
