<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "file:/S:/TRANSCRIPTIONS/XML%20Drafts/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/07/08 MM</prepDate>
        <docAuthor><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret
            Sanger</person></docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1952-11-11 ">11 Nov 1952</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Speech to the <org>Hong Kong Family Planning
                    Association</org></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421967</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">South China Morning Post</title>
                11/12/1952</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">Sanger addressed the <place>Hong Kong</place> Family
        Planning Association at St. John's Cathedral Hall. Professor <person
            reg="King, Gordon">Gordon King</person> introduced her. <index
            level1="Hong Kong Family Planning Association"/><index
            level1="overpopulation"/><index level1="birth control"
            level2="international"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>FAMILY PLANNING</head>
        <byline>Mrs. Margaret Sanger's Lecture On Birth Control</byline>
        <byline>A GREAT RESPONSIBILITY</byline>
        <byline>A plea for birth control as the most practical means for
            regulating population in accordance with economics and hygiene was
            made by Mrs Margaret Sanger, internationally-famous authority on the
            subject, in a lecture sponsored by the Hongkong Family Planning
            Association at St. John's Cathedral Hall yesterday.</byline>
        <p>In the talk she repeated most of the opinions she has held for a
            number of years, and which she had occasion recently to expound in
                <place> Japan</place>.</p>
        <p>She described birth control as the conscious control of the birth
            rate by means of prevention of conception, in accordance with the
            fundamental need to consider the mother's heath, the father's
            economic potentialities, the environment of the offspring and their
            proper place in society.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger denied the argument of some religious circles who claimed
            that birth control meant the murder of children. She said that
            prevention of conception involved no interference with life, as no
            life began until conception had taken place. This was strictly in
            accordance with the facts of biology.</p>
        <p>She said she was delighted to note the sound organisation and
            leadership of the Hongkong Family Planning Association because of
            the significant nature of its work, and appealed for more support
            for it.</p>
        <p>She deplored the current trend towards over-population with its
            attendant deterioration of national health and hygiene, poising the
            inference that birth control really meant a striving for better
            national welfare.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger said that in the case of mothers their periods of
            pregnancy should be so spaced that no danger to health from such
            ailments as tuberculosis could be incurred, and among younger
            people, all the aspects of family responsibility should be fully
            considered and appreciated before the arrival of the first baby.</p>
        <p/>
    </docBody>
</doc>
