<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "file:/S:/TRANSCRIPTIONS/XML%20Drafts/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published statement">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/07/08 MM</prepDate>
        <docAuthor><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret
            Sanger</person></docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1954-04-28">28 Apr 1954</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Press Statement at the Moana
                    Hotel</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421970</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>"<title type="article">Birth Control Leader Finds
                        <place>Japan</place> Receiptive</title>"<title
                    type="journal">Honolulu Advertiser</title>04/29/1954, p.
                a9:1</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">Sanger discusses her recent address to the Japanese
        Diet at a mess conference at the Moana Hotel in <place
            reg="Honolulu, HI">Honolulu</place><index level1="Sanger, Margaret"
            level2="speaking tours" level3="1954 (Japan)"/><index level1="Japan"
            level2="overpopulation and"/><index level1="Japan"
            level2="population policies of"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Birth Control Leader Finds Japan Receiptive</head>
        <p>The woman who coined the phrase "birth control" broke a centuries old
            precedent in Japan a few days ago.</p>
        <p>She is Mrs. Margaret Sanger slee, president of the <org>International
                Planned Parenthood Federation</org>. Mrs. Slee arrived in
            Honolulu by Japan Air Lines late Tuesday.</p>
        <p>On April 15, she stood in the old House of Peers, now the Japanese
            House of Councillors, to discuss their over population problem. The
            first foreign woman to appear before the Diet, Mrs. Sanger said she
            was enthusiastically received.</p>
        <div>
            <p>"EVEN THE disturbance and criticism caused by the H-bomb
                explosion did not interfere with my work," Mrs. Slee said at the
                Moana motel yesterday. "But you can feel the attitude of the
                Japanese in the press and the personal questions put to me.</p>
            <p>"In the House of Councillors, the Japanese wanted to know why
                Americans did not protest to their government the H-bomb
                experiments. They countered with "<soCalled>the British are
                    protesting to their parliament, why don't
                you?</soCalled>"</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <p>MRS. SLEE made the air journey to Japan accompanied by her
                secretary-interpreter, Mrs.<person reg="Hara, Chieko"> Chieko
                    Hara</person> of <place>New York</place>. The purpose, to
                consult with leaders of the Planned Parenthood movement to see
                if Japan is strong enough nationally for Mrs. Slee, as
                president, to accept the invitation for the October, 1955,
                international meeting. </p>
            <p>What they lack in organization, the Japanese make up in sympathy
                and enthusiasm. Mrs. Slee has approved the international
                conference in Japan. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <p>AS SHE STOOD in the House of Councillors, Mrs. Slee said the
                questions flew thick and fast. The flash bulbs popped in the
                hands of at least 20 photographers. They represented English as
                well as Japanese newspapers.</p>
            <p>"It was like Hollywood," the dynamic little birth control banner
                carrier said.</p>
            <p>For two and one half hours the questions came, not only from one
                man, but from the women. One, also a midwife, said she spoke for
                30,000 other Japanese midwives. She saught enformation on
                setting up clinics, how they were financed, was knowledge
                availible to everyone?</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <p>A QUESTION was posed by one man. </p>
            <p>"<q>Is religion a barrier in this movement?</q>" he queried.</p>
            <p>Mrs. Slee said she gave a lengthy answer to this one. She told
                them that "God gave us intelligence and it is the responsibility
                of every adult man and woman to use this intelligence. Our first
                responsibility is when man creates a child and brings it into
                the world."</p>
            <p>"They seemed pleased with this answer," Mrs. Slee said.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <p>ANOTHER COUNCILLOR said he considered population Japan's most
                pertinent problem and asked "<q>advice from an expert.</q>"</p>
            <p>"I told them the whole movement has moved into the medical,
                public health, welfare, demography, and laboratory field. There
                is no need for Japan to have 100 million people in 10 years as
                prophesied. The answer lies in individual insttruction as in the
                three villages used for demonstration purposes.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <p>MRS. SLEE said that 1,300,000 babies were born in Japan last
                year, but at least 1,500,000 women submitted to abortions. A
                eugenic law passed in Japan during the occupation permits
                abortion as well as the use of contraceptives. Mrs. Slee hopes
                that education will lessen the need for such clinics, to improve
                the humane aspect as well as material health.</p>
            <p>The population expert attended a meeting of 800 Japanese women in
                    <place reg="Tokyo, Japan">Tokyo</place>'s vast Hibiya hall.
                She heard them discuss their lot under their new status.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <p>"THEY ARE PROUD of the advances gained since 1947 when centuries
                of tradition were swept aside and Japanese women were placed, at
                least legally, on the same footing with their men. They have
                made greate strides, particularly in education, in the spread of
                women's suffrage. Now we hope to have their help in our work in
                population control." Mrs. Slee said. </p>
            <p>She remains here until May 6, when she flies to <place
                    reg="San Francisco, CA">San Francisco</place> to meet with
                    <place>California</place> groups who have organized under
                Planned Parnethood.</p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
