<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published pamphlet">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014/06/24 MM</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-12-18 CH correct and enter tags</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1920-00-00">
			<supplied resp="MSPP">1920</supplied>
		</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>Legislating Women's Morals</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp421980</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
			<bibl>Library of Congress Microfilm 129:183</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<name id="FRE">French</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP"><p>This was Chapter 14 of <title type="book">Woman and the New
				Race</title>, pp. 186-197, reprinted in pamphlet form.</p>
		<index level1="Comstock, Anthony"/>
		<index level1="Comstock Laws"/>
		<index level1="obscenity"/><index level1="poverty" level2="family size and"/></headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>LEGISLATING WOMEN'S MORALS</head>
		<head type="sub">"Woman and the New Race"</head>
		<byline>By Margaret Sanger.</byline>
		<p>ONE of the important duties before those women who are demanding birth control as a means
			to a New Race is the changing of our so-called obscenity laws.</p>
		<p>Enacted, avowedly, to protect society against the obscene and the lewd, they make no
			distinction between the scientific works of human emancipators like <person
				reg="Forel, Auguste">Forel</person> and <person reg="Ellis, Havelock">Ellis</person>
			and printed matter such as they are ostensibly aimed at. Naturally enough, then,
			detectives and narrow-minded judges and prosecutors who would chuckle over pictures that
			would make a clean-minded woman shudder, unite to suppress the scientific works and the
			birth-control treatises which would enable men and women to attain higher physical,
			mental, moral and spiritual standards.</p>
		<p>Woman, bent upon her freedom and seeking to make a better world, will not permit the
			indecent and unclean forces of reaction to mask themselves forever behind the plea that
			it is necessary to keep her in ignorance to preserve her purity. In the birth-control
			movement, she has already begun to fight for her right to have, without legal
			interference, all knowledge pertaining to her sex nature. </p>
		<p>Within a few years the tragic combination of false moral standards and infamous obscenity
			laws will be as ridiculous in the public mind as are the now all but forgotten blasphemy
			laws. If the obscenity laws are not radically revised or repealed, few reactionaries
			will dare to face the public derision that will greet their attempts to use them to stay
			woman's progress.</p>
		<p>The French have a saying concerning "<foreign lang="FRE">mort main</foreign>'"--the dead
			hand. This hand of the past reaches up into the present to smother the rising flame of
			modern ideals, to reforge our chains when we have broken them, to arrest progress. It is
			the hand of such as have lived on earth but have not lived humanity. At the call of
			those who fear progress and freedom, it rises from the gloom of forgotten things to
			oppress the lviing. </p>
		<p>It is the dead hand that holds imprisoned within the obscenity laws all direct
			information concerning birth control.</p>
		<p>Previous to the year 1868, the obscenity laws of the various states in the <place
				reg="United States">Union</place> contained no specific prohibition of information
			concerning contraceptives. In that year, however, the <org
				reg="New York State General Assembly">General Assembly of New York</org> passed an
			act which specifically included the subject of contraceptives. The act made it exactly
			as great an offense to give such information as to exhibit the sort of pictures and
			writings at which the legislation was ostensibly aimed</p>
		<p>In 1873, the late <person reg="Comstock, Anthony">Anthony Comstock</person>, who with a
			list of contributors, most of whom did not realzie the real effects of his work,
			constituted the so-called <org reg="New York Society for the Suppression of Vice"
				>Society for the Suppresssion of Vice</org>, succeeded in obtaining the passage of
			the <name type="law" reg="United States Criminal Code, Section 211">federal obscenity
				act</name>. This act was presented as one to prevent the circulation of pornographic
			literature and pictures among school children. As such, it was rushed through with two
			hundred sixty other acts in the closing hours of <org reg="United States Congress"
				>Congress</org>. This act made it a crime to use the mails to convey contraceptives
			or information concerning contraceptives. Other acts later made the original law
			applicable to express companies and other common carriers, as well as to the mails. </p>
		<p>With this precedent established--a precedent which a majority of the congressmen could
			hardly have understood because of the hasty passage of the act--Comstock secured the
			enactment of state laws to the same effect. Meanwhile, the provisions regarding
			contraceptives had been dropped from the amended <place>New York</place> State law of
			1872. In 1873, however, a new section, said to have been drafted by Comstock himself,
			was substituted for the one enacted in 1872, and that section is essentially the
			substance of the present law. None of these acts made it an offense to prevent
			conception--all of them provided punishment for anyone disseminating information
			concerning the prevention of conception. In the federal statutes, the maximum penalties
			were fixed at a fine of $5,000 or five years imprisonment, or both. The usual maximum
			penalty under a state law is a fine of $1,000 or one year's imprisonment, or both.</p>
		<p>Comstock has passed out of public notice. His body has been entombed but the evil that he
			did lives after him. His dead hand still reaches forth to keep the subject of prevention
			of conception where he placed it--in the same legal category with things unclean and
			vile. Forty years ago the laws were changed and the chief work of Comstock's life
			accomplished. <emph rend="bold"> Those laws still live, legal monuments to ignorance and
				to oppression. Through those laws reaches the dead hand to bring to the operating
				table each year hundreds of thousands of women who undergo the agony of abortion.
				Each year this hand reaches out to compel the birth of hundreds of thousands of
				infants who must die before they are twelve months old.</emph></p>
		<p>Like many laws upon our statute books, these are being persistently and intelligently
			violated. Few members of the well-to-do and wealthy classes think for a single moment of
			obeying them. They limit their families to one, two or three well-cared-for-children.
			Usually the prosecutor who presents the case against a birth-control-advocate, trapped
			by a detective hired by Cosmtock society, has no children at all or just a small family.
			The family of the judge who passes upon the case is likely to be smaller still. The
			words "It is the law" sums it all up for these officials when they pass sentence in
			court. But these words, so magical to the official mind, have no weight when these same
			officials are adjusting their own private lives. They then obey the higher laws of their
			own beings--they break the obsolete statutes for themselves while enforcing them for
			others.</p>
		<p><emph rend="bold">This is not the situation with the poorer people of the United States,
				however. Millions of them know nothing of reliable contraceptives.</emph> When women
			of the impoverished strata of society do not break these laws against contraceptives,
			they violate those laws of their inner beings which tell them not to bring children into
			the world to live in want, disease and general misery. They break the first law of
			nature, which is that of self preservation. Bound by false morals, enchained by false
			conceptions of religion, hindered by false laws, they endure until the pressure becomes
			so great that morals, religion and laws alike fail to restrain them. Then they for a
			brief respite resort to the surgeon's instruments.</p>
		<p>For many years the semi-official witch hunting of the Comstock organization had a
			remarkable and a deadly effect. Everyone, whether it was novelist, essayist, publicist,
			propagandist or artist, who sought to throw definite light upon the forbidden subject of
			sex, or upon family limitation, was prosecuted if detected. Among the many books
			suppressed were works of physicians designed to warn young men and women away from the
			pitfalls of veneral diseases and sexual errors. The darkness that surrounded the whole
			field of sex was made as complete as possible.</p>
		<p>Since then the feeling of the awakened women of America has intensified. The rapidity
			with which women are going into industry, the increasing hardship and poverty of the
			lower strata of society, the arousing of public conscience, have all operated to give
			force and volume to the demand for woman's right to control her own body that she may
			work out her own salvation.</p>
		<p>
			<emph rend="bold">Those who believe in strictly legal measures, as well as those who
				believe both in legal measures and in open defiance of these brutal and unjust laws,
				are demanding amendments to the obscenity statutes, which shall remove inforamtion
				concerning contraceptives from its present classification among things filthy and
				obscene.</emph>
		</p>
		<p>
			<emph rend="bold">Shall we go on indefinitely driving the now healthy mother of two
				children into the hands of the abortionist, where she goes in preference to constant
				ill health, overwork and the witnessign of dying and starving babies? It is each
				woman's duty to herself and to society to hasten the repeal of all laws against the
				communication of birth-control information. Now that she has the vote, she should
				use her political influence to strike, first of all, at these restrictive statutes.
			</emph>
		</p>
		<p>
			<emph rend="bold">It is time that women assert themseleves upon this fundamental right,
				and the first and best use they can make of the ballot is in this direction. These
				laws were made by men and have been instruments of martyrdom and death for
				unnumbered thousands of women.</emph>
		</p>
		<p>
			<emph rend="bold">The law of woman's being is stronger than any statute, and the
				man-made law must sooner or later give way to it. Man has not protected women in
				matters most vital to her-- but she is awaking and will sooner or later realize this
				and assert herself. If she acts in mass now, it will be another cheering evidence
				that she is moving consciously toward her goal.</emph>
		</p>
		<p/>
	</docBody>
</doc>
