<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/04/23 VS initial tags</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1939-03-01"> 1 March, 1939</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Mothers Health Clinic Speech</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421941</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Immunization Against Pregnancy Aim Of Birth Control
                    Federation of U.S.</title><title type="journal"> El Paso Herald Post</title>
                March 2, 1939</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="EPHP">El Paso Herald Post</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Sanger spoke to social welfare workers at the El Paso Mother's Health
            Center on March 1, 1939.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="population and"/>
        <index level1="Birth Control Federation of America"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="decline in"/>
        <index level1="children" level2="education of"/>
        <index level1="children" level2="rights of"/>
        <index level1="sterilization" level2="methods of"/>
        <index level1="birth control methods"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Immunization Against Pregnancy Aim Of Birth Control Federation of <place
                reg="United States">U.S.</place></head>
        <div>
            <q who="EPHP"><p>
                    <org>The Birth Control Federation of America</org> is now working on temporary
                    immunization against pregnancy, Mrs. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret
                        Sanger</person> told a group of social welfare workers and <org
                        reg="El Paso Mother's Health Center">Mother’s Health Center</org> directors
                    at a meeting at the Health Center yesterday. There were 25 present.</p></q>
            <q who="EPHP"><p> Mrs. Sanger conferred with workers, representing the various agencies
                    in <place reg="El Paso, TX">El Paso</place>, on local problems. She discussed
                    the progress of birth control in the United States and foreign
                countries.</p></q>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Praises Center</head>
            <p> “Immunization for a temporary period against pregnancy is not far distant,” <q
                    who="EPH">Mrs. Sanger said.</q> “Research is going forward in this field. The
                Birth Control Federation of America is for this. It will be a wonderful day when it
                comes.”</p>
            <q who="EPHP"><p> Mrs. Sanger said that sterilization of all persons with mental
                    diseases of any kind, of syphilitics or persons with any transmissible disease
                    should be provided for in the laws of every state.</p></q>
            <p> “Sterilization should go hand in hand with any preventive work,” <q who="EPHP">she
                    said.</q></p>
            <q who="EPHP"><p> She praised the work of the El Paso Mother’s Health Center to the
                    social workers and asked for their co-operation with the Center.</p></q>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> California Ready</head>
            <p> “<place>California</place> is ready to take up the question of birth control with
                the welfare workers,” <q who="EPHP">Mrs. Sanger said.</q> “There will be no official
                opposition. Governor <person reg="Olson, Culbert Levy">Olson</person> is heartily in
                accord with the idea. California will do a good work. <place>Tennessee</place> is
                next.”</p>
            <q who="EPHP"><p> Mrs. Sanger said that she recently visited the project in California
                    where 43,000 families are provided for by the Federal Government in a
                    reservation while they are occupied with seasonal labor.</p></q>
            <p> “The asked me to come out there and see about establishing birth control clinics
                among these people,” <q who="EPHP">Mrs. Sanger said.</q> “I found that clinics of
                the kind we have here in El Paso would not be possible with this group because of
                the lack of facilities for a setup. But birth control information will be given to
                them.”</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> New Dealer</head>
            <q who="EPHP"><p> Mrs. Sanger praised the governmental provision for the families she
                    visited.</p></q>
            <p> “It almost made a New Dealer of me,” <q who="EPHP">she said.</q> “It is wonderful
                what the Government is doing for those families.”</p>
            <q who="EPHP"><p> Mrs. Sanger cited the “new population scare” that by 1960 there will
                    be a stationary population and by 1980, a decline and that there will be fewer
                    infants and children for primary grades while a larger number of older
                    people.</p></q>
            <p> “This means that people living today are taking better care of themselves and will
                live longer,” <q who="EPHP">she said.</q> “More young people can marry and have two
                or three children while older ones will have ceased to bear after the second or
                third child.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Will Survive</head>
            <p> “It means that children born in a small family will survive through infancy and
                childhood and have better facilities for trade schools or colleges. With a
                stationary population our standard of living will soar upward. We will have an
                opportunity to assimilate into the American system those who are alive today. We’ll
                have a lower death rate, less unemployment. There will be fewer hands to compete
                with the machines for jobs. America is coming into an era where purely physical
                labor will not be an asset. She needs superior brains, high intellects, more
                integrity in politics and in administration of public health and welfare
                activities.”</p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
