<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="(Published Speech)">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/07/01 CH proof tags</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1956-05-31">31 May 1956</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Speech to the Planned Parenthood Center of Buffalo</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421991</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Mrs. Sanger Reports on Visit to Asia</title>, <title type="journal">Buffalo
                    Courier-Express</title>, May 31, 1956, p. 9</bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="BCE"/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <index level1="Japan" level2="overpopulation and"/>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">Sanger spoke to the annual luncheon of the Planned Parenthood Center of
        Buffalo at the Hotel Statler, 107 Delaware Ave. 14202. Other speakers included <person
            reg="Abbott, Lois P.">Lois P. Abbott</person> and <person reg="Greenberger, Jane">Jane
            Greenberger.</person><index level1="xxxx"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="overpopulation and"/>
        <index level1="International Planned Parenthood Federation"/>
        <index level1="eugenics" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="eugenics" level2="positive"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Mrs. Sanger</person> Reports On Visit to
                <place>Asia</place></head>
        <q who="BCE"><p>Population problems in <place>Japan</place> and <place>India</place> are
                being met by the governments in a realistic way, Mrs. Margaret Sanger said here
                yesterday. She spoke at the annual luncheon of the <org>Planned Parenthood Center of
                        <place reg="Buffalo, NY">Buffalo</place></org> at <org>Hotel
                Statler.</org></p>
            <p>Mrs. Sanger, president of the <org>International Planned Parenthood Federation</org>
                visited Japan and India in 1954 and spoke before the <org>House of Peers</org> in
                Japan. She predicted that if the present plans are carried out Japan and India will
                be in two generations "the most culturally and eugenically advanced countries in the
                world."</p>
            <p><div type="section">
                    <head type="sub">Industry's Aid</head>
                </div></p>
            <p>In India, she said, each medical school will teach the subject of family planning,
                industry will disseminate all available information to the workers and social
                agencies are instructed to give all the information possible in their work.</p></q>
        <p rend="MSPP">The remainder of the article, which did not deal with Sanger's appearance, was not included.</p>


    </docBody>
</doc>
