<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="(Published Article) ">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/04/11 YG</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="(1937-02-18) ">18 Feb 1937</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Interview with the Arizona Republic</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421913</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>The Arizona Republic</title></bibl>
            <bibl><title>MSM</title></bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="AR">The Arizona Republic</name>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">Sanger was staying in <place reg="Chandler, Arizona">Chandler,
            Arizona</place>at the <place reg="Hotel San Marcos">Hotel San Marcos</place> when the
        interview was conducted. <index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="in Arizona"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="and marriage"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="medical community and"/>
    </headNote>

    <docBody>
        <div>
            <head><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">MARGARET SANGER</person>, AWARD WINNER, HERE; PLANS
                BIRTH CONTROL CLINIC</head>
        </div>
        <div>
            <p>Resting briefly after the most decisive battle in a career which has been unceasing
                war waged on a front which ranged from crowded tenement districts to <org
                    reg="United States Senate">U.S. senate</org> committee rooms, Margaret Sanger,
                noted birth control crusader, is a visit in the <place reg="Phoenix, Arizona">Salt
                    River valley</place>.</p>
            <p>With her husband, <person reg="Slee, James Noah H.">J. Noah N. Slee</person>, retired
                president of the <org reg="3-in-1 Oil Company">3-in-1 Oil Company</org>, who has
                been vacationing in the valley for some time, she is a guest at Hotel San Marcos in
                Chandler and will remain in <place>Arizona</place> for several weeks.</p>
            <p>Shortly before leaving her <place reg="Fishkill, New York">Fishkill, N.Y.</place>home
                for Arizona, she was honored at a dinner by the <org
                    reg="Town Hall, New York, New York">Town Hall Club of Manhattan</org>, composed
                of social elite of the East, and was presentred with the club's award of honor for
                the year's most conspicuous contribution to the enlargement and enrichment of life.
                The award was made January 15.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Court Rules Favorably</head>
        </div>
        <div>
            <p>From prison to palace Mrs. Sanger since 1914 has carried her crusade to permit the
                dissemination of scientific information which would enable parents to limit their
                families to a number for which they can care properly. On December 7, the <org
                    reg="United States Circuit Court of Appeals">U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals</org>
                removed the greatest obstacle in the way of success of the crusade when it ruled
                that physicians might send contraceptives by mail. This decision nullified a
                63-year-old law which made sending such material by mail or common carrier a crime
                punishable by $5,000 fine and five years in prison. The court ruling also gives
                physicians the right to advise their patients when they deem it necessary for their
                general health and well-being.</p>
            <p>A measure embodying much the same idea introduced into the last session of congress
                with the support of the <org reg="General Federation of Women's Clubs">General
                    Federation of Women's Clubs</org>, the <org
                    reg="National Federation of Business and Women's Professional Clubs">National
                    Federation of Business and Professional Clubs</org>, <org
                    reg="the Young Women's Christian Association">the Young Women's Christian
                    Association</org> and other large groups, died in <org
                    reg="Senate Judiciary Committee">the senate judiciary committee</org>, of which
                    <person reg="Ashurst, Henry Fountain">Sen. Henry F. Ashurst</person>of Arizona
                is chairman.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Crusader Still Active</head>
        </div>
        <div>
            <p>Elated over the victory which the court ruling gave the cause to which she has
                devoted much of her life, Mrs. Sanger has no thought of ceasing her efforts. Rather,
                two weeks after the verdict she celebrated with a birth control conference in <place
                    reg="New York, New York">Manhattan</place>, and during her stay here she plans
                the establishment of a birth control clinic in <place reg="Phoenix, Arizona"
                    >Phoenix</place>. Such a clinic would be operated along the same lines as the
                one opened in Tucson last June.</p>
            <p>Improvement of the race through the limitation of families to a number for which the
                parents can provide proper physical, mental and spiritual support and lessening of
                the tax burden through reducing the number of indigents to be provided for from
                public funds are two important results which Mrs. Sanger expects from wide-spreadh
                birth control. She believes it also will reduce that some authorities refer to as
                the abortion “racket.”</p>
            <p>“Add to that- call it sentimentality if you will- the happiness of the man and woman
                who, loving each other enough to marry, find themselves bound to the wheel in order
                to provide even the bare necessities for an ever-increasing brood. The mother, her
                strength sapped by constant child-bearing and attempts to care for her children, and
                the father, tired and careworn with the economic battle, have no times for that real
                companionship which is a right of marriage.</p>
        </div>

        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Holds Happiness Important</head>
            <p>“Human happiness IS important. It must be, else our forefathers who wrote the
                constitution would not have included ‘pursuit of happiness’ among the inalienable
                rights. “Society at large is adversely affected by addition to it of children for
                whom there is no chance of proper development. Families so large that the parents
                cannot care for them become the burden of the taxpayer who must provide funds for
                their care. Crime, too, breeds in the crowded districts, and again the taxpayers and
                citizens at large are the losers.” </p>
            <p>More than 320 clinics have been established in the United States through the efforts
                of the dynamic little crusader, and her work has not stopped on this side of the
                    <place reg="Atlantic Ocean">Atlantic</place>. Last year she spread her gospel in
                    <place>India</place>, <place>Switzerland</place>, <place reg="Soviet Union"
                    >Russia</place>, <place>Canada</place> and <place>England</place> all know of
                Margaret Sanger.</p>
            <p>Foreign nations-with the exception of <place>Italy</place>and
                <place>Germany</place>and other military nations “where men are only cannon fodder
                and women sources of war material” - are friendly toward the birth control movement,
                Mrs. Sanger said. In England clinics are established under the jurisdiction of the
                government and doctors must provide the information. Other nations have similar
                setups.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head>Compliments Phoenician</head>
        </div>
        <div>
            <p> “One trouble in the United States has been,” Mrs. Sanger said, “that physicians
                themselves do not all know proper contraceptive methods. Medical schools have not
                trained students in contraception. Even now only five schools so train their embryo
                physicians.”</p>
            <p>Mrs. Sanger paid high tribute to <person reg="Struckmeyer, Fritzi">Fritzi
                    Struckmeyer</person> as the first woman in any state legislature or in congress
                to "have the courage to introduce legislation which would remove obstacles to the
                movement which means so much to their own se." Last week, Miss Struckmeyer, serving
                her first term as a member of the <org reg="13th Arizona State Legislature">13th
                    legislature</org>, introduced such a bill.</p>
            <p>Asked concerning activity of women in office in support of the movement, Mrs. Sanger
                expressed disappointment, saying it has been phraseology only with little actual
                support. To woman’s newness in official positions she attributes this attitude,
                believing that in many instances they have not gained the poise necessary to
                publicly espouse a movement which might prove unpopular.</p>
            <p>She does believe ardently that women's influence in legislative matters is making
                itself felt, to the benefit of the nation. Women on juries have been an active
                influence toward lceaning up the courts and influencing justice, she believes.,
                expressing surprise at Arizona's continued attitude of banning women from jury
                service.</p>
            <p>The fact that Arizona has the highest maternal and infant mortality rate of any state
                in the union except <place reg="New Mexico">New Mexico</place>she characterized as
                "ridiculous - and unnessary."</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Gracious Personality</head>
        </div>
        <div>
            <p>Looking back over Margaret Sanger's career and realizing that it has carried her into
                court many times, put her in prison and placed her before senate committees, it
                would be, for one who has not met her easy to imagine her the "Amazon type" woman.
                Nothing could be farther from a true description.</p>
            <p>Gracious, vital, there is about her a sweetness which inspires belief in her
                sincerity when in answer to the question, “But how is it with you? Truly the fight
                is well on the way to being won-- but at what a personal sacrifice to you! Has it
                been worth it, personally?”, she answered, “A hundred fold. I feel that instead of
                being given the award of honor I should have given it. There is a great sense of
                peace in fulfilling one’s destiny.” </p>
            <p>The red of her hair has been subdued somewhat by a generous sprinkling of gray - for
                    <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Higgins</person> was born in 1883 - but
                there is no lessening of the fire with which she champions her cause. Her sparkling
                wit and quick perception, a heritage from Irish-born parents, highlight a magnetic
                personality.</p>
            <p>She is the mother of two sons, one of whom is a practicing physician and the other
                studying to become a doctor. Her only daughter she lost through death.</p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
