<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Publishe article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/04/16 VS initial tags</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1937-01-17 ">17 January, 1937</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Overpopulation: A Cause of War</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421919</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Urges Birth Control To Keep World Peace</title><title
                    type="journal">New York Times</title> January 18, 1937</bibl>
            <bibl><title type="article">Overcrowding Peril Discussed By Mrs. Sanger</title><title
                    type="journal">Washington Post</title> January 18, 1937</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="NYT">New York Times</name>
            <name id="WP">Washington Post</name>
            <name id="LUBIS">Lubin, Isador</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">Sanger spoke at the Washington Town Hall, the event also featured Rev.
        Russel J. Clinchy and Frederick C. Howe. Text is drawn from coveratge in <title
            type="journal">New York Times</title> and <title type="journal">Washington Post</title>.
            <index level1="birth control" level2="and war"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="war and"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="population growth and"/>
        <index level1="Italy" level2="overpopulation and"/>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="overpopulation and"/>
        <index level1="overpopulation" level2="threat to peace as"/>
        <index level1="population" level2="war and"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="population growth in"/>
        <index level1="Germany" level2="population policies of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Urges Birth Control to Keep World Peace</head>
        <dateline>Jan. 17 <date value="1937/01/1937"/> and <place reg="Washington, D.C."
                >Washington</place></dateline>
        <div>
            <q who="NYT"><p> Asserting that rapidly increasing populations of
                    <place>Germany</place>, <place>Italy</place> and <place>Japan</place> are a
                    menace to peace because of the “inevitable need” for territorial expansion, Mrs.
                        <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person> pleaded tonight
                    before a <org>Washington Town Hall</org> audience that birth control was
                    necessary if world peace was to be assured. </p></q>
            <q who="NYT"><p> The international leader of the birth-control movement scored the
                    motives of Chancellor <person reg="Hitler, Adolf">Hitler</person> and Premier
                        <person reg="Mussolini, Benito">Mussolini</person> in urging population
                    increases in their countries. She declared that war was inevitable unless the
                    rapid gain in births was halted. </p></q>
            <p>
                <q who="NYT">Mrs. Sanger said health officials estimated that 3.1 acres were needed
                    to produce food and clothing necessary for one person to live ideally; 1.8 acres
                    necessary for health, and 1.2 acres were absolutely necessary for existence. She
                    pointed out that, within a few years, the tillable land in the three countries
                    would not be sufficient to sustain life properly, and then, she added,</q> “the
                explosion will come.” <q who="NYT">Japan’s “seizure” of <place>Manchukuo</place> and
                    Italy’s conquest of <place>Ethiopia</place>, she said, were necessary for them
                    to acquire the land to sustain the populations and offer some outlet for their
                    surplus populations.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
                <q who="NYT">In so far as the <place>United States</place> was concerned, Mrs.
                    Sanger said, of the 4,500,000 births recorded during the present depression, 65
                    per cent came in families on relief. She declared that</q> “relief is not a
                temporary situation,” <q who="NYT">and that the problem could be best solved through
                    birth control.</q></p>
            <p> “We have increased that strata of our population that we do not need,” <q who="NYT"
                    >she said.</q></p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head> Overcrowding Peril Discussed by Mrs. Sanger</head>
            <q who="WP"><p> Birth control, crop control, the machine age and the slaughter of the
                    AAA’s little pigs were debated last night at the Town Hall of Washington after
                    Mrs. Margaret Sanger spoke on “Overpopulation- A Cause of War.”</p></q>
            <q who="WP"><p> Mrs. Sanger called for a 25-year moratorium on population increase in
                    the world as a method of assuring peace, but members of the discussion panel
                    contended that redistribution of natural resources and more efficient methods of
                    distributing the products of industry was the solution. </p></q>
            <q who="WP"><p> Contending that warlike tendencies in Germany, Italy and Japan were the
                    result of overpopulation, Mrs. Sanger advocated making birth control an
                    important function of every State and municipal health department. She warned
                    that the world is approaching the day when it cannot support its population.
                </p></q>
            <p>
                <q who="WP"><person reg="Lubin, Isador">Isador Lubin</person>, commissioner of
                        <org>Labor Statistics, Department of Labor</org>, declared the world has not
                    yet begun to intelligently approach the problem of supporting its
                    population.</q>
                <q who="LUBIS">“We have a fetish that everyone should work all of the time,”</q>
                <q who="WP">he said.</q>
                <q who="LUBIS">“We must utilize the full capacity of industrial machines and to
                    distribute work and income that persons could retire early and live
                well.”</q></p>
            <q who="WP"><p> Both Lubin and Mrs. Sanger agreed that while crops were being plowed
                    under and pigs slaughtered in this country because of “overproduction,” the
                    farmers were not producing enough to support the population.</p></q>
            <q who="WP"><p> The Rev. <person reg="Clinchy, Russell J.">Russell J. Clinchy</person>,
                    pastor of the <org>Mount Pleasant Congregational Church</org>, said the
                    intelligent approach to birth control called for discarding the theory that
                    relations between married couples not intended to produce children were carnal.
                </p></q>
            <q who="WP"><p> The audience cut short a speech by <person reg="Howe, Frederick C."
                        >Frederick C. Howe</person>, special assistant to the <org
                        reg="United States Secretary of Agriculture">Secretary of Agriculture</org>,
                    while he was contending that lust for power was responsible for wars and
                    advocating restricting the freedom of the press. The audience demanded Howe put
                    his remarks in a question to Mrs. Sanger. </p></q>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
