<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="(Published Statement)">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/07/01 CH proof tags</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1958-09-13">13 Sep. 1958</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Statement on the New York City Hospital Ban on Birth Control</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421988</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">At 71, Mrs. Sanger Scores Dr. Jacobs</title>, <title type="journal">New York
                    Times</title>, Sept. 14, 1958, p. 59</bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="NYT">New York Times</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><index level1="Catholic Church" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="New York" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="conferences" level2="International Conference on Planned Parenthood"
            level3="1958 (6th)"/>
        <index level1="International Planned Parenthood Federation"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="religion and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="opposition to"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>AT 71, MRS. SANGER SCORES DR. JACOBS</head>
        <byline>By <person reg="Asbury, Edith Evans">EDITH EVANS ASBURY</person></byline>
        <q who="NYT"><p><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger,</person> founder of the
                birth control movement in the <place>United States,</place> said yesterday she was</q>
                "delighted at the leadership taken by the different religions in defense of birth
                control" <q who="NYT">in the controversial city hospital policy.</p></q>
        <p>"It comes a little late, but it is never too late," <q who="NYT">Mrs. Sanger said. She
                was interviewed by telephone on the eve of her seventy-first birthday, which she
                will celebrate today.</q></p>
        <q who="NYT"><p>Mrs. Sanger lives in <place reg="Tucson, AZ">Tucson,</place>
                Ariz.,</place> next door to her son, <person reg="Sanger, Stuart">Dr. Stuart
                    Sanger.</person> Another son, <person reg="Sanger, Grant">Dr. Grant
                    Sanger</person> of <place reg="Mount Kisco, NY">Mount Kisco,</place> reached
                Tucson yesterday to join the birthday celebration.</p>
            <p>Mrs. Sanger said it was time the fight for birth control was not leftM</q> "to those of us
                in <org>Planned Parenthood</org> who have been fighting all these years."</p>
            <q who="NYT"><p>Mrs. Sanger faced strong opposition and was even sentenced to jail, when, as a young
                nurse in <place reg="New York, NY">New York City,</place> she sought to disseminate
                birth control information.</p>
            <p>She was moved to action by dismay over young mothers in the slums. She said they were
                overburdened by more children than they were physically able to bear or care
                for.</p></q>
        <p>"Laws have changed since then, and public opinion has changed, but the fight must still
            go on, because we still have strong opposition," she said yesterday.</p>
        <p>"I am amazed that New York City, where I founded the <org reg="Brownsville Clinic">first birth control clinic</org> in the
            country, is still so backward. I have just come back from <place reg="Honolulu, Hawaii"
                >Honolulu,</place> where they have birth control therapy in city hospitals. Imagine,
            more advanced than New York!"</p>
        <q who="NYT"><p>Mrs. Sanger said she believed that the public airing of the controversy in
                New York City would prove</q> "beneficial to all, including the Catholics." <q who="NYT">She
                described the ban on birth control therapy in city hospitals by <person
                    reg="Jacobs, Morris A.">Dr. Morris A. Jacobs,</person> Commissioner of
                Hospitals, as a </q> "disgraceful policy."</p>
        <p>"Many catholics across the country have told me they disapprove of this one position of
            their church," she said.</p>
        <p>"Many of them come to our clinics. A look at statistics will prove that Catholics are
            having smaller families."</p>
        <q who="NYT"><p>Mrs. Sanger is still active. With the aid of two secretaries she handles
                correspondence from all parts of the world. She is president of the
                    <org>International Planned Parenthood Federation</org> and plans to go to the
                organization's <org reg="International Conference on Planned Parenthood, Sixth"
                    >international conference</org> at <place>New Delhi, India,</place> next year.</p>
            <p>In her spare time, she paints, concentrating on the deserts and mountains in Arizona.
                She has eight grandchildren. Six are the children of Dr. Grant Sanger and his
                    <person reg="Sanger, Edwina">wife.</person></p></q>

    </docBody>
</doc>
