<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="(Published article) ">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/04/04 VS initial tagging</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="(1936-11-16) ">16 November, 1936</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>The Present Day Trend of Birth Control</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421910</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Buffalo Courier Express</title></bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="BCE">Buffalo Courier Express</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">Sanger spoke under the auspices of the <org>Buffalo Family Relations
            Institute</org> at the <org>Hotel Fillmore</org> on November 16, 1936, on the platform.
        Also appearing was Dean <person reg="Alden, Carlos C.">Carlos C. Alden</person>, Dr. <person
            reg="Clarke, Alfred">Alfred Clarke</person>, <person reg="Mitchell, Ellen">Ellen
            Mitchell</person>, <person reg="Sawyer, Esther Hoyt">Esther Hoyt Sawyer</person>, Mrs.
            <person reg="Davis, Mrs. Herbert R.">Herbert Davis</person>, <person
            reg="Penkey, Thomas Jr.">Thomas Penkey Jr.</person>, Mrs. <person>Barday</person> and
            <person reg="Gaylord, Gladys">Gladys Gaylord</person>. <index level1="xxxx"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Mrs. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger</person> Gives Hearers Plenty to Think
            About</head>
        <byline>Champion of birth control says she met no opposition in India.</byline>
        <div>
            <p><supplied resp="MSPP">Part of this section has been omitted</supplied></p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <p> “Control of the population is one of the great problems of life, and the greatest
                problem of our age,” <q who="BCE">she said</q>. “When we call into the world a new
                life consciously, then we begin on a new and better civilization.</p>
            <p> “Birth control is, however first of all, an answer to the prayer of the poor-- the
                sad, unfortunate people all over the world who are asking what they can do to keep
                from wrecking the lives of countless of mothers and keep fathers from becoming
                hopeless and despairing.”</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Tells About <place>India</place></head>
            <q who="BCE"><p> She labeled it the country of contrasts, filled with the horribly rich
                    and the poor to whom life is a starved, living death, where the weather is
                    either intensely hot or icy cold; where persons are either abysmally ignorant or
                    deeply learned. India, she said, has tried everything, and she pointed out that,
                    in the face of “Purdah,” that state where women as a majority were kept in
                    virtual imprisonment never being seen by any man except their husbands. <person
                        reg="Gandhi, Mahatma">Gandhi</person> had but to send out the call and the
                    women heroically revolted to free themselves almost overnight. </p></q>
            <p><supplied resp="MSPP">Part of this section has been omitted</supplied></p>
            <p> “There were no legal objections in India in my work and absolutely no religious
                interference like that in this country,” <q who="BCE">she continued.</q> “Because in
                India, the problem has become acute and leaders and educators have been forced to
                this action.”</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Reason for Control</head>
            <p> “But the identical factors necessitating birth control exist in this country that
                exist in India. First, the infant mortality rate; second, the father’s wage; third,
                the need to space children to give mothers and children a chance; and fourth, the
                place of the child in the family. Certainly to regard to this last point it is
                apparent that it makes little difference if the mother has waited two and three
                years between each child, if there are too many children in the family. Figures from
                any health report show that. When there are seven children in a family, the
                mortality rate jumps drastically. When we get up to twelve children in the family,
                the records show that 60 per cent of the twelve die. </p>
            <p> “Who, then, benefits from this? Does the community? Does the nation? Does the church
                gain by the unhappy deaths of hundreds of mothers and hundreds of children? I
                maintain that we are in a state of barbarism when we have the knowledge that will
                make these tragic lives happy, that will save these suffering mothers, that will
                insure children a right place in their family picture-- and we withhold it. Why not
                make life something constructive. Why waste it?</p>
            <p> “We are trying to make a new world,” <q who="BCE">said Mrs. Sanger</q>, “to pass on
                the torch of life in bodies, fit, perfect and beautiful. We want young people to
                look on marriage not filled with fear, to have women exist without the sword of
                death hanging over their heads. We want to give to the poor the same knowledge those
                of wealth have. We want to amend the federal laws so that all hospitals can
                distribute information and that the information can be transmitted through the
                mails.” </p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <p><supplied resp="MSPP">Part of this section has been omitted</supplied></p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
