<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/04/16 VS initial tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-12-15 CH proof and correct tags</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1917-05-17 ">17 May 1917</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Should U.S. Soldiers Be Compelled to Marry Before Going to War?</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421945</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Salt Lake Telegram</title>, May 17, 1917</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="SLT">Salt Lake Telegram</name>
            <name id="FORWI">Forbes, William Cameron</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>This article compiled responses to the title question and included a series if responses.
            Only Sanger's response has been included.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="and marriage"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="and war"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="in marriages"/>
        <index level1="family planning, principles of"/>
        <index level1="marriage"/>
        <index level1="reproductive responsibility"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
        <index level1="World War I" level2="MS on"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Should U.S. Soldiers Be Compelled to Marry Before Going to War?</head>
        <div>
            <q who="SLT">
                <p> Shall <place>United States</place> soldiers be obliged to marry before they go
                    to the front?</p>
                <p> Shall the young troopers be compelled to take unto themselves wives so the race
                    shall not lose in perpetuation by their going?</p>
                <p> This is a big new question hurled into the midst of <place reg="United States"
                        >America</place>’s preparation for the war, touch most intimated the future
                    of every unmarried man sent to the front and beating at the heart strings of
                    every unmarried young woman who watches the troops march away.</p>
                <p>
                    <person reg="Forbes, William Cameron">W. Cameron Forbes</person>, former
                    governor general of the <place>Philippines</place>, financier and student of
                    sociology, has brought forward the proposal that no soldier be allowed to march
                    away unmarried.</p>
            </q>

            <p>
                <q who="FORWI"> “The future of the race requires that these young men, the best of
                    our youth, should be represented in future generations,”</q> Forbes says. </p>
            <q who="SLT">
                <p> Forbes also says that if the 2,000,000 young men whom it is proposed to select
                    for service are permitted to go to the front unmarried it will mean:</p>
            </q>
            <q who="FORWI">
                <p> “Complete failure to realize the necessity of the maintenance of the race.”</p>
                <p> “Two million women deprived of the privilege of marriage and the bringing up of
                    families.”</p>
                <p>“These young women will be left mateless,” says Forbes. </p>
            </q>
            <q who="FORWI">
                <p> "The offspring of soldiers will be a necessity in the next generation to carry
                    out the social requirements of the nation."</p>
            </q>
            <q who="SLT">
                <p> These declarations by a man of national reputation and a former high government
                    official have aroused men and women in all parts of the country to discussion of
                    the issue.</p>
                <p> Should soldiers be compelled to marry?</p>
                <p> Should women be compelled to marry soldiers about to go to war?</p>
                <p> If there should be compulsion, how?</p>
                <p> Forbes is a grandson of <person reg="Emerson, Ralph Waldo">Ralph Waldo
                        Emerson</person>, formerly was head of the financial department of
                        <org>Stone and Webster</org>, a big electrical engineering firm, has been
                    connected in important capacities with probably half a hundred <place>New
                        England</place> corporations and is something of a poet and a writer.</p>
                <p> But, can Forbes, financier and former arbiter of the destines of the little
                    brown Filipinos, induce America to adopt compulsory marriage for soldiers and
                    for young women – for it takes two to make this kind of a bargain.</p>
                <p> What do you think about this proposal?</p>
                <p> Here are opinions of noted persons asked by The Telegram to give their
                    views:</p>
            </q>
        </div>
        <div>
            <p>
                <supplied resp="MSPP"> [Opinions written by Rev. <person reg="Ames, Waldo A.">Waldo
                        A. Ames</person>, Miss <person reg="Todd, Helen">Helen Todd</person>, Dr.
                        <person reg="Wile, Ira S.">Ira S. Wile</person>, <person
                        reg="Widtsoe, John, A.">John A. Widtsoe</person>, and Mrs. <person
                        reg="Fels, Mary">Joseph Fels</person> were omitted.]</supplied>
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> By Margaret Sanger</head>
            <p> Let the women of America marry the two million soldiers who are called to the front
                if they desire to. The result would be mutual development a spiritual awakening.</p>
            <p> But let the war wives think seriously before they bear children for fathers who may
                never return. Only women can realize double sorrow for the loved ones gone and a
                little fatherless one to come which a woman would endure during those long months of
                waiting.</p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
