<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "file:/S:/TRANSCRIPTIONS/XML%20Drafts/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published statement">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/07/08 MM</prepDate>
        <docAuthor><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret
            Sanger</person></docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1942-04-30">30 Apr 1942</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Statement on Infant Mortality in the Southwest United
                States</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421996</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>"<title type="article">Here are the Facts</title>"<title
                    type="newspaper">Llano News</title> 04/30/1942</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">The same article was also published at: <title
            type="journal">Port Neches Chronicle</title> 05/01/1942 and <title
            type="journal">Bronte Enterprise</title> 05/15/1942 <index
            level1="United States" level2="southern region"/><index
            level1="United States" level2="western region"/><index
            level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"
            level3="negative consequences of"/><index level1="mortality rates"
            level2="infant"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>HERE ARE THE FACTS</head>
        <byline>SOUTHWEST HAS HIGHEST INFANT DEATH RATE IN THE UNITED
            STATES</byline>
        <p>LABELING the Southwest as "the most dangerous part of the United
            States in which to be born," Mrs. Margaret Sanger this week appealed
            to citizens of <place>Arizona</place>, <place>New Mexico</place>,
            and <place>Texas</place> to initiate community programs that will
            reduce the infant mortality rate in those three states.</p>
        <p>"Figures just released by the Children's Bureau of the U.S.
            Department of Labor show that while the infant mortality rate for
            the country as a whole was only 47 per thousand in 1940, the rate
            for New Mexico was 99.6 per thousand, for Arizona, 84 per thousand,
            and for Texas, 69 per thousand."</p>
        <p>"We who live in the Southwest should be ashamed to have the world
            know that it is twice to three times as dangerous for a baby to be
            born here as in <place>Minnesota</place>, <place>Oregon</place>, or
                <place>Connecticut</place>," Mrs. Sanger declared.</p>
        <p>"The shocking thing about the fact that as many as one in ten of our
            children die at birth or in the first year of life is that half to
            two-thirds of these deaths could be prevented.</p>
        <p> "An increased standard of living, made possible by increased incomes
            in the agricultural areas of the Southwest will, to some extent,
            help prevent some of these deaths. Extension of hospital and
            maternity center services to rural areas and to city slums will also
            help. Establishment of properly authorized and staffed clinics where
            mothers may get free information about planning their families is of
            basic importance. </p>
        <div>
            <p>"There is no question but what the high infant death rate in some
                sections of the Southwest is due to the fact that the mothers
                who are least able to bear children have the most. Afflicted
                with tuberculosis or other disabling diseases, living in
                overcrowded homes, badly undernourished, they have neither the
                strength to bear a healthy child nor the means to give it decent
                care after it is born. Birth control information should be made
                availible to these women, just as it is availible to women who
                can afford to pay for the advice of a private physician," Mrs.
                Sanger said.</p>
            <p>Mrs. Sanger, for many years a winter resident of the Southwest,
                is honorary chairman of the <org>Planned Parenthood Federation
                    of America</org>. Recognized as the founder of the birth
                control movement in the United States, she established the first
                birth control clinic in the United States twenty-five years ago.
                She has seen the work grow until there are now 612 birth control
                centers in the country. Although the movement encountered
                considerable opposition at the start it now has the support of
                leading religious, health, medical, and civic organizations. A
                recent Gallup poll indicated that 77% of the people of the
                United States favor the spread of birth control knowledge.</p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
