<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="(Published Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/04/04 Initials</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="(1952-04-26) ">26 April 1952</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Speech to the El Paso Planned Parenthood
                Center</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421935</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>El Paso Times</title></bibl>
            <bibl><title>MSM</title></bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="EPT">El Paso Times</name>
            <name id="HP">Herald Post</name>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>addressed the 15th anniversary meeting
        of the <org>El Paso Planned Parenthood Center</org>, at the Country Club, on April
        26. Quotes from the El Paso Times follow the Herald Post article. <index
            level1="birth control" level2="access to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="American opinion on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="class-based"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="civilization and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="morality of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Speech to the El Paso Planned Parenthood</head>
        <head type="sub">Margaret Sanger Plans Tour in Far East</head>
        <head type="sub">Praises Work Here</head>
        <div>
            <p>Mrs. Sanger praised the work of the three clinics in El Paso.
                “This is one of the most encouraging spots in the nation,” <q who="HP">she told local workers</q>
            “You are doing wonderful work in <place reg="El Paso, Texas">El Paso</place>. I
                am also proud of the men here. They have given complete backing
                to their wives who are members of the clinic staffs. I am
                pleased at the support given to the work by the people and
                officials of El Paso. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Plan Foreign Program</head>
            <p>
                <q who="HP">Mrs. Sanger outlined her plans for expanding planned
                    parenthood programs in <place>India</place>, <place>Japan</place>and <place>China</place>. She will
                    leave early in the fall to supervise the establishment of
                    new units in those countries. </q> “There is still a great
                need for constructive work in the Far East,” <q who="HP">she
                    said.</q> “Fifteen countries have asked for our help in
                setting up new programs. “The work is easiest in India, where
                the officials speak English and have been trained in English
                schools.” </p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <p><supplied resp="MSPP">Remaining text taken from the El Paso Times
                    article.</supplied></p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Margaret Sanger Discusses Reasons for Birth
                Control</head>
            <p>“We were lucky in <place reg="United States">America</place>to have opposition,” <q who="EPT">she said.</q>
                “It brought out the strength and conviction that we were right. We
                had something to fight for and against. We don’t mind the
                opposition, we just want the opportunity to express our views.”</p>
            <p>
                “If the public health departments do not take it upon themselves
                to instruct the poor, ignorant people, they will multiply in
                numbers not only in poor physical condition but also in low
                mental conditions. If we keep on like this, we shall be
                reproducing toward a race of morons,” <q who="EPT">she asserted.</q></p>
               <p> “It is a benighted opposition who ties the hands of our public health
                authorities . This opposition is cruel because these people will
                be forced to continue having the children they do not want or
                cannot afford to have.” </p>
                <p>“I knew then that birth control was a
                human, a physical need,” she said. </p>
        </div>


    </docBody>
</doc>
