<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Summarized speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/06/26 CH proof tags</prepDate>
        
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1939-03-01">1 Mar 1939</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied>Speech to the El Paso Kiwanis Club</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421960</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <p><bibl><title type="article"> State Birth Control Instruction Is Proposed By Margaret
                        Sanger</title>, <title type="journal">Herald Post</title>, Mar. 1,
                    1939</bibl> and <bibl><title type="article">Birth Control Need Told by Mrs.
                        Sanger</title>, <title type="journal">El Paso Times</title>, Mar. 2,
                    1939</bibl></p>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="HP">Herald Post</name>
            <name id="EPT">El Paso Times</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">Sanger addressed the Kiwanis Club of El Paso at a lunch at the Hotel
        Cortez. An article the next day in the <title type="journal">El Paso Times</title> noted
        that though the audience was interested, <q who="EPT">"They were not deeply stirred. After
            all, the subject to hardly any of them was of personal application. Theirs was only an
            academic interest. Either because of age or financial resources, or martial status or
            lack of same, they were not in situations where birth control touched their
            lives."</q><p>The summary of this speech was drawn from two newspapers; for Sanger's
            rough notes, see <title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S72:66. </p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="and war"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="class-based"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="population and"/>
        <index level1="Birth Control Federation of America"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="consequences on"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="increase in"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="population growth and"/>
        <index level1="children" level2="rights of"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="infant"/>
        <index level1="mortality rate" level2="maternal"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>State Birth Control Instruction Is Proposed By Margaret Sanger</head>
        <div>
            <q who="HP"><p> Birth control instruction in the public health programs of the states
                    and the <org reg="United States, Government of">Federal Government</org> is the goal
                    of the <org>Birth Control Federation of America</org>, the federation’s honorary
                    president, Mrs. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>, said in
                        <place reg="El Paso, TX">El Paso</place> today.</p></q>
            <q who="HP"><p> Mrs. Sanger, youthful and brimming with health and enthusiasm, arrived
                    today from <place reg="Tucson, AZ">Tucson</place> to pay an official visit to
                    the <org>El Paso Mother’s Health Center</org>. She spoke today at the <org
                        reg="El Paso Kiwanis Club">Kiwanis Club</org> at <org>Hotel Cortez</org> and
                    at the Health Center to mothers and to the board of directors.</p></q>
            <q who="HP"><p>Citing the increase of the national birth rate of "over a million a
                        year<q who="HP">,” she said she refused to weep crocodile tears over our
                        falling birth rate.</q></p>
                <p>
                    <q who="HP">She said that, "</q>young married couples in love will have babies<q
                        who="HP">,” regardless of the predictions that the better class of people
                        will not with birth control knowledge.</q></p>
                <p> “They will get an economic footing and have their babies<q who="HP">,” she
                        said.</q> “They want to reproduce the one they love.”</p>
                <q who="HP"><p> The Birth Control Federation of America now incorporates all the
                        birth control activities and clinics in the <place>United States</place>
                        under its direction, Mrs. Sanger said. She told of the increase, by 125, of
                        the privately directed clinics, now 480 in the past two years.</p></q>
                <p> “The total of 480 clinics does not include clinics operated by civic
                    organizations in communities,” <q who="HP">Mrs. Sanger said.</q> “<place
                        reg="North Carolina">North</place> and <place>South Carolina</place> have
                    included birth control instruction in their public health programs.”</p>
                <p><q who="HP"> The South will lead the country in putting birth control instruction
                        in the public health programs, Mrs. Sanger predicted.</q></p></q>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> South Sees Need</head>
            <p> “The South sees the need in her own confines,” <q who="HP">she said.</q></p>
            <q who="HP"><p> Birth control is not only a national but an international need, the
                    internationally known woman said.</p></q>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Crowded Nations</head>
            <p> “<place>Germany</place>, <place>Italy</place> and <place>Japan</place>, the three
                high pressure nations, have become the danger spots to the peace of the world,” <q
                    who="HP">she said.</q> “While they make their claim for more territory and
                colonies, they are not content to cut down their birth rate and keep their
                population within their national resources. They too wish to increase their
                population for military strength.”</p>
            <q who="HP"><p> She emphasized that Germany’s population in 1935 was 67,000,000, only
                    one million less than it was in 1914, after which there was a loss of 10 million
                    in the World War and 27,000 square miles in territory.</p></q>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Talks to Kiwanians</head>
            <p> “In other words, her present population and density is back to explosion point of
                1914 which caused the World War,” <q who="HP">Mrs. Sanger said.</q> “There is no use
                asking any nation to reduce its armaments without reducing its birth rates. There
                has got to be an equalization of birth rates as well as of territory if we will have
                peace.”</p>
            <q who="HP"><p> Mrs. Sanger defined birth control for the Kiwanians today. She pointed
                    out that birth control does not interfere with life.</p></q>
            <p> “It is a conscious control of the birth rate by means that prevent conception,” <q
                    who="HP">she said.</q> “It does not kill, does not interfere with life. It is
                ‘control’ and not ‘limit.’”</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> 150,000 Useless Deaths</head>
            <q who="HP"><p> The United States has not reduced its maternity mortality rate in 20
                    years, Mrs. Sanger said.</p></q>
            <p> “A total of 150,000 mothers and infants died in 1937,” <q who="HP">she said.</q>
                “More than one-half of them could have been saved through scientific knowledge if it
                had been applied. The opponents of birth control must take a large share of
                responsibility for their deaths. The report of the <org
                    reg="United States Children's Bureau">Children’s Bureau</org>, from which I got
                these figures, shows that where there is spacing of children in a family, there are
                147 infant deaths out of 1000, when only one year apart. While 95 deaths occur in
                1000 where there is two years of spacing between babies.</p>
            <p> “Sixty-five per cent of the babies born in 1937 were in families either on relief or
                with incomes of less than $20 a week,” <q who="HP">she said.</q></p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Hits Old Age Theory</head>
            <p> “There are 13,000,000 children in families on relief, or with a total income of less
                than $15 a week,” <q who="HP">she said.</q></p>
            <p> “I object to the philosophy that parents have the right to have children to sustain
                them in their old age,” <q who="HP">Mrs. Sanger said.</q> “With the labor saving
                machines fast taking the place of man labor, by the time the children born today
                will be able to assist their parents, machines will have superseded those children.
                Their labor will not be needed. But the laws of a humane government will further
                advance the age of exploitation of children. Children will be kept longer in school.
                It is a short sighted policy of any group to encourage the birth of children in this
                strata of our population.”</p>
        </div>
        <head>Birth Control Need Told By Mrs. Sanger</head>
        <div>
       <p><supplied resp="MSPP">Additional quotes by Sanger from the <title type="journal">El Paso Times</title> appear below.</supplied></p><p>"There can only be peace in the world when all nations will keep their populations within the scope of national resources," <q who="EPT">Mrs. Sanger said.</q></p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
