<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="(Published Article) ">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/11/04 YG</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="(1937-07-19) ">19 Jul 1937</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Statement on the National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth
                Control</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421916</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Unity</title></bibl>
            <bibl><title>MSM</title></bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="U">Unity</name>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">Sanger released a press notice about the disbanding of the National
        Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control. Unity was the journal of the Unity
        Church, a spiritual philosophical movement. 
        
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Federal"/>
   <index level1="birth control" level2="medical community and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="American opinion on"/> 
        <index level1="birth control" level2="history of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="medical community and"/>
        
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Birth Control Committee Disbands, Victorious</head>
        <p>The work of the <org>National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control</org> is done and
            well done, the organization is therefore dissolved, <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>, president,
            announced in an editorial in the current issue of her magazine, The National Birth
            Control News. Hailing the action of the <org reg="American Medical Association">American Medical Association</org>as strengthening
            the cause of birth control, already victorious through the clarification of the Federal
            Comstock statute, Mrs. Sanger disclosed that her Committee has been formally dissolved
            by unanimous action of its Board of Directors. The Resolution embodying this action
            reads:</p> 
        <p>“Whereas the purposes of the National Committee on Federal Legislation for
        Birth Control, Inc., have been accomplished, in the light of the recent decision by the
        <org reg="United States Circuit Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit">Circuit Court of Appeals</org>,</p>
        <p>“Be it Resolved that the National Committee on Federal Legislation
        for Birth Control, Inc., be dissolved...” </p>
        <p>Her own education as a trained nurse made her see
        more than twenty years ago that birth control was a medical and technical problem, over and
        above everything else, said Mrs. Sanger. </p>
        <p>“This has been my steadfast policy,” she continued.
        “We have fought for medically directed clinics, for medical support and for medical
        endorsement and recognition. Time and again members of the profession, even those in high
        standing, have told us that we could never win. But individual support grew. Organized
        support grew. Today we can feel that the same principles of right have won.” </p>
        <p><org>The U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit</org> handed down a decision in a test case on
        November 30, 1936, stating that the design of the Federal Comstock statute “was not to
        prevent the importation, sale or carriage by mail of things which might intelligently be
        employed by conscientious and competent physicians for the purpose of saving life or
        promoting the well being of their patients.” Thus Mrs. Sanger won her fight for an amendment
        to the statute exempting physicians from its restrictions. </p>
        <p>The American Medical Association
        at its annual Convention in <place reg="Atlantic City, New Jersey">Atlantic City</place>unanimously adopted the report of its 
       <org>Committee to Study Contraceptive Practices</org>, by action of its <org>House of Delegates</org> on June 8th. The
        Committee recommended the teaching of contraception in medical schools, the investigation of
        materials, devices and methods, and the clarification of physicians of their legal rights in
        relation to the use of contraceptives. </p>
        <p>“Now comes the future, full of hope and challenge,”
        says Mrs. Sanger. “The impetus of the work is doubly renewed. We can now consolidate the
        gains we have made, and move steadily forward in a larger program of national and
        international scope.” The educational work of the birth control movement will be carried on
        by the <org>Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau of New York</org>, of which Mrs. Sanger is the
        director. </p><p/>
    </docBody>
</doc>
