<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "file:/S:/TRANSCRIPTIONS/XML%20Drafts/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published interview">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/07/08 MM</prepDate>
        <docAuthor><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret
            Sanger</person></docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1939-05-00"> May 1939</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Interview with <person reg="Estcourt, Zilfra">Zilfra
                    Estcourt</person></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421993</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>"<title type="article">Margaret Sanger Carries on Crusade for
                    Health and Peace through Birth Control</title>"<title
                    type="newspaper">SF Chronicle</title> 05/21/1939 p.
                65</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="biography"
            /><index level1="birth control" level2="international"/><index
            level1="birth control" level2="economic benefits and risks of"
            /><index level1="birth control" level2="eugenic justifications"
            /><index level1="birth control" level2="population and"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Margaret Sanger Carries on Crusade for Health and Peace through
            Birth Control</head>
        <p>A dauntless crusader was guest in our town last week--a woman who
            never quivered at the clang of the police gong, who took
            misunderstanding, humiliation and jail in stride--Margaret Sanger,
            advocate of birth control.</p>
        <p>And whether you agree or disagree with her ideas, you must admire the
            courage that, undaunted, could go on year after year until the tide
            of public opinion changed and brought honors in place of scorn and
            the respect of statesmen as well as the idolatry of the women of the
            poor, for a cause that is still a matter of controversy.</p>
        <p>We met Mrs. Sanger the other day at luncheon, after a lapse of 17
            years. The hair that once was a coppery fluff was silver but the
            blue eyes with their zealot's light were the same. And so we knew
            before we heard her speak that Margaret Sanger was still in the ring
            battling for liberated mothers, for better childhood, for controlled
            populations, for peace and a more civilized world. For in her mind
            and in those of thousands of others, birth control, peace and
            civilization are inexorably linked.</p>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Start of Career</head>
            <p>Before we tell you some of the things Mrs. Sanger said at the
                joint luncheon of the <place reg="San Francisco, CA">San
                    Francisco</place> Center of the <org>League of Women
                    Voters</org>, the local branch of the <org>American
                    Association of University Women</org> and the <org>Family
                    Relations Center</org>, we must go back to the beginnings of
                a career that parallels those of other deeply beloved feminist
                leaders.</p>
            <p>Following a college education, she studied nursing at a <place
                    reg="White Plains, NY">White Plains, New York</place>
                hospital. To this she added a post graduate course at the <place
                    reg="New York, NY">Manhattan</place> Eye and Ear Hospital.
                With this background she plunged into volunteer nursing in the
                East Side tenements of Manhattan. Even after her marriage to
                    <person reg="Sanger, William">William Sanger</person>, New
                York artist, she continued her social service work and it was
                through her experiences in trying to aid the pitiful mothers of
                the poor, that her ideas crystalized and her tremendous reform
                movement was begun.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Battle With Death</head>
            <p>In her reminiscence, <unclear resp="MSPP">she recalls</unclear>
                going to aid the mother of a destitute family who had tried to
                stop the coming of another child. For days and nights "Nurse"
                Sanger fought a battle with death and won. Hardly was the fight
                over than she was called again in the same tenement, but this
                time she arrived just in time to close the eyes of a dying
                woman.</p>
            <p>Returning sadly to her home where her husband and her own three
                children were peacefully asleep, she stood at her window until
                dawn visioning thousands of poverty-stricken mothers, facing
                more and more births and then death.</p>
            <p>"I decided then I was through with nursing broken bodies," she
                related in after years. "I was determined to strike at the root
                of the evil, to save the bodies before they were broken."</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Launches Campaign</head>
            <p>And so she gave up her work in the tenements to launch, in a
                contrary world, a move to make availible to all women asking it,
                information that would permit them to regulate the size of their
                families. And what a bitter battle she precipitated.</p>
            <p>For years she devoted herself to writing, lecturing and
                organizing the <org>American Birth Control League</org>. Over
                and over again she was hauled from her platform and hurried off
                to face the law. But nothing could stop her. And gradually the
                strong silent sentiment that grew up in support of her theories
                became vocal and under <person reg="Wilson, Woodrow">President
                    Wilson</person>'s administration, the hounds of the law were
                called off. </p>
            <p>How this work has grown is indicated by the fact that California
                has just organized a State Federation of Birth Control League
                with some 24 units as a starter.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Many Now Approve</head>
            <p>And now in a world depressed with economic problems and faced
                with a war of nations fighting for space for their overflowing
                populations, Margaret Sanger's ideas have the approval not only
                of social workers, and the great feminist organizations such as
                the League of Women Voters, the Business and Professional
                Women's Clubs, and the <org>American Association of University
                    Women</org>, but of statesmen.</p>
            <p>Figures cited by her at a luncheon Thursday at the Western
                Women's Club under auspices of a group of the leading women's
                groups showed that the World war was caused by
                    <place>Germany</place>'s need for territory to provide for
                her increasing population. Similar conditions in Germany,
                    <place>Italy</place>, and <place>Japan</place> today, she
                said, make another conflict almost inevitable.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">A Bar to Peace</head>
            <p>"Italy and Germany have spawned themselves into another world
                conflict," she said. "I believe there will never be world peace
                in this world until a definite population policy is formed."</p>
            <p>As to the situation in the United States, Mrs. Sanger pointed to
                the fact that 65 per cent of the 2,000,000 babies born in the
                United States last year were in families on relief. Women of the
                more affluent class have access to information that permits them
                to space their children, she said, and it is only among the
                desperately poor that children are brought into the world faster
                then they can be cared for. Of the 2,000,000 mor ethan 75,000
                were still-born and 69,000 died in their first month of life.
                This mortality, public health reports indicated, is due to the
                lack of vitality of the mothers, due to overwork and too
                frequent maternity, she said.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Public Health Burden</head>
            <p>With a large percentage of children coming from families least
                able to care for and educate them, the public heatlh problem of
                the United States is growing by leaps and bounds, Mrs. Sanger
                said. The latest demand is for $85,000,000 for increased
                services under the national health program.</p>
            <p>These tremendous national burdens could be avoided if the
                information were availible to the poor through clinics and
                health centers that the well-to-do receive through other
                sources.</p>
            <p>We are breeding now from the 25 per cent of our population that
                has an intelligence level of 15 years of age or less," she said.
                "If we could deal with this subject as a public health problem
                in 25 years we would see a great change in the intelligence
                ratio of our country, and we could build for quality among our
                people and for peace."</p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
