<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-06-25 CH proofed </prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <supplied><docDate value="1920/00/00"/></supplied>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Abortion</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421979</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="book">Woman and the New Race</title></bibl>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress, LCM 129:179</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>

            <name id="MH">Hirsch, Max</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>This is a pamphlet reprint of "Chapter 10 - <title type="article"
                >Contraceptives or Abortion?"</title> from <title type="book">Woman and the New
                Race,</title> pp. 118-29.</p>
        <index level1="abortion" level2="birth control vs."/>
        <index level1="abortion" level2="frequency of"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="infanticide"/>
        <index level1="Hirsch, Max"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="class-based"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/>
        <index level1="Family Limitation"/>
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="MS on"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>ABORTION "Woman and the New Race"</head>
        <head type="sub">"Woman and the New Race"</head>
        <byline>By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger.</person></byline>
        <p>SOCIETY has not yet learned the significance of the age-long effort of the feminine
            spirit to free itself of the burden of excessive childbearing. It has been singularly
            blind to the real forces underlying the cause of infanticide, child abandonment and
            abortion. It has permitted the highest and most powerful thing in woman's nature to be
            hindered, diverted, repressed and confused. Society has permitted this inner urge of
            woman to be rendered violent by repression until it has expressed itself in cruel forms
            of family limitation, which this same society has promptly labeled "crimes" and sought
            to punish. It has gone on blindly forcing women into these "crimes," deaf alike to their
            entreaties and to the lessons of history.</p>
        <p>As we have seen in the second chapter of this book, child abandonment and infanticide are
            by no means obsolete practices. As for abortion, it has not decreased but increased with
            the advance of civilization. The reader will recall that one authority says that there
            are 1,000,000 abortions in the <place>United States</place> every year, while another
            estimates double that number.</p>
        <p>Most of the women of the middle and upper classes in America seem secure in their
            knowledge of contraceptives as a means of birth control. Under present conditions, when
            the laws in most states regard this knowledge, howsoever it be imparted, as illicit, and
            the federal statutes prohibit the sending of it through the mails, even the women in
            more fortunate circumstances sometimes have difficulty in getting scientific
            information. Nevertheless, so strong is their purpose that they do obtain it and use it,
            correctly or incorrectly.</p>
        <p>The great majority of women, however, belong to the working class. Nearly all of these
            women will fall into one of two general groups-the ones who are having children against
            their will, and those who, to escape this evil, find refuge in abortion. Being given
            their choice by society-to continue to be overburdened mothers or to submit to a
            humiliating, repulsive, painful and too often gravely dangerous operation, those women
            in whom the feminine urge to freedom is strongest choose the abortionist. One group goes
            on bringing children to birth, hoping that they will be born dead or die. The women of
            the other group strive consciously by drastic means to protect themselves and the
            children already born.</p>
        <p><q who="MH">"Our examinations,"</q> says <person reg="Hirsch, Max">Dr. Max
                Hirsch,</person> an authority on the subject, <q who="MH">"have informed us that the
                largest number of abortions (in the United States) are performed on married women.
                This fact brings us to the conclusion that contraceptive measures among the upper
                classes and the practice of abortion among the lower class, are the real means
                employed to regulate the number of offspring."</q></p>
        <p>Thus a high percentage of women in comfortable circumstances escape over-breeding by the
            use of contraceptives. A similarly high percentage of women not in comfortable
            circumstances are forced to submit to forced maternity, because their only alternative
            at present is abortion. When accidental conception takes place, some women of both
            classes resort to abortion if they can obtain the services of an abortionist.</p>
        <p>When society holds up its hands in horror at the "crime" of abortion, it forgets at whose
            door the first and principal responsibility for this practice rests. Does anyone imagine
            that a woman would submit to abortion if not denied the knowledge of scientific,
            effective contraceptives? Does anyone believe that physician and midwives who perform
            abortions go from door to door soliciting patronage? The abortionist could not continue
            his practice for twenty-four hours if it were not for the fact that women come
            desperately begging for such operations. He could not stay out of jail a day if women
            did not so generally approve of his services as to hold his identity an open but
            seldom-betrayed secret.</p>
        <p>The question, then, is not whether family limitation should be practiced. It is being
            practiced; it has been practiced for ages and it will always be practiced. The question
            that society must answer is this: Shall family limitation be achieved through birth
            control or abortion? Shall normal, safe, effective contraceptives be employed, or shall
            we continue to force women to the abnormal, often dangerous surgical operation?</p>
        <p>This question, too, the church, the state and the moralist must answer. The knowledge of
            contraceptive methods may yet for a time be denied to the woman of the working class,
            but those who are responsible for denying it to her, and she herself, should understand
            clearly the dangers to which she is exposed because of the laws which force her into the
            hands of the abortionist.</p>
        <p>It needs no assertion of mine to call attention to the grim fact that the laws
            prohibiting the imparting of information concerning the preventing of conception are
            responsible for tens of thousands of deaths each year in this country and an untold
            amount of sickness and sorrow. The suffering and the death of these women is squarely
            upon the heads of the law-makers and the puritanical, masculine-minded persons who
            insist upon retaining the abominable legal restrictions.</p>
        <p><q who="MH">"He who would combat abortion,"</q> says Dr. Hirsch, and at the same time
            combat contraceptive measures may be likened to the person who would fight contagious
            diseases and forbid disinfection. For contraceptive measures are important weapons in
            the fight against abortion.</p>
        <p><q who="MH">"America has a law since 1873 which prohibits by criminal statute the
                distribution and regulation of contraceptive measures. It follows, therefore, that
                America stands at the head of all nations in the huge number of abortions."</q></p>
        <p>There is the case in a nutshell. Family limitation will always be practiced as it is now
            being practiced-either by birth control or by abortion. We know that. The one means
            health and happiness-a stronger, better race. The other means disease, suffering,
            death.</p>
        <p>The woman who goes to the abortionist's table is not a criminal but a martyr, a martyr to
            the bitter, unthinkable conditions brought about by the blindness of society at large.
            These conditions give her the choice between the surgeon's instruments and the
            sacrificing of what is highest and holiest in her-her aspiration to freedom, her desire
            to protect the children already hers. These conditions-not the woman-outface society
            with this question:</p>
        <p><q who="UNK">"Contraceptives or Abortion-which shall it be?"</q></p>

        <p/>
    </docBody>
</doc>
