<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article) ">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/06/17 AS</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1916-02-20">20 February 1916</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied>Address on Woman Rebel Case Dismissal</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421997</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">New York Tribune</title></bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="NYT"><org>New York Tribune</org></name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
            <name id="ALG"><person reg="Goldwater, A.L.">Dr. A.L. Goldwater</person></name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person> was the guest of honor at the <place>Bandbox Theatre</place> in <place reg="New York, New York">New
            York</place> to celebrate the dismissal of charges for publishing the Woman Rebel. She was
            introduced by <person reg="Cothren, Marion B.">Marion B. Cothren</person> and additional comments were made by Dr. A.L. Goldwater.
    </p><index level1="Goldman, Emma"/>
        <index level1="Netherlands, the" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="France" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="England" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="physicians" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="infant"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="international"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="opposition to"/>
        <index level1="birth control clinics and leagues"/>
        <index level1="birth control movement" level2="MS on"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Mrs. Sanger Glad She Was Indicted</head>
        <q who="NYT"></q><p>A prima donna on a farewell tour could have justifiably envied the enthusiastic reception given Mrs. Margaret Sanger at the Bandbox Theatre last evening.</p>
        <p>When the little woman, plainly garbed in a brown suit of corduroy, stepped to the front of the stage she was greeted with an outburst of applause which lasted ten minutes.</p>
        <p>The playhouse was jammed. Hundreds were refused admission, and what was to have been a meeting tendered to a martyr became a jubilee accorded a victor.</p>
        <p>Birth control was the topic of the evening, but this important subject was shelved at times for criticism of the Federal authorities, the unsympathetic public and the newspapers.</p>
        <p>Prosecution was called persecution, the newspapers were thanked for advertising</p></q> <p><q who="UNK">"The Little Rebel,"</q></p> <p><q who="NYT">and Mrs. Sanger herself brought a burst of applause when she declared:</q></p> <p>"You can no longer say the courts do not serve their  purpose, for in helping to promote the fight for birth control they have more than served a purpose."</p>
        <q who="NYT"><p><div type="section"><head type="sub">Mrs. Sanger Says Publicity Will Aid</head></p></q>
        <p>"Women want birth control in this country, and organized action will bring it about. Publicity will hasten it," said Mrs. Sanger.</p>
        <p>"When birth control leagues are established here we will soon resolve all social problems, such as mental defectiveness, deformity, settlement problems and child labor conditions. We will practically wipe out infant mortality. I have made a study of conditions abroad and have a message for you to-night. <place reg="Holland, the Netherlands">Holland</place> has the lowest death rate of infants in the world. There they have fifty-seven clinics for teaching birth control in most densely populated districts.</p>
        <p>"In <place>France</place> conditions are just the opposite, and the infant mortality is the highest in the world, because the authorities and clergy have fought birth control. <place reg="Great Britain">England</place> is almost in the same condition. There is a greater need in this country for the work. The facilities and equipment are much better. We can outstrip all <place>Europe</place> in ten years if this matter is taken up. The trouble over here is that we are regulated by conventions.</p>
        <p>"Pardon me if I refuse to thank the government because I am  now free and no longer a criminal. How kind of the government after a persecution of two years to tell the people of New York I am an orderly person. Two years ago I was branded.</p>
        <p>"To-night I thank the grand jury for indicting me. I thank the Federal authorities for fanning the flame, and I thank the dear newspapers for publicity. They have done wonders to arouse interest in birth control."</p>
        <q who="NYT"><p><div type="section"><head type="sub">Will Establish Clinics</head> </p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger, who will leave in two weeks to establish clinics in several Western cities, charged the government with</q> <q who="UNK">"contemptible spying"</q> <q who="NYT">into her home, and said overtures were continually made to compromise the case.</p></q>
        <p>"Why, the United States Attorney," she declared, "declared to me that the birth control reading matter would be all right if written for an American magazine, but written in such direct, plain and simple language was too much for the <place>United States</place> mails."</p>
        <q who="NYT"><p>The birth control movement has the hearty sanction of at least one New York physician. Dr. A.L. Goldwater, brother of the former <person reg="Emerson, Haven">Health Commissioner,</person> assailed brother members of his profession.</p></q>
        <q who="ALG"><p>"Half the physicians are opposed to birth control," he said, "because it will cut down their incomes. This is a work the medical profession should be identified with. I am pleased to give it my hearty indorsement. It is unfortunate you have to defy the law to crystallize public sentiment."</p></q>
        <q who="NYT"><p><person reg="Goldman, Emma">Emma Goldman,</person> who will face trial next Monday for alleged indiscreet utterances on birth control, lost an opportunity to speak at the conclusion of the meeting. A sympathizer made an eloquent plea for her, but when he glanced about she was not in the audience.</p></q>
    
    </docBody>


        <p/>
    </docBody>
</doc>
