<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/04/25 YG</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1943-07-20">20 Jul 1943</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Statement on Japan</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421958</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Jap Military Leaders Block Birth Control, Says Mrs.
                    Sanger</title></bibl>
            <bibl><title type="journal">El Paso Herald Post</title></bibl>
            <bibl><title>MSM</title></bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="EPHP">El Paso Herald Post</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">Sanger made this statement in El Paso while on a travel layover. <index
            level1="birth control" level2="and war"/>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="population policies of"/>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="government of"/>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="overpopulation and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="civilization and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Jap Military Leaders Block Birth Control, Says <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Mrs.
                Sanger</person></head>

        <p><q who="EPHP">The people of <place>Japan</place>have been victimized by their military
                leaders even more than the people of <place>Germany</place>is the opinion of Mrs.
                Margaret Sanger. Mrs. Sanger, stopping with friends in <place reg="El Paso, TX">El
                    Paso</place>between planes today, told of her visit to Japan in 1937. </q></p>
        <p>I was on my way to <place>China</place>at the invitation of <person
                reg="Soong May-ling (Madam Chiang Kai-Shek)">Madam Chiang Kai-Shek</person>, but
            never got any further than <place reg="Tokyo, Japan">Tokyo</place>Tokyo because of the
            China-Japanese war,<q>she said</q>. A Japanese woman told me that the country’s
            social-minded liberals realized that their population increase must be curtailed or they
            would be enemies of the whole world. For years these liberals had been crying for
            population control and the acquisition of a modern social system, but the militaristic
            party had become so firmly entrenched that these people simply went to jail for their
            efforts.</p>
        <p><q>Mrs. Sanger’s friend, <person reg="Shidzue Ishimoto">Baroness Ishimoto</person>, the
                leading Japanese liberal, has been in jail for years, and none of her friends can
                get any word from her. She has visited Mrs. Sanger in the <place>United
                    States</place>, and Mrs. Sanger visited her in Japan.</q></p>
        <p>The birth rate in Japan is about two million a year, and one million of these survive, <q
                who="EPHP">Mrs. Sanger said.</q>You can see that putting that many people on those
            tiny islands is like putting several families in a very small house. Their policy of
            aggression is exactly the same as if the inhabitants of the overcrowded house went next
            door and took charge of three or four rooms and helped themselves to the groceries. It’s
            the same with <place>Italy</place>. For <place>Germany</place>there is absolutely no
            excuse. Germany has had the opportunity for centuries to be civilized and to make her
            population conform to her boundaries.</p>
        <p><q who="EPHP">Mrs. Sanger is en route to <place reg="Palm Beach, FL">Palm Beach</place>to
                visit her son, <person reg="Sanger, Stewart">Stewart Sanger</person>, a doctor now
                in the <org reg="United States Army">Army</org>. He is a specialist in tropical
                diseases. Her other son, <person reg="Sanger, Grant">Grant</person>, is also a
                doctor now in the <org reg="United States Navy">Navy</org>. He is a surgeon.
            </q></p>
        <p><q who="EPHP">Head of the post-war planning committee of the <org
                    reg="Planned Parenthood Federation of America">Planned Parenthood League of
                    America</org>, Mrs. Sanger’s interest in the possibilities of the post-war world
                is high.</q></p>
        <p>Since the leading scientists of <place reg="United States">America</place>are on our
            board, Planned Parenthood will certainly have a representative on whatever final
            post-war planning council is formed,<q>she said</q>. <person reg="Wells, H.G.">H.G.
                Wells</person>said the most intelligent people of America are on our board, and he’s
            right.</p>
        <p><q who="EPHP">Mrs. Sanger was enthusiastic in her praise of the <org>El Paso Mothers’ Health
            Center</org>, of which <person reg="Pogson, Catherine H.">Mrs. Percy W. Pogson Jr.</person>, is president. </q></p>
        <p>I am proud of the work you have done here, <q who="EPHP">Mrs. Sanger said</q>. It will
            take just that kind of perseverance and devotion to make the post-war world a fit place
            in which to live. The American people have become somewhat timid in the last few years
            and have listened too much to the words of vociferous minorities, but this group in El
            Paso proves how unnecessary that is.</p>
        <p><q who="EPHP">The years of hardship, persecution and misunderstanding through which Mrs.
                Sanger has passed in her efforts to improve the lot of humanity have left no mark,
                unless it be her deep understanding and genuine gentleness. She is one liberal
                thinker who has not become discouraged with the failure of others to catch up with
                her, and has maintained her reverence and flexibility of mind.</q></p>
        <p>Children are the most important things in the world,<q who="EPHP">she said</q>, And it is
            our foremost duty to improve the conditions under which our children and our children’s
            children must live.</p>
        <p/>
    </docBody>
</doc>
