<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/06/19 MM</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1959-08-11"><supplied>11 Aug 1959</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied>Speech at the Mountain View Presbyterian
                Church</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421986</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>"Safe, Sure Birth Control Means Seen in 10
                    Years"</title><supplied resp="MSPP"><title>Tuscon Daily
                        Citizen</title></supplied> Aug. 12, 1959.</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Sanger spoke at a dinner held at the <org>Mountain View
            Presbyterian Church</org> in <place reg="Scottsdale, AZ">Scottsboro, AZ</place> along with <org>Planned Parenthood</org>
            of Tuscon members Rev. <person reg="Lindamood, Samuel">Samuel J. Lindamood</person>, Jr., <person reg="Nelson, Lois">Lois Nelson</person>, and
            <person reg="Kincaid, Della">Della Kincaid</person>. </p><index level1="birth control methods" level2="pill"/>
        <index level1="birth control movement" level2="international"/>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="birth control in"/> </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Safe, Sure Birth Control Means Seen In 10 Years</head>
        <p>Ten more years should bring safe, sure and cheap means of birth
            control, Mrs. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>, founder of the Planned Parenthood
            Movement, said last night at Mountain View Presbyterian Church.</p>
        <p>She said it was proving effective in experiments, but was not ready
            for the general market. </p>
        <p>"That is what we need for worldwide progress," she said.</p>
        <p>"This is my first invitation to your church and I appreciate it
            deeply."</p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger appeared on the platform and answered about a dozen
            questions put to her, but attempted no speech.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger said she was a nurse in <place reg="New York, New York">New York City</place>.</p>
        <p>"I saw the difference (in living conditions) among parents who could
            space their children from those who could not," she said. </p>
        <p>"I began a crusade and was surprised by the difficulties," she added.
            "I became aware of federal laws, and state laws and religious
            prejudice."</p>
        <p>She said birth control movements were spreading in <place>India</place> and other
            nations of Asia. </p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger candidly admitted that <place>Japan</place> relied heavily on abortions
            in reducing its birth rate. However, the public health service in
            Japan, she said, was seeking to protect the health of women by
            spreading information about safer means of spacing children."</p>
        <p>In the United States she said "the careless ones who know nothing are
            the ones having the children they can't care for."</p>
        <p/>
    </docBody>
</doc>
