<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-05-02 JK initial tag</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1946-/-/-/- ">1946</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Birth Control, 1945</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421953</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Birth Control</title>, <title type="book">Britannica Book of
                    the Year, 1946</title></bibl>
            <bibl><title>LCM</title> 49:234</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="Planned Parenthood Federation of America"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Birth Control.</head>

        <p>The activities of the <org>Planned Parenthood Federation of America</org>, Inc. (formerly
            the Birth Control Federation of America), through its 347 state leagues and committees
            and 599 clinics, were given material support and stimulation by events of 1945, which
            found child spacing services either through clinics or referral systems. available in
            every state except <place>Connecticut</place> and <place>Massachusetts</place>. These
            were in 1945 the only states retaining legal barriers which prevented physicians
            prescribing birth control under any condition.</p>
        <p> Legal Decisions.- Two pertinent decisions were handed down in 1945 by the district court
            of appeals in <place>Washington, D.C.</place> The first, a permanent injunction barring
            the postmaster general from interfering with the mailing of the <org>Consumer’s
                Union</org>
            <title type="pamphlet">“Report on Contraceptive Material</title>”; the second,
            overruling the postmaster general’s mailing ban on <person reg="Popenoe, Paul">Paul
                Popenoe</person>'s pamphlet, <title type="pamphlet">“Preparing for
                Marriage.”</title></p>
        <p> In Connecticut a bill to permit physicians to prescribe birth control for patients in
            poor health was killed in committee, although a <org
                reg="Roper Center for Public Opinion Research">Roper</org> survey made just previous
            to the bill’s introduction revealed that 85% of the state’s adult voters were in favor
            of changing existing laws.</p>
        <p> Medical and Public Health.- <person reg="Herrick, William W.">Dr. William W.
                Herrick</person>, president of the <org>New York Academy of Medicine</org>, <place
                reg="New York, New York">New York city</place>, headed a committee of 40 of the
            city’s distinguished physicians who presented a program on “Responsibility for the
            Health of Tomorrow’s Family” at the federation’s 24th annual dinner. Dinner speakers
            included <person reg="Williams, R.C.">Dr. R. C. Williams</person>, assistant U.S.
            surgeon-general, U.S. public health service; <person reg="Schumann, Edward A.">Dr.
                Edward A. Schumann</person>; and <person reg="Grinker, Roy R.">Lt. Col. Roy R.
                Grinker</person>, medical executive, Army Air Force Convalescent hospital, <place
                reg="St. Petersburg, FL">St. Petersburg, Fla</place>. A luncheon address by <person
                reg="Roosevelt, Eleanor">Mrs. Franklin D. Roosevelt</person>, before a symposium of
            social agencies interested in postwar family health, including planned parenthood, was
            broadcast over a national network.</p>
        <p> Temperature chars to assist in determining optimum fertility were made available to
            physicians by the federation’s medical committee, to aid in the treatment of
            infertility. This phase of the planned parenthood program was increased with
            establishment of added infertility services or referral systems in various parts of the
            country. </p>
        <p>From a study of 7,000,000 births, <person reg="Yerushalmey, Jacob">Dr. Jacob
                Yerushalmey</person>, principal statistician of the U.S. public health service,
            published a report advocating an optimum interval between births to decrease the number
            of stillbirths.</p>
        <p> Research. - To stimulate research in the field of human fertility, the <org
                reg="The Lasker Foundation">Albert and Mary Lasker foundation</org> made the first
            of its two annual awards of $500 each to the scientist and public health official making
            significant contributions during the year. Awards for 1945 went to <person
                reg="MacLeod, John James Rickard">Dr. John MacLeod</person>, department of anatomy,
                <org>Cornell University</org> Medical college, <place reg="Ithaca, NY">Ithaca,
                N.Y.</place>, for research in the motility of the <org>Mississippi state board of health</org>
            for including planned parenthood in his state’s public health program to improve infant
            and maternal health. </p>
        <p>Education. - The publication of two new patient pamphlets, <title type="pamphlet"
                >“Planning to Have a Baby?”</title> and <title type="pamphlet">“The Soldier Takes a
                Wife”</title> contributed materially to the large amount of literature requested
            during the year. <title type="pamphlet">“To Those Denied a Child”</title> and <title
                type="pamphlet">“Population and Peace,”</title> a reprint of an address by <person
                reg="Fairchild, Henry Pratt">Dr. Henry Pratt Fairchild</person> at the
                <org>University of Virginia</org>, were also in great demand. Quantities of
            technical manuals and other planned parenthood literature were sent on request to
            physicians, educators, health officer, clergymen and social workers.</p>
        <p> Social Work. - <org reg="National Association of Social Workers">National Social Work
                Advisory </org>committee was organized to give professional advice on the social
            work program. The <org reg="Young Women's Christian Association">Y.W.C.A.</org>
            announced its resolution favouring “the principles of planned parenthood.” Planned
            parenthood literature was included by the <org>National Publicity council</org> in its mailings to
            social agencies throughout the country, many of which ordered further literature for
            distribution. </p>
        <p>Work With Negroes. - A second consultant on work with Negroes was added to the national
            staff, and several state organizations employed Negro field workers and included Negro
            members in their executive committees. A model clinic, the <org>Hannah Stone Planned
                Parenthood centre</org>, was established in <place reg="New York, NY">Harlem
            </place>district, New York city, to aid in reducing stillbirth, infant and maternal
            mortality, which is twice that of other parts of the city. Following an intensive study,
            the <org>National Congress of Colored Parents and Teachers</org> drew up a discussion
            outline of planned parenthood to be distributed to Negro community groups.</p>
        <p> Religion.- A syllabus on marriage and family counseling was published by the
            federation’s <org> National Clergyman’s Advisory council </org>and made available for us
            in seminaries, community training schools and to individual clergymen. Army and navy
            chaplains made wide use of the G.I. pamphlet, <title type="pamphlet">“The Soldier Takes
                a Wife,”</title> and the library of congress translated the pamphlet into braille
            for blinded veterans. The <place>Illinois</place> league for planned parenthood added 500 ministers and
            rabbis to its Clergyman’s Advisory committee and a number of other state organizations
            established similar complanned parenmittees.</p>
        <p> Press and Radio. - Eighty articles reflecting favourable planned parenthood attitudes
            appeared in national popular and technical magazines during 1945. The announcement of
            the federation’s two new pamphlets, (see Education, above) attracted considerable
            newspaper comment, and wire services carried the story throughout the country. Cordial
            relations with many local radio stations were strengthened and both <org>National
                Broadcasting Company</org> and org system carried important annual meeting speakers.
            The <org>Mutual Broadcasting system</org> requested a speaker to discuss <title
                type="pamphlet">“The Soldier Takes a Wife”</title> during a national news cast. The
            <org><place reg="Houston, TX">Houston (Texas)</place> Maternal health centre</org> produced a 15 minute transcription which is
            available to all planned parenthood groups for local broadcast. </p>
        <p>International. -Interest in planned parenthood showed new gains throughout the world with
            the ending of World War II. In <place>England</place>, governmental inquiries disclosed
            that economic and national insecurity, not the knowledge of birth control, was the
            determining factor in the declining birth rate. <place>China</place> and
                <place>Japan</place> took official steps to adopt birth control measures to help
            solve their problems of overpopulation. Students of demography reported that <place>India</place> must
            include birth control in its health program if the high infant and maternal mortality
            was to be reduced. The western world learned of a ruling of the <person reg="al-Husseini, Haj Amin">grand mufti of <place>Egypt </place></person>in
            1937 grating legal and religious permission for the practice of birth control. (See also
            <title type="article">BIRTH STATISTICS</title>.) (M. Sr.)</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
