<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-07-02 AS encoded</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-08-15 CH proof and enter</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1916-10-26">26 Oct 1916</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>A Day With Margaret Sanger in her Birth Control Clinic</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421999</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Brooklyn Daily Eagle</title>, Oct. 24, 1916, p. 4</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="BDE">Brooklyn Daily Eagle</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><index level1="Brownsville Clinic"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="civilization and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="population and"/>
        <index level1="birth control clinics and leagues"/>
        <index level1="children" level2="education of"/>
        <index level1="poverty" level2="family size and"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>A DAY WITH MARGARET SANGER IN HER BIRTH CONTROL CLINIC</head>
        <q who="BDE"><p><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person> is conducting the
                    <org reg="Brownsville Clinic">first birth control clinic</org> ever operated in
                the <place>United States</place> and a day in the clinic from the time you first
                view the scrim covered windows, about which strange to say, no curious crowd
                clusters, to your departure at night, after you have heard the tale of each visitor,
                is one surprise after another.</p></q>
        <p>"It is the feministic note again," <q who="BDE">said Mrs. Sanger to <title type="journal"
                    >The Eagle</title> reporter as she pointed out the eager women who were coming
                in groups to see her at 46 Amboy street, in the Brownsville section of this <place
                    reg="Brooklyn, NY">borough.</place></q></p>
        <p><q who="BDE">And the reporter interviewed these "feminists" and heard again the cry of
                the women who are craving for the things that have been denied them-only these were
                not pining for the privilege of expressing their individuality through the medium of
                a profession, neither were they asking to be relieved from the burdens of a
                household. The plea of these rebels was a very simple one.</q></p>
        <p>"<q who="UNK">Perhaps if I don't have any more children I can give out the washing," said
                one.</q></p>
        <p><q who="BDE">The reporter had talked to Mrs. Sanger of the social significance of her
                work and for a moment the conversation had dwelt on the possible effect on
                population that might be incurred by teaching the foreigners birth control.</q></p>
        <p><q who="BDE">But the women were unconscious of the fact that a problem might center
                around their coming, each had brought her individual burden, that was all. As one
                explained it in answer to a question,</q>
            <q who="UNK">"It is so much easier to talk to a woman than to a man, that is why I never
                tell my doctor."</q>
            <q who="BDE">And another whom the tired lines on her face made look like 40, although
                she could hardly have been more than 80, said:</q></p>
        <p>"<q who="UNK">This is the kind of place that we have been wanting all the time. I have
                had seven children, two are dead, and my husband is a sick man. Do you know how I
                got bread for them? By getting down on my knees and scrubbing floors for the baker;
                that's what I did when we couldn't pay the bill. Seven children," she repeated,
                "that's enough for any woman."</q></p>
        <p><q who="BDE">And so it went on. Most of the women are foreigners. They leave their baby
                carriages outside, some enter timidly, not a few smilingly, and the others, well, as
                they themselves say,</q> "it is easy to talk to a woman," <q who="BDE">and they
                certainly do.</q></p>
        <p>"They tell me of hungry children of neglected and deceased ones," said Mrs. Sanger.
            "They, too, long to be companions to their youngsters in the way they are always
            advising the American mother, they want to enjoy their sons and daughters. But how can
            they? They see educational ideals fostered all about them, and then see their own
            children cheated out of these wonderful American opportunities that we talk so much
            about. You have heard the foreign mother prophesy about her baby: 'He'll be a professor
            when he grows up,' but they see the fallacy of dreaming, as they watch them go into the
            factories instead of the High Schools. It is the first signs of the awakening
            intelligence of a woman, when she insists that she have fewer children so that she can
            have better ones and give them more advantages.</p>
        <p>" <q who="BDE">But let's go back to our foreigners," asked the reporter. "How about
                reducing the number of American citizens which they give us each year?"</q></p>
        <p>"The quality of its citizens and not the quantity is the new keynote of civilization. Do
            you remember when the newspapers in <place>France</place> editorially pointed out the
            fact that the population of their country was being drained and exhausted. The European
            women will never again have sons just to be slaughtered."</p>
        <p>"Women should hold motherhood in their hands," she continued, "and the women here are
            beginning to feel it."</p>
        <p><q who="BDE">Just then the postman interrupted, by poking his head in and throwing some
                letters on the table. "Margaret Sanger, Birth Control Clinic, Brooklyn, <place
                    reg="New York, NY">New York,</place>" was the way in which they were addressed.
                "And they got here," said the recipient with a laugh.</q></p>
        <p><q who="BDE">Side by side, with the letter in which the professor informed Mrs. Sanger
                that</q>
            <q who="UNK">"I am interested in your clinic from a sociological point of view and I
                know that your pioneer movement is to be a mighty force in solving a great social
                problem," is the following typical little note from a woman: "I saw by the
                newspapers that you have a clinic. We have four children and it seems wrong for me
                to have any more as we can just about get along on what we have." Another which
                states "that we are poor as the general run," adds that "my husband is earning $11 a
                week and I have had five children,"</q>
            <q who="BDE">and invites Mrs. Sanger out to a town in <place>Ohio</place> from which the
                letter was sent.</q></p>
        <p><q who="BDE">An unusual request which reads,</q>
            <q who="UNK">"I am a trained nurse, most of my work is maternity cases, often the poor
                delicate mothers ask me for information and I do not know what to tell
            them</q>."</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
