<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published/Draft/Speech/Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/04/23 VS intital tags</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1933-05-17"> 17 May, 1933</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Hotel Boise Speech</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421942</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Birth Control Speaker Urges Sensible Laws</title><title
                    type="journal">Idaho Statesman</title> May 18, 1933</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="IS">Idaho Statesman</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Sanger also appeared at the Owyhee Hotel in Boise the next day.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="and marriage"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="medical justifications"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="medical community and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="politicians and"/>
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="&quot;unfit&quot; to reproduce" level2="social burden of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Birth Control Speaker Urges Sensible Laws</head>
        <div>
            <q who="IS"><p> Speaking in the crystal ball room of <org>Hotel Boise</org>, Friday
                    evening, <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>, advocate of
                    birth control, told why she had spent the last 20 years of her life trying to
                    amend a law which was passed more than 60 years ago.</p></q>
            <q who="IS"><p> She declared that were it possible for birth control information to be
                    given legally, the country would benefit and future citizens would be of a
                    higher type of human beings. The bill now pending on <org
                        reg="United States Congress">congress</org> is in the <org
                        reg="Judiciary Committee of the United States Congress">judiciary
                        committee</org>, of which Senator <person reg="Borah, William Edgar"
                        >Borah</person> is a member.</p></q>
            <p> “Birth control laws were passed by congress 63 years ago,” <q who="IS">she said.</q>
                “A federal law now exists which makes it impossible for scientific or medical
                literature or supplies to be sent through the mails or common carriers.”</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Doctors Not Exempted</head>
            <p> “<name reg="United States Penal Code">This law</name> makes no exemption to the
                medical profession, nor to hospitals nor to medical colleges. It makes it a crime of
                five years in prison or $5,000 fine for anyone to send or receive through the <org
                    reg="United States Postal Service">U.S. mails</org> any information on birth
                control. It also makes it a crime to send the address of a doctor or of a hospital
                or clinic through mails where such information might be obtained.</p>
            <p> “The state laws are different. Nearly all of the state laws exclude and exempt the
                medical profession so that it is perfectly legal for a doctor in the state of
                    <place>Idaho</place> to give oral information to his patients.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Trying to Save Lives</head>
            <p> “We are trying to change this federal law. We are trying to amend this congressional
                law to exempt hospitals, doctors and medical colleges from the penalty of the law.
                Our bill is now in the judiciary committee of the <org reg="United States Senate"
                    >senate</org>, of which Senator Borah is a member. By the amending of this law
                through our bill, we can save thousands of woman and save the state tax payers from
                filling up institutions with a generation of children who are bound to become a
                burden upon society,” <q who="IS">she said.</q></p>
            <q who="IS"><p> Out of about 250 present, 125 signed cards saying they were interested
                    in Mrs. Sanger’s work, and 60 who expressed a desire for a clinic in <place
                        reg="Boise, ID">Boise</place>. This matter will be discussed with Mrs.
                    Sanger today.</p></q>
            <q who="IS"><p> There were 95 at the luncheon at the <org>Owyhee hotel</org> Friday noon
                    to meet Mrs. Sanger.</p></q>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
