<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-05-07 JK initial tag</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1944-04-24">24 Apr 1944</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>
                <supplied resp="MSPP">Statement on Japan Militarists</supplied>
            </titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421955</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Japs Hit Birth Control As War Block</title>, <title
                    type="journal">Seattle Post Intelligencer</title>, Apr. 15, 1944.</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="COHLU">Cohen, Lucille</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger</person> gave this statement in <place
                reg="Seattle, WA">Seattle</place> during a visit with her son, <person
                reg="Sanger, Grant">Grant Sanger</person>, and his family.</p>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="birth control laws and legislation in"/>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="overpopulation and"/>
        <index level1="war" level2="overpopulation and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Japs Hit Birth Control As War Block</head>
        <byline>by <person reg="Cohen, Lucille">Lucille Cohen</person></byline>
        <q who="COHLU">
            <p>Japanese militarists as far back as 1921 were fighting dissemination of birth control
                information, fearful that a lowered birth rate would block their plans for war, Mrs.
                Margaret Sanger, national leader of the birth control movement, declared yesterday
                in Seattle. </p>
            <p>And unless the men who dictate the peace terms force <place>Japan</place>,
                    <place>Germany</place> and <place>Italy</place> to control their birth rates
                instead of their armament production, the three countries will throw the world into
                war again in 20 years, she added. </p>
            <p>Mrs. Sanger bases her opinions on her own experiences in Japan in 1921 when she was
                invited to make a speaking tour with <person reg="Russell, Betrand">Bertrand
                    Russell</person>, the English philosopher, and <person reg="Einsten, Albert"
                    >Albert Einstein</person>, the German mathematical genius. </p></q>
        <p>
            <q who="COHLU">First the Japanese government canceled Mrs. Sanger’s visa and then when
                she managed to get into the country--</q>“by intrigue,”<q who="COHLU"> she says--
                she found she was allowed to make only private speeches. </q></p>
        <p> “The people were clamoring for the information I was bringing,” she said. “Japanese
            women are like women everyplace else. They didn’t want to be burdened down with a baby
            every year until they had more children than they could raise or educate.</p>
        <p>“But the military group wasn’t going to let them hear me. The militarists were beating
            the tom-toms for the glory of prolific motherhood and what it would do for Japan and her
            place in the sun.”</p>
        <p>
            <q who="COHLU">When Mrs. Sanger returned to Japan in 1939 for the second and last time
                she discovered plans for increasing the birth rate were getting along fine--with the
                help of American money. </q></p>
        <p> “The first time I was there the birth rate was about two million a year, of which about
            one million babies lived” she said. "The second time I found tha with private American
            funds given for improving public health the Japanese were cutting down the infant
            mortality rate so that between 1,500,000 and 1,800,000 of the babies born each year
            lived.”</p>
        <q who="COHLU"><p> As outlined to her by Japanese parliament members, the militarists’ plan
                was to encourage population growth to create a need for expansion that would, in
                turn, provide an excuse for war.</p>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger is here visiting her son, Lt. Grant Sanger of <place reg="Seattle, WA"
                    >4702 W. Ruffner St.</place>, a member of the naval medical corps stationed in
                Seattle. Her other son, <person reg="Sanger, Stuart">Ctp. Stuart Sanger</person>, is
                in <place>England</place> with the army. </p></q>
    </docBody>
</doc>
