<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-05-07 JK initial tag</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1941-/--/-/--/">1941</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Birth Control, 1940.</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421940</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Birth Control.</title>, <title
                    type="book">Britannica Book of the Year</title>, 1940, pp.
                94-95.</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S72:227, S72:238,
                L129:77.</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="YBAJE">Ybarnegaray, Jean</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>For draft versions see <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret
                Sanger</person> Microfilm <org reg="Smith College">Smith</org>
            Collection S72:227 and 238, and <org>Library of Congress</org>
            microfilm 129:77.</p>
        <p>For other articles in the <title type="book">Britannica Book of the
                Year</title> series, see <xref from="320976.xml"><title
                    type="article">Birth Control, 1944</title></xref>; <xref
                from="320980.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control,
                    1946</title></xref>; <xref from="320979.xml"><title
                    type="article">Birth Control, 1947</title></xref>; <xref
                from="320981.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control,
                    1949</title></xref>; <xref from="321981.xml"><title
                    type="article">Birth Control, 1950</title></xref>; <xref
                from="320983.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control,
                    1951</title></xref>; <xref from="320984.xml"><title
                    type="article">Birth Control, 1952</title></xref>; <xref
                from="321984.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control,
                    1953</title></xref>; <xref from="320985.xml"><title
                    type="article">Birth Control, 1954</title></xref>; <xref
                from="320986.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control,
                    1955</title></xref>; <xref from="none.xml"><title
                    type="article">Birth Control, 1956</title></xref>; <xref
                from="320987.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control,
                    1957</title></xref>; <xref from="320988.xml"><title
                    type="article">Birth Control, 1958</title></xref></p>
        <index level1="birth control clinics and leagues" level2="in US"/>
        <index level1="birth control clinics and leagues"
            level2="physicians and"/>
        <index level1="Birth Control Federation of America"/>
        <index level1="birth control clinics and leagues"/>
        <index level1="birth control movement" level2="international"/>
        <index level1="birth control movement" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to" level3="international"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="American opinion on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="history of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="international"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Birth Control.</head>

        <p> With the outbreak of the war in 1939, the continued drive of the
            totalitarian nations for increased population and the subjugation of
            the democracies where birth control programs had been in progress,
            not only did activities cease in large part in those countries, but
            with the rigid censorship no news on what was transpiring filtered
            through. </p>
        <p> The forced migration of millions of people in Central
                <place>Europe</place>, the starvation of millions more, the
            separation of families, with great bodies of troops either in
            movement or at the various fronts and away from home, all acted as a
            form of birth control. The malnutrition extending over large areas
            in Europe will affect fertility adversely during and after the
            European war. With these factors will come the fear of depopulation
            which manifested itself before the war. It is to be hoped that there
            will also follow increased recognition of the need for intelligent
            and honest efforts to solve the problems of population pressure,
            especially those dealing with population distribution in relation to
            national resources. Without such solution, a lasting peace can never
            be achieved for these causes are basic reasons for aggression. </p>
        <p> Emphasis in the <place>United States</place> birth control movement
            was, in 1940, on the need for expanding birth control services as a
            means of strengthening the physical and economic well-being of the
            nation as it planned for national defense. </p>
        <p><place>Australia</place>. - Birth control clinics continued to
            operate in Australia, but mothers in the low income group were given
            a maternity bonus of $20 on the birth of each child and in
                <place>New South Wales</place> a small weekly payment for each
            child after the first. </p>
        <p>
            <place>Cuba</place>. - In <place reg="Havana, Cuba">Havana</place>,
            films dealing with the <title type="article">“Technique of
                Contraception”</title> were widely presented to the medical
            profession and the leading medical associations. These is particular
            interest in the birth control program of its neighbouring island,
                <place>Puerto Rico</place>, where efforts to solve similar
            problems of overpopulation have been under way for several years. </p>
        <p><place>England</place>. - Activities of the <org>Family Planning
                association</org> continued in <place>Great Britain</place> up
            to the outbreak of the war. Birth control clinics still functioned.
            The clinic of <person reg="Stopes, Marie">Dr. Marie Stopes</person>,
            the first established in <place reg="London, England"
            >London</place>, was bombed in an air raid in Oct. 1940 and partly
            demolished. </p>
        <p>
            <place>France</place>. - The new code which went into effect late in
            1939, not only provided new and drastic regulations against
            abortion, but prohibited the advertising of contraception. Because
            of censorship of everything published, including even a discussion
            of contraception,<title type="journal"> La Grande Reforme</title>,
            the French Neo-Malthusian journal, edited by <person
                reg="Humbert, Eugene">Eugene Humbert</person>, suspended
            publication late in that year. </p>
        <p> Following the conquest of France, <person reg="Ybarnegaray, Jean"
                >Jean Ybarnegaray</person>, minister of youth in the <place
                reg="Vichy France">Vichy government</place>, announced a new
            policy to stimulate the birth rate. The young women of France will
            be educated for one purpose only! <q who="YBAJE">“To return to their
                traditional purpose of life- being in their homes and living
                only to raise strong useful men.” </q>Fathers of families will
            be given preference over bachelors in both public and private
            employment and will be paid in proportion to the size of their
            families. </p>
        <p><place>Germany. </place>- Germany continued an uncompromising
            opposition to any form of birth control. In Dec. 1939, a new
            population policy was officially announced. All soldiers going to
            the front were expected to leave children or prospective children
            behind them. </p>
        <p> Since the outbreak of the war, censorship in Germany has resulted in
            a complete cessation of all statistical material on population. </p>
        <p><place reg="Holland, Netherlands">Holland. </place>- New birth
            control clinics were opened in <place reg="Amsterdam, Netherlands"
                >Amsterdam</place> and <place reg="Enscede, Netherlands"
                >Enschede</place>, both in industrial sections where many
            factory workers live. This progress took place prior to the invasion
            of Holland. After that, no news was received. </p>
        <p>
            <place>India</place>. - The <org>All-India Women’s conference</org>,
            which met in <place reg="Allahabad, India">Allahabad</place> in Jan.
            1940, adopted a new resolution on family planning which urged that
            women medical officers in municipal and government hospitals,
            dispensaries and health centres advise married women on child
            spacing and that the technique of contraception be taught these
            officers. </p>
        <p> The <org reg="Planning Commission">National planning
                commission</org> appointed by the national congress passed a
            resolution that family planning and limitation of children were
            essentials in the interest of national economy and urged the state
            to adopt a policy encouraging the establishment of birth control
            clinics and other necessary measures to encourage the spread of
            cheap and safe methods of birth control. </p>
        <p>
            <place>Japan</place>. - Japan’s official pressure for a higher birth
            rate during the Sino-Japanese war resulted in an increase in the
            rate of infant mortality. Coupled with the demand for an increase in
            population, as a patriotic duty during the war, suppression of birth
            control clinics and of discussion of birth control continued. </p>
        <p><place>New Zealand</place>. - <org>The Sex Hygiene and Birth
                Regulation society of New Zealand</org> dissolved during 1940 to
            re-form as the <org>Family Planning Association</org>, affiliated
            with the British organization. A deputation of workers from the
            association in conference with the ministry of health requested that
            contraceptive advice be given by physicians, when necessary, at
            state maternity hospitals. </p>
        <p> Puerto Rico. - With the legality of contraceptive advice, under
            medical direction, established in Puerto Rico by legal decision in
            1939, clinic services have been established under the supervision of
            the Puerto Rico board of health. The <org
                reg="Salud Materna e Infantil de Puerto Rico">Associacion pro
                Salud Maternal e Infantil de Puerto Rico</org>, under the
            medical direction of <person reg="Belaval, Joseph S.">Dr. J.S.
                Belaval</person>, continued its educational and research efforts
            to determine the type of contraceptive best adapted for use on the
            island. Public interest in the medical and public health aspects of
            birth control were stimulated by a visit from Mrs. Sanger in 1940
            and the medical films on contraception were being widely shown among
            scientific and medical groups. </p>
        <p>
            <place>Sweden</place>. - The new population measures instituted in
            Sweden which went into effect Jan. 1, 1938, based on the principle
            that voluntary parenthood and a positive population policy must be
            brought together, were in their second year. This policy emphasizes
            that only children welcome to their parents are wanted by the
            nation; but it also recognizes that certain social conditions must
            be rearranged so that more children can be welcomed. Birth control
            services were widely extended to reach all groups of society, but to
            reduce the economic motive for extreme family regulation, a series
            of measures, involving not cash premiums to parents but health and
            environmental services benefitting the children themselves, were put
            into effect. Hence skilled labourers and artisans in Swedish cities
            are having more children than the unskilled. It is to be hoped that
            the war will not destroy Sweden’s interesting and historic
            experiment. </p>
        <p> United States: Clinics. - The growth of birth control centres in the
            United States continued. On Nov. 1, 1940 these totalled 589, of
            which 106 were in hospitals, 178 in health departments and 305 in
            other quarters, largely extramural. Of these centres, 206 were
            supported wholly or in part by public funds. </p>
        <p> Human Fertility. - In Jan. 1940 the <title type="journal">Journal of
                Contraception</title>, published by the medical department of
            the <org reg="Birth Control Federation of America">Birth Control
                federation</org>, changed its name to <title type="journal"
                >Human Fertility</title>, as more truly expressing its contents. </p>
        <p> Field Work. - Representatives of the Birth Control Federation of
            America, Inc. co-operating with various health agencies, extended
            birth control services to underprivileged mothers in 11 states not
            yet ready to undertake state-wide programs under their health
            departments. The services were medically supervised and simple
            contraceptives were advised. </p>
        <p>U.S. Population Policies. - Wide attention was given to a report by
            the Population committee of the <org>National Economic and Social
                Planning association </org>which advocated “Provision for
            scientific information concerning appropriate methods of
            contraception for all potential parents is an essential measure for
            sound population policy.”</p>
        <p>Special Negro Project. - The federation, through a special grant of
            funds, established a division of Negro service, sponsored by a
                <org>National Advisory council</org> which included Negro
            leadership in all fields. Two special Demonstration projects were
            established, one in <place reg="Nashville, TN">Nashville,
                Tenn.</place> and one in <place reg="Berkeley, SC">Berkeley
                county, S.C</place>., to study the effects of medically directed
            contraception upon the health and welfare of the Negro populations
            of those sections. The Urban project in Nashville is under the
            direction of the <org
                reg="National Association of County and City Health Officials"
                >City Health officers</org> and the Rural project will be
            supervised by the chairman of the <org>Committee on Maternal Welfare
                of the South Carolina State Medical association.</org>
        </p>
        <p> Legal Action.- The <org>Federal Trade commission</org> was active
            during 1940 against false claims for a number of commercial
            contraceptives. Cease and desist order were issued against some and
            suits instituted against others. Such government action was welcomed
            by the organized movement for birth control, as a step in regulation
            of the bootleg traffic in undependable contraceptives. </p>
        <p> Legal Decisions: <place>Connecticut</place>.- On March 21, 1940, the
                <org>Supreme Court of Errors</org> of the State of Connecticut,
            by a vote of 3 to 2, handed down a decision patterned on that in
                <place>Massachusetts </place>in 1938. The Connecticut decision
            upheld the existing statute and ruled that under it, it was illegal
            for a physician to prescribe, or a patient to use, contraceptives,
            even where definite medical indications existed. Connecticut is now
            one of the only two states in the Union where a doctor is forbidden
            to advise a patient on contraception and remains the only state
            where the use of contraceptives is illegal. </p>
        <p>
            <place>Iowa</place>.- A decision in a suit brought against a
            druggist in Iowa, in 1937, was handed down by the supreme court of
            that state in 1939. The druggist was accused of violating the law by
            distributing a pamphlet entitled <title type="pamphlet">“Birth
                Control.”</title> The court ruled him not guilty because the
            code of laws of the state specifically exempted medical schools,
            physicians and druggists from the provisions of the act governing
            distribution of contraceptive literature or materials. </p>
        <p> Massachusetts. - While previous court decisions declared it illegal
            for a physician to give contraceptive information under any
            conditions, the decision of the Massachusetts supreme court, Sept.
            17, 1940 by a vote of 3 to 1, reversed a former ruling and declared
            a pharmacist not guilty in selling certain articles for the
            prevention of conception because there was no proof they were to be
            used for the prevention of conception. This decision added to the
            existing legal confusion in Massachusetts, making it possible for
            bootleg traffic in questionable contraceptives to flourish, while
            legitimate medical contraceptive service remained outlawed. An
            Initiative Petition distributed by the <org>Massachusetts Mothers
                Health council</org> to amend the statutes involved was filed
            with over 45,000 signatures, though only 20,000 were legally
            required. </p>
        <p> State Birth Control Federations. - There are now 32 organized state
            birth control organizations co-operating with the Birth Control
            federation. <person reg="Rose, Kenneth">Dr. Kenneth Rose</person>
            became executive vice-president of the federation in 1940 and
                <person reg="Morris, Woodbridge E.">Woodbridge E. Morris,
                M.D.</person>, former director of the division of <org>Maternal
                and Child Health of the Delaware</org> state board of health
            became general medical director. </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
