<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/07/03 MM</prepDate>
        <docAuthor><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1956-05-29">29 May 1956</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Address to the Rochester-Monroe County League for
                    Planned Parenthood Annual Meeting</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421989</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>"<title type="article">Mrs. Sanger Offers 'Key to World Peace'</title>"<title
                    type="newspaper">Democrat and Chronicle</title> 05/30/56</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">Sanger addressed the <place reg="Rochester, NY">Rochester</place>-Monroe
        County League for <org>Planned Parenthood</org> at the Rochester Chamber of Commerce, to an
        audience of 400 people. <index level1="Japan" level2="overpopulation and"/><index
            level1="Japan" level2="population policies of"/><index level1="overpopulation"
            level2="threat to peace as"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Mrs. Sanger Offers 'Key to World Peace'</head>
        <p>The speaker, Mrs. Margaret Sanger, argued that family planning must be persued to
            eliminate overpopulation, a cause of wars. "It is," she said, "the keynote of a new
            social awakening."</p>
        <p>She addressed the annual meeting of the Rochester-Monroe County League for Planned
            Parenthood in the Chamber of Commerce. About 400 persons--including health and welfare
            leaders--heard her speak.</p>
        <p>"It would have been laughable to talk about overpopulation in this country," she grinned.
            But, Mrs. Sanger added, not so in Asia.</p>
        <p>In 1952, when <place>Japan</place>'s population was 90 million, Mrs. Sanger returned to
            the country to find that her proposals had at least been endorsed by the government and
            accepted by women.</p>
        <p>"They are going about it in a very scientific way," she explained. "In fact, I would say
            they are leading the world."</p>
        <p>"When this work is properly directed, it can relieve untold suffering for countless
            number of women. It is an essential step we must take if we are to eliminate war and
            bring peace to the face of the world."</p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger, who had three children, reaffirmed her belief that "many people are parents
            today who have no right to be parents."</p>
        <p>"We believe firmly," Mrs. Sanger said, "that a man who can take care of two children well
            should not have eight children. But many of them do."</p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger also suggested that young couples wait at least two years before they have
            children. She said: "They should postpone parenthood until they are sure they are going
            to be happy so as to prepare a harmonious atmospehre for the child."</p>
        <p>The bulk of Mrs. Sanger's addresss was devoted to her early--and often stormy--work in
            the birth control movement.</p>
        <p/>
        <p/>
    </docBody>
</doc>
