<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/07/08 AS encoded</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-08-15 CH proof and enter</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1926/11/00">Nov. 1926</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Spreading Birth Control: A Woman's Activity</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp422024</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title>, Nov. 1926, pp. 343 and
                353.</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
            <name id="LUTMA">Luther, Martin</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>This unsigned article may have been written by Margaret Sanger.</p>
        <index level1="Birth Control Review, The"/>
        <index level1="Birth Control Federation of America"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="class-based"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="religion and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Spreading Birth Control: A Woman's Activity</head>
        <div type="section">
            <p>FOR the third time the <org>American Birth Control League</org> has had its booth at
                the <org reg="Women's Arts and Industries Exposition">Woman's Activities
                    Exhibit</org> in <place reg="New York, NY">New York,</place> which was held this
                year in the ballroom of the <org>Hotel Astor</org> September 27th-October 1st.
                Exhibitors from many other booths came to congratulate the League on its
                advantageous position near one of the main entrances, and to get information about
                its work. As for visitors to the exhibit, though the faces of those who stopped or
                passed the booth by were new, the interest was the same as last year. Many of those
                who passed by turned as though arrested by something of great interest and looked
                back as if they fain would stop. Some did come back later, to find that interest in
                Birth Control was nothing to be ashamed of or afraid of.</p>
            <p>Of those who stopped, some were critics, others friends and still others people who
                wanted to know what Birth Control was or who wanted to have their doubts laid to
                rest by learning what it was not. With the latter <person reg="Cartere, Mrs.">Mrs.
                    Cartere</person> and <person reg="Vandever, Martha R.">Mrs. Vandever,</person>
                who, with a changing group of helpers, had charge of the booth throughout the
                exhibit, were especially successful. After a talk with them it was a common thing to
                hear a vistor say <q who="UNK">"I did not know that was what Birth Control meant.
                    That is very different. I certainly am for it."</q> Visitors who came to enquire
                were of all classes.</p>
            <p>Among those who were most eager to learn all there was to know about Birth Control
                were the people at the exhibit who represented the very poor, the doormen, the
                colored porters, the cleaning women-already parents of larger families than either
                health or pocketbook could properly support. A special effort was made to reach
                these and the effort was amply repaid by the close attention with which they
                listened and the look of relief and hope with which they accepted a card to the <org
                    reg="Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau">Clinical Research
                Department.</org></p>
            <p>The <org>Continuation School</org> girls who came through in groups-girls forced
                through poverty to work so young that they must carry a certain amount of school
                work while employed-were also fertile soil.</p>
            <p>AMONG our critics were some Roman Catholics, but Roman Catholics were among our
                friends and supporters also. This was even more noticeable than at last year's
                exhibit, women stated they belonged to this <org reg="Roman Catholic Church"
                    >church</org> came up, some in groups and some singly, to express appreciation
                of the work of the League. One of these was an Irishwoman, a house to house
                saleswoman of stockings, whose work took her to the doors of many crowded homes in
                city and country. "<q who="UNK">I believe our priests don't approve, but that does
                    not influence me</q>," she said. "<q who="UNK">I never had no children so I
                    don't need it myself, but I know many that does and I will do my bit to help the
                    work along as I go from house to house</q>."</p>
            <p>A group of three Catholic women-one of them a teacher of feeble-minded children who
                held it a sin and a shame that these poor little souls should be thrust into a world
                they were not equipped to cope with-told many stories of the intolerances of their
                pastors and masters. One of these ladies had been a regular customer of <person
                    reg="Marion, Kitty">Kitty Marion</person> ever since a priest told her of "<q
                    who="UNK">a bold and brazen woman</q>" who sold the <title type="journal">BIRTH
                    CONTROL REVIEW</title> on New York streets. Another owed her keen interest in
                the movement in large part to the intolerant and cruel reaction of her physician-a
                woman and a Catholic like herself-to the subject.</p>
            <p>What, she had asked her, of babies born only to die? "<q who="UNK">Let them be born
                    to die</q>," answered the physician. But if the woman has heart disease? "<q
                    who="UNK">Let her go through with it.</q>" Behind this modern doctor whose
                thought is still medieval one can almost see the shadow of <person
                    reg="Luther, Martin">Martin Luther</person> and hear his reverberating voice
                dictate the words that will, in the minds of women at least, eternally stain his
                fame. "<q who="LUTMA">Let her only die in bearing. She is there to do it.</q>" The
                    <org>Protestant church</org> he founded has outgrown this point of view and the
                testimony of some of these Catholics show that the laity in that church also is fast
                outgrowing it.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">SPREADING BIRTH CONTROL</head>
            <p>These were the new types at the Birth Control booth this year. Besides this there
                were all the old Social workers, nurses, doctors, college students and other
                broadminded men and women expressed hearty approval. On the other side were those
                who had "<q who="UNK">outgrown the need of Birth Control</q>" and who didn't see
                that others had not, those who were too squeamish to touch such a subject, those
                who, offhand on the basis of their own individual experience of spinsterhood or
                motherhood, condemned it.</p>
            <p>One of these brought a quick answer from Mrs. Vandever. Said she, as she looked back
                disdainfully in passing, "<q who="UNK">I am a <emph rend="italics"
                >mother</emph></q>" "<q who="VANMA">And some of us are grandmothers and
                    great-grandmothers</q>," answered Mrs. Vandever, picking up the photograph of
                the presiding genius of the booth. This was the Birth Control great-grandchild-Birth
                Control because born when its mother wanted it and not by accident-of one of the
                    <person reg="Unknown">strongest members of the board of directors</person> of
                the American Birth Control League.</p>
            <p>These are stories of individual visitors. As to numbers, some idea of how many were
                reached at the Woman's Activities Exhibit can be gained by the fact that 5,000
                pieces of literature were given, though an effort was made to give only to those who
                manifested a real interest.</p>
        </div>

    </docBody>
</doc>
