<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/07/16 AS encoded</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-08-15 CH proof and edit</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1917/12/00">Dec 1917</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Editorial Comment</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp422041</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title>, Dec. 1917, p. 16.</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="CROJA">Cropsey, James C.</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><index level1="Birth Control Review, The"/>
        <index level1="Mindell, Fania"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="rights associated with"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="opposition to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="war and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>EDITORIAL COMMENT</head>
        <p>THE APPEAL in the case of <person reg="Mindell, Fania">Fania Mindell</person> has been
            won. Miss Mindell was arrested in the <org reg="Brownsville Clinic">Brownsville birth
                control clinic</org> for selling <title type="book">"What Every Girl Should
                Know,"</title>
            <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger's</person> book on sex hygiene. By a 2 to
            1 vote, the <org reg="New York City Court of Special Sessions">Court of Special
                Sessions</org> declared this book to be "indecent," Judges <person
                reg="Hermann, Moses">Herman</person> and <person reg="O'Keefe, George J."
                >O'Keefe</person> voting for conviction and <person reg="Freschi, John J.">Judge
                Freschi</person> for acquittal. The forces of reaction were bolstered up by <person
                reg="Cropsey, James C.">Judge James C. Cropsey,</person> of the <org
                reg="New York State Supreme Court">Supreme Court,</org> who went out of his way to
            declare that the information in the book was what "<q who="CROJA">no girl should
                know</q>." Yet the reversal of judgment accorded by the <org
                reg="New York State Court, Appellate Division">Appellate Division</org> was by an
            unanimous vote. This victory was of great importance, because several other persons who
            had been arrested for selling "<title type="book">What Every Girl Should Know</title>,"
            and whose cases were being held in abeyance, had the charges against them dismissed as
            soon as the final verdict was rendered in the Mindell appeal. The latter cost several
            hundred dollars in fees for records, copies of the minutes, printing bills, etc. But it
            goes without saying that under our present system of justice no compensation has been
            awarded to those who financed the appeal. To date, the Court has not even refunded the
            $50, which Fania Mindell was, by its own admission, wrongly fined. Once again it has
            been proved that it takes money to obtain "justice," and that the workers cannot
            possibly afford to appeal cases.</p>
        <p><place reg="New York">NEW YORK</place> has just enfranchised more than 3,000,000 women.
            The ardent, self-sacrificing workers who devoted years of their lives to bringing this
            result about deserve the highest praise and the gratitude of their sex. After their long
            fight, they can now enjoy the fruits of victory. But only too large a proportion of
            those they have set free politically will be quite unable to take advantage of the vote
            that has been so dearly earned. There are hundreds of thousands of mothers who are so
            submerged beneath the burdens of child-bearing that they will not have the time even to
            cast their vote, much less to take an intelligent interest in the problems of society.
            Surely the next step is to set these women free. Birth control is the fundamental
            liberty which they must have. We appeal to the new women citizens of New York State to
            assist us in waging the battle which now takes pre-eminence-that for the repeal of laws
            preventing the dissemination of birth control knowledge.</p>
        <p>THE WAR has taken the best energies of most radical and forward movements. Persons who
            formerly were willing to work for the advancement of humanity are now devoting all their
            strength to the world tragedy. But there are still some of us who believe birth control
            to be a fundamental solution to the problems of poverty, prostitution, child labor and
            even war itself. The intolerance of our public censors prevents us from being very
            active on the platform or in the press, at least until peace is restored. But there is
            one way in which we can use this dark period of repression to serve the future of the
            movement. We can do definite and constructive work by gathering data so convincing that
            the Legislature of New York State will be unable to ignore the demand for the repeal of
            Section 1142. <person reg="Whitman, Charles S.">Governor Whitman</person> promised last
            Spring to appoint a commission to investigate the conditions bearing upon birth control,
            but the war has delayed this official action for the present. The thing for us who are
            still devoted to our cause to do, is to hasten the appointment of the commission by
            preparing the material on which it must work. Were we, for instance, to collect the
            histories of</p>
        <list>
            <item>5,000 women living in prostitution,</item>
            <item>5,000 women toiling in factories,</item>
            <item>5,000 women toiling in mills,</item>
            <item>5,000 inmates of prisons,</item>
            <item>5,000 derelicts of poorhouses,</item>
        </list>
        <p>and show what percentage of these people come from large families, so searching a light
            would be thrown on this new angle of social betterment that the Governor's commission
            would be stimulated into action and the benighted laws against birth control would be
            wiped off the statute books. The editors of this magazine would be glad to hear from
            readers in all parts of the country willing to help either by contributing to an
            investigation fund or by volunteering their time and services for research work.</p>
        <p>THE JUSTICES of the Supreme Court of New York state receive $17,500 a year. On this
            pitiable salary, it is, of course, unreasonable to expect them to put in much time on
            writing opinions which would serve to explain their frequently obscure acts to the
            public that pays them. For instance, when the Appellate Division, First Department,
            decided to uphold the Commissioner of Licenses as against <person reg="Bijur, Nathan"
                >Judge Bijur,</person> in connection with the <rs type="film" reg="Birth Control"
                >birth control photoplay</rs>, they made absolutely no comment. The scholarly
            document in which Judge Bijur demonstrated that the film was not immoral was thrown out
            of court with the rubber-stamp comment, "Decision reversed." Again, when "<title
                type="book">What Every Girl Should Know</title>" won the right to be circulated, the
            Court merely O.K.'d it as being "decent," without handing down a written opinion which
            would have served as a precedent in future appeals for the right to print the truth.
            Similar books will have to go through the same ridiculous procedure, and unwind the same
            red tape which one strong, intelligent opinion would have cut for good and all.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
