<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Editorial">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/07/16 AS encoded</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-08-15 CH proof and enter</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1918/06/00">June 1918</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Editorial Comment</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp422028</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title>, June 1918, p. 16.</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="BCR">Birth Control Review</name>
            <name id="HNJ">Holy Name Journal</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="religion and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="war and"/>
        <index level1="Birth Control Review, The"/>
        <index level1="Catholic Church" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="New York Women's Publishing Co."/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>EDITORIAL COMMENT</head>
        <p>EVEN CONFERENCES are human. Each has a spirit of its own and it is this spirit that
            counts and makes such gatherings useful. The keynote of the recent Birth Control
            Conference in <place reg="New York, NY">New York</place> was struck when workers in the
            movement testified that everywhere they found a greedy acceptance that birth control is
            a necessity for women. They found it easy to convince people of its desirability and
            expediency even when doubt was felt at first. War has opened the eyes of women to their
            own position in the world. What birth control advocates now need in their work is a
            classification of facts, scientific facts on health, facts on population, increase and
            decrease, facts as to what the laws are in different countries and different states.
            They want facts as to what doctors can legally do now and how clinics can be legally
            opened. They want to know why so many physicians are indifferent and ignorant regarding
            contraceptive methods. The facts are scattered through many volumes, some of which
            cannot be had by the layman. The birth control movement now wants accurate knowledge of
            all these things made readily available for their use in a campaign of education. It is
            a hopeful note. It shows the workers in the movement feel victory coming soon. We wish
            to add a word of gratittude and appreciation to the splendid work of <person
                reg="Dennett, Mary Ware">Mrs. Mary Ware Dennett</person> who organized the
            Conference and also to the devoted spirit of <person reg="Pinchot, Gertrude Minturn"
                >Mrs. Amos Pinchot</person> who though constantly active in various war activities,
            has rightly proclaimed that standing by the birth control movement today is a great
            national duty toward generations yet to be.</p>
        <p><org reg="Roman Catholic Church">THE CATHOLIC CHURCH</org> is the bigotted, relentless
            enemy of birth control. It makes no bones about its stand. This movement threatens its
            hold upon the poor and the ignorant, and probably only the existence of restraining laws
            prevents it from applying the thumb-screw and the rack to all those who believe in
            woman's right to practise voluntary motherhood. But, since the methods of the
            Inquisition are out of date, it would compromise by clapping us all into jail. "The
            birth-controllers are at it again!" runs a medieval editorial in <title type="journal"
                >The Holy Name Journal,</title> the organ of one of the most powerful Catholic
            societies in <place reg="United States">America.</place> "<q who="HNJ">Prison starvation
                seems but to have whetted their desire to continue the propaganda for what will
                ultimately be the extermination of the masses upon which our country must rely in
                the future</q>." Observe the admission that our propaganda (as the Holy-Namers see
            it) "<q who="HNJ">will ultimately</q>" succeed. "<q>Aside from its ethical and moral
                depravity</q>," the article goes on to say, "<q who="HNJ">the birth-controllers are
                disseminating a doctrine that is decidedly shortsighted and subversive of even the
                material welfare of the land. We need our teeming masses now, we shall need them
                more in the future. Would it not be a wise move on the part of the <org
                    reg="United States Government">Government</org> to intern all birth-controllers
                and suppress their teaching? It would be a prudent war measure</q>." Do we expect
            ever to win over the Catholic Church to our way of thinking? Not right away. We are
            aware that it will fight to the last ditch against this ideal. But we propose to go on
            enrolling Catholics under our banner of progress-by the thousands today, by the hundreds
            of thousands in a year or two. In the long run, reason will inevitably triumph over
            darkness and superstition. Even the Catholic Church will yield to the force of public
            opinion.</p>
        <p>PRIESTS AND MINISTERS of many Christian sects (outside of the Catholic Church) have been
            among the converts to birth control during recent years. That men of their calling
            should join us has not sent us into special ecstasies of tickled vanity and gratified
            respectability. We have welcomed them as individuals, as intelligent persons who have
            had the courage of their opinions in the face of a good deal of social opposition. So
            the fact that the Rev. <person reg="Inge, William Ralph">William Ralph Inge,</person>
            dean of <org>St. Paul's Cathedral,</org>
            <place reg="London, England">London,</place> has recently come out in favor of birth
            control and eugenics does not impress us merely because he is a dean. We consider it
            deserving of comment, because in his public statement on the subject Dr. Inge pointed
            out that a reduction of births will be necessary to combat unemployment after the war.
            He is reported as saying that this movement would "<q who="INGWI">save and make happy
                the population</q>." <org>Church of England</org> incumbents are paid by the State,
            and the <org reg="United Kingdom Government">British Government</org> is clamoring for
            babies. Consequently, by telling the plain truth at this time Dr. Inge proved himself to
            be an honest and brave man, and we take off our hats to him. It is interesting to note
            that he asserted that the average lifetime has increased one-third during the last sixty
            years-an additional reason for the general practice of birth control.</p>
        <p>A REGRETTABLY FALSE idea of present conditions in the birth control movement has been
            caused in some quarters. The <org>Birth Control League of New York</org> held a meeting
            early in May, at which <person reg="Myers, Hiram">Hiram Myers</person> was unanimously
            elected president, <person reg="Stone, Margaret Grant">Mrs. Eugene P. Stone,</person>
            vice-president, <person reg="Goldstein, J.J.">J.J. Goldstein,</person> treasurer, and
                <person reg="Stuyvesant, Elizabeth">Elizabeth Stuyvesant,</person> secretary. An
            erroneous newspaper report of the proceedings at this meeting stated that most of the
            leagues which had been founded following the prosecution of various leaders of the
            movement had now become inactive or gone out of business. "<q who="UNK">There seems to
                be something in the private nature of the subject</q>," an ex-officer was said to
            have declared, "<q who="UNK">which makes it unsuited for a public movement.</q>" The
            misleading nature of the above statements must be apparent to the members of the twenty
            or more active leagues listed in our directory on Page 2. It is one of the few radical
            movements which has not been destroyed by America's participation in the war. <org>The
                New York Women's Publishing Company</org> has been formed to finance this magazine,
            and is offering $10 shares in a $10,000 fund to our friends and supporters. We have a
            growing circulation and have never felt more hopeful of the future.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
