<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/07/08 AS encoded</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-08-15 CH proof and edit</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1926/06/00">June 1926</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Editorial</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp422023</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title>, June 1926, pp. 185-86.</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="DAVRA">Davidson, Randall, (Arch.)</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>This unsigned editorial may have been written by Margaret Sanger.</p>
        <index level1="Birth Control Review, The"/>
        <index level1="public health" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="birth control clinics and leagues"/>
        <index level1="motherhood"/>
        <index level1="voluntary motherhood"/>
        <index level1="overpopulation"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="civilization and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>EDITORIAL</head>
        <p>OUR co-workers in <place>England</place> in the cause of Birth Control are indeed to be
            congratulated that on April 28th, the <org reg="United Kingdom House of Lords">House of
                Lords</org> passed <person reg="Buckmaster, Stanley">Lord Buckmaster's</person>
            motion, and voted for liberty for public health officers and clinic doctors to give
            contraceptive advice at welfare centers. What this would mean to the spread of Birth
            Control knowledge may be realized when it is remembered that, after long years of work,
            and with great difficulty as regards funds, there have been established in England only
            ten or twelve Birth Control clinics, while there already exist 2,122 health centers, and
            of these 641 are especially devoted to pre-natal and post-natal infant care. These
            centers are supported out of public funds, part of the expense being defrayed by the
            local authorities and part by the <org reg="United Kingdom National Treasury">National
                Treasury.</org> There is no law against Birth Control information being given at
            them. The obstacle is a regulation drawn up by the <org
                reg="United Kingdom Ministry of Health">Ministry of Health,</org> the breach of
            which would entail the loss of the money received from the central government. No law is
            necessary for the alteration of this regulation. It would be entirely sufficient if the
                <org reg="United Kingdom House of Commons">House of Commons</org> would pass a
            similar resolution to that passed by the Lords.</p>
        <p>THE opposition to Lord Buckmaster's motion was voiced by the <person
                reg="Gascoyne-Cecil, James">Marquess of Salisbury,</person> who apparently
            represented the <org reg="Conservative Party">Conservative Government,</org> and <person
                reg="Fitzalan-Howard, Bernard">Lord Fitz-Alan,</person> a Roman Catholic peer. The
                <person reg="Davidson, Randall">Archbishop of Canterbury</person> made an indecisive
            speech. He objected to the duty of giving Birth Control advice being laid upon the
            Welfare Centers, but did not condemn Birth Control entirely. Speaking of his church, he
            said "<q who="DAVBE">The question now divides us</q>" "<q who="DAVBE">I have never been
                able</q>," <q who="DAVBE">he added, "to take the stern and uncompromising view of
                some people who think that the thing per se is wrong and evil, although I discourage
                it by every means in my power</q>." His opinion was that women who wanted such
            advice should obtain it from private physicians. The difficulties in the way for the
            poorer women did not seem visible to His Grace. Among those who spoke in favor of Birth
            Control were <person reg="Russell, Frank">Earl Russell,</person> elder brother of
                <person reg="Russell, Bertrand">Bertrand Russell,</person> who made a strong plea
            for the right of the woman to settle with her own conscience whether she would bear a
            child or not, <person reg="Balfour, Arthur">Earl Balfour of Burleigh,</person>
            <person reg="Sackville, Herbrand">Earl de la Warr</person> and <person
                reg="Norton, Cecil">Lord Rathcreedan.</person></p>
        <p>THE world is the poorer for the loss of <person reg="Key, Ellen">Ellen Key,</person> who
            died on April 25th, at her home in <place>Sweden.</place> She was born in 1849, and the
            three quarters of a century, over which her life extended, saw greater changes in the
            position, and especially in the outlook of women than any similar period since the world
            began. And in this changed outlook Ellen Key had her part. Perhaps it would be a
            misnomer to call her a leader, for she headed no popular movement, she identified
            herself with no organized agitation for change or progress. She raised her voice against
            the suffrage fight. She warned the eager feminists of the early twentieth century that
            they were on the wrong path when they sought equal rights with men in education and in
            industrial and professional opportunity. It was her fate to shock the sensibilities and
            the moral ideals of her contemporaries, and yet to be considered a conservative and even
            a reactionary by the women who were pushing out so earnestly into the life of the great
            world. Yet it may be that in some respects her vision was clearer and more far-seeing
            than that of the women who had thrown themselves into the struggle for education, for
            the vote, for the right to a career and to freedom to control their own lives. It may be
            that when all these lesser rights have been secured, women will find that the greatest
            right of all is the right to their own special function-the right to responsible,
            freely-chosen maternity.</p>
        <p>THE great service rendered by Ellen Key was that she sounded a clarion cry-a cry that was
            harsh and discordant in the ears of many who heard it first, but a cry that woke up the
            womanhood of the world and forced women everywhere to think and to revalue their
            accepted ideas and traditions. When "<title type="book">The Century of the
            Child</title>" appeared in 1909, it marked the beginning of a new era, an era which is
            slow in being fully realized, for it required an unpheaval of the thoughts of men which
            cannot be accomplished in less than a generation. Towards its accomplishment there is no
            movememnt which is doing more effectual work than ours for Birth Control. Ellen Key
            herself never seemed fully conscious of the importance of Birth Control for the
            accomplishment of her aim of true motherhood, but Birth Control is the necessary
            corollary to her insistence on the right of every woman to choose motherhood. The
            essence of her teaching was that women must develop themselves as women-as mothers. They
            could not reach their full stature by forcing themselves into the molds of life created
            by men. It was not desirable for the world that they should follow the example of men in
            education, in industry, in business, in the professions, in government, if the world
            were to be made fit for little children. The men had not succeeded in doing this. The
            world, from the point of view of the child, was a failure. It remained for the women to
            recreate it, and they must do this through the development of their own unique qualities
            as mothers-through freely chosen, responsible motherhood.</p>
        <p>A REMARKABLE object lesson in the relation of over-population to lower standards of
            civilization was presented to the world early in May when the great general strike broke
            out in England. It will be recalled that the cause of the strike was the effort of the
            mine-owners to reduce the wages and increase the hours of the miners. The miners
            strenuously objected, and trade unions in other lines of industry joined in the fight.
            It was generally acknowledged that the condition of the miners was considerably worse
            than it had been in 1914 before the war. It was also conceded that mining was worse paid
            in England than other lines of work requiring equal skill and fewer privations. But the
            fact remained that there were 130,000 more miners than could be employed profitably in
            the industry, and that markets were lacking for English coal-markets that had been
            available before the war. The birth-rate of miners is higher than that in any other
            group in England, and it has been the habit of the miners to put their sons into their
            own industry. Whether England as a whole is over-populated or not, it is plain that the
            mining industry suffers from over-population and it is a problem beyond the wits of the
            wisest statesman to find a way out of the difficulty which will not cause wide
            suffering, and probably a very general lowering of the level of living for hundreds of
            thousands of English men, women and children.</p>
        <p>WHAT is clearly discernible on a large scale for nations and industries is also equally
            true for families. <person reg="Sauer, Carl O.">Dr. C. O. Sauer,</person> head of the
            Geography Department of the <org>University of California,</org> recently declared that
            a lower standard of living would help to solve the problem of finding food and shelter
            for the ever growing population of the world. It does not take a university professor to
            find out that too many children in the family of a working man means a lowering of
            standards for the whole family. The mother soon finds that it is impossible to give the
            large family as good food as she could easily supply to a smaller number. The house
            becomes congested. We read of "two rooms for a family of six," "man and wife and five
            children crowded into three rooms," and even of worse housing conditions-conditions
            which would not be tolerated in a public institution for our dependent poor. Educational
            standards have to be lowered. The children must leave school just as soon as they can
            get their working papers and the dream of a high school course fades away. Books,
            lectures, music, cultural possibilities become an almost absurd impossibility for the
            over-burdened mother and the hard-driven father of too large a family, while any
            continued sickness-so probably a contingency when people are underfed-breaks down their
            independence and lays a burden on the whole community. Does unrestrained reproduction
            destroy civilization? Ask mother, she knows!</p>

    </docBody>
</doc>
