<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/07/16 AS encoded</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-08-15 CH proof and enter</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1918/04/--">Apr. 1918</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Editorial Comment</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp422026</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Editorial Comment</title>, <title type="journal">Birth
                    Control Review</title>, April 1918, p. 16.</bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="STEJO">Stelk, John</name>
            <name id="MAFLO">Maffert, Louis</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>This unsigned editorial may have been written by Margaret Sanger.</p>
        <index level1="New York Women's Publishing Co."/>
        <index level1="Birth Control Review, The"/>
        <index level1="France" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"
            level3="negative consequences of"/>
        <index level1="infanticide"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>EDITORIAL COMMENT</head>
        <p><person reg="Stelk, John">JUDGE JOHN STELK,</person> of the <org
                reg="Chicago Court of Domestic Relations">Court of Domestic Relations,</org>
            <place reg="Chicago, IL">Chicago,</place> has issued a report of his work in which he
            proves himself to be a genuine humanitarian and an exceptionally enlightened jurist. He
            advocates birth control, handles without gloves the war baby problem and scores the
            hypocrisy and ienfficiency of organized charity. The poor, overburdened mother has the
            right, he affirms, to "<q who="STEJO">guard against another mouth to feed</q>." The same
            knowledge that is "<q who="STEJO">given out every day to her sisters in the higher walks
                of life</q>" should be extended to her. "<q who="STEJO">I don't hesitate to
            say,</q>" he declares, "<q who="STEJO">that it is a thing of sheer brutality to compel a
                physically debilitated wife to further burden herself and society with defective
                offspring, aside from the almost criminal shortcomings, with attendant misery,
                visited upon the latter. I am of the opinion that some day the entire question will
                be considered by the <org>Federal Government.</org></q>" So far as we know, he drew
            his conclusions directly from the problems he was called upon to solve in the Court of
            Domest Relations. We regard it as only a matter of time before all thinking persons with
            the interests of society at heart will hold similar views. But it is gratifying to find
            a judge in the vanguard of progress, usually men of his calling are among the last to
            fall in line. We shall have more to say about Mr. Stelk, of Chicago, in a subsequent
            issue.</p>
        <p>WORD HAS COME that Dr. <person reg="Reitman, Ben">Ben Reitman</person> has lost his
            appeal in the higher courts of <place>Ohio</place>. He was first tried about a year ago
            and convicted of giving out birth control leaflets. His sentence, now affirmed, was six
            months in the workhouse and a fine of $1,000. <place reg="Cleveland, OH"
                >Cleveland</place> newspapers state that he began to serve this outrageous jail term
            on March 18. It is to be regretted that no mention was made of his case in the report of
            the <org reg="Ohio Birth Control League">Cleveland league</org> printed elsewhere in
            this issue. Dr. Reitman does not appear to have received the full local support to which
            any idealist battling in this cause was surely entitled.</p>
        <p>OFFICIAL <place>FRANCE</place> is crying for more children to fill the places of those
            who have been slain. But the people, militarized and stricken economically, are unable
            properly to care for all those who come into the world as it is. Let two incidents
            recorded in recent <place reg="Paris, France">Paris</place> newspapers demonstrate the
            point. <person reg="Maffert, Louis">Louis Maffert,</person> one of the editors of the
            patriotic <title type="journal">La Victoire,</title> writes as follows. "<q who="MAFLO"
                >We are certainly too fond of formulas. When we discover a phrase which is
                applicable to a problem, we repeat it with unwearied zeal. We say sanctiomoniously
                to every woman 'Have children!' and the day before yesterday two poor girl-mothers
                arrived at my office, at nine o'clock in the evening, with two new-born infants.
                They were without food, without money, without shoes and without lodging. The hotels
                never seem to have rooms for unfortunates of their kind. We did our best for them
                and finally turned them over to the <org>Saint Sulpice home</org>. But, all the
                same, such things ought not to happen.</q>" Again, the Socialist newspaper, <title
                type="journal">l'Humanite,</title> tells how a father, mother and four young
            children, unable to meet their obligations, were dispossessed in mid-winter not by a
            flinty-hearted bourgeois landlord, but by a munitions concern controlled by the <org
                reg="France Ministry of War">Ministry of War</org>, on whose property their poor
            lodging was located. Had the parents practised birth control, the repopulation of France
            would have suffered, but they probably would have been financially able to cope with
            their ironical tragedy.</p>
        <p>WE WISH THAT WE had available space in this magazine to record every case of wife murder
            and infanticide occurring as a result of unrestricted childbearing. Every month sees
            scores of such tragedies in the <place>United States</place>, only a small proportion of
            which are considered sufficiently sensational to be played up in the newspapers. Of the
            thousands that take place in other countries we, of course, hear nothing. We have before
            us accounts of two incidents which illustrate the extremes of the problem. The birth of
            a seventh child ina poverty-stricken Italian home in <place reg="New York, NY">New York
                City</place> rendered the <person reg="Unidentified">father</person> temporarily
            insane. He stamped up and down the room where his wife was lying in bed, muttering in
            his desapir, then drew a knife and stabbed the baby. The mother threw herself across the
            little body and received a mortal wound. Horrified the man fled. In a <place>New
                Jersey</place> suburb of Greater New York, a <person reg="Unidenitifed">middle-aged
                mother</person> with a boy of sixteen and a girl of eleven gave birth to a third
            girl. This was an eventuality which she had plainly not figured upon. She brooded until
            her mind was affected. With a small quantity of chloroform bought at the drug store, she
            ended her baby's life. When placed under arrest, she stated that she had felt herself
                "<q who="UNK">unable to raise the child properly</q>," that her everyday domestic
            work had become too formidable for her to cope with. Can any one doubt that this was a
            case of unwanted pregnancy? By every dictate of reason, knowledge of how to prevent
            conception should have been available for her, no less than for the murdered Italian
            mother with her seven babies produced in blindness and ignorance and probably in all too
            rapid succession to each other.</p>
        <p>WE CALL ATTENTION to the prospects on another page of <org>The New York Woman's
                Publishing Company, Inc.</org> This new organization is composed of fifteen women,
            who propose to leave no stone unturned to put <title type="journal">The Birth Control
                Review</title> on a financial basis. Application for papers of incorporation has
            been made, and $10,000 worth of stock will be offered to the public at $10 a share.</p>
        <p>When this magazine resumed publication last December, we printed an appeal for help and
            told our subscribers that the continued existence of the only organ of the birth control
            movement in America depended upon their co-operation. The response was almost nil, but
            we have struggled along through the winter at a financial loss. The little group that
            has borne the burden cannot do so indefinitely. If YOU want your magazine to live, buy
            at least one share and urge your friends to do likewise. It is a case of now or
            never.</p>

    </docBody>
</doc>
