<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="(Published Statement)">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/07/01 CH proof tags</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="(1917-01-27)"><supplied resp="MSPP">27 Jan. 1917</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Statement on Ethel Byrne's Hunger Strike</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp422003</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Birth Control Women Launch Drive for
                    Law</title>, <title type="journal">Chicago Daily Tribune</title>, Jan. 27, 1917</bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="CDT">Chicago Daily Tribune</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><index level1="jails and imprisonment" level2="Blackwell's Island Workhouse (New York)"/>
        <index level1="National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control"/>
        <index level1="National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control" level2="birth control bills"/>
        <index level1="birth control movement" level2="goals and strategies"/>
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Federal"/>
        <index level1="New York" level2="birth control laws and legislation"/>     
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>BIRTH CONTROL WOMEN LAUNCH DRIVE FOR LAW</head>

        <dateline><date value="Jan. 27"/>
            <place reg="New York, NY">New York</place></dateline>
        <q who="CDT"><p>The first result of the hunger strike and forcible feeding of <person reg="Byrne, Ethel">Mrs. Ethel
                Byrne</person> at <org reg="Blackwell's Island Penitentiary">Blackwell's Island</org> came tonight.</p>
            <p>A drive on <org reg="United States Congress">congress</org> Tuesday by <person reg="Fassett, Lillian Griffs">Mrs. Lillian Fassett</person> and others to get national
                legislation favoring birth control is being organized.</p>
            <p>Meanwhile Mrs. Byrne, hunger striking in protest against her conviction and
                imprisonment for disseminating birth control information, gave up her battle.</p>
            <p>It was not until Mrs. Byrne, having gone 108 hours without food or water, collapsed
                that <person reg="Lewis, Burdett G.">Commissioner Lewis</person> established a precedent in American prison annals by
                ordering her forcibly fed.</p>
            <p>Later the prisoner apparently abandoned all resistance and allowed attendants to feed
                her. She said she would not feed herself but would not object to being fed.</p>
            <p>Visitors, including Mrs. Sanger, were denied permission to visit the prisoner.</p></div>
            <p><div type="section">
                    <head type="sub">Calls Sister Critically Ill.</head>
                </div></p></q>
        <p>"My sister," said <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Mrs. Margaret Sanger,</person> leader of the birth control movement, "is in very
            critical condition since she was rolled in a blanket and milk, eggs and a stimulant
            forced into her stomach through a rubber tube.</p>
        <p>"As for helping my sister, we are balked at every turn. The women of the <org reg="Committee of 100">committee of one
            hundred,</org> Mrs. Fassett, <person reg="Finch, Mrs. Amos">Mrs. Amos Finch</person> and others have therefore concentrated on getting
            favorable action by congress.</p>
        <p>"A canvas of congressmen will be made by Mrs. Fassett and the others and one of our
            friends chosen to introduce the proposed law.</p>
        <p>"The bill has not been completely drafted, but it will seek the nullification of the
            federal statute against the dissemination of birth control information and the
            establishment of the righ to tell poor women who need it, all about it."</p></div>
        <p><div type="section">
                    <head type="sub">Explains "Hunger Strike."</head>
                
            <p><q who="CDT">Mrs. Sanger explained today that her sister is hunger striking "against the action of
                the course in refusing her the right to test the constitutionality of the <place reg="New York, NY">New York</place>
                anti-birth control law."</p>
            <p>Describing it as</q> "the most outrageous piece of legislation on the statute books,"
                Mrs. Sanger declared that it keeps poor working people in ignorance, while those
                with money and intelligence can get the forbidden information and use it.</p>
        <p>"Birth control is a new movement in this country," she said, "and misunderstood. Its only
            object is to prevent the birth of more children than the parents can give good health,
            good minds, and a good chance to win the battle of life. It is not opposed to the birth
            rate, as such."</p></div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
