<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Editorial">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/07/15 AS encoded</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-08-15 CH correct and edit</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1918/09/00">Sept. 1918</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Editorial Comment</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp422029</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title>, Sept. 1918, p.9.</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="BCR">Birth Control Review</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><index level1="poverty"/>
        <index level1="Birth Control Review, The"/>
        <index level1="children" level2="rights of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="opposition to"/>
        <index level1="Birth Control Review, The" level2="suppression of"/>
        <index level1="mentally disabled and diseased" level2="birth control and"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>EDITORIAL COMMENT</head>
        <p>IF ANY SUBSCRIBERS to <title type="journal">THE BIRTH CONTROL REVIEW</title> failed to
            receive the August number of the magazine, we wish them to know that it was because that
            issue was ordered barred from the mails by the authorities in <place
                reg="Washington, DC">Washington.</place> The reason given was, that we had printed a
            review and an advertisement of an important book which had been enthusiastically
            received in the <place reg="Great Britain">British Empire,</place> but which was
            declared to be unmailable here. Our readers know that we have been exceedingly careful
            to keep within the letter and the spirit of postal regulations. We did not propose to
            give reactionary minds in officialdom an opportunity to interfere with the work for
            woman's freedom to which this publication is devoted. At last, however, a cause has been
            found. Our answer to this attack, as to all others, is to be propaganda of the most
            effective kind. It will be the only answer intelligible to the type of official who is
            seeking to hamper the birth control movement. In the future, as in the past, we shall
            not intentionally violate postal regulations. But, by means of a bigger, broader, still
            more fearless magazine, we shall combat the spirit which led to the assault upon us. To
            that end we have asked our subscribers to co-operate with us in trebling the REVIEW's
            circulation. We intend to deal telling blows at the dark superstitions which perpetuate
            in <place reg="United States">America</place> the lust of witch burning. Those who read
            the leading article in the suppressed number know what difficulties have been overcome
            in bringing out the first twelve issues of <title type="journal">THE BIRTH CONTROL
                REVIEW</title>. Said difficulties did not deter those who have made the publication
            a power for free womanhood. The barring of an edition from the mails, far from
            discouraging us, has moved us to new efforts. But it is possible that this first
            interference with the <title type="journal">REVIEW</title> may have more significance
            than now appears to be the case. The powers of reaction have recently taken away many of
            the reforms that American women have won in fifty years of toil, hardship and sacrifice.
            Yesterday, the Federal child labor legislation, such as it was, went to the scrap heap.
            Tomorrow, the attack may be wider in its scope. As for the advocates of birth control,
            they intend to battle in the first ditch, not the last one. With all that we have of
            inspiration, courage and resource, we shall hold fast to what we have gained. We shall
            not let up in our fight on the medieval in tolerance, which makes it possible to deny
            the mails of this country to a message of woman's freedom.</p>
        <p>THE <person reg="Hylan, John Francis">MAYOR</person> of <org
                reg="New York Committee on Women on National Defense"><place reg="New York, NY">New
                    York's</place> Committee of Women on National Defense,</org> the <org
                reg="New York City Department of Health, Division of Child Hygiene">Division of
                Child Hygiene</org> of the same city's <org reg="New York City Department of Health"
                >Department of Health,</org> the <org>New York Milk Committee</org> and similar
            agencies have united in a "save 100,000 babies" campaign. One child in every seven born
            in the United States dies from malnutrition or from some disease directly traceable to
            poverty. So the "save 100,000 babies" movement has for its slogan "<q who="UNK">Save
                that seventh child!</q>" We confess to finding this a ghastly mockery and an
            intolerable piece of irony. The agencies quoted appeal to the mothers to do the saving,
            but why more mothers do not save their babies is indicated pretty clearly by a circular
            sent out by a <org reg="Unidentified organization">charitable association</org>, which
            says "<q who="UNK">Tired and despairing mothers with the telling mark of day in and
                day-out grind on their features, midnight retiring and five o'clock rising-keeping
                the tattered ends of the housework together, struggling with the everyday problems
                of sickness, poverty and widowhood-three thousand seven hundred such mothers and
                children are waiting an invitation to <org reg="Sea Breeze Amusement Park">Sea
                    Breeze</org>, but we must have help if we are to continue these outings</q>."
            The best that Society offers the child today is occasional charity to keep it alive, the
            only help that has thus far been suggested for the mother is two weeks of fresh air a
            year, plus a few weeks of prenatal care. But what is the matter with making birth
            control information free and open to all, so that seventh children shall not be born in
            an age when food, shelter, clothing and wholesome air are at a premium? The earlier
            offspring might then have a chance to grow up in decency and the mother to preserve her
            health. If the philanthropic reformers have not thought of that solution of the problem,
            we call it to their attention.</p>
        <p>THE CARE of the insane cost the <org reg="New York State">State of New York</org>
            $8,320,000 last year. The total economic loss on the insane for the year is officially
            estimated at more than $35,000,000. The institutions for the insane in <place>New
                York</place> are overcrowded to the extent of nearly 6,000 persons. There are
            already 37,069 persons in public institutions for the mentally defective and it is to be
            presumed that if these hospitals were not now overcrowded there would be some thousands
            more. And the number of insane and feeble-minded is increasing. And it is still a crime
            to impart to the mothers of such the information concerning birth control, which would
            save the state $35,000,000 a year and the relatives of the unfortunates inestimable
            trouble and sorrow. The facts and figures given are those of the recent annual report of
            the <org reg="New York State Hospital Commission">State Hospital Commission.</org> The
            commissioner recommended five means of preventing the increase of the number of the
            insane.</p>
        <list>
            <item>Checking the excessive use of alcohol.</item>
            <item>Checking the ravages of syphilis.</item>
            <item>Informing the public more fully concerning mental diseases and teaching mental
                hygiene.</item>
            <item>Steps to eliminate extreme poverty.</item>
            <item>Extension of out patient departments of state hospitals, etc.</item>
        </list>
        <p>It did not recommend the repeal of those survivals of witch burning days, the anti-birth
            control statutes. So far as the committee is concerned, this direct, simple and
            effective means of saving this huge cost of money and human agony is still criminal. And
            so far as the committee is concerned, it prefers $35,000,000 worth of criminal prejudice
            upon the part of officials and lawmakers, to birth control.</p>

    </docBody>
</doc>
