<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published testimony">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014-06-26 MM </prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-15 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1923-02-13">13 Feb 1923</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Address Before the Connecticut State Assembly Judiciary
					Committee</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422015</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Margaret Sanger Pleads for Bill Before Committee</title>,
					<title>Bridgeport Telegram</title>, Feb. 14, 1923, p. 1.</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="BT">Bridgeport Telegram</name>
			<name id="BELJ">Bell, J. Mortimer</name>
			<name id="DAREL">Darbie, Elbert L.</name>
			<name id="MURJO">Murray, John G. (Bishop)</name>
			<name id="ELLAR">Ells, Arthur</name>
			<name id="BUTEL">Butler, Ellen A.</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<index level1="Connecticut" level2="birth control in"/>
		<index level1="Connecticut" level2="birth control"
			level3="birth control laws and legislation"/>
		<index level1="race suicide"/>
		<index level1="reproductive responsibility"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>MARGARET SANGER PLEADS FOR BILL BEFORE COMMITTEE</head>
		<head type="sub">Crowd of 300 Attend Hearing on Proposed Legalizing of Birth Control in
			Connecticut</head>
		<div type="section">
			<dateline><place reg="Hartford, CT">Hartford</place>,<date value="1923-02-13"/>Feb.
				13.</dateline>
			<q who="BT">
				<p>The question as to whether or not <place>Connecticut</place> shall legalize the
					practice of birth control provoked, at a hearing before the <org
						reg="Connecicut State Assembly, Judiciary Committee">Judiciary committee of
						the general assembly</org> this afternoon, the keenest and most absorbing
					debate and rough and tumble controversy that the present session has seen in
					connection with any matter. The hearing on the proposed birth control bill
					brought to the old <org reg="Connecticut State Senate">Senate</org> chamber,
					where the Judiciary committee holds its sessions, a crowd estimated at 300
					persons, which packed the seats on the floors, the galleries, and the interior
					window spaces. Most of those present were women.</p>
			</q>
			<p>
				<q who="BT">A discussion by Mrs. Margaret Sanger, introduced as "the champion for
					birth control in the <place>United States</place>," on the one hand, and Bishop
						<person reg="Murray, John G. (Bishop)">John G. Murray</person>, chancellor
					of the <org reg="Catholic Diocese of Connecticut">Catholic diocese of
						Connecticut</org>, sometimes referred to among scholars as "the pride of
						<org reg="Universit&eacute; Catholique de Louvain">Louvian
					University</org>," on the opposition, developed substantial arguments, which
					were applauded at intervals by the entire assemblage. </q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="BT">The proposed birth control bill, introduced by Representative <person
						reg="Sisiky, Samuel">Samuel Sisiky</person>, of <place reg="Enfield, CT"
						>Enfield</place>, at the request of <person reg="Fletcher, Henry F."
						>Attorney Henry F. Fletcher</person> of Enfield, who was the first speaker
					in behalf of the bill, repeals sections of the general statutes, which prohibits
					the use of drugs instruments or articles intended to prevent conception, and the
					dissemination of literature intended to prevent conception.</q>
			</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="subhead">Considered too Drastic.</head>
			<p>
				<q who="BT">An informal pool of the Judiciary committee at the clsoe of the hearing
					indicated it was learned by the <org reg="Bridgeport Telegram">Telegram</org>
					correspondent a probable majority of the committee in favor of some revision of
					the existing statutes, by which birth control information is forbidden, although
					the bill sponsored by the <org>American Birth Control League</org> is likely to
					be unfavorably reported on the ground that some of its provisions are too
					drastic.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="BT">Mrs. Sanger was introduced as the principal speaker in support of this
					bill, after Mrs. <person reg="Porritt, Annie Goodrich">Annie G. Porritt</person>
					of <place reg="Hartford, CT">Hartford</place>, <person reg="Butler, Robert P."
						>Robert P. Butler</person>, corporation counsel of Hartford, and Attorney
					Henry F. Fletcher of Enfield, had spoken briefly in favor of the bill. Mrs.
					Porritt also said she was authorized to introduce the names of Dr. <person
						reg="Swett, Paul P.">Paul P. Swett</person>, Dr. <person
						reg="Stoll, Henry F.">Henry F. Stoll</person>, and Dr. <person
						reg="Chester, T. Weston">T. Weston Chester</person>, noted obstetricians of
					Hartford, in favor of the measure. Dr. Stoll appeared later personally to
					express his approval of modification of the statutes which would permit the
					imparting of birth control information, but not to the point of legalizing
					abortions.</q>
			</p>
		</div>

		<div type="section">
			<head type="subhead">Mrs. Sanger Applauded.</head>
			<p><q who="BT">When Mrs. Sanger was introduced, the chamber resounded with applause. She
					said the question to be settled</q> "is not, shall the use of birth control be
				permitted, but what kind of birth control shall we use." <q who="BT">The idea of
					birth control has been used all through the history of mankind, she said.
				</q>"Nature uses the cruelest method of birth control, with pestilence, famine and
				war, but we don't believe in those methods, nor in infanticide or the abandonment of
				children. It is a disgrace to our civilization that we permit the enormous waste of
				women's lives. What we want to do is to bring the subject out of the gutter, where
				we have put it, to raise it to the plane of science."</p>
			<p><q who="BT">Mrs. Sanger called attention to the numerous bills which had been heard
					by the committee that afternoon, relating to the State's burden of child
					welfare, and maintaining or protecting children</q> "who ought never to have
				been born." <q who="BT">When we go on doing this, and do not correct the condition
					that produces it,</q> "we are like the ostrich burying its head in the sand. We
				don't look the facts in the face," <q who="BT">Mrs. Sanger said.</q></p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="subhead">Conscious Responsibility. </head>
			<p>"We are trying to build up the conscious responsibility of parenthood," <q who="BT"
					>she said,</q> "to make people of whatever station in life, realize that it is
				the greatest, the most sacred responsibility. When the parents are diseased or the
				children are likely to be diseased, or mentally deficient, or the parents cannot
				provide a living and an education, and the decencies of life, we ought to take care
				of the problem at the start, and not just shiftlessly have large families, and then
				have the burden of support fall on the state."</p>
			<p><q who="BT"><person reg="Bell, J. Mortimer">Representative Bell</person>, of <place
						reg="Salisbury, CT">Salisbury</place>, a member of the Judiciary committee,
					questioned Mrs. Sanger, saying "</q><q who="BELJ">This particular bill permits
					the giving by any physician or registered nurse to any person applying to him or
					her, of information to prevent conception. Do you favor giving this information
					to woman, whether she be married or unmarried?</q>"</p>
			<p>"No one has ever asked except the married woman,"<q who="BT"> Mrs. Sanger
					replied.</q> "We ought to be able to leave it to the discretion of the
				physicians or nurses. If they can't use good judgment, they ought not to be allowed
				to have their licenses. We are trying to help the married woman, the married
				mother."</p>
			<p><q who="BT"><person reg="Darbie, Elbert L.">Representative Darbie</person> asked</q>
				"Do you think the feeble-minded person would be likely to inquire for this
				information?" "Yes," <q who="BT">Mrs. Sanger answered,</q> "we know of many cases of
				women who come to us and say there is something wrong with them, or something wrong
				with their husband, and they do not want a child if it is going to have 'something
				wrong.'"</p>
			<p>"<q who="ELLAR">What progress has this legislation made in other states, and what has
					been the trend of the movement?</q>" <q who="BT">Senate Chairman <person
						reg="Ells, Arthur">Arthur Ells</person> asked.</q> "The movement is very
				young," <q who="BT">Mrs. Sanger replied.</q> "We are trying to get the repeal of
				statutes in <place>New York</place> and <place>Pennsylvania</place>, and we are
				concentrating our efforts on these three states. <place>Ohio</place> has no law
				prohibiting the information, and some effective work is being done in that
				state."</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="subhead">Women Favor it</head>
			<p><q who="BT">A poll of those attending the hearing who were in favor of the bill was
					asked by the committee, and about 40 persons, all women, raised their
				hands.</q></p>
			<p><q who="BT">Bishop Murray, opposing the bill, said </q>"<q who="MURJO">We would have
					to convert the whole state of <place> Connecticut</place> into an enormous
					insane asylum if there are to be found people in the state who are foolish
					enought to make use of this legislation if it is made into law.</q>"</p>
			<p>"<q who="MURJO">The inference is made,</q>" <q who="BT">Bishop Murray said,</q> "<q
					who="MURJO">that poverty tends to cause conditions which are unfavorable to the
					race. The whole theory is fallacious. A law of nature governs the whole matter
					of the birth state. Attempting to interfere has meant race suicide, wherever it
					has been tried, and it would mean race suicide here.</q></p>
			<p>"<q who="MURJO">The statute now existing, preventing the use of any drug, article or
					instrument, and preventing the spread of any 'information intending to prevent
					conception,' was adopted by this state in 1821, and was the result of the wisdom
					and experience of those who established this state," the bishop said. "To do
					otherwise is to prevert a <name type="deity">God</name>-given function. This
					bill which these people now propose is contrary to the recognition of natural
					laws which have been on the statute books for over 100 years, and recognition of
					the laws has made this commonwealth, in my judgement, the most ideal in the
					United States.</q>"</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="subhead">"Atheistic."</head>
			<p>"<q who="MURJO">This movement is essentially atheistic,</q>"<q who="BT"> Bishop
					Murray remarked making his concluding points. <person reg="Smith, William J."
						>Representative Smith</person>, of <place reg="Avon, CT">Avon</place>,
						<person reg="Jones, Francis E.">Francis E. Jones</person>, president-elect
					of the <org>Connecticut Council of Catholic Men</org>, <person
						reg="Wilson, Mrs. David">Mrs. David Wilson</person>, wife of the <person
						reg="Wilson, David">Hartford postmaster</person>, <person
						reg="Butler, Ellen A.">Mrs. Otis Butler</person>, who described herself
					as</q> "<q who="BUTEL">one of eight children and mtoher of five</q>,"<q who="BT">
					<person reg="Curry, Mary M.">Mary M. Curry</person>, of Hartford, and the Rev.
						<person reg="Ekins, G. Herbert (Rev.)">G. Herbert Ekins</person>, who
					occupies a seat at the reporters' table in the House, spoke in oppositon to the
					bill.</q>
			</p>
			<p><q who="BT">Mrs. Sanger challenged Bishop Murray's statement concerning the violating
					of natural laws in practicing birth control. </q>"Is there not anything today
				which is not a violation of natural laws?" <q who="BT">she asked. </q>"There are men
				in this room, and the gentlement is one of them, who are clean-shaven. That is
				against a law of nature. We are wearing clothes. We are walking upright instead of
				on all fours. We are benefiting by medicine and surgery. All those are violations of
				natural laws. It's absurd, sayign that this would be contrary to nature. It's the
				control of nature that we want to accomplish." </p>
			<p><q who="BT">At the close of her remarks, Mrs. Sanger said she was one of eleven
					children and the mother of three, and had been a trained nurse, practicing in
						<place reg="New York, NY">New York city</place> for fourteen years. She said
					she spoke in the interest of thousands who were inarticulate, but who earnestly
					besought the right that the bill proposes to give.</q></p>
		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
