<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/07/08 AS encoded</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-08-15 CH proof and edit</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1928/02/00"> Feb. 1928</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Editorial</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp422025</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title>, Feb. 1928, pp. 37-38</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
            <name id="NCPM">United Kingdom National Council of Public Morals</name>
            <name id="AES">American Eugenics Society</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>This unsigned editor may have been written by Margaret Sanger.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="eugenic justifications"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="medical community and"/>
        <index level1="food supply"/>
        <index level1="heredity" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="eugenics"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>EDITORIAL</head>
        <p>NEWSPAPERS and periodicals have been full of reviews of the various happenings of 1927.
            But no review of the past year is completel which does not take note of the tremendous
            growth of the movement towards Birth Control. After a long struggle, at the beginning of
            which the advocates of Birth Control were voices crying in the wilderness and finding
            few to listen, Birth Control seems now to be taking the place in the minds of men to
            which its importance entitles it. Gradually the idea began to penetrate and Birth
            Control found supporters among scientists and thinkers. The new aspect of the movement
            is that writers on social questions questions now do not seem to think it necessary to
            argue the question. They simply take Birth Control for granted, as part of the basis on
            which any better social structure must be built. Such is the attitude of <person
                reg="Smith, Thomas Vernor">Thomas Vernor Smith,</person> in <title type="book">"The
                Democratic Way of Life"</title> and of <person reg="Huntington, Ellsworth"
                >Huntington</person> and <person reg="Whitney, Leon Fradley">Whitney</person> in
                <title type="book">"The Builders of America."</title>
            <person reg="Ross, Edward Alsworth">Professor E. A. Ross</person> makes a more definite
            appeal for Birth Control in <title type="book">"Standing Room Only",</title> but one
            could cite book after book, among those recently published, where Birth Control is
            accepted as essential, rather than advocated as a reform. Many magazines and periodicals
            have opened their pages to articles and letters giving the pros and cons on Birth
            Control or announcing it as the subject of an Open Forum. Among the events of 1927 also
            must be recorded the great English debate held by the <org reg="Cambridge Union Society"
                >Cambridge Union</org> when Birth Control, after a magnificent forensic display, was
            approved by a vote of 512 to 315.</p>
        <p>MORE significant than lay opinion, is it that in 1927 there was a distinct awakening in
            the medical profession to the importance of Birth Control. The profession is being urged
            by some of the more far-sighted of its own members to "<q who="UNK">stop driving the
                subject of Birth Control to propaganda organizations, and try ourselves to regulate
                control of conception,"</q> an admonition which was lacking until the propaganda
            organizations had beaten a path along which the medical profession could advance with
            ease and comfort. The way of the doctor was made easier in 1927 by the Report made by
            the <org reg="United Kingdom National Council of Public Morals">Special Committee to the
                National Council of Public Morals,</org> which was published in <place
                reg="London, England">London</place> in November. This Committee recorded its
            opinion that <q who="NCPM">"no impediment should be placed in the way of married couples
                who desired information as to contraceptives, when this was needed for medicals
                reasons, or because of excessive child-bearing poverty."</q> It also recommended the
            giving of such information by medical practitioners and at hospitals. The time seems to
            be speedily coming when the medical profession, forgetting its long reluctance, will
            unhesitatingly claim contraception as a ncessary part of medical practice. They will not
            be allowed the whole field without protests from the Economists, who were out in favor
            of Birth Control while the doctors, in general, were still hesitant. It is worth noting
            in this review of progress in 1927 that Birth Control and its Relation to the Food
            Supply was one of the questions suggested for those who wished to compete for the
            Thousand Dollar Economic prize, offered for the 24th time, through the generosity of
                <org reg="Hart Schaffner &amp; Marx">Hart Schaffner and Marx</org> of <place
                reg="Chicago, IL">Chicago,</place> and supervised by the Committee of which <person
                reg="Laughlin, James Lawrence">J. Lawrence Laughlin</person> of the <org>University
                of Chicago</org> is chairman.</p>
        <p>THE recent <org reg="National Conference on Race Betterment, 3rd">Race Betterment
                Conference,</org> held at <place reg="Battle Creek, MI">Battle Creek,
                Michigan,</place> January 2-6, is an example of the universal acceptance of Birth
            Control. We have no story of the Conference to publish in the <title type="journal"
                >BIRTH CONTROL REVIEW</title> this month. The reason is that, from the official
            program, Birth Control--the cornerstone of the arch of race betterment--was omitted. But
            we have the evidence of <person reg="Knopf, S. Adolphus">Dr. S. Adolphus Knopf,</person>
            who was refused the privilege of speaking on this subject but requested to speak there
            on tuberculosis, that Birth Control was present unofficially throughout the sessions. A
            good three-quarters of the speakers, he states, made it part of their program. And what
            brought it home to those at the conference who may not have given it much thought before
            was the statistics, graphically exhibited by electric time signals, of the <org
                reg="American Eugenics Society">American Eugenics society.</org> We have given these
            before in the <title type="journal">BIRTH CONTROL REVIEW</title>, but they should be
            learned by heart.<q who="AES">"Every second,"</q> said the lights, "<q who="AES">crime
                costs America $100,000, every 15 seconds $100,000 go for the care of persons with
                bad heredity, such as insane, feeble-minded, and other defectives. Every 16 seconds
                a person is born in the <place>United States,</place> every 7 1/2 minutes a
                high-grade person is born in the United States who will have ability to do creative
                work and be fit for leadership. About 4 percent of all American citizens come within
                this class. Every 48 seconds a person is born who will never grow up mentally beyond
                the age of a normal 8 year old child, every 50 seconds a person is committed to jail
                in the United States. Very few normal persons go to jail."</q>There is no true
            Eugenics-no practical Race Betterment-that does not have Birth Control as its base.</p>
        <p>THE price society pays for crime in money is only part of what it pays. The whole price,
            the perverted curiosity and perverted sympathy a shocking crime may arouse, is a far
            heavier one. The melodrama of the <person reg="Snyder, Ruth">Snyder</person> case has
            come to an end, but its effects are not over. Personalities like Ruth Snyder and <person
                reg="Gray, Judd">Judd Gray</person> are the true unfit, their influence is even more
            fateful than their crime and the evidence they furnish of the morbid instincts to which
            the crowd responds calls for eugenic action. So far is the newspaper reading public
            debased that it went to Ruth Snyder for an opinion on Birth Control. Just after her
            conviction the papers published an attack by her in which she said that a houseful of
            children would have saved her from sin. The bankruptcy of the opposition is shown by the
            character of this witness they bring forward. The Snyder case is a most convincing
            argument for Birth Control. Ruth Snyder should never have had any children. The child
            Mrs. Snyder left behind is far the most pitiable figure in the drama, but we can at
            least be thankful that she had only one. For children are forced not only to bear the
            stigma before the world but the inner stigmata of a bad inheritance.</p>
        <p>Not the smallest evidence of the need for Birth Control eugenics is the evidence this
            case presents that even the decent instincts of the public are crookedly applied. It is
            inexcusable crimes such as this which stimulate opposition to capital punishment. This
            is unjust, for as long as a campaign against capital punishment is associated with such
            cases, decent and thoughtful people will be antagonized. When Birth Control has cut down
            the huge proportions of the problem of unfitness, when humanity, furnished with a normal
            inheritance and a normal and ample environment itself grows normal, capital punishment
            will, with very little agitation, become an institution of the dark past.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
