<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/07/15 AS encoded</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-08-15 CH proof and edit</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1925/01/00">Jan. 1925</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Editorial</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp422031</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Editorial</title>, <title type="journal">The Birth Control
                    Review</title>, Jan. 1925, pp. 3-4.</bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="BCR">Birth Control Review</name>
            <name id="DAW">Dawson, Bertrand (Lord)</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><index level1="England" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="National Birth Control League"/>
        <index level1="conferences" level2="International Conference on Planned Parenthood"
            level3="1958 (6th)"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="in marriages"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="as a term"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="religion and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="opposition to"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>EDITORIAL</head>
        <p><person reg="Dawson, Bertrand (Lord)">LORD DAWSON of Penn,</person> physician to the
                <person reg="George VII (England)">King of <place>England</place>,</person> has with
            incisive courage again come forward as one of the most authoritative champions of Birth
            Control. In his recent evidence given before the national <org
                reg="British National Birth-rate Commission">Birth Rate Commission</org> set up by
            the <org reg="British National Council of Public Morals">English National Council of
                Public Morals,</org> Lord Dawson roundly denounced the current hypocrisy of the
            churches and made a strong plea for sex love as essential to a happy normal life. Sex
            love, asserted Lord Dawson of Penn, is and should be the physical expression of a
            lasting affection, cementing the unity in marriage of spirit, mind and body."<q
                who="DAW">The right view is that sex love has, apart from parenthood, a purpose of
                its own. It is something to prize and cherish for its own sake. It is an essential
                part of health and happiness in marriage.</q></p>
        <p><q who="DAW">Without the physical desire and its periodic satisfaction for its own sake,
                the union is a poor spiritless thing, feebly cemented-without glow or fire. Sexual
                union under proper conditions makes for health. When love has come and men and women
                are united in marriage, sexual intercourse is right and desirable, provided both
                parties are fit.</q>" There is nothing shocking in these simple truths so
            courageously stated. But there is something supremely fine and noble in a man who dares
            to state such simple wholesome truths in an unfaltering voice to his nation and to the
            world, as Lord Dawson has so courageously done.</p>
        <p>FURTHERMORE, Lord Dawson has the insight to recognize that there can be no substantial
            happiness in marriage without the recognition and acceptance of the ethics of Birth
            Control. By Birth Control he means what we all mean that the conception of children
            should be a matter of choice, not chance. The regulation of childbirths is being brought
            about, in the opinion of Lord Dawson, by these factors (1) increasing density of
            population, (2) increasing sense of the value of child-life and of the responsibility of
            parenthood, (3) the desire of parents to equip to the very best of their ability their
            children, both in body and mind, (4) the social and domestic difficulties in the homes
            of growing numbers, (5) the desire of increasing numbers of women for a larger share in
            the work and the interests of the world-a share they cannot take if enslaved to
            unceasing and involuntary maternity. Church authorities, continued the physician to the
            king, have evaded the real problem. They have counseled restraint and abstinence. At
            times they apologize for sex-love, at times they seem to ignore this dominating force.
                "<q who="DAW">That is the moving force</q>," to quote further from Lord Dawson's
                evidence-"<q who="DAW">and man glorifies in its possession. Why not take account of
                it? Why not give it its place? Why apologize for it? Mere statements that it is
                immoral, is contrary to the teachings of Christianity, or is condemned by the <title
                    type="book">Bible</title>, will only bring disrepute on those who make them and
                especially among the young, who matter most.</q>" Bravo! Lord Dawson of Penn! Our
            only regret is that there are no men in public life in <place reg="United States"
                >America</place> courageous enough to speak so openly on the legitimacy of sex love
            and its importance to the individual and the nation and the world at large.</p>
        <p>IT IS especially gratifying to the directors of the <org>American Birth Control
                League</org> that Lord Dawson's pronouncement is an agreement with our stated
            policies and program. This agreement with our principles is doubly satisfying not only
            because Lord Dawson of Penn is one of the most distinguished medical authorities of
                <place>Great Britain,</place> but his position as a legislator in the <org
                reg="United Kingdom House of Lords">House of Lords</org> gives emphasis and
            authority to his opinions. Discussion of the principles and the methods of Birth
            Control, he says, should be kept separate. The methods of Birth Control should be set
            forth by the scientists whom they properly concern. This position is that of the
            American Birth Control League and determines our program, both practical and
            legislative. We hold that laws should be revised to enable the physician to work in
            clinics. Lord Dawson, whose reported evidence before the English Birth Rate Commission
            shows every sign of deep and clear thinking upon Birth Control and all its allied
            problems, has arrived at the same conclusion. On the other hand, he realizes as we do
            that the great broad principles of the doctrine, which touch at every point the
            fundamental problems of humanity, must be openly and frankly and seriously
            discussed.</p>
        <p>PLANS for the <org reg="International Neo-Malthusian and Birth Control Conference, Sixth"
                >SIXTH INTERNATIONAL BIRTH CONTROL CONFERENCE</org> are under way. Supporters of
            Birth Control in many countries are expressing their desire to attend. But the poverty
            of <place>Europe</place>, which affects both individuals and organizations makes it very
            doubtful whether some of these delegates can get here unless the American Birth Control
            League can pay part of their expenses. The International should not be deprived of these
            men and women for money reasons. For our benefit and for theirs we must have them. But
            to have them we must have funds. OUR INTERNATIONAL CONFERENCE FUND must be sufficient to
            provide not only the general expenses of the Conference but to help bring foreign
            delegates over. We ask our readers to contribute to this fund and to urge their friends
            to contribute. A coupon for this purpose is to be found on the news section of the
                <title type="journal">REVIEW.</title></p>
        <p>WITH profound regret we announce the resignation of Mrs. <person reg="Porritt, Anne G.">
                Anne G. Porritt</person> as managing editor of <title type="journal">THE BIRTH
                CONTROL REVIEW</title>. For the past two years Mrs. Porritt has fulfilled this
            difficult post with untiring energy, devotion and keen intelligence. Under her editorial
            direction, THE REVIEW has assumed an added dignity. Especially from our English friends
            have we received much praise for the appearance and tone of the magazine under the
            editorial guidance of Mrs. Porritt. We take this opportunity of expressing our gratitude
            to Mrs. Porritt for her always conscientious and cheerful co-operation with the hope
            that her much-needed rest will restore her without delay to the best of health. We
            regret the loss of Mrs. Porritt as managing editor. Her successor is <person
                reg="Boyd, Mary Sumner">Mrs. Mary Sumner Boyd.</person></p>


    </docBody>
</doc>
