<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="(Published Statement)">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/07/01 CH proof tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-08-15 CH proof and enter</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docAuthor>Ligaya Fruto</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="(1955-09-22)"><supplied resp="MSPP">22 Sept 1955</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Interview at the Pacific Club</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp422007</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Planned Parenthood Held Answer to War Danger</title>, <title
                    type="journal">Honolulu Star-Bulletin</title>, Sept. 24, 1955</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="HSB">Honolulu Star-Bulletin</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><index level1="birth control" level2="and war"/>
        <index level1="conferences" level2="International Conference on Planned Parenthood"
            level3="1955 (5th)"/>
        <index level1="Italy" level2="overpopulation and"/>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="overpopulation and"/>
        <index level1="Catholic Church" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="birth control movement in"/>
        <index level1="midwives" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="birth control in"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Planned Parenthood Held Answer to War Danger</head>
        <byline>By <person reg="Fruto, Ligaya">LIGAYA FRUTO</person></byline>
        <q who="HSB"><p>Birth control is the answer to war, according to <person
                    reg="Sanger, Margaret">Mrs. Margaret Sanger,</person> the world's foremost
                exponent of <org reg="Planned Parenthood Federation of America">planned
                    parenthood.</org></p>
            <p>Mrs. Sanger was in <place reg="Honolulu, HI">Honolulu</place> Thursday on the <name
                    reg="S.S. President Cleveland" type="ship">President Cleveland.</name></p>
            <p>She is on her way to <place>Japan</place> for the <org
                    reg="International Conference on Planned Parenthood and Overpopulation, Fifth"
                    >Fifth International Conference on Planned Parenthood and
                Overpopulation.</org></p></q>
        <p>"We've seen the three countries which are overpopulated-<place>Italy,</place>
            <place>Germany,</place> and Japan," <q who="HSB">Mrs. Sanger said at an interview at the
                    <org>Pacific Club</org>, where a luncheon was given for her by the <org>Watumull
                    Foundation.</org></q></p>
        <p>"They had to branch out to other countries and finally move on to war.</p>
        <p>"With the terrible lesson of war fresh in their minds, the peoples of these countries are
            now looking for something like birth control so they will not be urged into another
            war."</p>
        <q who="HSB"><p>MRS. SANGER said that 22 countries from the East and the West will be
                represented in the planned parenthood conference in Japan.</p></q>
        <p>"They are all interested in knowing what to do," she stated.</p>
        <q who="HSB"><p>Even Catholic countries like Italy are now receptive to the idea of birth
                control, according to Mrs. Sanger.</p></q>
        <p>"In all the time that I have worked for birth control," she went on, "the greatest
            opposition that I have met has come from the American Catholic groups in <place
                reg="New York, NY">New York.</place></p>
        <p>"Even in Italy, there is now a group of brilliant scientists and professional people that
            is working to do away with the <person reg="Mussolini, Benito">Mussolini</person>
            laws.</p>
        <p>"They never had a law against birth control until Mussolini made one, and you know what
            Mussolini was."</p>
        <q who="HSB"><p>Mrs. Sanger emphatically asserted that she had never met with any hostility
                in her work to propagate birth control.</p>
            <p>She said that birth control had been practiced "way back in old-<place>Egypt</place>"
                and in <place>France</place> during the days of <person reg="Bonaparte, Napoleon"
                    >Napoleon.</person></p>
            <p>SHE EXPRESSED gratification at the success of the birth control program in
                    <place>India,</place> although it has been introduced in that country only in
                the last few years.</p></q>
        <p>"In India, we are doing it with moving pictures," she said. "In the slums, we are doing
            what we can do with children, showing the disadvantages when the parents cannot support
            their children, and the difficulties to the family when children come too fast."</p>
        <q who="HSB"><p>The Japanese are not going to build birth control clinics, she said, but
                utilize their midwives to teach birth control to the people.</p></q>
        <p>"In Japan, they have so many midwives and not enough doctors," she explained.</p>
        <p>"It will be the first country to use midwives to go into homes and teach the
            mothers."</p>


    </docBody>
</doc>
