<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Editorial">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/07/15 AS encoded</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-08-15 CH proof and correct</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1925/10/00">Oct 1925</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Editorials</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp422032</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title>, Oct. 1925, pp. 275-76.</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="BCR">Birth Control Review</name>
            <name id="HUXJU">Huxley, Julian</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
            <name id="PAIPA">Painlev&eacute;, Paul</name>
            <name id="AUG">Augustine of Hippo (St.)</name>
            <name id="LEAHE">Lea, Henry C.</name>
            <name id="ATH">Athenagoras of Athens</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="Birth Control Review, The"/>
        <index level1="National Birth Control League"/>
        <index level1="Huxley, Julian"/>
        <index level1="League of Nations"/>
        <index level1="overpopulation"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="opposition to"/>
        <index level1="Catholic Church" level2="birth control and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>EDITORIALS</head>
        <p>IN December, the <org>American Birth Control League</org> will go to <org
                reg="United States Congress">Congress</org> for the first time with a Birth Control
            Amendment to <rs type="law" reg="United States Criminal Code, Section 211">Section 211
                of the Postal Law</rs>. The great work to be done in the Fall will be to put all
            candidates for the <org reg="United States Senate">Senate</org> and <org
                reg="United States House of Representatives">House of Representatives</org> on
            record for or against the bill before the November election and to follow up those who
            are elected and enlist their active support even before they take their seats in
            Congress. For this we need all the help our members and sympathizers in all states can
            give us. If you want to help, write to the <person reg="Kennedy, Anne"
                >Secretary</person> at the League headquarters, who will send you copies of the bill
            with questionnaire to candidates attached. If you want to help in another way you can
            send a check. A dollar will help, five will make you a member of our <org
                reg="American Birth Control League, Congressional Committee">Congressional
                Committee</org> and ten will bring you our blessings and a monthly report from
                <place reg="Washington, DC">Washington.</place></p>
        <p>DO we still really care whether it is a girl or a boy? Do "<q who="UNK">families consider
                a boy an asset, a girl a liability?</q>" It is hard to believe that great numbers of
            people still feel this way about the relative value of the sexes, and yet the reception
            given by the English press to <person reg="Erskine, Cicely Quicke">Mrs. Montieth
                Erskine's</person> book, <title type="book">"Sex at Choice,"</title> would seem to
            indicate that they do. We have not read Mrs. Erskine's book, it may or may not have any
            value as a contribution to a subject that is now much discussed in scientific circles.
            Mrs. Erskine alone so far claims that she knows the secret of creating male or female,
            but medical science has gone part of the way. It has reached the point of forecasting
            the sex of the unborn child.</p>
        <p><person reg="Fried, Isaac">Dr. Isaac Fried</person> of the <org>Jewish Maternity
                Hospital,</org>
            <place reg="New York, NY">New York,</place> has according to the <title type="journal"
                >Medical Review of Reviews</title> been able, by special blood test, to judge
            correctly the sex of many hundred children in utero. That science will soon go farther
            than this is the prediction of the English biologist <person reg="Huxley, Julian">Julian
                Huxley,</person> who states in an interview in the <title type="journal">London
                Daily News</title> that in fifty years the problem of sex determination will be
            solved. He adds however, that this may not be an unmixed blessing and "<q who="HUXJU"
                >believes that the result may easily be chaos</q>" unless the direction of this
            power is under scientific control. With sex determination Professor Huxley links Birth
            Control as a subject which scientific bodies should be taking seriously, and recommends
            that "<q who="HUXJU">the controlling of these two very powerful factors in human
                history</q>" should be in the hands of a Medical Research Council.</p>
        <p>With science thus set on taking these important matters out of the haphazard control of
            nature, it is interesting to know the latest figures on the proportions of the sexes. In
            the <place>United States</place> (census of 1920) it was 104 males to 100 females. A
            compilation for <place>Europe</place>
            <person reg="Maurel, Dr.">Dr. Maurel</person> has been given recently in the <title
                type="journal">Bulletin de L'Academie de Medecine (<place reg="Paris, France"
                    >Paris</place>).</title> It shows that most European countries since 1865 show
            an excess of boy babies. In <place>France</place> the latest figure is about 102 boys to
            100 girls, in some other countries the excess is greater. Maurel believes that the age
            of parents, especially of the father, has some influence, since figures from
                <place>Norway</place> show that the younger the father the greater the proportion of
            boys.</p>
        <p>AT the opening of the Sixth Assembly of the <org>League of Nations</org> on September
            7th, <person reg="Painlev&eacute;, Paul">Paul Painleve,</person> the French Premier, who
            delivered the opening address apologized, according to press reports, "<q who="PAIPA"
                >because greater effort for peace had not been put forth</q>" by the League. The way
            to help the peace movement in a fundamental way is still open. It is two years since
            France tried to have information about contraception read into the obscenity laws of the
            nations which are members of the League. The effort was defeated, mainly it is believed
            by the efforts of England, and since then England has gone far toward government support
            of Birth Control. So we may hope that she will soon be added to <place reg="Netherlands"
                >Holland</place> as an active supporter of Birth Control in the League.</p>
        <p>THE Roman Catholic opposition in England, forced to try to meet in other ways some of the
            problems demanding Birth Control for their solution, has presented a program for the
            relief of overpopulation. The program, framed by <person reg="Deegan, Fr.">Father
                Deegan</person> of <place reg="Leicester, England">Leicester</place> is given in our
            news from England. With the exception of one item it is based from beginning to end on
            self control.</p>
        <p>This mirage of relief for their miseries&mdash;this program based on emotional
            starvation-is all the greatest of the Christian churches has to offer its children as
            the alternative for Birth Control. The self control which would limit a marriage to a
            reasonable family of, say, three children means that many years of married life must be
            passed in absolute celibacy.</p>
        <p>This church, of any institution in the world, ought to know that such self control is a
            mirage. For more than fifteen hundred years the <org>Roman Catholic Church</org> has
            been trying to enforce celibacy not upon the rank and file, but upon a picked body of
            the honest men in its membership. Its experience is told in one of the great source
            books of medieval history, <person reg="Lea, Henry C.">Henry C. Lea's</person>
            <title type="book">"History of Sacerdotal Celibacy in the Middle Ages."</title></p>
        <p>THE struggle began in the fourth century when the Church irrevocably committed itself to
            an unmarried priesthood. An immediate result was the institution of the
                <org>Agapetae</org>, a body of young women in platonic relations with the monks and
            secular priests. The Agapetae, it is hardly necessary to state, soon lost its platonic
            character and became one of the most scandalous institutions of the early middle ages.
            Nor was this the only scandal that followed in the tram of sacerdotal celibacy.</p>
        <p>The general situation in his lifetime is described by <person reg="Augustine of Hippo"
                >St. Augustine</person>, himself one of those by whose efforts sacerdotal celibacy
            was unposed. He found everywhere "<q who="AUG">ecclesiastics surrounded by young female
                slaves and leading an existence which differed from matrimony only in the absence of
                marriage ceremony.</q>" Like reports of conditions are given century after century.
            A stream of laws, punishments, and supervisory vists by church authorities prove at
            once, says Mr. Lea, "<q who="LEAHE">the hopelessness of the attempt and the incurable
                nature of the disorders of which the church was at once the cause and the
            victim</q>."</p>
        <p>IN the ninth century after long continued and vigorous "cleanups," the <org
                reg="Council of Aix-en-Provence">Council at <place reg="Aix, France"
                >Aix</place></org> found that the convents were often brothels and that in the
            monestaries the denial of appropriate and healthful affection led to fearful and
            unnatural crimes.</p>
        <p>By the tenth century the decenter parish clergy, disgusted with the prevailing sacerdotal
            looseness, began to take wives, sometimes, if they could find like-minded priests to
            perform it, with the religious ceremony, sometimes as concubines, but even in these
            cases in a permanent and honorable union. Sometimes all the priests in a diocese were
            marned. In one case where a higher church dignitary protested they replied that "<q
                who="LEAHE">marriage was necessary to protect the church against the most hideous
                vices.</q>" In certain <place reg="Spain">Spanish provinces</place> indeed, for this
            very reason the parishioners compelled their parish priests to marry. Whether broken by
            immorality of marriage, the law was always, with whatever penalties it was enforced
            throughout the centuries, a dead letter with a large body of the clergy. The fight for
            sacerdotal celibacy was never fought to a successful conclusion.</p>
        <p>Today the priesthood is a smaller class relatively to the whole population, it can
            perhaps be recruited from that small group who have a vocation for asceticism. In the
            Middle Ages not ascetics alone, but all peace-loving men and women sought refuge in the
            religious life. Of such as these is the worldly man and woman of today and with such
            evidence as this of the impracticability of enforcing celibacy, or such self control in
            marriage as amounts to celibacy on the rank and file, we can only agree with <person
                reg="Athenagoras of Athens">Athenagoras,</person> one of the early fathers of the
            Church who opposed the inauguration of the practice, that "<q who="ATH">that law is not
                from <name type="deity">God</name> which enjoins upon us practices contrary to our
                nature.</q>"</p>
        <p>Mr. Lea's study has a moral not only for Roman Catholics, but for all those who believe
            that sex and population problems can be solved by the magic formula Self-control.</p>
        <p/>
    </docBody>
</doc>
