<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Editorial">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/07/08 AS encoded</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-08-14 CH proof and edit</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1925/11/00">Nov 1925</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Editorials</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp422033</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">The Birth Control Review</title>, Nov. 1925, pp.
                307-08.</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="ECHB">Episcopal Church House of Bishops</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>This unsigned editorial was written during Sanger's tenure as editor of
            the <title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title>, but it is not certain that she
            is the author.</p>
        <index level1="Marion, Kitty"/>
        <index level1="Birth Control Review, The"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="religion and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="in marriages"/>
        <index level1="birth control movement" level2="disputes within"/>
        <index level1="Comstock Laws"/>
        <index level1="Comstock, Anthony"/>
        <index level1="birth control clinics and leagues" level2="research benefits of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>EDITORIALS</head>
        <p>THE daily papers this month have given widespread publicity to the report of a committee
            of the <org>Protestant Episcopal Church</org>, convening in <place reg="New Orleans, LA"
                >New Orleans</place> which condemns the theory and practice of Birth Control as "<q
                who="ECHB">hostile to the family</q>." The committee presenting this report was
            composed of six bishops, two clergymen and a lay delegate. While the account published
            by the daily press is fragmentary and no adequate answer is possible until the full
            report is at hand, there is evident a painful lack of clear, constructive or courageous
            thinking. The attitude of this committee is a familiar one--glib condemnation of
            contraception, and an equally thoughtless insistence upon "<q who="ECHB">the paramount
                importance of deliberate and thoughtful self-control</q>." As for the "unfit" and
            mentally defective the committee urges the enactment of state legislation forbidding the
            marriage of such persons.</p>
        <p>It would be manifestly unfair to enlightened members of the Episcopalian clergy to accept
            this report as representative of the best opinion of the Protestant church concerning
            Birth Control. Readers of these pages will recall the recent courageous sermon delivered
            in <place>Brighton, England,</place> by the <person reg="Barnes, Ernest">Bishop of
                Birmingham,</person> in which that leader of religious thought pointed out that
            Birth Control is not only consistent with the fundamental tenets of Christian ethics,
            but that in the present situation of the world community, with its chaos and conflict,
            it is moreover the imperative duty of every thoughtful Christian courageously to
            participate in our battle for individual and racial regeneration. It is not necessary to
            reiterate here the courageous words of <person reg="Inge, William Ralph">William Ralph
                Inge,</person> the Very Reverend Dean of <org>St. Paul's Cathedral,</org>
            <place reg="London, England">London.</place> Nor is it necessary to recall that
            ever-growing list of enlightened and brave members of the Episcopal clergy who have come
            out without subterfuge or equivocation in defence of contraception.</p>
        <p>Birth Control, as anyone who has taken the trouble to probe beneath the surface of the
            marriage problem knows, is not inimical to the best interests of marital or family
            relations. On the contrary Birth Control, as <person reg="Dawson, Bertram (Lord)">Lord
                Dawson of Penn</person> so vigorously pointed out to the Bishops of England in an
            assemblage not unlike the recent convention at New Orleans, is one of the first
            requisites to happy marriage. The consummation of marriage effected without fear and the
            establishment of a creative, life-giving, joyful relationship between the husband and
            wife-such are the foundations upon which permanent monogamy is established. Only thus
            can the divorce "evil" be combatted and cured in any constructive fashion. And likewise
            only by Birth Control-the instrument which empowers parents to determine when and where
            and under what conditions they shall bring children into this world-can permanent,
            happy, healthy, wholesome family relations be established. These facts are so
            "idiotically obvious" that it must bore the readers of the <title type="journal">BIRTH
                CONTROL REVIEW</title> to find them repeated here. But it is precisely these axioms
            of racial hygiene which have been overlooked by the high dignitaries of the Protestant
            Episcopal Church, who are crying aloud against the marriage of mental defectives and for
            stricter divorce laws.</p>
        <p>THE position against Birth Control evidenced in the committee's report is obstructive. It
            stands in the path of progress--the progress of the splendid awakening within the ranks
            of the Protestant clergy which may be observed on all sides. The younger men are coming
            to see that in this great twentieth century task of human liberation and racial rebirth,
            the Church cannot afford to assume an attitude of arrogant paternalism. The clergy, as
            the finer more courageous churchmen well realize, must descend from its throne, must
            join the ranks, and battle for the <name type="deity">Lord</name> in tangible concrete
            effort, translating its religious and ethical truths into contemporary human terms. And
            first of all, and last of all, it must learn to understand human nature. In
            understanding, the Protestant Episcopal Church will no longer condemn it, but lead it
            onward toward the City of <name type="deity">God</name>.</p>
        <p>EDUCATION in contraceptive hygiene will, we believe, be gradually disseminated. It will
            spread so gradually, so quietly and withal so steadily that even those of us most
            profoundly interested may never know the full extent of our influence. To aid in this
            dissemination one of our main tasks must be to remove the most outstanding obstacles in
            the path of this beneficient stream. For the first time we are extending our work this
            year to campaign for an amendment to the notoriously obstructive <name type="law"
                reg="United States Criminal Code, Section 211">Section 211 of the Federal Penal
                Code</name>. This is the ignominious law passed in 1878 under the influence of
                <person reg="Comstock, Anthony">Anthony Comstock.</person> It has never been
            amended. The most lamentable effect of Section 211 is that it hinders the free
            circulation among reputable physicians and scientists of data and technical information
            concerning the progress of contraceptive science abroad and at home. In
                <place>Europe</place> the results of clinical research are given out to physicians
            and scientists working in the same fields of investigation. Splendid work is
            accompolished, and investigators are kept in touch with the achievements of colleagues
            in other countries.</p>
        <p>Lamentably, the reports of clinical research in contraception, as well as all discoveries
            and improvements in the instrument of Birth Control are refused transmission by the
            United States mails. Thus an obsolete law, enacted under the sinister regime of the
            prurient Comstock, stands in the path of scientific and humane progress.</p>
        <p>FRIENDS of Birth Control may extend real help toward the removal of thsi shameful Section
            211 by writing vigorous protests against its injustice and recommending no less
            vigorously the support of the proposed amendment to their Senators and Congressmen.
            November is the month in which these letters should be written. Let us find out exactly
            how those who have been elected to represent the men and women of the <place>United
                States</place> stand in this matter.</p>
        <p>COURAGE expresses itself in many ways. There is the exceptional spectacular act of
            heroism which stands out like a bright light on a dark night against the background of
            undistinguished conduct, or even, sometimes, of cowardice or pettiness. Such acts of
            heroism shine by contrast. They bring publicity, praise and medals for valor. The
            soldier whose every-day behavior may be the very opposite of medal is rewarded by
            distinguished service medals and thus bribed, like a child, into renewed bravery. Then
            there is the unexpected adventurous courage of the criminal, often driven to desperate
            straits by circumstance. Far finer than the courage that is commended by daily
            newspapers or appeals by its underlying melodrama to the writers of fiction is a type of
            courage that seems to us peculiarly feminine in quality. Feminine, I mean, in its
            modesty, its steadfastness, the day-in and day-out type of courage that seeks neither
            publcity nor the cheap reward of gold medals or public recognition. This is a heroism
            totally devoid of hysterical enthusiasm, a heroism steady-footed and never marred by any
            sign of depression or ignoble collapse.</p>
        <p>THERE are thousands of women whose lives are the expression of this silent, inartciulate
            bravery, women who would not know what you were talking about if you praised their
            indomitable courage. This type of courage, indomitable, invincible, elemental, is
            incarnate in our own <person reg="Marion, Kitty">Kitty Marion.</person> For years, in
            point of fact ever since we have been publishing this <title type="journal"
                >REVIEW</title>, she has sold it on the streets of <place reg="New York, NY">New
                York.</place> Firmly planted and holding aloft our printed challenge of the
            proximate liberation of suffering womankind.</p>
        <p>Standing there immutable, untiring and sure of herself and her conviction in the endless
            changing eddies and currents of human traffic in over-crowded thoroughfares, the object
            of ill-concealed curiosity, at times bitterly denounced by the enemies of Birth Control,
            Kitty Marion has held aloft with telling dramatic gesture the challenge of Birth
            Control. She has been a beacon light for lost mothers seeking in desperation some way
            out of the labyrinth of torture to which the laws and the prejudices of legislators have
            subjected them.</p>
        <p>Her absence has made us appreciate more sharply than ever before the significant and
            finely poised heroism of Kitty Marion. For three summer months she has been away, her
            vacation taking her to England wehre, in the militant suffrage movement she had served
            so valuable an apprenticeship. But now the mothers passing in the hurried eddying tides
            of Broadway traffic are again seeking her out. They are telling their neighbors and
            friends of the reappearance of the brave indomitable torchbearer again at her various
            posts. And we who have during these past months missed Kitty Marion welcome her return
            and greet her as a true heroine of the Birth Control movement.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
