<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published statement">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-06-25 AS encoded</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-06-26 CH proofed and entered</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1923-12-11">1957</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Statement on Secret Birth Control
                Clinic</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp422021</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Birth Control to be Nation's Salvation?</title>, <title
                    type="journal">The Hutchinson News</title>, Dec. 11, 1923</bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="HN">Hutchinson News</name>
            <name id="FRE">French</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><index level1="birth control clinics and leagues" level2="in US"/>
        <index level1="National Birth Control League"/>
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="American opinion on"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Birth Control to be Nation's Salvation?</head>
        <byline>By <person reg="Van de Grift, Josephine">JOSEPHINE VAN de GRIFT</person></byline>
        <dateline><date value="1923/12/11">Dec. 11</date>
            <place reg="New York, NY">New York</place></dateline>
        <div type="section">
            <p>"Within ten years birth control clinics will excite no more comment than school
                houses; charitable institutions will largely have disappeared; and the little short
                word <foreign lang="FRE">finis</foreign> will have been written over the tragedy of
                the unwanted child."</p>
            <q who="HN"><p><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger,</person> foremost
                    proponent of birth control, clad in a frock of black, becomingly frilled with
                    white, a bunch of violets at her belt, thus jubilantly predicts a future based
                    upon the successful operation of the first birth control clinic here.</p>
                <p>For 11 months, she reveals, the clinic has been secretly operating at the
                    headquarters of the <org>American Birth Control League,</org> 104 Fifth avenue,
                    during which time it has given contraceptive information to 900 women, turned
                    away twice as many more and answered 65,000 letters from women in all parts of
                    the country.</p></q>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">Keep Within the Law</head>

            <p><q who="HN">And all, she says, within the spirit and the letter of the law.</q></p>
            <p><q who="HN">The operation of the clinic was kept secret, not because of any fear that
                    it was illegal, explains Mrs. Sanger, but in order that the project might be
                    given an unhampered trial.</q></p>
            <p>"And its results answer conlusively," she maintains, "the claims of our opponents
                that the giving of contraceptive information would increase immortality, that the
                poor didn't want it, that others wouldn't tolerate it.</p>
            <p>"I have no knowledge of a woman of loose morals ever applying at the clinic.</p>
            <p>"The 900 women who were given information were all married. Of these, 73 per cent
                wanted the information because their families were already larger than they could
                care for and 27 per cent needed it for health reasons."</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">Clinics Planned for Other Cities</head>

            <p><q who="HN">Mrs. Sanger does not fear the interference of the law in her present
                    project.</q></p>
            <p>"I do not see how the legality of the clinic can be questioned," she asys, "as we
                have followed the letter of the law in every respect.</p>
            <p>"Already our workers are planning to open similar clinics in <place reg="Chicago, IL"
                    >Chicago</place> and <place reg="Milwaukee, WI">Milwaukee</place> and within a
                few years I expect to see them in every city and town of the <place>United
                    States.</place></p>
            <p>"It isn't only the club women who want it. The women of the lower classes are
                clamoring for it, as our 65,000 pathetic, generally poorly spelled letters show.</p>
            <p>"It has got to come, else the United States will be like <place>China.</place> We may
                not feed our surplus children to the crocodiles but disease and vice are even worse
                monsters."</p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
