<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Editorial">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/07/16 AS encoded</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-08-15 CH proof and edit</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1918/05/00">May 1918</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Editorial</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp422027</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title>, May 1918</bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="BCR">Birth Control Review</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>This unsigned editorial may have been written by Margaret Sanger.</p>
        <index level1="abortion" level2="birth control vs."/>
        <index level1="Birth Control Review, The"/>
        <index level1="birth control movement" level2="disputes within"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="medical community and"/>
        <index level1="voluntary motherhood"/>
        <index level1="birth control clinics and leagues" level2="physicians and"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <p>A <person reg="Unidentified">CONSERVATIVE FRIEND</person> who has often relieved my
            "neediest cases" with clothing, medical attention or cash, took me to task for endorsing
            birth control.</p>
        <p><q who="UNK">"Why do you have anything to do with the dangerous doctrine?</q>" she
            inquired.</p>
        <p>"Because of these letters" And I handed her a sheaf of them. She was quite shaken by the
            reading.</p>
        <p>"<q who="UNK">It's shocking,</q>" she murmured with a shudder. "<q who="UNK">Such
                Ignorance is appalling. These women do not know how to protect themselves. What sort
                of doctors do they have?</q>"</p>
        <p>"Doctors who do not believe in birth control," I retorted.</p>
        <p>"<q who="UNK">Neither does mine, but--</q>"</p>
        <p>"He does not endorse it--he merely supplies it to patients who can afford to pay for
            it-patients like you--"</p>
        <p>Her eyes flashed.</p>
        <p>"<q who="UNK">Are you suggesting that Dr. Blank would perform a criminal
            operation?</q>"</p>
        <p>I could hardly believe my ears. This woman of intelligence, leader in club, civic and war
            relief work, did not know the difference between criminal abortion and birth control.
            And then I realized as I have often realized it before, that the enemies of physical
            emancipation for women deliberately, maliciously, confuse the two terms. This woman
            whose strength and beauty had been conserved for years by contraceptives has been
            fighting the movement to grant the same protection and privilege to her less fortunate
            sisters because her physician has misled her, intentionally or otherwise.</p>
        <p>We will never have voluntary motherhood until we tear away the <unclear>veil</unclear> of
            hypocrisy and misrepresentation by which physicians hide the truth from their patients,
            and especially the smugness of those medical men who inform their overburdened patients
            that there are no safe and sure contraceptives, while they protect their own wives and,
            incidentally, their own bank accounts by practising birth control in their private
            lives. These are the worst offenders against the health and the freedom of American
            women.</p>
        <p>Birth Control Leagues have been formed in many localities and then allowed to languish or
            die. But the day is coming when they will be supported by the very women who once drew
            back their skirts. War is a great awakener of women. It stirs their souls and opens
            their eyes to the futility and emptiness of traditions. Haphazard, unregulated
            child-bearing as woman's world-duty is a dying tradition.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
