<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Interview">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/07/15 AS encoded</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-08-15 CH proof and enter</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1916-04-20">20 Apr. 1916</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Interview with the Chicago
                Herald</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp422038</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Birth Control Clinic Planned</title>, <title type="journal"
                    >Chicago Herald</title>, Apr. 29, 1916, p. 1.</bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="CH">Chicago Herald</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>For drafts of the texts Sanger used during her American speaking tour
            in 1916, see "<xref from="236132.xml">Birth Control (Chicago Address on Women)</xref>,"
                "<xref from="101859.xml">Birth Control and Society</xref>," Apr.-June, 1916, “<xref
                from="128002.xml">Woman and Birth Control</xref>," Apr-July 1916, and "<xref
                from="128003.xml">Condemnation is Misunderstanding</xref>," Apr.-Jun. 1916.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
        <index level1="Illinois" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="propaganda and publicity"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>BIRTH CONTROL CLINIC PLANNED</head>
        <p>"Although I am not ready to state the details, it is practically settled that <place
                reg="Chicago, IL">Chicago</place> will have a birth control clinic located in the
            stockyards district, where poor women who desire information regarding this subject may
            be accommodated," <q who="CH">declared <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Mrs. Margaret
                    Sanger,</person> the birth control propagandist, to the <org
                    reg="Chicago Herald">HERALD</org> last night.</q></p>
        <p>"I am delighted beyond measure at the reception I have received in Chicago, and at the
            interest manifested by people of all classes in this great subject. I have been fairly
            swamped with letters from women with large families, and others not in a position to
            rear any more children at present, requesting literature that will aid them in the
            matter of birth control. I take this as a sign the women of <place reg="United States"
                >America</place> are awakening to the fact that in birth control lies the solution
            of many of the social evils and problems that confront this nation."</p>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">WHAT WOMEN WRITE.</head>
            <q who="CH"><p>Here are some interesting excerpts from a few scores of similar letters
                    from women received by Mrs. Sanger:</p></q>
            <q who="UNK"><p>"I am a young married woman, 22 years of age. I have a considerate and
                    good husband and the dearest little 20-month-old boy. I would like to know a
                    safe and legitimate manner of controlling the size of my family. I wish to have
                    more children, but for a year or two I will not be in condition physically or
                    financially to bear or educate more children. At the same time I wish to be as
                    nearly a perfect mother, wife and loving companion as it is possible for a woman
                    to be."</p></q>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">ASKS FOR INFORMATION.</head>
            <q who="UNK"><p>"Please tell me about this birth control, for I had a bad case with my
                    first baby and would not like to have them come very close. I want more than
                    one, but far apart. I am 20 years old."</p>
                <p>"I believe your work is worthy of the respect and help of all thoughtful people,
                    and that general knowledge of birth control will produce a better
                    generation."</p></q>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
