<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published interview">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014/05/28 MM</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-12-19 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1916-05-19">19 May 1916</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Press Interview for <title type="journal">St. Louis
						Star</title></supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp431938</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">"Mrs. Sanger, Tells of Her Propaganda for Birth
					Control"</title>, <title type="journal">St. Louis Star</title>, May 19,
				1916</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="SLS">St. Louis Star</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>On her arrival in <place reg="St. Louis, MO">St. Louis</place>, Sanger gave several
			interviews to reporters.</p>
		<index level1="abortion" level2="illegal"/>
		<index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="speaking tours" level3="1916 (U.S.)"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="publicity and propaganda"/>
		<index level1="Sanger, William"/>
		<index level1="Family Limitation" level2="legal case"/>
		<index level1="mentally diseasedand disabled" level2="and family size"/>
		<index level1="physically disabled and diseased" level2="and family size"/>
		<index level1="working classes" level2="and family size"/>
		<index level1="marriage" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="nurses training"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="opposition to"/>
		<index level1="Woman Rebel, The" level2="legal case"/>
		<index level1="physicians" level2="and birth control"/>
	</headNote>
	<head>MRS. MARGARET SANGER TELLS OF HER PROPAGANDA FOR BIRTH CONTROL</head>
	<docBody>
		<div type="section">
			<p>
				<q who="SLS">Meeting the Federal Authorities at close quarters and having an
					indictment hanging over hear head like the sword of <name
						type="fictional character">Damocles</name>, has not lessened the enthusiasm
					of Mr.s margaret sanger, the "woman rebel" of <place reg="New York, NY">New
						York</place>, or diminished her intention to teach the women of <place
						reg="United States">America</place> how they may control the size of their
					families.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="SLS">Mrs. Sanger is in <place reg="St. Louis, MO">St. Louis</place> this
					week to lecture and will give her talk on birth control at the <org>Victoria
						Theater</org> next Monday evening.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="SLS">"Mrs. Sanger is married to <person reg="Sanger, William">William
						Sanger</person>, an artist, and is the mother of three children.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="SLS">Mrs. Sanger is making a coast-to-coast lecture tour and is attempting
					to get a committee of women, physicians and trained nurses together to establish
					a clinic at which birth control propaganda amy be spread.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="SLS">Mrs. Sanger says she has no message for the rich woman, or even the
					middle class woman--as she believes both already are in possession to a great
					extent of the information she is giving women of the working classes and of
					foreign birth.</q>
			</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">Will Defy U.S, Marshalls</head>
			<p>"Every woman wants this information," <q who="SLS">she said today.</q> "And as long
				as I believe this to be the case, I shall continue to defy the federal
				authorities.</p>
			<p>"When I was indicted it was on the charge that my pamphlet '<title type="book">Family
					Limitation</title>' was 'obscene.' When the indictment was dropped, the federal
				authorities intimated that it was because I virtually had agreed not to use the
				mails further.</p>
			<p>"But I did not agree, and they knew I would not refrain from the use of the mails. I
				told them at the time that no true woman could retain her self-respect if she
				permitted herself to be frightened off, and that I intended to spread my propaganda.
				And I have continued to do so."</p>
			<p>
				<q who="SLS">Mrs. Sanger attributes most of the insanity, all of the mental, moral
					and physical defectives and feeble-minded children and adults to the practice of
					having large families where living conditions are not right.</q>
			</p>
			<p>"No workingman is able to support more than two children." <q who="SLS">Mrs. Sanger
					said.</q> "The workingman makes an average salary of $10 a week. On this he
				cannot afford to let his wife bring into the world more than two children. He cannot
				take care of them."</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">She Believes in Marriage</head>
			<p>
				<q who="SLS">Mrs. Sanger was asked if she did not believe it better for those who
					were unwilling to assume the responsibilities of parenthood to remain
					unmarried.</q>
			</p>
			<p>"Decidedly no," <q who="SLS">she replied.</q> "I think it is much more moral for a
				fine young man to take a girl as wife, and raise two or three children to be decent,
				moral, upright citizens. But if they can have other children only by jeopardizing
				the futures of all, by throwing some into charitable institutions and others into
				jail, is not my plan of helping them to hold down the size of the family much
				better?"</p>
			<p>
				<q who="SLS">"But suppose you are putting means into people's hands of bringing race
					suicide?" it was suggested.</q>
			</p>
			<p>"I hardly think we need consider that," she said. All women who are fit to be mothers
				want to be mothers. The majority are willing to be the mother of two or three
				children, or even more, according to their circumstances.</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">Children Must be Born Right</head>
			<p>"As for the women who do not want to be mothers and would use this knowledge to
				prevent such a happening--is such a woman fit to bring a child into this world?
				Wouldn't she bear an unloved boy or girl? Children must be born right; and one of
				the first principles of being born right is to be born of love and longing."</p>
			<p>
				<q who="SLS">Mrs. Sanger was asked if her doctrine might not be considered
					anti-Christian."</q>
			</p>
			<p>"Only persons fogyish in their views ever advance that argument." <q who="SLS">she
					said.</q> "It has nothing to do with Christianity."</p>
			<p>
				<q who="SLS">Mrs. Sanger said the idea of spreading this knowledge on birth control
					first came to herduring her work as a trained nurse. She pursued this occupation
					fourteen years.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="SLS">"She said in her hospital work she saw so many women broken in health
					and spirit because of their efforts to keep from having children, that she
					determined to help them. Statistics on the deaths of women from criminal
					operations are appalling, she said. They occur chiefly among the lower classes,
					where women are the victims of quacks and malpractitioners.</q>
			</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">Began Work Two Years Ago.</head>
			<p>
				<q who="SLS">Mrs. Sanger began the publication of <title type="journal">The Woman
						Rebel</title> early in 1914. The first issue of the magazine was suppressed.
					Seven issues out of nine were confiscated in the mails. In August, 1914, a
					federal Grand Jury in <place reg="New York, NY">New York</place> indicted her,
					basing the charges of obscenity on articles in the March, May and July issues of
						<title type="journal">The Woman Rebel</title>.</q>
			</p>
			<p>"I decided to avoid imprisonment," <q who="SLS">she said</q> "at least until I had
				given out my information. One hundred thousand copies of a pamphlet '<title
					type="article">Family Limitation</title>,' were prepared and distributed and I
				sailed for <place>England</place>.</p>
			<p>"There I discussed my work with many prominent persons and it was indorsed by such
				thinkers as <person type="Wells, H. G.">H. G. Wells</person> and <person
					reg="Bennett, Arnold">Arnold Bennett</person>, the novelists; <person
					reg="Ellis, Havelock">Havelock Ellis</person>, noted sociologist; <person
					reg="Carpenter, Edward">Edward Carpenter</person> and <person
					reg="Murray, Gilbert">Gilbert Murray</person>--the latter a professor at <org
					reg="Oxford University">Oxford</org>.</p>
			<p>"My sole desire has been to throw the matter open for discussion. I am not so anxious
				actually to put means of birth control in women's hands, as to have the world of men
				and women stop and think and determine for themselves if it will not be better for
				all to have this information."</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">Physicians Endorse Her Work</head>
			<p>
				<q who="SLS">Mrs. Sanger says the majority of physdicians with whom she has come in
					contact endorse her work, but themselves are prevented by law from taking up the
					propaganda, except in a secret manner."</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="SLS">Her chief difficulty is in getting people to come "out in the open"
					with endorsements--because the movement is such a radical one."</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="SLS">In West Virginia, in the mining district, her pamphlets had been sent
					to thousands of miners, through a central distributing committee. the men on
					this committee determined that women who had borne nine children were the only
					ones to have the information. The women petitioned them, however, to give it to
					mothers of five children, and this distribution is now being made.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="SLS">Mrs. Sanger also sent the pamphlets to colonies of working people in
						<place reg="Butte, MT">Butte, Mont.</place>, in the textile plants at <place
						reg="Lowell, MA">Lowell</place> and <place reg="Fall River, MA">Fall River,
						Mass.</place>, <place reg="Paterson, NJ">Paterson, N.J.</place>, and the
						<place reg="Chicago, ILL">Chicago</place> Stock Yards.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="SLS">On her present lecture tour she has been in many cities. In Akron,
					Ohio, when the hours for the lecture came, the man who owned the hall notified
					the committeee that the lecture could not be held there. He brought the police
					in to keep Mrs. Sanger and her audience out of the building. He said he was
					willing to be sued, but that the lecture should not be given. She also had
					difficulties with the police in Milwaukee, she said."</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="SLS">"Unlike <person reg="Goldman, Emma">Emma Goldman</person>, the
					anarchist, who was thrown into jail for giving facts and ways of birth control
					in her lecture, Mrs. Sanger gives none of this information from the platform.
					She gives it in person, or though her pamphlets."</q>
			</p>
		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
