<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published interview">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014/05/28 MM</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-12-19 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-28 EK divide</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015/02/10 EKcorrect proof and index</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1916-05-19">19 May 1916</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Interview for <title type="journal">St. Louis Post
						Dispatch</title></supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp431939</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="Published Interview">"Mrs. Sanger Here to Spread Gospel of Birth
					Control,"</title>
				<title type="journal">St. Louis Post-Dispatch</title>, May 19, 1916</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="STPD">St. Louis Post Dispatch</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p> On her arrival in St. Louis, Margaret Sanger gave similar interviews to other local
			reporters.</p>
		<index level1="abortion" level2="birth control and"/>
		<index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="speaking tours" level3="1916 (U.S)"/>
		<index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="nursing background"/>
		<index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="children of"/>
		<index level1="mortality rates" level2="infant"/>
		<index level1="race suicide"/>
		<index level1="Netherlands, the" level2="birth control in"/>
		<index level1="Netherlands, the" level2="birth control clinics"/>
		<index level1="New Zealand" level2="birth control clinics"/>
		<index level1="United States" level2="birth control clincis"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information"/>
		<index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Federal"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="morality of"/>
		<index level1="Woman Rebel, The" level2="legal case"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="publicity and propaganda"/>
		<index level1="working classes" level2="and birth control"/>
		<index level1="upper classes" level2="and birth control"/>
		<index level1="nurses and nursing" level2="and birth control"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>

		<div type="section">
			<head>MRS. SANGER HERE TO SPREAD GOSPEL OF BIRTH CONTROL</head>
			<p>
				<q who="STPD"> Mrs. Margaret Sanger of New York is in <place reg="St. Louis, MO."
						>St. Louis</place> to spread the knowledge of birth control. She will
					deliver a lecture and take steps toward the organization of a birth control
					clinic for the instruction of women.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="STPD"> Mrs. Sanger, was the editor of <title type="journal">the Woman
						Rebel</title>, which was discontinued after seven of the nine issues had
					been confiscated by the postal authorities, and is the author of pamphlets on
					family limitation. A Federal indictment charging her with improper use of the
					mails was dismissed in February on the eve of her trial in <place
						reg="New York, NY">New York</place>. The reason given was that it was
					desired to avoid making a martyr of her.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="STPD">Mrs. Sanger, who arrived at the <org>Jefferson Hotel</org> this
					morning, said to a <title type="journal">Post-Dispatch</title> reporter that she
					had no wish to be a martyr but she wanted the case to go to trial, desiring
					acquittal at the hands of a jury and confidant that she would have been
					acquitted.</q>
			</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">Making Tour of Country.</head>
			<p>
				<q who="STPD">She is touring the country in advocacy of birth control. She came here
					from <place reg="Indianapolis, IN">Indianapolis</place>, where she spoke at the
					national charity conference and where such interest was aroused, she says, that
					birth control teas and birth control luncheons are crowding out other society
					functions.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="STPD">Not that her message is to society women, she explained, except as she
					desires to interest them in the propaganda, which is intended to benefit the
					women of the laboring classes.</q> "I have no message for wealthy women," she
				said. "They have been taken care of. The woman of Fifth Avenue and Riverside Drive
				controls her family. It is the woman of the poorer classes who needs
				enlightenment."</p>
			<p>"I was prompted by my experience as a nurse and as a mother to take up this
				propaganda. In my work as a nurse on <place reg="New York, NY">New York</place>'s
				East Side I saw that there was overbreeding of the least desirable elements, which
				was not making for a racial improvement.</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">Studied Problems Abroad.</head>
			<p>"If I had been all the time on the East Side I might have become hardened to the
				conditions, as others do, but I returned each night to my own home and my three
					<person reg="Sanger, Stuart"><person reg="Sanger, Grant"><person
							reg="Sanger, Peggy">babies</person></person></person>, and the contrast
				inspired me to do what I could to improve conditions among the poor by limitation of
				their families."</p>
			<p>"Birth control does not lead to race suicide. I studied the problem four years in
					<place>England</place>, <place reg="Netherlands, the">Holland,</place>
				<place>France</place> and <place>Spain</place>. In Holland there are 52 clinics
				where married women are taught by nurses how to exercise birth control. This has
				been done for 30 years. The result is that Holland has the lowest general death rate
				in <place>Europe</place>. The infant mortality in <place
					reg="Amsterdam, Netherlands, the">Amsterdam </place>and <place
					reg="The Hague, Netherlands,the">The Hague</place> is lower than in any other
				city in the world. There are fewer births, but the babies that are born have a
				better chance to survive, and the population goes on increasing.</p>
			<p>"<place>New Zealand</place> has had birth control clinics for 20 years, and the
				infant mortality in that country is also low. Commercialized vice is almost unknown
				in both countries."</p>
			<p>"In <place reg="United States">this country</place> there has never been a clinic for
				the instruction of married women. I want to see them established in every city.
				Interest has been manifested by St. Louis nurses and social workers, and something
				has been done toward organizing a branch of the <org>National Birth Control
					League</org>, which has already spread to 12 states."</p>
			<p>"Unfortunately there is a Federal statute which forbids the use of the mails to
				disseminate such information, and there are hindering laws in some of the states.
				The object of the National Birth Control League is to bring about the repeal of
				these laws, so that nurses and doctors can be free to give instruction."</p>
			<p>"In European countries, except Holland and New Zealand, the information is
				disseminated improperly. I want it done here properly, by doctors and nurses. Such
				information will go far toward preventing the illegal operations which cause the
				death of thousands of women."</p>
			<p>"The objection is made that the dissemination of this knowledge will encourage
				immorality. But the women of the upper classes have possessed this knowledge and it
				will hardly be said that the knowledge has encouraged immorality among them."</p>
		</div>

	</docBody>
</doc>
