<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published interview">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-02-04 VV Transcribe and encode</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-02-04 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1954-10-05"> 5 Oct 1954</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Interview with <title type="journal">The Daily
						Collegian</title></supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp431937</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Margaret Sanger Explains Birth Control Movement</title>,
					<title type="journal"> The Daily Collegian</title>, 5 Oct 1954, p. 5</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>

		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="DC">The Daily Collegian</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>Sanger also spoke at <org>Penn State College</org> on 5 October 1954, but the speech was
			not found.</p>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="history of"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Margaret Sanger Explains Birth Control Movement</head>

		<p/>
		<p>"Birth control is a concious control of the birth rate by means of preventing
			conception," <q who="DC">Mrs. Margaret Sanger, originator of the birth control movement,
				gives as her definition of the work she has been doing for more than 30
			years.</q></p>
		<p>
			<q who="DC">Mrs. Sanger is in State College visiting her brother Coach <person
					reg="Higgins, Robert A."> Bob Higgins</person> professor of physical
				education.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="DC">She points out that birth control does not mean to limit or interfere with
				life, because life is not there to destroy. Many people, Mrs. Sanger said, at first
				believe that it advocates abortion, which is very far from the idea.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="DC">The first organization started in 1921. Now called "The <org>Planned
					Parenthood Federation of America</org> "it has its own <org
					reg="Margaret Sanger Research Bureau">research bureau</org> which is the largest
				of its kind in the world. It gives marriage counseling to more than 6,000 new
				patients each year.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="DC">Mrs. Sanger said that her first publication, "The<title type="journal">Woman
					Rebel</title>" was published for the express purpose of exposing the Comstock
				Law. It lasted almost a year, but each copy was suppressed almost immediately after
				printing. Today the organization publishes the scientific "<title type="journal"
					>Journal of Fertility</title>" and the "<title type="journal">Birth Control
					News</title>," which is distributed to its members.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="DC">When asked about other hinderances that faced her and the organization, she
				said that the big trouble today is in getting religious leaders to see the value of
				this movement and to secure their help. However, many clergymen have helped, and
				more are pointing in that direction.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="DC">Mrs. Sanger said that she has many hobbies, but at the moment painting is
				occupying her attention. While visiting at the College, she is studying painting
				under <person reg="Pittman, Hobson">Hobson Pittman</person>, nationally known artist
				and summer instructor at the College.</q>
		</p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
