<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-02-4 CH Transcribe and encode</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-02-04 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1932-11-15">15 Nov 1932</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Future of the American Family</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp431936</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Margaret Sanger Addresses Forum</title>, <title
					type="journal">Daily Collegian</title>, Nov. 18, 1932, p.1 and <title
					type="article">Solve Europe's Population Problem, Or War Will Result, Sanger
					States</title>, <title type="journal">Daily Collegian</title>, Nov. 18, 1932, p.
				1</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="DC">Daily Collegian</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>Sanger spoke at the <org>Schwab Auditorium</org> at <org>Penn State College</org> on
			November 15, 1932, the first in a series of talks sponsored by the <org>Penn State
				Christian Association</org>. The speech was not found, but quotes were taken from
			reports in the <title type="journal">Daily Collegian</title>. </p>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits and risks of"/>
		<index level1="overpopulation" level2="threat to peace as"/>
		<index level1="women" level2="freedom and rights of"/>
		<index level1="family size"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>MARGARET SANGER ADDRESS FORUM</head>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">Speaker at First Meeting Cites 7 Definite Reasons for Birth Control
				Practice</head>
			<p>"Birth control is not a panacea for all the social and economic ills in the world but
				at least it is the most important immediate help which can be applied as a solution
				to the present problems of millions of men and women here and now,"<q who="DC"> Mrs.
					Margaret Sanger said at the opening Forum of the year in the Auditorium Tuesday
					night.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="DC">Mrs. Sanger cited several definite reasons for the practices of birth
					control. Contraception, she belives, should be used in the case of communicable
					diseases, where the mother is physically weak and incapable of bearing children,
					and where the parents produce sub-normal offspring. The practice is also
					valuable to the spacing of children in a family, protecting adolescent married
					couples from having children too soon, and also in the case of poverty stricken
					parents.</q>
			</p>
			<p>"Birth control will give women a chance to develope and to express themselves; it
				will, above all, mean happier marriages," <q who="DC">Mrs. Sanger stated.</q>
				"Instead of the customary single child in families of the higher classes, and ten or
				eleven in the poorer classes, birth control will usher in a new era of families with
				three or four children. This will consitute the American family of the future," <q
					who="DC">the speaker believes.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="DC">Mrs. Sanger left the College yesterday afternoon. In addition to her
					open lecture, she addressed a women's club meeting Tuesday night. While here, a
					number of teas and luncheons were held for her by her sister-in-law <person
						reg="Higgins, Virginia Gaylord">Mrs. Robert A. Higgins</person> and several
					faculty members.</q>
			</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head>Solve <place>Europe</place>'s Population Problem, Or War Will Result, Sanger
				States</head>
			<p>"Europe's over-population problem is sizzling now; in five or six years something is
				going to explode!"</p>
			<p>
				<q who="DC">Mrs. Margaret Sanger usually convinces the skeptical with her smile, but
					now a vague shadow of seriousness hovered over it. As she spoke, small, almost
					unnoticeable gestures betrayed long trying hours on the lecture platform in
					championing the cause of birth control.</q>
			</p>
			<p>"Already <place>Italy</place> has its eye on several choice pieces of territory. And
				when its congested mass of humanity is so much in excess that it reaches the brim
				and overflows, we shall have a war." <q who="DC">She paused and then added
					crisply</q> "This is as inevitable as was the outbreak in 1914."</p>
			<p>"Population must be controlled. Unless it is limited or some system of distribution
				worked out the nations of the world might just as well throw all their peace
				treaties to the winds," <q who="DC">Mrs. Sanger said.</q> "Peace will never be
				achieved until this problem is solved; that's why the birth control question has
				become not only of family importance but of international significance." </p>
			<p>"Fortunately, statesmen are beginning to acquire some concept of the importance of
				the over-populated plight of many countries." <q who="DC">Mrs. Sanger, who has
					travelled extensively in foreign countries, is particularly interested in the
					Italian and Japanese situations.</q> "They must have some outlets for these
				increasing internal numbers, and they're resorting to invasion to find them," <q
					who="DC">she said.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="DC">Mrs. Sanger explained that the de-population could be accomplished by
					either increasing the death rate of decreasing the birth rate. In the past the
					death rate has been raised by means of famine, disease, epidemics, and wars;
					what will happen in the future remains to be seen, she said.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="DC">And then her voice softened, she almost seemed shy, so that one would
					hardly suspect her of being a crusader, a pioneer.</q>
			</p>
			<p>"After all, no matter how hard we fight, birth control will come. It's just a matter
				of how soon."</p>
		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
