<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed statement">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014-05-28 MM</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-02-04 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1926-10-00">
			<supplied resp="MSPP">Oct 1926</supplied>
		</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>Reply to the Views Offered by the Committee of the <org>United Lutheran
					Church</org></titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp021510</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
			<bibl>Library of Congress Microfilm L72:727</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="ULC">United Lutheran Church</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP"><p>This statement was written for the <org
				reg="United Lutheran Church Biennial Convention, 5th">Fifth Biennial Convention of
				the United Lutheran Church</org>, held in <place>Richmond, VA</place> between Oct
			19-27, 1926. Sanger did not attend the meeting.</p>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="religion and"/>
		<index level1="marriage"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="and marriage"/></headNote>

	<docBody>
		<head>REPLY TO THE VIEWS OFFERED BY THE COMMITTEE OF THE UNITED LUTHERAN CHURCH TO BE
			PRESENTED AT THE CONVENTION FOR 1926 IN RICHMOND, VIRGINIA</head>
		<byline>by Margaret Sanger.</byline>
		<p>When one reads the twelve views to be offered by the <org
				reg="United Lutheran Church Committee">Committee</org>, one is at a loss to know how
			such inconsistent thinking can permeate so important a subject as marriage and its
			sanctity.</p>
		<p>It is less than a year ago that the <org>National Lutheran Council</org> tabled a
			resolution condemning the practice of Birth Control because it was recognized by the
			majority of the Council that the practice of Birth Control is considered an economic
			rather than a moral issue. What has happened to make a change of front, Birth Control is
			still an economic issue. It is a health issue. It presses more and more upon the
			economic conscience of the community.</p>
		<p>The United Lutheran Church surely is strong enough to stand upon its own feet and not
			need to echo the views of other Church bodies. I believe that the members of the
			Lutheran Church will oppose such inconsistency as offered by the Committee when the
			assertion is made that the chief aim of married life is the birth of children. This is
			dogma, pure and simple. With ninety-nine people out of a hundred the birth of children
			is the result and not the aim of marriage. That the limitation of birth by artificial
			means is anti-Christian is a matter of opinion. There are many good Lutherans who
			disagree with this point. In fact, I should like to take a poll of the number of
			children born to the Lutheran Committee, and I believe I would verify my belief that
			such a statement is hypocritical.</p>
		<p>The attitude taken <q who="ULC">The pastors so consent to marry only the innocent party
				of a divorce</q> is ludicrous. Like many other well-intentioned designs, it will
			drive people from the church and in many cases seek relations outside of marrige. The
			ban of Birth Control will be futile. It will be far better for the Committee in its aim
			to recognize that marriage is one of the most important problems of the home. To study
			these problems and to face the facts squarely that the greatest immediate problem of the
			home is to have unwatned children.</p>
		<p>The Church would do a great service to bring scientific instruction to the poor,
			diseased, defective members in the Community, such as is already obtainable to the
			well-to-do and the intelligent parishoners of the Church.</p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
