<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/06/01 CE</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-18 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1936-12-29">29 Dec 1936</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Notes for Welcoming Address, Conference on
                    Contracepting Research and Clinical Practice</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp101798</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Library of Congress Microfilm</title>, 128:0262</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="USCCA">United States Circuit Court of Appeals</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>The Conference on Contraceptive Research and Clinical Practice was held
                <place reg="New York, NY">New York City</place> at the <org>Hotel Roosevelt</org>on
            December 29 and 30, 1936. It was attended by over fifty representatives from birth
            control clinics around the country. No final version of Sanger's welcome has been
            found.</p><p>For earlier versions, see the Library of Congress Microfilm 128:0264,
            131:0062B, 0072, 0076, and S71:0865 and 870.</p>
        <index level1="eugenics" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="eugenics" level2="positive"/>
        <index level1="mentally disabled and diseased"/>
        <index level1="physicaly disabled and diseased"/>
        <index level1="reproduction"/>
        <index level1="unfit to reproduce" level2="descriptions of"/>
        <index level1="unfir to reproduce" level2="MS on"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <p>LADIES AND GENTLEMAN:</p>
        <p>On behalf of the <org>Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau</org>, it is my privilege
            and my great pleasure to welcome you.</p>
        <p>I am not going to take up the precious time of this <org
                reg="Conference on Contraceptive Research and Clinical Practice">Conference</org> to
            tell you all that our clinic has achieved in the thirteen years it has been functioning.
            We are justly proud of its record, not only as a research center specializing in
            mechanical methods of contraception, but as an educational organization where students
            of administration and technical problems may come to study aspects of contraceptive
            methods not available elsewhere. We have kept the records of some fifty-six thousand
            women who have voluntarily appealed to us for help.</p>
        <p>The outstanding achievement of this Clinic has been to remove the whole question of Birth
            Control from the field of hot and angry theoretical controversy to the calm quiet of
            scientific research, and to enlist the cooperation of competent scientists and
            physicians in amassing a wealth of incontrovertable evidence supporting the feasibility
            and the desirability of contraceptive practice.</p>
        <p>Patient effort has been rewarded with a large measure of success. But we are not content
            to rest upon our laurels, to make large-scale claims. On the contrary: instead of
            looking back, we continue to look forward. We feel that these thirteen years, and the
            twelve that preceded them, must be considered as merely preliminary, pioneering years,
            during which we have succeeded in clearing away the tantalizing underbrush of prejudice
            and legal obstacles.</p>
        <p>We stand at the dawn of a New Day.</p>
        <p>This new era we are entering will be characterized, I hope, as that of
                <emph>scientific</emph> philanthropy, in contra-distinction to what may be rightly
            termed non-scientific. The old philanthropy is bankrupt. It has concerned itself mainly
            with the problem of CLEANING UP THE MESS created by the centuries of uncontrolled
            breeding.</p>
        <p>We can thank the late DEPRESSION for one thing at least. It has turned a pitless X-ray
            upon the failure of private and organized charities, upon scattered, un-coordinated and
            individualistic philanthropies, the aims of which have been ameliorative rather than
            preventive.</p>
        <p>What a waste of money! What a waste of effort! What selfish vanity inspired these great
            donations. Along came the Depression, and suddenly the seamy side of human society was
            dragged out into the open for all with intelligent eyes to see.</p>
        <p>What did we see?</p>
        <p>Millions of Unemployed--and Unemployable.</p>
        <p>Millions of Children Hungry, Undernourished, Starving.</p>
        <p>Crime Multiplying a thousandfold; Gangs; Racketeers; Kidnappers.</p>
        <p>Slums, Breeding Grounds of Disease, Crime, Defects.</p>
        <p>Prisons, Asylums, Institutions for the Delinquent, the Defective, the Dependant.</p>
        <p>Insanity, Feeble-mindedness propagating itself.</p>
        <p>In spite of all the useless millions contributed in Charities, the Normal were compelled
            to bear the burden of the sub-normal. The whole crisis in racial health can be summed up
            in one word:</p>
        <p>WASTE:</p>
        <p>Waste of lives, waste of resources, waste of money.</p>
        <p>Worst of all, the appalling, criminal waste of the precious materials out of which we
            must build the future of humanity-- Waste of Mother life and Child Life.</p>
        <p>We must face the obvious fact that it is not enough to try to Clean up the Mess, to
            approach the problem of human breeding with perfumed disinfectants, to indulge ourselves
            in the vicious sentimentality of degrading charity. All the advances in Public Health
            and Sanitation have been made by attacking problems at their source--have been
                <emph>preventive</emph> in aim.</p>
        <p>No advance in racial health and well-being can be attained until the POLLUTION Of the
            racial stress is stopped at its source. This PROBLEM IS NOT INSOLUBLE. RACIAL HEALTH IS
            NOT ONLY POSSIBLE: IT IS AN IMPERATIVE NEED. AND IT CAN BE ATTAINED IF [YOU?]
            DISINTERESTED SCIENTISTS. Fully realize the basic and leading role you must play in the
            supreme Drama of the Destiny of the Human Race. Your role is no secondary one to
                <add>subordinate</add> that of strutting Politicians, Dictators, or Captains of
            Industry. You are the CAPTAIN on the BRIDGE, guiding HUMANITY into the Unknown
            Future.</p>
        <p>Give us your cooperation, your wisdom, your impersonal courage and bravery! Your
            greatness will not be measured by the cheap applause of the public: it will be measured
            by the greatness of the ideal to which you consecrate your efforts.</p>
        <p>At the dawn of our New Day, the poor old Human Race seems to be STREAMLINING itself to an
            EASY EXTINCTION in a general IMBECILITY, since it is increasing and multiplying from its
            worst stocks. But with the aid of scientific research, the Race has wonderful, almost
            miraculous powers of regeneration and redemption.</p>
        <p>I like to think of the Human Race as a broad deep stream flowing on to its fulfillment
            and realization. Now it is polluted, muddied. It is the function of the scientist to
            trace the source of that pollution and to get rid of it. RACE SALVATION awaits the
            fruits of scientific research and discovery.</p>
        <p>I cannot close without expressing our jubilation <add>over</add> the recent opinion
            handed down by the <org>United States Circuit Court of Appeals</org>, declaring that the
            Federal Statutes were not designed to <q who="USCCA">obstruct the circulation of
                articles which may be intelligently employed by conscientious physicians for the
                purpose of saving life and promoting well-being</q>.” This means the field is
            cleared for the discovery of cheap, reliable, scientific methods of controlling human
            fertility. Contraceptive research is now free to pursue its course,
                <add>emancipated</add>
            <del>freed</del> of the stigma of prejudice.</p>
        <p>Let us close with the hope that this Conference marks not the end of a troubled era, but
            rather the inauguration of a new epoch--not alone in contraceptive research and clinical
            methods, but more profoundly of a truly profound and far-seeing scientific love of
            Mankind.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
