<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2010/02/03 ac</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/07/13 NC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/08/18 EK</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1932-04-20">20 April 1932</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>American Women's Association Testimonial Dinner Address</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp101793</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
            <bibl>LCM 128:0237B-243A</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>The following speech was given at the <org>American Women's
                Association</org> Testimonial Dinner on April 20, 1932 after a medal was awarded to
                <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger</person> for her achievements. For draft
            version see <xref from="129022.xml">Medal Speech</xref>. Other versions can also be
            found at LCM 128:0251-025, 237B-243, and 0235-023.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Federal"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="doctor's only laws"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="MS on"/>
        <index level1="National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control"
            level2="goals of"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="awards"/>
        <index level1="United States Congress"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <p>You must know that my heart is too full to express my gratitude in words.</p>
        <p> I have been sitting here listening to these beautiful tributes by such distinguished men
            and women that I ask myself is it true? Am I really awake? Or is it all a dream?</p>
        <p> For after nearly twenty years of indictments suppressions, courts, jails, patrol wagons
            and police raids, it is simply wonderful to live to receive something besides a
            warrant!</p>
        <p>
            <person reg="Morgan, Anne">Miss Morgan</person>, I shall always prize this medal far
            more than a <emph rend="underline">reward</emph> for my humble efforts. To me it
            symbolizes public recognition by a representative group of enlightened women of the
            basic importance of birth control as a necessary instrument in the making of our
            civilization.</p>
        <p> In conferring upon me this great honor, I feel that you are joining in the battle for a
            new civilization and that is why this medal means so much to me. The memory of it will
            go with me into the thick of the fight. In moments of weariness, discouragement, it will
            reassure me that we are no longer alone in this battle for knowledge. That intelligent,
            courageous groups of women are not only standing behind us but standing with us shoulder
            to shoulder in spirit!</p>
        <p> I want to take this opportunity to tell you something of the work in <place
                reg="Washington, D.C."> Washinton</place>, where I have been for the past five
            months. In the Congressional trenches, you might say. Our little group of workers,
            valiant and undaunted, were veritable <emph rend="underline">shock troops</emph> in
            trying to get our bill through <org reg="United States Congress">Congress</org>. A bill which dares to ask that women have free
            access to scientific knowledge of their own bodies through the medium of the medical
            profession.</p>
        <p> We arrived there to find the very air surcharged with the present and immediate problems
            of the day.</p>
        <p> War debts, Reparations, Moratoriums, Unemployment Relief, Sales’ Tax, War in <place
                reg="Manchuria, China">Manchuria</place>, Peace Conference, Tariffs, Budget
            Balancing; Light Wines and Beers, Prohibition, Bonuses. No basic plan for their
            solution.</p>
        <p> The mind of each Representative, each Senator was like a busy telephone switchboard;
            with the Secretary as the operator, all the wires were busy. How could one plug in with
            a subject like birth control!</p>
        <p> To the busy, frantic, hectic driven Congressman, the announcement of the subject was
            like a message from Mars, less interesting, or some planet even more remote.</p>
        <p> Some days as many as forty calls were made and if we succeeded in getting two interviews
            it was a good day's work.</p>
        <p> The great difficulty was in getting to see any of them before the bill had been
            introduced–“busy”, “in conference”, “committee meetings”, delegations arriving, desks
            heaped with letters–come back tomorrow–come back next week. Anything to put you off and
            get you out. We always came back promptly on the hour!</p>
        <p> When we finally had the opportunity of an interview we found the great majority of men
                <emph rend="underline">un-informed</emph>. They believed in birth control for
            themselves; but the right of another to have knowledge? Well? He'd have to think <emph
                rend="underline">that over</emph>!</p>
        <p> Those who were informed were full of fears–fear of public opinion, fear of the opponents
                <emph rend="underline">mainly</emph></p>
        <p> These opponents are skilled in the art of tactics. They know how to operate and block
            progress through psychology of <emph rend="underline">fear</emph>.</p>
        <p> They are known to be in the minority but by group activity they give the impression of
            being twice as strong as they actually are. Our supporters give single occasional aid,
            but the opponents spring into double and intense activity at every step or plan. The
            opponents use the negative weapons of fear. We must use the constructive positive
            inspiring instrument of courage.</p>
        <p> We have persuaded two Congressmen in to activity <emph rend="underline">for</emph>
            constructive legislation. We have worked to make them birth control conscious.</p>
        <p> The result has been achieved because of persistent, determined activity expressed in
            letters, telegrams, telephones, visitors, constituents, who would not be turned away or
            silenced by the conventional polite routine letters or dismissal. Southern constituents
            demanded point blank <q who="UNK">will <emph rend="underlined">you introduce</emph> this bill?</q>
            Knowing their earnestness he replied that he would and he did.</p>
        <p> Being of a trusting and believing nature.</p>
        <p> House–Bill referred to Ways and Means.</p>
        <p> Judiciary.</p>
        <p><person reg="Hancock, Frank">FRANK HANCOCK</person></p>
        <p><person reg="Hatfield, Henry">SENATOR HATFIELD</person></p>
        <p> And now that our bill has been introduced in Congress-–one in the <org reg="United States House of Representatives">House
                of Representatives</org> and one in the <org reg="United States Senate"
            >Senate</org>. Date for Hearings has been set. This meeting tonight! This award! This
            recognition by representative progressive women–-<emph rend="blockquotes">FIGHTING GIBRALTAR–ALL MEANS THAT</emph></p>
        <p rend="blockquotes"><emph rend="underline">WE ARE ON OUR WAY</emph>!</p>
        <p> Who can compute the tremendous sufferings saved the human race when this bill shall be
            passed? I verily believe when fear shall be removed from women's lives that heaven will
            be millions of miles nearer the earth.</p>
        <p> The Social and economic chaos of today stems back to the prolific reckless breeding of
            our forebears. Countless men and women are today entangled and enmeshed in the ignorance
            and prejudice of the past.</p>
        <p rend="blockquotes"> We must disentangle their lives:</p>
        <p rend="blockquotes"> We must release them from ignorance and fear:</p>
        <p rend="blockquotes"> We must free them from archaic laws:</p>
        <p rend="blockquotes"> We must direct our best efforts to settling questions we <emph
                rend="underline">know</emph> in <emph rend="underline">order</emph> to explore and
            enlarge the sphere of the unknown. The sphere of real life.</p>
        <p> All around us in every city and town are women living tortured troubled lives. Many of
            them come to us appealing for help, but millions of them are helplessly inarticulate who
            like doomed souls are crushed beneath the weight of a cruelly prolific nature.</p>
        <p rend="blockquotes"> IT IS THESE WOMEN WHO WE ARE DEDICATED TO FREE.</p>
        <p> This medal, this award shall be the pledge to bind us together and spur us on in the
            continuation of our fight for the liberation of <emph rend="blockquotes">WOMANKIND</emph>.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
