<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/05/24 CE</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/06/21 CE Corrections</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1936-02-04">04 Feb 1936</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Birth Control and Religion</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp101858</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Collection, Library of Congress.</bibl>
            <bibl><title>LCM</title> 128:0454.</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="CLIRU">Clinchy, Russell J.</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="birth control" level2="religion and"/>
        <index level1="child spacing"/>
        <index level1="family planning"/>
        <index level1="men" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>BIRTH CONTROL AND RELIGION</head>
        <p>Proponents and opponents of birth control quote scripture to support
            their point of view, and the number of quotations on each side will
            probably total to an equal number. A better way of determining where
            religious organizations stand on this issue is to consider the
            actual organized religious groups which have expressed an opinion on
            the subject. Outstanding among those who have placed themselves on
            record as supporting the principles of birth control are the <org
                reg="Episcopal House of Bishops">House of Bishops</org> and the
                <org reg="Episcopal House of Deputies">House of Deputies</org>
            of the <org>Episcopal Church</org>, the <org
                reg="Federal Council of the Church of Christ in America, Committee on Marriage and the Family"
                >Committee on Marriage and the Home of the Federal Council of
                the Churches of Christ in America</org>, the <org>Unitarian
                Associations</org>, the <org>Universalist General
                Convention</org>, <org
                reg="Methodist Church Regional Conferences">Regional Conferences
                of the Methodist Church</org>, a Special Committee of the
            Women's Problems Group of <org
                reg="Philadelphia Yearly Meeting of the Religious Society of Friends"
                >Philadelphia Yearly Meeting of Friends</org>, the
                <org>Rabbinical Assembly of America</org>, the <org>General
                Council of Congregational and Christian Churches</org>, and the
                <org>Central Conference of American Rabbis</org>. Add to these
            and many others, the support of special and local organizations
            within the general denominational divisions and we have a pretty
            complete united front of the Protestant and Jewish faiths, endorsing
            birth control as an aid to mortality and happy marriage. Lay groups
            affiliated with the church, such as <org
                reg="Young Women's Christian Association">Y.W.C.A.</org>, <org
                reg="Young Men's Christian Association">Y.M.C.A</org>.,
                <org>National Council of Jewish Women</org>, and other women's
            church organizations, bring up reinforcements.</p>
        <p>What is the reasoning behind this support? Birth control, it is felt,
            will make for earlier marriages and happier marriages. Many young
            people will marry and start a home if they can feel that they can
            postpone the arrival of children and plan their families, instead of
            leaving the matter to blind and ruthless chance. Many a marriage
            will be preserved if birth control can be used to space the arrival
            of babies to conserve the mother's health so that she can make an
            adequate home life for herself, her husband, and her children.</p>
        <p>Reverend <person reg="Clinchy, Russell J.">Russell J.
                Clinchy</person>, Minister of the <org>Mount Pleasant
                Congregational Church</org> in <place reg="Washington, D.C."
                >Washington</place>, summed the matter up recently in an address
            as follows: “<q who="CLIRU">There is now laid before mankind a new
                power which may be used in the creation of healthier, happier,
                more richly endowed generations of children; of homes in which
                children may be given an adequate birthright and the fullest
                portion of love and care; of marriage in which the spectre of
                unwanted pregnancies need not occur; of a social order which may
                be created without war and economic disaster through
                overpopulation. For those who believe that the knowledge of the
                universe is of <name type="Deity">God</name>, birth control,
                this new power, will open the gates of life and usefulness, and
                will bring the realization of the true joy and meaning of human
                love</q>.”</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
