<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/06/21 CE</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/08/17 EK tags corrected</prepDate><prepDate>2011-11-21 CH correct typo</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1937-00-00">1937</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>THE BIRTH CONTROL OF A NATION</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp101878</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
            <bibl><title>LCM</title> LC 128:520.</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="AMA">American Medical Association</name>
            <name id="COMAC">Comstock Act of 1873</name>
            <name id="HANLE">Hand, Learned</name>
            <name id="MOSGR">Moscowitz, Grover C.</name>
            <name id="NYCA">New York Court of Appeals</name>
            <name id="STOHA">Stone, Hannah Mayer</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>Handwritten additions made by an unidentified author have been omitted. </p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="arrests and imprisionment"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues" level3="in US"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Comstock act"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Connecticut"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="doctors-only bills"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Federal"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Massachusetts"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="MS on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="New York "/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="North Carolina"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Oregon"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Puerto Rico"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="State"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="legal cases" level3="U.S. v. One Package of Japanese contraceptives"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="legal cases" level3="Crane Decision'"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="pessaries"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="legalization of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="medical community and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="opposition to"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="infant"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="maternal"/>
        <index level1="National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control"
            level2="goals of"/>
        <index level1="physicians" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="government" level3="public health programs"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>The Birth Control of a Nation</head>
        <byline>by <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></byline>
        <div type="section">
            <p>Birth control is legal at last in the <place>United States</place>. The right to
                provide contraceptive information and service under medical direction is finally
                recognized under the Federal law as now interpreted, and it also is legal under
                state laws in all but two States, <place>Mississippi</place> and
                    <place>Massachusetts</place>--and the Massachusetts law is vulnerable on
                constitutional grounds.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">THE ROAD TO VICTORY</head>
            <p>The road to victory has been long--and hard. But the goal now has been gained, and a
                new era has dawned for birth control.</p>
            <p>It is one of the anomalies of modern civilization that the forces of bigotry,
                reaction and legalism could so long have kept on the statute books a law which
                classed contraceptive information with obscenity and was interpreted to prevent
                physicians from prescribing contraceptives. Year after year this vicious law legally
                tied the hands of reputable physicians while quacks and purveyors of bootleg
                contraceptives and “marriage hygiene” articles and formulas flourished. It was an
                absurd situation in which the Federal law in effect nullified the laws of
                practically every State.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">NOW THEY CAN BE TOLD</head>
            <p>But now mothers can be told! The story of how motherhood ultimately was rescued from
                bondage is an absorbing one. It required two-thirds of a century to remove the
                Federal fetters placed upon birth control by <person reg="Comstock, Anthony">Anthony
                    Comstock</person> and a <org reg="New York Society for the Suppression of Vice"
                    >“reform” group</org> which induced a timid and over-awed <org
                    reg="United States Congress">Congress</org> to pass the overreaching <name
                    reg="Comstock Act of 1873">law</name>. That famous, or rather infamous,
                law--Section 211 of the U.S. Penal Code--and supplementary laws, prevented the
                dissemination of birth control information even by a physician, and barred anything
                pertaining to the subject from the mails. Nor could supplies be sent by express or
                other common carrier. Other sections were even more rigid, forbidding even the
                permission of any article for preventing conception--<emph rend="underline">and
                    there were no exceptions</emph>. While the original bill carried the exemption,
                    “<q who="COMAC">except on a prescription of a physician in good standing, given
                    in good faith</q>,” these words were omitted from the bill which firmly became
                law. Violations of the law were punishable by fines of from $2,000 to $5,000, or
                imprisonment for five years, or both.</p>
            <p>The laws made no distribution between contraception and abortion, though they are as
                far apart as the poles. Birth control is the conscious control of the birth rate by
                scientific means which prevent conception. It is not interference with life after
                conception has taken place.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">LAWS SET BACK THE CLOCK OF PROGRESS</head>
            <p>And the law had teeth. Many supplies and much literature were confiscated and
                destroyed. Even if no outstanding, distinguished physicians were actually prosecuted
                for violating the law, it was mainly because they would not publicly do so. They
                were intimidated and kept in fear of persecution.</p>
            <p>With Federal and State laws is conflict and confusion, a physician might legally
                dispense information under State statutes, but it was illegal for him under a
                literal interpretation of the Federal statutes, to send or to receive the necessary
                technical information and medical supplies. The law hampered the progressive
                physician, eager to adopt preventive health measures, and willing to advise his
                patients privately, but reluctant to take a similar stand in public practice because
                of confusion as to his legal rights in this field of medicine.</p>
            <p>The Comstock laws not only thwarted efforts to protect mothers from excessive child
                bearing and children from being born sick, weak, unwanted and unprovided for, but
                were responsible, directly or indirectly, for the deaths of a million mothers during
                the six decades they were enforced. These deaths occurred needlessly among mothers
                who were the victims of abortions or of bearing children when in unfit physical
                condition.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">MATERNAL AND INFANT MORTALITY</head>
            <p>Even today the situation is still appalling <add>in</add> some respects. Out of every
                few mothers who dies in America, one death is due to abortion. Out of approximately
                15,000 mothers <add>each year</add> who die from causes due to child-birth or
                pregnancy, a large percentage are “poor maternity risks” from the start.</p>
            <p>As for infant mortality, statistics of the <org reg="United States Children's Bureau"
                    >U.S. Children’s Bureau</org> tell their elegant, but unheeded story. When the
                interval between births is too shorts, death rates climb. Babies born one year apart
                die at the rate of 147 per thousand; babies born two years apart have a mortality
                rate of only <unclear>96</unclear> per thousand. These figures are a challenge to
                the nation.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">THE WINNING FIGHT</head>
            <p>For many years efforts to induce Congress to amend the Comstock laws were unavailing,
                but sentiment for changing them increased rapidly from 1880 onward. In the campaign
                undertaken by the <org>National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth
                    Control</org>, Inc., nearly 1,000 organizations with approximately twenty
                millions of members eventually endorsed the lifting of Federal restrictions, and
                $25,000 individual endorsements were filed with Congress. Few causes have won the
                adherence of such a vast number of active supporters.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">VICTORY FOR PUBLIC OPINION</head>
            <p>The decision which finally freed contraception from its Federal fetters represents
                basically the triumph of facts and public opinion over archaic law, ignorance and
                prejudice. Through a liberal Court this informed and potent public opinion finally
                found expression. One of the <person reg="Hand, Billings Learned">Justices</person>,
                in a separate opinion, observed: “<q who="HANLE">A statue stands until public
                    opinion gets enough momentum to change it, which may be long after a majority
                    would repeal it, if a poll were taken</q>.”</p>
            <p>The National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control had proceeded along
                both legislative and legal lines of battle. As confiscations of books and materials
                increased, a particularly strong test case was instituted by the Committee in behalf
                of <person reg="Stone, Hannah Mayer">Dr. Hannah M. Stone</person>, Medical Director
                of the <org>Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau</org> in <place
                    reg="New York City, NY">New York</place>. The <org
                    reg="United States Government">U.S. Government</org>, through the <org
                    reg="United States Bureau of Customs">Bureau of Customs</org>, had seized a
                package containing 120 pessaries to prevent conception, which the government alleged
                had been imported contrary to Section 305 (a) of the <name type="law">Tariff Act of
                    1930</name>, which originated from the Comstock law of 1873. These pessaries had
                been sent to Dr. Stone by a physician in <place>Japan</place> for trial in her
                practice, and she had been asked to give an opinion as to their usefulness for
                contraceptive purposes. Dr. Stone testified at the trail that she prescribed the use
                of pessaries in cases where it would not be desirable for a patient to undertake a
                pregnancy.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">EMANCIPATION DECISION</head>
            <p>It was in this case, on November 30, 1936, that birth control under medical direction
                was finally recognized as legal. The <org>United States Circuit Court of Appeals for
                    the Second Circuit</org> rendered a decision that the Federal obscenity laws do
                not apply to the legitimate activities of physicians, and that they may prescribe
                contraceptives in the interests of the health and general well being of their
                patients. That enlightened decision brought birth control tot he goal it had long
                sought through legislation and was an emancipation proclamation to the motherhood of
                America. With its objective won, the National Committee disbanded.</p>
            <p>With sharp, surgical precision the historic decision cut through the tangled
                confusion of Federal laws. It removed the shadow of illegality and the stigma of
                obscenity and brought the Federal statutes into conformity with most State statutes.
                In the few States remaining where outmoded statutes still await reinterpretation by
                the Courts, the decision is a beacon-light for other Courts to follow.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">A BILL OF RIGHTS</head>
            <p>The decision constitutes a Bill of Rights for the medical profession in the field of
                contraception, <gap reason="illegible" extent="several words"/>. The nation owes a
                debt of gratitude to the wisdom, the logic and the humanity of <person
                    reg="Hand, Augustus Noble">Justices Augustus N. Hand</person>, <person
                    reg="Swan, Thomas Walter">Thomas W. Swan</person>, and Learned Hand, whose
                far-seeing interpretation of the Federal statues brought to an end the 53-year reign
                of muddle and tyranny inaugurated by the Comstock legislation.</p>
            <p>It was on January 6, 1938, that <person reg="Moscowitz, Grover C.">Judge Grover
                    Moscowitz</person>, of the <org>United States District Court, Southern District
                    of New York</org>, in a very lucid decision, held that contraceptives imported
                for a lawful purpose did not come within the restrictions of the statue.</p>
            <p>The government appealed the case, but Justice Moscowitz's decision was affirmed by
                the United States Circuit Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit, which held that
                physicians importing such articles, in order to use them for the health of their
                patients, were exempted by implication from the literal terms of the statute.</p>
            <p>The most significant passage of this decision read:</p>
            <p>“<q who="MOSGR">. . . . While we may assume that Section 305 (a) of the Tariff Act of
                    1930 exempts only such articles as the Act of 1873 exempted, yet we are <unclear
                        resp="MSPP">convinced</unclear> that this statue, as well as all the acts we
                    have referred to, embraced only such articles as Congress would have <unclear
                        resp="MSPP">denounced</unclear> as immoral if it had understood all the
                    conditions under which they were to be used. Its design, in our opinion, was not
                    to prevent the importation, sale, or carriage by mail of things which might
                    intelligently be employed by conscientious and competent physicians for the
                    purpose of saving life or promoting the well being of their patients</q>.”</p>
            <p><person reg="Cummings, Homer Stille">Homer S. Cummings</person>, Attorney General of
                the United States, announced that the government would rest its case and not carry
                it to the <org>United States Supreme Court</org>. Thus the decision of the Circuit
                Court of Appeals became the law of the land, and the <org
                    reg="United States Treasury Department">Treasury Department</org> thereupon
                issued instructions to Customs authorities to admit contraceptive supplies addressed
                to physicians.</p>
            <p>For the ultimate victory we are also deeply grateful to <person
                    reg="Ernst, Morris Leopold">Morris L. Ernst</person>, counsel for Dr. Stone and
                the Committee, for his gallant and successful fight, as well as for his constant
                championship of civil liberties and clarification of obstructive laws.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">PHYSICIANS APPROVE</head>
            <p>Medical, as well as legal sanction for birth control at last exists. Less than a year
                after the legal decision, and following a long investigation by a special committee,
                the <org>American Medical Association</org>, in June 1937, approved birth control as
                an essential part of medical practice and education, and urged the necessity for
                informing physicians of their legal rights in relation to the use of contraceptives.
                A resolution declared that</p>
            <p>“. . .<q who="AMA"> it seems fair. . . to assume that the State Courts, if called
                    upon to construe the statues relating to the dissemination of contraceptive
                    information, will adopt lines of reasoning similar to these followed in the case
                    cited (<name type="legal case"
                        reg="United States vs. One Package of Japanese Contraceptives">U.S. vs. One
                        Package</name>) and in other cases decided by the United States Courts,
                    leaving physicians free to give information concerning contraception when
                    required to meet the medical needs of patients</q>.”</p>
            <p>This reference was to the Dr. Hannah Stone case. The public may now look to the
                Association to carry on research in contraception and to promote the teaching of
                birth control in medical schools.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">STATE STATUES</head>
            <p>Birth control, therefore, from a national standpoint is at last <emph
                    rend="underline">freed</emph>. The Federal statutes are no longer a stumbling
                block.</p>
            <p>However, there is need for clarification of State statutes in the few States where
                the literal wording of the law may still be involved unless public opinion makes the
                force felt.</p>
            <p>In the past some States followed the land of the Federal Government in enacting and
                clinging to obsolete statutes restricting the dissemination of contraceptive
                knowledge, but, fortunately, these statutes contain exemptions of many types and
                degrees as regards the medical profession. There are 24 States with statutes of this
                character. Some of them are confused, outmoded conglomerations of provisions aimed
                indiscriminately at birth control, obscenity, indecency, abortion, miscarriage,
                lotteries, nostrums, drops, pills, tinctures, compounds, poisons, drugs,
                prophylastics, lust, crime, and “sex exciting devices.”</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">DAGUERREOTYPE DAYS</head>
            <p>Some of the States are still in the daguerreotype days in the phrasing of their laws
                about birth control. Under the <place>Indiana</place> and <place>Wyoming</place>
                State laws “daguerreotypes and stereoscopes” are literally verboten as media of
                contraceptive information! Almost as quaint phraseology meets the eye in some of the
                other State statutes, and no rhyme or reason is discernable in their provisions.
                Nevertheless, these statutory relics of the past do not impose any obstacles for the
                medical profession. The situation may be summed up as follows:</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">THE SITUATION TODAY</head>
            <p>There are 21 States, as well as the <place>District of Columbia</place> and the
                Territories of <place>Alaska</place>, <place>Hawaii</place>, <place>Philippine
                    Islands</place> and the <place>Virgin Islands</place>, where the prevention of
                conception has not been classed with obscenity. A modern law permitting
                contraception was recently enacted in <place>Puerto Rico</place>. The 21 States
                whose codes do not refer to contraception comprise <place>Alabama</place>,
                    <place>Arkansas</place>, <place>Florida</place>, <place>Georgia</place>,
                    <place>Illinois</place>, <place>Kentucky</place>, <place>Maryland</place>,
                    <place>New Hampshire</place>, <place>New Mexico</place>, <place>North
                    Carolina</place>, <place>North Dakota</place>, <place>Oklahoma</place>,
                    <place>Rhode Island</place>, <place>South Dakota</place>,
                    <place>Tennessee</place>, <place>Texas</place>, <place>Utah</place>,
                    <place>Vermont</place>, <place>Virginia</place>, and <place>West
                    Virginia</place>.</p>
            <p>Ten States have limited laws, but physicians are exempt and drug stores are permitted
                to sell contraceptives. These are <place>Colorado</place>, <place>Indiana</place>,
                    <place>Ohio</place>, <place>Delaware</place>, <place>Iowa</place>,
                    <place>Montana</place>, <place>Wisconsin</place>, <place>Wyoming</place>,
                    <place>Oregon</place> and <place>Idaho</place>.</p>
            <p>Three States permit physicians to prescribe contraceptives, but druggists are not
                mentioned. They are <place>New York</place>, <place>Nevada</place> and
                    <place>Minnesota</place>. The New York law has held by a decision of the
                    <org>Court of Appeals</org> in 1918 to be “<q who="NYCA">broad enough to protect
                    the physician who in goo faith gives such help or advice to a married person to
                    cure or prevent disease... the protection thus afforded the physician would also
                    extend to the druggist, or vendor, acting upon the physicians’ prescription or
                    order</q>.” A similar ruling exists in Minnesota.</p>
            <p>Six States have statutes aimed at <del>against</del> advertising and the
                indiscriminate distribution of material. They are <place>Arizona</place>,
                    <place>California</place>, <place>Louisiana</place>, <place>Maine</place>,
                    <place>Michigan</place> and <place>Washington</place>.</p>
            <p>One State, <place>New Jersey</place>, allows the dissemination of contraceptive
                information “for just causes.”</p>
            <p>One State, <place>Kansas</place>, exempts medical text books, and by implication the
                medical profession.</p>
            <p>Three States, <place>Missouri</place>, <place>Nebraska</place> and
                    <place>Pennsylvania</place>, exempt chartered medical schools and medical text
                books, and by implication, the medical profession.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">THREE BACKWARD STATES</head>
            <p>There remains then, three States. In one, <place>Connecticut</place>, the use of
                contraceptive is forbidden. This statute, incapable of enforcement, has long
                subjected Connecticut to ridicule, but this blue-law relic has remained as part of
                the code, despite earnest and repeated efforts by the enlightened citizens of
                Connecticut to amend it. Nevertheless, seven birth control clinics are in operation
                in Connecticut.</p>
            <p><place>Mississippi</place> makes no exceptions in its statues, which ban even oral
                information.</p>
            <p>In <place>Massachusetts</place> the State laws have been challenged. While they make
                no exception of any kind, eight birth control clinics directed and sponsored by
                outstanding medical and civic lenders of the State have served the public for many
                years without legal hindrance. Meanwhile, repeated efforts have been made to
                modernize the Massachusetts laws, but without success. In the summer of 1937 three
                Massachusetts birth control clinics were raided. Doctors, nurses, social workers and
                officials were arrested, convicted and fined. Their cases are being appealed to the
                higher courts and pending decision all clinics in the State have closed.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">LEGAL WITCHERY</head>
            <p>Contraceptives are forbidden in Massachusetts under a blue law entitled “<name
                    type="law">Crimes Against Chastity, Decency, and Good Order</name>.” Commenting
                on the closing of the clinics in <place reg="Salem, Massachusetts">Salem</place>,
                Dr. Hannah Stone said: “<q who="STOHA">The day of witch hunting has passed. It is no
                    more possible to stem the flow of contraceptive knowledge then to stem the tides
                    of the ocean that wash the shore of Massachusetts</q>.”</p>
            <p>The reactionary step taken in Massachusetts is a warning to all who cherish liberty,
                that while prohibitory laws of the type existing in that State remain on the statue
                books, they constitute a continuing threat to the freedom of the medical profession
                and the welfare of mothers. Therefore the outcome of the appeals will be awaited
                with interest throughout the country.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">PROGRESSIVE STATE LEGISLATION</head>
            <p>Oregon holds the distinction of being the first State to divorce contraception from
                abortion and obscenity. It is the first State also to attempt to safeguard its
                citizens by setting up a control of contraceptive products and advertising under its
                    <org reg="Oregon State Board of Pharmacy">State Board of Pharmacy</org>. To
                North Carolina goes the honor of being the first State to provide birth control
                clinical service through its <org
                    reg="North Carolina Department of Health and Human Services">State Department of
                    Health</org> and county physicians. As above stated, <place>Puerto Rico</place>
                has also enacted progressive birth control legislation.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">NEXT STEPS</head>
            <p>What lies ahead? It is not enough merely to <emph rend="underline">establish</emph>
                the rights of physicians through the Courts. This ethical gain must be used. We have
                taken a great step forward, but other hurdles must be cleared. With birth control
                legalized by national statutes, all States should now completely catch up with
                public sentiment, judicial ___interpretation and the demand for contraceptive
                services by clarifying and modernizing the laws. All State laws should be positive,
                not vague or negative. They should clearly and affirmatively declare and assure the
                right of medical birth control, not merely fail to forbid it, or limit it.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">A NEW CALL TO ARMS</head>
            <p>Therefore I ask all who have so loyally made our legal and medical victories
                possible, to join efforts with us again in the most important objective--the
                inclusion of birth control service in local, State and national health programs. In
                this way only can those mothers most desperately in need of this information secure
                it through reliable, medical channels. Help make it known to hospitals, relief
                agencies, philanthropic and public health officials, that the Federal decision has
                freed their hands. Challenge all plans for the reduction of maternal and infant
                mortality that ignore the basic need for including contraceptive service in such
                programs.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">WE MUST MOVE FAST</head>
            <p>We must move fast, for women and children are dying needlessly. Individual and group
                effort can point the way, and can do immeasurable good. But those guiding our
                programs for relief, for the reduction of maternal and infant mortality, and for the
                control of syphilis, must recognize that the provision of scientific birth control
                information is essential to the success of all such programs. Next steps in making
                contraceptive information and service actually as well as legally available to the
                mothers of America call for modernization of State laws and the incorporation of
                birth control into medical practice, preventive medicine and public health
                administration everywhere.</p>
            <p>Today there are more than 380 birth control centers in the country. Ten times that
                number are required to meet the need. There are 7,000 hospitals and 10,000 other
                agencies where medical aid is sought by mothers too poor to pay the fees of private
                physicians which ought to provide contraceptive service. And medical-charging
                service ought to bring birth control to thousands of forgotten women on farms and in
                isolated districts remote from medical centers. Their plight and pleas are among the
                most poignant of all.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <note><p>*Footnote:</p><p>“<title>Federal and State laws Pertaining to Birth
                        Control</title>,” a pamphlet containing the complete State and Federal
                    statutes may be obtained from the Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau. 17
                    West 16th Street, New York City. [two words illegible].</p></note>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
