<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2009/07/27 LL</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2009/08/06 CH proof and correct</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-10 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1932-02-00">Feb. 1932</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Birth Control</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp101855</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Church and Society</title> Feb. 1932 [Vol 4, No 5]: 1-2. </bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title>, LCM 128:0414.</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="TAUFR">Taussig, Frederick J.</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>For an earlier version possibly drafted by Florence Rose, see LCM 8:721.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="definitions of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits and risks"/>
        <index level1="child spacing"/>
        <index level1="family size" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="infant mortality rate"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="in marriages"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Birth Control</head>
        <byline>By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></byline>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">WHAT is Birth Control?</head>
            <p> It is the conscious control of the birth rate by means that prevent conception.</p>
            <p>Emphasis is placed on the word <emph rend="italics">prevent</emph>. In preventing
                conception, one does not destroy life; one does not interfere with the development
                of life; no life has been conceived to destroy. The ovum, when it is not fertilized,
                passes out of the body regularly, as it does when one remains unmarried or lives a
                continent or celibate life.</p>
            <p>Emphasis is also placed on the word <emph rend="italics">control</emph>. In
                controlling the birth rate or the size of the family, it does not mean one must
                    <emph rend="italics">limit</emph> births to any given number. We control our
                motors; we control the heat from the furnace; we control our time, our appetites,
                our resources, our lives. Birth Control applied to the family does not mean to limit
                the number of children to a one or two-child family system. It means to have the
                number of children consistent with and in consideration of <lb/>(1) The mother’s
                health <lb/>(2) The child’s possible heritage <lb/>(3) The father’s earning capacity
                <lb/>(4) Standards of living desirable to maintain</p>
            <p>The <emph rend="italics">conscious</emph> control of the powers of fertility would
                awaken men and women to the responsibility of Parenthood. That <emph rend="italics"
                    >consciousness</emph> is a growing and awakening force now developing in the
                human race is generally conceded. When consciousness is applied to the process of
                generation there will be fewer children born as the result of a reckless abandon to
                the hour; fewer children brought into the world unwanted and unloved; more children
                planned for and conceived in love; more born of the mother’s conscious desire; and
                more given the heritage of healthy bodies and sound minds.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">WHY do we need Birth Control?</head>
            <p>Because the practice is both a health and an economic necessity.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">1. HEALTH</head>
            <p>Women suffering from tuberculosis, heart disease, kidney disease and other ailments
                are known to die as the results of pregnancy. There were over 20,000 mothers who
                died last year besides the large number of mothers who are “always ailing, never
                failing.” Many of these mothers died needlessly from diseases such as those
                mentioned, and from abortions, and would have been alive today had contraceptive
                instruction been given them in time. The number of deaths due to abortions each year
                are a blot on our civilization and a disgrace to any country. I refer you to Dr.
                    <person rend="Taussig, Frederick J.">F. J. Taussig</person>’s illuminating
                treatise on this subject, “<title type="book">Abortion in Relation to Fetal and
                    Maternal Welfare.</title>” This article was prepared by the <org>Committee on
                    Prenatal and Maternal Care </org>for the <name type="conference"
                    reg="White House Conference on Child Health and Protection">White House
                    Conference</name>. Dr. Taussig makes the following statements in his summary:
                    <lb/>“<q who="TAUFR">The increase in the number of abortions is noticed
                    primarily among married women who have three or more children.</q>” and <lb/>“<q
                    who="TAUFR">The maternal death loss from abortion in the <place
                        reg="United States">United States</place> has been estimated as 15,000
                    annually. Deaths from puerperal sepsis following abortions are relatively seven
                    times as frequent as those from puerperal sepsis after childbirth</q>.”</p>
            <p>While the practice of birth control is a humane expedient for <emph rend="italics"
                    >maternal health</emph>, it is even more urgent as a means of curtailing the
                    <emph rend="italics">infant death rate</emph>. We know that this question of
                infant mortality has three very vital factors: the first factor is the father’s
                wage. As it goes up, a larger number in the family survive, and if it goes down, a
                larger number of the children die. Second is the spacing of the number of children
                in a family. If children are born with three or four years between each birth, their
                chances are better because the mother has had an opportunity to recuperate and
                rebuild her health. The family income has been stretched out over the intervening
                period of years to meet the coming infant’s needs. Statistics from our <org
                    reg="United States Children's Bureau">Children’s Bureau</org> clearly show that
                the second child has a better chance to live than the 5th and the 5th a better
                chance than the 12th certainly. Sixty per cent of all the 12th children born in this
                world are doomed to die before they reach their first birthday. Thus, about 6 out of
                every 10 children who are 12th in the family are doomed to death before they breathe
                their first breath. How much better to have a declining birth rate with a greater
                decline in the death rate–-fewer children born but more children to live to grow up
                decently and develop their God-given powers. What a waste of mother power and child
                life now goes on which might be put into the constructive forces of this world.</p>
            <p>A government which allows men and women to become parents whose records show
                insanity, feeble-mindedness, epilepsy, syphilis, pauperism, idiocy and various other
                transmissible defects, cannot be said to consider the welfare or happiness of the
                country or of the next generation. Billions are now spent on charities, both public
                and private, in the U.S.A. The normal and intelligent citizens are being taxed and
                drained and bled to keep alive an increasing horde of human beings who never should
                have been born into a civilized society.</p>
            <p>Birth Control should be practiced in early marriages, especially when the young
                people are in the adolescent period. Parenthood should be deferred until the girl is
                at least 23 and the boy at least 25 and they have had a chance to gain their own
                full development.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">2. ECONOMIC NECESSITY</head>
            <p>The father’s economic responsibilities should be given full consideration in planning
                a family and birth control comes as a blessing to help young fathers get on their
                feet financially, and keep their earning power ahead of the needs of a growing
                family.</p>
            <p>Birth Control should be practiced for a year or two years after marriage as a means
                of adjustment. Greater stress should be placed on the importance of giving marriage
                a chance to develop and grow into the ideal relation many of us believe possible.
                The young romantic bride who returns from her honeymoon in a pregnant condition
                never has a chance to develop the woman in her, and both are deprived of the
                opportunity to cement the love bond, to play, grow and expand together in mutual
                affection and love. Premature parenthood has made them skip over a period of
                development at a time and in circumstances when adjustment is essential. Two years
                to play, grow, develop together, will make for more permanent marriages, happier
                homes and larger families.</p>
            <p>There are other questions–-WHO? WHERE? and HOW?--which could be answered, and are
                given in full in the literature available on the subject.</p>
            <p>Birth Control is not a panacea for all the social and economic ills in the world but
                at least it is the most important immediate help which can be applied as a solution
                to the present problems of millions of men and women <emph rend="italics"
                    >here</emph> and <emph rend="italics">now</emph>. Those who are practicing birth
                control because they are fully conscious of the moral responsibility of bringing a
                child into the world are units in the building and reconstruction of the new world.
                They are laying the foundation for the unfolding of a vast experiment in race
                building never before known in the history of mankind. </p>
        </div>

    </docBody>
</doc>
