<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "file:/S:/TRANSCRIPTIONS/XML%20Drafts/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed draft article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2009/07/27 LL</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1932-01-25">25 Jan. 1932</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>
                <supplied resp="MSPP">Birth Control</supplied>
            </titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp101853</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Papers</title>, Library of
                Congress</bibl>
            <bibl>LCM 128:410</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="PROV">Proverb</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>For other versions of this article see LCM 045:37, 048:167, 128:414,
            417, 136:348, <emph rend="underline">MSM</emph> S71:390, 1000.
            Interlineations and deletions by Sanger.</p>
        <index level1="eugenics"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="history of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <p> I cannot express too firmly my conviction that this is the way to
            national suicide, politically, physically, and economically. The
            vote of the moron has the same numerical significance as that of the
            college graduate. A nation drawing the largest portion of its
            population from the strata living at subsistence level cannot
            produce the <add><del>citizens with</del> the</add> stamina,
            initiative, and vigorous health needed<del> to maintain its
                standing</del> to <add>constantly</add> forge forward. <del>A
                nation drawing more than half of its <add>future</add>
                population from</del></p>
        <p>The further contention is made, etc.</p>
        <p>I am frequently asked if I am not proud of the great progress made in
            this movement during my lifetime. I am reminded that there has been
            a general breakdown of secrecy and ignorance, not only on the
            subject of birth control, but relating to the entire field of sex
            education. Birth Control <del>is recognized today as</del> has won
            legal and medical recognition as an important branch of preventive
            public health procedure. <del>Magazines</del></p>
        <p>A new literature has been created. Thousands of pamphlets and books
            have been written on this subject since 1916. This literature has
            been made available both to the public and to the medical
            profession.</p>
        <p>Magazines <add>and publications</add> outstanding for their
            conservatism are today frankly dealing with the social implications
            of birth control, <del>although</del> with appropriate editorial
            implications.</p>
        <p>National public polls taken among all classes of population reveal
            from that 80% desire extension of birth control service under
            medical guidance. The same polls reveal <del>that</del> the public
            mind is no-longer confused, that and understands that birth control
            is <del>
                <unclear>really exactly the reverence of abortion</unclear>
            </del> not abortion.</p>
        <p>Nearly 400 birth control clinics have been established under <gap
                extent="page(s)"/>And from all their letters and from the
            personal problems and tragedies, which strangers in increasing
            numbers constantly laid before me, came a clear-cut understanding of
            the part birth control could and must eventually play in any
            constructive program of race-building.</p>
        <p>We went forward therefrom from the beginning with a broad program. We
            stressed the importance of parents refraining entirely from bringing
            children into the world if they themselves suffered from insanity,
            feeble-mindedness or a venereal disease. We called upon parents who,
            though normal themselves, had already brought mental defectives into
            the world, to avoid the risk of ruining another life, much as they
            might desire a normal child. <del>We pleaded for the right of every
                woman, rich or poor, sick or well, to obtain the necessary kn
            </del></p>
        <p>We urged the necessity of giving contraceptive information to women
            suffering from tuberculosis, heart or kidney disease, to
                <del>cut</del>
            <add>lower</add> the death rates from these diseases which are
            seriously complicated by pregnancy.</p>
        <p>We pleaded for the right of every woman, rich or poor, sick or well,
            to obtain the necessary <del>information</del> knowledge to space
            the births of her children; <add>we</add> pointed <del>to</del>
            <add>out</add> the statistical evidence that children born <add>one
                year apart die at the rate of 147 per thousand; born two years
                apart the death rate falls to 96 per thousand; while children
                    born<del> three years apart to 86 per thousand</del></add>
            three years apart have the best chance of survival, and give
                <del>the</del> children already born <add>in the family</add>
            their opportunity for the mother’s undivided attention during the
            first critical years of life.</p>
        <p>We emphasized the importance of the family income in determining
            family size, and pointed out that a father with an earning capacity
            to take care of only two children should not have ten or twelve to
            become a burden upon <del>the family and</del> the community. And
            lastly, we made a plea for marriage itself. We urged that young
            married people be given knowledge to enable them to make a fine
            thing of marriage by having at least a year or two for adjustment to
            each other, physically, <add>mentally,</add> and spiritually, before
            assuming the responsibilities of parenthood.</p>
        <p>The American public listened, and approved. To them it was “just
            plain common-sense”. The masses, especially the working people, were
            with me, etc. etc.</p>
        <p>In India I heard the proverb: “<q who="PROV">Knowledge is to know
                what to do, skill is knowing how to do it, virtue is in doing
                it</q>”. We have in birth control a new instrument for freedom.
            It makes possible a larger life, the creation of a finer race.
                <del>We have the knowledge and the skill to apply that
                knowledge</del>. <add>We have this knowledge. <del>We
                    possess</del> We have developed skill to apply our
                knowledge.</add> When shall we as a nation <del>pass the virtue
                of utilizing the knowledge we have</del> USE our knowledge and
            our skill, <add>and acquire virtue?</add>
        </p>


    </docBody>
</doc>
