<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2007-08-30 EK Initial tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007/09/04 CH Corrections</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/03/05 EK cleanup</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1934-09-07 ">Sept. 7, 1934</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Birth Control</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp101856</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>State Government</title>Sept. 7, 1934</bibl>
            <bibl>LCM 128:421</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        
        <respStmt>
            <resp>
                <name id="CRAFR">Crane Frederick E. Crane</name>
                <name id="INGWI">Inge, William Ralph</name>
                <name id="SWATH">Swan, Thomas W.</name>                
                <name id="TAUFR">Taussig, Frederick J.</name>                          
                <name id="USCON">United States Congress</name>        
       </resp>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p> For draft version see LCM 42:111.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Comstock act"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="State"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Postal Code and Regulations"/>
        <index level1="physicians"/>
        <index level1="abortion" level2="birth control vs."/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="definitions of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="socioeconomic benefits of"/>
        <index level1="poverty" level2="family size and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Tariff Act"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Postal Codes and Regulations"/>
        <index level1="quackery"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="maternal"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="research"/>
        <index level1="conferences" level2="White House Conference on Welfare Needs" level3="1933"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="legal cases" level3="U.S. V. One Book Entitled 'Contraception'"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="legal cases" level3="U.S. V. OneOne Package of Japanese contraceptives'"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="diaphragm"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues"/>
        <index level1="Congressional bills" level2="S.600" level3="1934"/>
        <index level1="Congressional bills" level2="H.R. 5978" level3="1934"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="doctors-only bills"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="New York "/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="legal cases" level3="Youngs Rubber Corp. vs. C.I. Lee and Co'"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>BIRTH CONTROL.</head>
        <byline>By Margaret Sanger</byline>
        <div type="section">
            <p>How many people know that over sixty years ago Congress passed a law making it a
                penitentiary offense for anyone (even a doctor) to send or received through the
                United States Mails even the <emph rend="italics">address</emph> of a physician or a
                clinic where information concerning ways to prevent conception could be obtained?
                And conversely, how many people know that it is entirely legal for them to obtain
                contraceptive information under existing state statutes, subject to certain
                limitations, in every state of the Union except <place>Mississippi</place>?</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">
                <emph rend="bold">An unjustified reputation</emph>
            </head>
            <p>For we have the extraordinary situation of a federal law in effect nullifying the
                laws of forty-seven states. While a physician may legally dispense information under
                the statutes of his state, it is illegal for him to received through the mail the
                necessary technical information and medical supplies. The federal attitude toward
                contraceptive information has given rise to misunderstanding and confusion on this
                subject, particularly as to the difference between birth control and abortion; it
                has enshrouded in secrecy a subject important to the health and welfare of may
                persons; it has deterred legislatures from action on a subject made unsavory by its
                legal association with obscenity; it has hampered and confused the medical
                profession, anxious to give advice to their patients where desirable for health
                reasons, but fearful of jeopardizing their professional standing through ignorance
                of the law.</p>
            <p>The federal obscenity law, passed in 1873, classes the prevention of conception with
                abortion, pornography, filth, and indecency. Two generations have passed since that
                law was enacted; women have gained suffrage; and social hygiene is part of our
                educational program. It was as a challenge to this law that the birth control
                movement arose and the <org>National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth
                    Control</org> was organized.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">
                <emph rend="bold">A question of health and income</emph>
            </head>
            <p>First, let me emphasize that birth control is not abortion. Birth control is the
                conscious control of the birth rate by means that prevent conception. The essential
                facts are: First, it is the prevention of conception, not the interruption of
                pregnancy after conception has taken place. In preventing conception one does not
                destroy life as no life has been conceived to destroy. Second, it is control, not
                necessarily limitation. To control the birth rate is to control the size of the
                family and the spacing of births with some regard to the mother’s health, to the
                inheritance both husband and wife are able or likely to pass on to their children
                already born, to the father’s earning power, and to the standards of living the
                parents wish to maintain.</p>
            <p>Ignorance of the methods of birth control has become an acknowledged factor in infant
                and maternal mortality, unemployment, child labor, slum conditions, overcrowding,
                illiteracy, and feeble-mindedness. Relief authorities are alarmed by the rapid
                increase in population among the destitute families of the nation. The high birth
                rate among the unemployed adds to our relief burdens. Parents who cannot support two
                or three children are unable to obtain contraceptive information under our present
                federal laws. Thus more children are brought into the world without any adequate
                provision for their future and with the resultant probability of an added burden on
                society.</p>
            <p>The federal law, Section 211 of the Penal Code, was passed by <org
                    reg="United States Congress">Congress</org> in 1873 during the last hectic hours
                of a hurried and confused session of Congress. The chief object of the legislation,
                as revealed by a study of the official records, was to stamp our the widespread
                traffic -- particularly among the school children -- in pornographic literature. As
                a matter of legislative history, it appears beyond question that when these laws
                were first enacted the members of Congress had no inkling that they were legislating
                on the subject of birth control. the drastic restrictions and penalties surrounding
                the subject of contraception under Section 211 and additional statutes passed
                subsequently are briefly outlined.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">
                <emph rend="bold">Inflexible rules</emph>
            </head>
            <p>1. Section 211 of the <title>United States Penal Code</title> -- Prohibits sending
                by, or receiving from, the United States Mails information or supplies pertaining to
                the prevention of conception. <emph rend="italics">There are no
                exemptions</emph>.</p>
            <p>2. Section 245 of the <title>United States Penal Code</title> -- Also prohibits
                sending by, or receiving from, an express company or other common carrier
                information or supplies pertaining to the prevention of conception. <emph
                    rend="italics">There are no exemptions</emph>.</p>
            <p>3. Sections 311 and 312 affect the territories and districts of the United States and
                are even more rigid in their prohibition, as the forbid even the <emph
                    rend="italics">possession</emph> of any article intended for the prevention of
                conception. <emph rend="italics">There are no exemptions</emph>.</p>
            <p>4. Section 305 of the <title>Tariff Act</title> prohibits the importation of articles
                pertaining to the prevention of conception. <emph rend="italics">No
                    exemptions</emph>.</p>
            <p> The penalties for violation of these laws are of two kinds: a fine of $2,000 to
                $5,000; or imprisonment for five years. Either or both may be imposed.</p>
            <p>It should be noted that these federal laws make no exemption in their prohibitions
                for literature of a scientific character. Nor have they made an exception for the
                physician in his regular practise, nor for hospitals and clinics, nor for patients
                of these hospitals and clinics, nor for the general and proper distribution of
                medical supplies. These laws have been the means of suppressing properly authorized
                scientific literature on the subject of contraception, while encouraging a vast
                underground "bootleg traffic" of unscientific and frequently dangerous methods by
                commercial agencies exploiting the needs of women.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">
                <emph rend="bold">Bonded or bootlegged?</emph>
            </head>
            <p>Over 20,000 women die yearly in the <place>United States</place> from causes due to
                child-bearing. the number of deaths due to abortions each year is a blot on our
                civilization and a disgrace to any country. Dr. <person reg="Taussig, Frederick J."
                    >F. J. Taussig</person>, in his article “<title type="article">Abortion in
                    Relation to Fetal and Maternal Welfare</title>” prepared for the <org>Committee
                    on Prenatal and Maternal Care</org> for the <org
                    reg="White House Conference on Welfare Needs (1933)">White House
                    Conference"</org> estimated the death loss from abortion as 15,000 annually and
                made the following significant statement in his summary: “<q who="TAUFR">The
                    increase in the number of abortions is noticed <emph rend="italics">primarily
                        among married women who have three or more children</emph></q>.”</p>
            <p>This brings us squarely to the point. Women will limit their families in <emph
                    rend="italics">some way</emph>. Are they to be granted the right to reliable
                medical information from responsible sources, or must they continue to pay in this
                toll of broken and wasted lives for a legislative blunder in 1873.</p>
            <p>The federal laws interfere with the importation of articles and with the transmission
                to this country of the results of the researches which are undertaken in other
                countries. Such materials and data would be of great assistance to the medical
                profession of this country in the proper functioning of their profession. Despite
                the enlightening decision of Judge <person reg="Woolsey, John Munro">Woolsey
                </person>in the case of <person reg="Stopes, Marie">Marie Stopes</person>’ book
                    “<title>Contraception</title>” in 1932, that there is nothing in Section 305 to
                prevent contraceptive information from coming into this country, the <org
                    reg="United States Customs">Customs Authorities</org> continue to prevent the
                importation of contraceptive materials. We are in constant receipt of communications
                from physicians frustrated in their attempts to secure materials from abroad, and at
                the present time a case is pending which deals with a shipment from Japan that has
                been denied entry to this country. This was sent by a Japanese physician to Dr.
                    <person reg="Stone, Hannah Mayer">Hannah M. Stone</person>, Medical Director of
                the <org>Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau</org>. The contraceptives in
                question represent a new departure from the present forms of contraceptives. If
                research proved them practical for American women, the cost would be reduced to an
                insignificant item and protection would be possible for countless women who cannot
                afford it at the present time.</p>
            <p>In spite of the fact that under varying limitations the laws of forty-seven states
                permit physicians to give contraceptive information -- as can be seen from the table
                on page 191 -- and in spite of the fact that there are in this country today 157
                legally operating birth control clinics distributed over twenty-nine states,
                medically established, medically directed, and organized solely for the purpose of
                giving contraceptive advice, yet it is illegal to send an inquiring mother the
                address of either physician or clinic where contraceptive information may be
                obtained, even through she be poverty stricken or diseased.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">
                <emph rend="bold">Exemptions sought</emph>
            </head>
            <p>The essential object of the birth control legislation recently before Congress is to
                exempt duly licensed physicians, hospitals, and clinics from the restrictions of the
                present laws. The inference has been, and is, constantly made that this bill would
                open the mails and common carriers to pornographic and obscene literature. Such
                statements wilfully misrepresent what this bill specifically intends to do. the bill
                leaves the law exactly as it is except that the subject of prevention of conception
                is taken from it and placed in the hands of the medical profession where it
                rightfully belongs. There is nothing in this legislation which forces the use of
                conception upon any individual or group who may object to is, but we do ask the
                members of Congress to give the millions of mothers who desire it, the right to have
                proper scientific information through the proper channels and from qualified medical
                persons. At the second session of the Seventy-third Congress bills <title type="law"
                    >"S.600"</title>
                <title type="law">"H.R. 5978"</title> were introduced by Senator <person
                    reg="Hastings, Daniel O.">Daniel O. Hastings</person> of <place>Delaware</place>
                and Congressman <person reg="Pierce, Walter M.">Walter M. Pierce</person> of
                    <place>Oregon</place> to amend <title type="law">Sections 211, 245, and
                    312</title> of the <title rend="United States Criminal Code">Criminal
                    Code</title>, above quoted, by adding the following paragraph to each
                section:</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">
                <emph rend="bold">Amendment</emph>
            </head>
            <q who="USCON">" <p>The provisions of this section shall not be construed to apply to
                    any book or information relating to the prevention of conception, or article,
                    instrument, substance, drug, medicine, or thing designed, adapted, or intended
                    for the prevention of conception, for use</p>
                <p>(1) by any physician legally licensed to practise medicine in any state,
                    territory, or the <place reg="Washington, D.C.">District of Columbia</place>, or
                    by his direction or prescription;</p>
                <p>(2) by any medical college legally chartered under the laws of any state,
                    territory, or the District of Columbia;</p>
                <p>(3) by any druggist in his legitimate prescription business; or</p>
                <p>(4) by any hospital or clinic licensed in any state territory, or the District of
                    Columbia.</p>"</q>
            <p>The passage of this legislation would automatically raise the ban which now prevents
                thousands of hospitals and public health agencies from giving this service in
                conjunction with their post-natal and pre-natal maternal care. It would enable
                relief agencies to ease the burden of millions of families of the unemployed by
                referring the mothers to responsible medical sources. </p>
            <p>The claim is frequently made that with the unquestioned change in public sentiment
                during the past twenty years, birth control information is now accessible to all
                classes, inasmuch as the present laws are not enforced against physicians. Few
                assumptions are more erroneous. In effect, today we have class legislation on the
                subject of birth control. Those financially able to consult a private physician may
                obtain contraceptive</p>
            <p>advice -- the value of which is dependent upon the thoroughness with which the doctor
                has been able to inform himself on the subject. Until recently, practically no
                medical college included the subject of contraception in its curriculum.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">
                <emph rend="bold">Not for the poor</emph>
            </head>
            <p>One can readily understand that while a physician may choose to break the law in his
                private practise in order to obtain medical textbooks on the science of
                contraception for himself, and medical supplies for his patient, he may hesitate to
                involve institutions with which he is affiliated in a like disregard for the law.
                Consequently, it is usually more difficult for the need of this advice -- to obtain
                it, since they are largely dependent on public hospitals and health agencies for
                medical service.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">
                <emph rend="bold">Judicial progress</emph>
            </head>
            <p>Despite the tremendous change in public sentiment since 1914, the federal laws remain
                unchanged. All progress has been through judicial decisions or interpretations. In
                1918, Judge <person reg="Crane, Frederick E.">Crane</person> opened the first
                loophole in the legal wall surrounding the subject of contraception by ruling that
                in <place>New York State</place>, under Section 1145 of the <title>Penal
                    Code</title>, physicians might legally give such advice for “<q who="CRAFR">the
                    cure or prevention of disease</q>.” As a result of this decision the <org>Birth
                    Control Clinical Research Bureau</org> was established in 1923 in <place
                    reg="New York, NY">New York City</place>. The case histories of over 40,000
                women are on record there, forming a remarkable analysis of the physical, economic,
                and emotional lives of these women. Every stratum of society and every religion is
                proportionally represented.</p>
            <p>Another notable decision was handed down by Federal Judge <person reg="Swan, Thomas "
                    >Swan</person> in 1930 when he indicated that the word “illegal” may be read
                into the federal statute preceding the word “contraceptive.” Thus to prove a case
                against the sender of contraceptive material it is necessary for the government to
                show that the sender intended the material to be used for illegal purposes. The
                court further stated: “<q who="SWATH">The intention to prevent a proper medicinal
                    use of drugs or other articles merely because they are capable of illegal uses
                    is not lightly to be ascribed to Congress.</q>”</p>
            <p>In several cases dealing with indictments for mailing “obscene” matter under Section
                211 the courts have recognized that what is “obscene” may depend upon the character
                of the addressee, and the manner of distribution, although there is nothing in the
                statute, apart from the elasticity of the word itself, to support such a
                qualification.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">
                <emph rend="bold">Legalizing the accepted</emph>
            </head>
            <p>The proposed legislation in a large measure merely seeks to incorporate in the
                federal laws the exemptions that have already been judicially recognized.
                Congressional recognition is also necessary if the prevention of conception is
                definitely and finally to be dissociated from an atmosphere of furtiveness and
                obscenity, and openly handled as a legitimate medical problem.</p>
            <p>Unquestionably today there is an overwhelming sentiment in the country for birth
                control. Many persons are in total accord with Dean <person reg="Inge, William R."
                    >Inge</person>’s opinion that “<q who="INGWI">the Comstock legislation in
                    America has done unmixed harm. It is worse than useless to put down by law a
                    practice which a very large number of people believe to be harmless, and which
                    must be left to the taste and the conscience of the individual.</q>” However,
                until this widespread sentiment becomes more articulate, Congress will not act.</p>
            <p>Birth control is not a panacea for all the social and economic ills in the world, but
                at least it is the most important immediate help which can be applied as a solution
                to the present problems of millions of men and women. Those who are practising birth
                control because they are fully conscious of the moral responsibility of bringing a
                child into the world, are laying the foundation of a vast experiment in race
                building which is without precedent in the history of mankind.</p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
