<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011-07-28 NC</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1952-08-00"><supplied resp="MSPP">Aug 1952</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Early Years of Margaret Sanger's Work in the Birth Control
                Movement</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp101826</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
            <bibl><title>LCM</title>128:0349</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="THA">Town Hall Association</name>
            <name id="PIUXI">Pius XI, Pope</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
            <name id="NYSCA">New York State Court of Appeals</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>No published version has been found.</p><p>For an earlier draft see MSM
            S72:0653 and 0664. For a carbon copy see S72:0675.</p><index level1="birth control"
            level2="movement" level3="history of"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>EARLY YEARS OF <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">MARGARET SANGER</person>'S WORK IN THE
            BIRTH CONTROL MOVEMENT</head>
        <p>It was in 1913 that I, with my <person reg="Sanger, William">husband</person> and three
                <person reg="Sanger, Stuart"><person reg="Sanger, Grant"><person reg="Sanger, Peggy"
                        >children</person></person></person>, embarked from <place reg="Boston, MA"
                >Boston</place> on a slow steamer for <place>Scotland</place>, en route to <place
                reg="Paris, France">Paris</place>. In <place reg="Glasgow, Scotland">Glasgow</place>
            I investigated the Municipal Housing Reform Movement, and found that the houses and
            apartments were by law limited to not more than a certain number of persons each
            dwelling: four (4) children was the limit allowed; no apartment in the municipality was
            built to have more than the equipment for father, mother, and four children. From
            Scotland we went to Paris to pick up, wherever possible, the customs and means which had
            given the French peasants the knowledge to control their birth rate and to limit their
            families. This desire had come to me because of my years of nursing experience in <place
                reg="New York, NY">New York City</place> where our maternal death rate was
            disgracefully high: abortions were estimated to run into the millions, and the infant
            mortality rate was a disgrace to such a prosperous nation. Nowhere could I find in the
            printed medical literature any information relative to contraception. Everywhere in the
            slums and working districts women were begging nurses, social workers, and physicians
            for the “secret” to help them space their pregnancies, and save them from abortions
            which oftentimes brought inevitable death. Nowhere was this information given in
            hospitals, public clinics, or even by private doctors. Women had been clamoring for the
            Vote, Legal Rights, Labor Legislation -- but not one voice had been raised in behalf of
            these millions of forgotten women who, from puberty to the grave, spent their lives as
            human incubators.</p>
        <p>I was determined that something must be done about this and so it was that I went on to
                <place>France</place>, to see what I could find. A great contrast existed between
            the women of Scotland, especially in Glasgow, and the women and mothers of France. I was
            able to go into the villages in France and get a great many formulas for suppositories,
            where some ingredients were considered better spermicidal agents that others. I learned
            all I possibly could in France, and later published this information in a pamphlet
            called “<title>Family Limitation</title>” which was later translated into 45 languages. </p>
        <p>I returned to New York after a short time in France, quite determined to do something to
            arouse the public to change the <name type="law" reg="U.S. Criminal Code, Section 211"
                >Federal law, Section 211</name>, which was known as the <name type="law">Comstock
                Law</name>, and which made it a crime for anyone to send any matter through the <org
                reg="United States Postal Service">U.S. Mails</org> or by common carriers that was
            intended to prevent conception. In this law there was no exemption made for scientific
            literature, for medical cards or charts, or for the medical profession. I determined
            that this law must be challenged.</p>
        <p>Gathering a few interested friends together in my apartment, I coined the term “Birth
            Control” and defined it as “conscious control of the birth rate by means that prevent
            conception.” This was the definition for the Birth Control Movement, emphasizing the
            words control, not limitation, and prevention rather than interruption. The educational
            campaign in the United States and elsewhere was centered on this definition of the
            meaning of “birth control.”</p>
        <p>In order to awaken a larger group of women, we then emerged from our domestic corners
            into the arena of education, and I decided to publish a paper called “<title>The Woman
                Rebel</title>”. This paper had, seemingly, a great attraction for people all over
            the country, and while the issue each month was never more than 2000, there were
            sometimes as many as 5000 willing subscribers clamoring for this unique, bold, and
            fearless paper. However, since the reason for publishing the paper was to call attention
            to the federal law, and to what birth control meant in the making of a happy family, and
            the cruelty and wickedness of legislation that would deny people knowledge by which the
            could attain health and happiness, each issue ran into conflict with the post office
            authorities. Nearly every issue was challenged and intercepted, and finally an arrest
            was ordered by the Post Office authorities. I was accused of sending “obscene
            literature” through the United States mails. The fight was on! There had been no
            contraceptive information given on the pages of “The Woman Rebel”, for I had kept
            strictly within the law, discussing the question only on its educational level. </p>
        <p>I was determined that this case would have to be fought and taken to the higher courts. I
            could feel, when I appeared before the <person reg="Hazel, John Raymond">Judge</person>,
            that I was going to be “railroaded”. I asked for ten days’ time to prepare my case -- it
            was refused. I then requested one week's time -- this was also refused. I was sternly
            ordered to return to the Court the following morning: just twenty hours’ time in which
            to prepare to defend myself!</p>
        <p>After consulting lawyers and friends and a good many splendid advisors, I left New York
            that evening for <place>Canada</place>. From there I sailed for <place>England</place>
            to prepare my case for my return. I had sent word to the Judge and the <person
                reg="Marshall, Hudson Snowden">District Attorney</person> informing them of what I
            planned to do, and told them that this was owning to their refusal to give me time to
            prepare for my defense. This case was making the Birth Control Movement known not only
            in <place reg="United States">America</place> but in <place>Europe</place> as well. </p>
        <p>At the time I arrived in England, Europe was already involved in World War One. The
            overpopulation of many of the European countries had forced them to seek more elbow
            room. A great deal of educational work had been done throughout the <place>British
                Isles</place> as a result of the <person reg="Besant, Annie">Annie Besant</person>
            and <person reg="Bradlaugh, Charles">Charles Bradlaw</person> trial in 1878. The
            Malthusian Doctrine was widely discussed, pro and con, in conjunction with the Darwinian
            Theory, so the English people were theoretically informed of the importance of
            population control. But the name “Malthusian” struck terror in their hearts; it had no
            meaning outside of theory. When the term “Birth Control” came to them in my lectures,
            talks, and in pamphlets that we distributed, they at once recognized it as one of their
            needs. “Birth Control” was the term used then, and still is used today, in the greatest
            part of the world. </p>
        <p>I spent 3 months in <place reg="Netherlands">Holland</place> in 1915, and while there I
            took a course of contraceptive technique under Dr. <person reg="Rutgers, Johannes"
                >Johannes Rutgers</person> at the <place reg="Hague, Netherlands">Hague</place>. The
            result of that visit to Holland was to change the course of the Birth Control Movement
            in the United States from a fight for “free speech” to a well-organized clinical set-up
            with doctors and nurses in charge. The United States is the only country where clinics
            have been under medical auspices from the very beginning of the movement. </p>
        <p>Upon my return to <place reg="London, England">London</place> from Holland, I was invited
            to speak in <org>Fabian Hall</org>, where about 500 men and women came to learn about
            the work I was trying to do in the United States, and of the splendid organization of
            clinics I had found in Holland. It was here that I met <person reg="Stopes, Marie">Marie
                Stopes</person>, whose book “<title>Married Love</title>” was to make a sensation.
            Later she included birth control in its pages. I spent months studying in the
                <org>British Museum</org> and writing several pamphlets. </p>
        <p>In the autumn of 1915 I returned to my home and my children. It was time to take up the
            federal fight and the Post Office challenge in the Federal Courts. The case against me
            was postponed several times, and finally dismissed -- for no particular reason, and with
            no explanation to me except that the Government did not wish to pursue the case. Owing
            to the great and widespread publicity, thousands and thousands of letters were sent to
            the Judge and the District Attorney in my behalf. An amazing awakening among the people
            throughout the country occurred, especially among those who had received “<title>Family
                Limitation</title>” and had been, or wanted to be, subscribers to the monthly
            publication “<title>The Woman Rebel</title>.” These letters came from working men and
            women in all walks of life. It was their fight I was waging, and they knew it!</p>
        <p>After the Federal case against me was dismissed early in 1916 I started a lecture tour
            across the continent. There were public forums and public addresses. I visited more than
            19 cities and addressed thousands of people: over 250 groups were organized into Birth
            Control Educational Centers or Leagues. <place reg="Pitssburgh, PA">Pittsburg</place>,
                <place reg="Cleveland, OH">Cleveland</place>, <place reg="Chicago, IL"
                >Chicago</place>, <place reg="Minneapolis, MN">Minneapolis</place>,
                <place>Indianapolis</place>, <place reg="Milwaukee, WI">Milwaukee</place>, <place
                reg="Detroit, MI">Detroit</place> -- all responded by forming these leagues. In many
            cities there were arrests and challenges; meetings sometimes could not be held, and many
            said that a subject of this kind could not be discussed. Outside the doors of the
                <org>Victoria Theatre</org> in <place reg="St. Louis, MO">St. Louis</place>, 2000
            people clamored for admittance to the auditorium where a lecture on Birth Control was
            scheduled. The contract for the rent of the auditorium for that evening had been signed,
            but pressure from “higher-ups” had intimidated the manager of the theatre and he had
            gone away for the week-end. However, the <org reg="Women's City Club of St. Louis"
                >Women's City Club</org> and the <org reg="Men's City Club of St. Louis">Men's City
                Club</org> of St. Louis promptly invited me to speak at their luncheons, under their
            auspices, which I did. I received over a thousand letters within a week, protesting the
            action and the arrogant behavior of the manager of the Victoria Theatre. </p>
        <p>During my tour across the country more than 100,000 leaflets were distributed, telling in
            plain English what Birth Control was all about, and calling on the public to join the
            movement and to help change the Federal law. In 1919 there were over 25 Birth Control
            Educational Leagues organized in the United States to help me repeal the Comstock Law. </p>
        <p>In my addresses throughout the country I described the clinics in Holland, and told what
            the organization of these clinics had meant to that little country in reducing the
            maternal death rate and raising the standard of education by limiting the number of
            children in each family. the description of, and interest in, these clinics as I had
            described them, spread like wildfire. Everyone wanted to know how to set up such
            clinics. This first American campaign was considered as educational success. I had
            created a public opinion of national scope, had won the press to discuss the subject,
            and to defend my right to speak. I had inspired the organization of Leagues to carry on
            the educational <supplied resp="MSPP">campaign. I had</supplied> set up standards of
            what Birth Control Clinics should be, and insisted that they must be conducted by
            members of the medical profession. While the policy was that all adults, married or
            about to be married, should have the right to this birth control knowledge, it should be
            given only by those who had knowledge of anatomy and physiology, which was, of course,
            the medical profession. </p>
        <p>Upon my return form my speaking tour in the west, I announced my intention of opening the
            first <org reg="Brownsville Birth Control Clinic">Birth Control Clinic</org> under
            medical auspices, as a demonstration of how this subject should be handled. this was
            also a challenge to the New York State Law, Section 1142. On October 16, 1916, this
            first clinic was opened at 46 Amboy Street, <place reg="Brooklyn, New York"
                >Brownsville</place>, Brooklyn. Leaflets were distributed in three languages --
            English, Italian, and Yiddish -- and were given out at meetings addressed to mothers.
            Our leaflets were identified as 1) “Can you afford to have a large family?” 2) “Do you
            want any more children?” 3) “If not, why do you have them?” 4) “Don't kill, don't take
            life, but prevent. Safe and harmless information can be obtained from trained nurses at
            46 Amoy Street”. The date was given, the doors were opened, and women came in droves.
            They came with babies in their arms or pushing baby carriages; they swarmed into the
            little waiting room!</p>
        <p>I had previously announced to the <person reg="unidentified">District Attorney</person>
            in Brooklyn that the Clinic was a challenge to the state law, and that I was willing to
            take it to the highest courts. After a period of 5 days the clinic was raided by the
            police; my two attendants (one, my <person reg="Byrne, Ethel Higgins">sister</person>
            who was a trained nurse, the other an <person reg="Mindell, Fania">interpreter</person>)
            and I were arrested. The records of 488 women were confiscated. These records contained
            the history of the women, and were proof of the need of the information, where poverty
            and disease were rampant, and birth uncontrolled. </p>
        <p>My sister, Ethel Byrne, was convicted by the <org>Court of Special Sessions</org> and
            sentenced for 30 days at the “<org reg="Blackwell's Island Penitentiary">Work
                House</org>”. She promptly went on a hunger strike for 103 hours, and was finally
            release by Governor <person reg="Whitman, Charles S.">Whitman</person> of February 1,
            1917. My trial followed on January 29th, and I was sentenced to 30 days in a more
            desirable and cleaner place than the <supplied resp="MSPP">work home the</supplied>
            <org>Queens County Penitentiary</org>. I was favored to that extent because the
            authorities dreaded the spotlight of publicity which must inevitably ensue. Because of
            the bad and primitive conditions at the work house, the publicity did have some good
            effects in bettering conditions. </p>
        <p>My case was carried to the <org>New York State Court of Appeals</org> on <emph
                rend="underline">Section 1142</emph>. In 1918 Judge <person
                reg="Crane, Frederick E.">Crane</person> issued a decision that, inasmuch as I was
            not a physician I was therefore, guilty. The interpretation of that Court was that <emph
                rend="underline">Section 1145</emph> allowed a physician, lawfully practising, to
            give information to prevent conception to anyone “<q who="NYSCA">for the cure or
                prevention of disease</q>.” This was a considerable triumph, because the decision
            was based on Webster's dictionary for the definition of “disease”, and it was found to
            be broad enough for a doctor to give proper information to any woman who needed it! This
            decision of the Court of Appeals of New York State settled the confusion regarding
            opening Birth Control Clinics in other states where it was not illegal to give birth
            control information. By 1940 there were nearly 600 such Birth control Clinics in the
            United States, affiliated with the <org reg="Planned Parenthood Federation of America"
                >Planned Parenthood Federation</org>. </p>
        <p>But while this cleared the state law, in a rather limited way, that was not enough. I
            mapped out plans for a National Education Campaign, to attack the Comstock Law. My plan
            was: 1) Agitation, to arouse interest. 2) Education and Organization. 3)Legislation.
            These were the steps by means of which we hoped to amend the federal law. </p>
        <p>In February of 1917 I became the editor and publisher of “<title>Birth Control
                Review</title>”. This monthly magazine continued to be published by me until 1928,
            at which time I turned it over to the <org>American Birth Control League</org>. </p>
        <p>In 1920 I again was abroad, and while spending several months in England and Scotland, I
            gave 35 lectures to groups of the <org reg="Women's Cooperative Guild">Women's
                Guild</org> in London and the surrounding communities. On July 4th of that year,
            more than 2000 working men stood on the Glasgow Green, listening, and nodding their
            heads in agreement, for they knew what Birth Control could mean to them. I traveled
            throughout Scotland, sharing the hardships in many of the homes of the working class,
            for it was to these men and women that the Movement was dedicated. I also spent several
            months in <place>Germany</place> that year, where I want to seek the chemist who had
            devised the formula for the contraceptive jelly. This was the formula which I brought
            back to the United States, and which has been the basis for the contraceptive jelly,
            used in conjunction with the diaphragm, up to this time. </p>
        <p>The <org>American Birth Control League</org> was formed November 10, 1921, incorporated
            under the Membership Law of New York State. The <org>First National Birth Control
                Conference</org> was held at the <org>Hotel Plaza</org> November 11th to 13th. One
            of the meetings, which was held at <org>Town Hall</org> on November 13th, was ordered
            closed by Cardinal <person reg="Hayes, Patrick">Hayes</person>. This was the first
            mistake of the Roman Catholic hierarchy in attempting to go over the heads of the police
            authorities and taking upon themselves (or upon himself, the Cardinal) the right of
            arrest and censorship. Here the challenge of free speech, and the arrogant action in
            closing Town Hall, swept across the country in headlines. Thousands of letters and
            telegrams of protest poured in from all parts of the country, and there came a great
            arousing of public indignation across the continent. Three arrests were made at Town
            Hall because we refused to obey the Cardinal's order. We stood our ground but were
            hauled off to the police station. Hundreds of people followed to the Night Court, where
            the case was postponed until the following morning -- and then dismissed, as usual.
            Nevertheless, the meeting had been disrupted, and none of us was able to carry on a
            dignified discussion. However, ten days later we held the meeting at the <org>Park
                Theatre</org>, and its large auditorium was packed to the doors. Men and women from
            many civic and religious agencies came to speak in our behalf. </p>
        <p>In 1921 I was the Founder and President of the American Birth Control League, and
            continued until 1928 when I resigned in order to do legislative work with the <org
                reg="National Committee for Federal Legislation on Birth Control">Federal
                Legislative Committee</org>, of which I was director, with headquarters in
                <place>Washington, D.C</place>. <person reg="Hepburn, Katharine Houghton">Mrs.
                Thomas Hepburn</person> was my legislative Chairman. We sent workers into the field
            to get the endorsement of all civic and religious organizations; we had Congressional
            hearings every year of great educational value; we received the endorsement of over 1000
            organizations : the <org>General Federation of Women's Clubs</org>, the <org>Federal
                Council of Churches of Christ in America</org>, and a long list of others. In the
                <title>Encyclical of the Pope</title> in <supplied>1930</supplied>, he states that
            the “<q who="PIUXI">natural method</q>” of birth control, the so-called “rhythm method”,
            could now be practised in Catholic families. The <org>New York Academy of Medicine</org>
            came into the fold; and finally, in 1937, we ceased our legislative activities owing to
            the legal decision of the <org>United States Circuit Court of Appeals</org> that
            supplies and literature coming into the country could be sent to doctors and members of
            the medical profession. This was a test case: we asked one of the hospitals in
                <place>Japan</place> to send, under a doctor's name, a box of diaphragms especially
            made in Japan, to our medical director, Dr. <person reg="Stone, Hannah Mayer">Hannah M.
                Stone</person>. these were intercepted and confiscated by the customs authorities,
            so we took the case to the Circuit Court of Appeals, and thereby got a decision that
            settled the rights of the medical profession of the United States to import as well as
            to send through the mails and by common carriers, contraceptive literature and supplies. </p>
        <p>In February of 1922 I sailed for Japan, where I had been invited to give a series of
            eight lectures. I gave an address in <place reg="Honolulu, HI">Honolulu</place>, en
            route, then went on to <place reg="Yokahama, Japan">Yokahama</place>, arriving there
            March 10th. While there was some difficulty in obtaining a visa from the Imperial
            Military authorities, so much noise and discussion arose on the part of the Japanese
            people that I was allowed to enter and to fulfill my engagements. The largest meeting
            was in <place reg="Tokyo, Japan">Tokyo</place>, at the <org
                reg="Young Men's Christian Association">Y.M.C.A</org>., where I spoke on “<title>War
                and Population</title>.” Thirteen public meetings were held throughout Japan, and
            also hundreds of small group meetings, including a very interesting one with the <person
                reg="Yucki, Mr.">Chief of Police</person>. The <org>Imperial Medical College</org>
            at their 29th Annual Meeting passed a Resolution that the medical point of view on Birth
            Control must be taught in their college. </p>
        <p>After Japan, I went to <place>Korea</place> and had meetings at <place reg="Seoul, Korea"
                >Seoul</place> with physicians and missionaries; and from there I went on to
                <place>China</place>. At <org>Peiping National University</org>, Dr. <person
                reg="Shih, Hu">Hu Shih</person> was Chairman and interpreter for my meetings. The
            pamphlet “<title>Family Limitation</title>” was translated into Chinese, and 5000 copies
            were off the press and ready for distribution the next day to the members of the
                “<org>Association for Family Reform</org>”. Meetings were held in <place
                reg="Shanghai, China">Shanghai</place> with the <org>National Association of
                Education</org>; then <place>Malaya</place>, <place>Singapore</place>, <place
                reg="Penang, Malaysia">Penyang</place>, and <place reg="Cairo, Egypt">Cairo</place>,
            en route to London. From the day of my arrival at Yokahama to the day of my leaving for
            England, my diaries showed that I had held over 500 interviews in Japan alone. At some
            of these interviews several reporters, representing various newspapers and magazines,
            were present; and as the Japanese are 98% literate people, there was a great awakening
            among the masses as to the meaning of the control of the birth rate and population in
            relation to peace and war. </p>
        <p>Then I went on to London to attend the <org
                reg="International Neo-Malthusian and Birth Control Conference, Fifth (London)">5th
                International Malthusian and Birth Control Conference</org>, which was held July 11,
            1922. </p>
        <p>In 1925 the <org
                reg="International Neo-Malthusian and Birth control Conference, Sixth (New York)"
                >6th International Birth Control Conference</org>, which I organized, was held in
            New York City. </p>
        <p>In September of 1927 the <org reg="World Population Conference, 1927 (Geneva)">World
                Population Conference</org>, which had taken me 20 months to organize was held in
                <place reg="Geneva, Switzerland">Geneva</place>, with 300 scientists from 30
            countries attending. </p>
        <p>My diaries estimate that I had 255 meetings from November 1916 to April 1918; and over
            2000 meetings in the United States alone up to 1928, including Conferences in various
            cities:- Boston, <place reg="Cincinatti, OH">Cincinnati</place>, Chicago, <place
                reg="Los Angeles, CA">Los Angeles</place>, and <place reg="Portland, OR"
                >Portland</place>. This seems an unbelievable record, but it was accomplished though
            the strain was terrific. </p>
        <p>In 1930 I organized a <org reg="International Birth Control Conference, Seventh (Zurich)"
                >Contraceptive Conference</org> in <place>Zurich, Switzerland</place>. In the same
            year I was made President of the <org
                reg="Birth Control International Information Centre">Birth Control Information
                Center</org> in London. </p>
        <p>In 1931 I was given the American Women's Award for “integrity, vision and valor”. </p>
        <p>In 1934 I went to <place reg="Soviet Union">Russia</place>, to investigate the research
            on teh so-called “Spermatozin”. A report had been given to me that 20,000 women had been
            immune from pregnancy for two years with less than 2% failures. I interviewed two of the
            scientists, and was able to get the components of the formula, which I later gave to the
                <org>University of Pennsylvania</org> under the direction of Dr. <person
                reg="Mudd, Stuart">Stuart Mudd</person>. I was also able to obtain $25,000 for that
            institution to do research on this formula. I regret to say that nothing tangible
            emerged from this study. </p>
        <p>In 1935-36 I was invited by the <org>All-India Women's Conference</org> to come to
                <place>India</place>, and I made a tour throughout India, covering thousands of
            miles, setting up over 50 Birth Control Clinics under medical auspices; addressed the
            medical and civic organizations in India and <place>Burma</place>. I had a beautiful
            three-day visit with <person reg="Gandhi, Mahandas">Mahatma Ghandi</person> at his
            ashram in <place reg="Wardha, India">Wardha</place>. I was also a guest for several days
            of the great poet, <person reg="Tagore, Rabindranath">Rabindranath Tagore</person>. I
            then went to <place reg="Hong Kong, China">Hong Kong</place> upon the invitation of the
                <org>Chinese Medical Association</org>, but unfortunately, I was there but a short
            time when I was taken ill and had to return home. </p>
        <p>In 1936 I was given the <org>Town Hall</org> Award of Honor for “<q who="THA">conspicuous
                contribution to the enlargement and enrichment of life!</q></p>
        <p>In 1939 there was a merger of the American Birth Control League and Federal Education
            Committee. The name was changed from American Birth Control League to the Planned
            Parenthood Federation of America, and I was appointed honorary chairman. </p>
        <p>In 1946 the <org>International Conference</org> in <place reg="Stockholm, Sweden"
                >Stockholm</place> was organized by <person reg="Ottesen-Jensen, Elise">Mrs.
                Ottesen-Jensen</person> of that city. There, Mrs. <person reg="Brush, Dorothy"
                >Dorothy (Charles F.) Brush</person>, now editor of the New Bulletin, and I set the
            stage for the <org
                reg="International Congress on Population and World Resources in Relation to the Family"
                >Conference</org> to be held in <place reg="Cheltenham, England">Cheltenham</place>,
            England, in 1948. </p>
        <p>In 1948 I helped to organize the conference at Cheltenham, England, on World Population
            and World Resources in relation to the Family.</p>
        <p>In 1949 <org>Smith College</org> conferred upon me an Honorary degree (LLD).</p>
        <p>In 1950 I was given the Lasker Award for the work done in Planned Parenthood. </p>
        <p>I was returned to England in 1950 to attend the meeting of the <org>International
                Committee on Planned Parenthood</org>, and there we initiated the next <org
                reg=" 3rd International Planned Parenthood Conference, Third (Bombay)"
                >Conference</org>, to be held in <place reg="Bombay, India">Bombay</place>, India,
            in November of 1952. In April, 1952, the <org
                reg="International Committee on Planned Parenthood, American Committee">American
                Committee</org> requested me to be Director of the American Division for the
            Conference. Lady <person reg="Rama Rau, Dhanvanthi">Rama Rau</person>, of Bombay, is
            President of the <org>Family Planning Association of India</org>, and is the Director
            for the Conference in India; Dr. <person reg="Blacker, C. P.">C. P. Blacker</person> is
            Director of the <org
                reg="International Committee on Planned Parenthood, British Committee">English
                Division</org>. Our plans now are to formulate a permanent <org
                reg="International Planned Parenthood Federation">World Organization</org> to emerge
            from the Bombay Conference November 24 to December 1, 1952. </p>


    </docBody>
</doc>
