<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/06/10 RT initial tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-18 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1937-04-09">9 Apr 1937</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Allentown Radio Address</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp101803</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
            <bibl>Library of Congress Microfilm 128:300-0</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="USCCA">United States Circuit Court of Appeals</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>For additional versions, see Library of Congress Microfilm 72:111.</p>
        <p><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger</person>'s 15-minute radio address was opened with
            the following announcement: Margaret Sanger, recognized as the leader of the birth
            control movement, will speak to you about "Family Welfare through Birth Control." Mrs.
            Sanger is in <place reg="Bethlehem, PA">Bethlehem</place> tonight on her invitation tour
            of the state. She will speak this evening at <org>Liberty High School</org> and both
            those who are planning to be present and those who cannot come will be glad of this
            chance to hear her. Mrs. Sanger..."</p>
        <index level1="family size" level2="class-based"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="economic benefits and risks of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits and risks"/>
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Federal"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="legal cases"
            level3="U.S. v. One Package of Japanese contraceptives"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <p>Every normal man and woman looks forward to having a home and rearing a family. Every one
            of us has deeply rooted in our heart a love for children. And therefore every one of
            you, I feel sure, are interested in family planning, as birth control might be called,
            which is one of the foundation stones of family life.</p>
        <p>Children, the most important creation of man, should be planned for, wanted, welcomed,
            and given every chance in life. Motherhood, woman’s noblest career, should be undertaken
            consciously, not stumbled into at the whim of blind chance.</p>
        <p>You will all doubtless agree with these ideas.</p>
        <p>You will also doubtless agree that three important factors should be taken into
            consideration in planning a family. First of all, the mother’s health. A woman should be
            physically fit when she undertakes motherhood, If she is suffering from tuberculosis or
            a heart or kidney ailment, pregnancy should be postponed. If she is weakened in mind or
            body from any cause whatsoever, she should have the knowledge of how to postpone the
            coming of a child until she is in good health.</p>
        <p>Second in importance is the economic factor. A man should plan his family in accordance
            with how many children he can support. If his wages remain stationary, and babies
            continue to arrive every year, he cannot do his duty by them. If, as is unfortunately so
            often the case at the present time he is unemployed and on relief or doing <org
                reg="United States Works Progress Administration">WPA</org> work, he should be able
            to control the size of his family until he regains a foothold in life.</p>
        <p>Third comes the question of child spacing. Even when the mother is in good health and
            there are ample funds, children should not be born too close together. The general
            consensus of medical opinion is that there should be an interval of not less than two
            years, preferably three, between births. In this way a mother can fully regain her
            strength after childbirth and give the best that she has to the children already born
            and those to come.</p>
        <p>Studies made by the <org>United States Children’s Bureau</org> show that children born
            one year apart die at the rate of 147 per thousand, while children born two years apart
            have a far greater chance of survival. Their death rate drops to 92 per thousand. As the
            interval between births increases, the infant death rate drops. So also mothers are more
            apt to die when there are too many pregnancies and when children come too close
            together.</p>
        <p>There are other factors to be considered. The mother’s age, the presence of any
            hereditary taint in either parent, their aptitude for bringing up children.</p>
        <p>But let us keep to the three fundamental reasons for family planning. Reliable and
            scientific birth control is needed for family welfare. Whether viewed as a health
            measure or a social measure, birth control information is necessary for successful
            family life, for building better homes and rearing better families.</p>
        <p>A birth control test case was fought out in <place>Ottowa, Canada</place>, last month
            which is of far reaching interest and importance. A social worker was being tried for
            distributing birth control information in <place reg="Eastview, Canada"
            >Eastview</place>, a suburb of that city. She had violated a statute forbidding such
            distribution, the government claimed. But there is in Canada a law a provision that the
            statute should not apply if it can be shown that the act performed was for the “public
            good.” Hence the case focused on the question of whether the giving of birth control
            information was “for the public good.” The magistrate decided that it was. He pointed
            out that 1000 of the 4000 inhabitants of Eastview were on the relief rolls and that in
            such a community there was no doubt that birth control was needed and that thus the
            worker deserved exemption from the restrictions of the statute.</p>
        <p>Here in the United States we too are rejoicing in a recent wise and far reaching court
            decision. The organization of which I am the president, the <org>National Committee on
                Federal Legislation for the Birth Control</org> has been seeking an amendment to the
            so-called <name>Comstock law</name>. This Federal statute, passed over sixty years ago,
            classed prevention of conception with obscenity and made it a crime to send birth
            control information or supplies by mail or by express. It also forbade importation. I
            saw many years ago that this law was the chief stumbling block to progress; doctors were
            hampered in giving information, that hospitals were prevented from giving this service.
            So we began to organize public opinion in support of a birth control bill to exempt
            physicians from the restrictions of this law. Each year we gained more ground, both
            inside the halls of <org reg="United States Congress">Congress</org> and in the public
            at large.</p>
        <p>This year, on November 30, 1936, to be specific, a decision of the <org>United States
                Circuit Court of Appeals</org> for the second Circuit interpreted and clarified the
            law and gave to the medical profession what we were trying to secure through
            legislation. It gave physicians a bill of rights in the field of contraception. The case
            involved the seizure by the <org reg="United States Customs">Customs</org> of birth
            control materials sent to a physician here in <place reg="United States">America</place>
            by a physician in <place>Japan</place>. I will read just one sentence from the decision.
                “<q who="USCCA">We are satisfied,</q>” said the judges, “<q who="USCCA">that this
                statute was not to prevent the importation, sale or carriage by mail of things which
                might intelligently be employed by conscientious and competent physicians for the
                purpose of saving life or promoting the well being of their patients.</q>”</p>
        <p>The United States government decided not to carry the case to the <org
                reg="United States Supreme Court">Supreme Court</org>. This means that the decision
            from which I have quoted becomes, in effect, the law of the land.</p>
        <p>Freed from legal confusion, birth control may now take its rightful place as a part of
            preventive medicine, as a necessary factor in promoting social welfare. Doctors may now
            give contraceptive advice in their public as well as their private practice, and thus
            contribute to the health and well being of the nation. Hospitals and dispensaries
            can--and should--now include birth control among their other health services.</p>
        <p>I believe that every married woman needs to know about birth control. Not merely to limit
            the number of her children, but to plan her family, and space the intervals between her
            children’s births so that she and her children may have the best possible chance for
            health and happiness. I believe that every married man should know about birth control
            so that he can equate his income and his expenses and give his children the best
            possible chance in life.</p>
        <p>In Bethlehem, I am happy to learn, they have made a fine start in this direction. The
                <org>Maternal Health Center</org> at 26 East 3d. Street <add>Bethlehem</add> is
            doing splendid work. I am told that the society has the active support of the
            representative people of the community and stands ready to give mothers who need it the
            best possible reliable, medical advice. I hope that all of you who have heard this talk
            will take an active part in this work, so necessary for the health and welfare of your
            community.</p>


    </docBody>
</doc>
