<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed draft speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2003/05/29 RK</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2003/07/01 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/23 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011-11-30 CH correct typo</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007/06/25 CH Oxygen update </prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/03/11 CH Entered corrections suggested by Andy Carloff.</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-01 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-14 CH added reference to another speech in that tour.</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-14 EK corrected proofreading</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-22 CH correcting headnote</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2012-04-22 CH changed to a speech</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1916-04-00"><supplied>Apr.-June 1916</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Birth Control and Society</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp101859</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
            <bibl>Library of Congress Microfilm 128:456</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>This draft was one of the texts Sanger used during her 1916 American
            speaking tour. For other speeches from that tour, see "<xref from="236132.xml">Birth
                Control (Chicago Address to Women)</xref>," "<xref from="128002.xml">Woman and Birth
                Control</xref>," Apr.-June, 1916, and "<xref from="128003.xml">Condemnation is
                Misunderstanding</xref>."</p>
        <index level1="divorce" level2="in U.S."/>
        <index level1="prostitution"/>
        <index level1="insane asylums"/>
        <index level1="Netherlands, the" level2="conditions in"/>
        <index level1="New Zealand" level2="conditions in"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="morality of"/>
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="federal"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="socio-economic benefits of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Birth Control and Society</head>
        <p>What would the general practice of Birth Control do for Society? This seems to be the
            question that all of us should carefully consider. Not only should we consider society
            as it is today but the society of the future state, and the effects the practice of
            birth control may have in bringing about a cleaner and better race.</p>
        <p>First let me state that I believe birth control to be a great racial step forward
                <del>illegible</del>, because the desire for this knowledge is already here, women
            and men want it and are willing and anxious to put it into practice when the laws
            against so doing shall be removed. Almost all other reforms and advanced ideas have to
            be agitated for and the desire to accept them implanted within the hearts of the people,
            but here we have a condition where the economic condition has done all the pioneering
            for us. The people are far in advance of the laws which continue to hold them in this
            slavery.</p>
        <p>The Government of the <place reg="United States">United States</place> is the only
            Government in the world which imposes a morality upon its citizens. </p>
        <p>Contrary to all the fundamental principles of a great Republic, and especially this
            republic, for the early founders and revolutionists made it clear that a state had no
            more right to impose a morality upon a people than it had to impose a religion or a
            political issue.</p>
        <p>Neither the law nor the penalty imposed by the law can make people moral. We ask the
            United States to make terms with Progress, with human needs, in fact with Civilization,
            and no greater service can be rendered to society than to break the chains of woman's
            sex subjection. Knowledge to control birth is the key to that dissolution.</p>
        <p>There is no greater insult hurled at American womanhood than that which our law makers
            and moralists imply when they say that knowledge to control birth would lead to
            unchastity among them. What an insult to the Nine million women who are living lives of
            sexual purity to day in this country, to suggest that it is the fear of childbirth which
            keeps them celibate. </p>
        <p>What have we as a country, with laws against imparting <del>this</del> information to
            control birth, in comparison with other countries where the same information is easily
            obtainable?</p>
        <p>Let us first begin with domestic happiness. In no other country has the growth of divorce
            been so remarkable or caused so much discussion as in USA. From 1886 to 1906 nearly one
            million marriages were dissolved. Recent figures as near as can be obtained state that
            there are now close upon 85000 divorces granted each year. I claim that ninety percent
            of these misunderstandings have their root in the sex problem where the fear of
            pregnancy is ever a present terror.</p>
        <p>Then we have the problem of prostitution which seems to hold its own with other countries
            not so "advanced" as ourselves, while the feeble minded among these unfortunate victims
            are so numerous that our institutions can not accomodate their increasing numbers. It is
            also stated by recent and reliable authorities that the fertility of the feeble minded
            parent is four times that of the normal parent.</p>
        <p>The insane institutions also record a tremendous increase in their institutions during
            the past few years and I have been told that twenty five cents of every dollar collected
            in <place reg="New York, NY">New York City</place> goes toward the upkeep of the insane
            asylums.</p>
        <p>Both these insane asylums and feeble minded institutions are modern monuments to careless
            and reckless breeding on the part of the working classes. Not only in <place
                reg="Netherlands, the">Holland</place> but in <place>New Zealand</place> do we find
            a constructive work going among the people to disseminate knowledge of Birth Control
            among the poor. </p>
        <p>For thirty years this work has been carried on in Holland and New Zealand in both of
            these countries we find infant mortality the lowest in the world while prostitution is
            almost negligible.</p>
        <p>In Holland the right of personal liberty involves three rights: the right of civilized
            man to have children; the right to limit their number; and the right to have none at all
            if physically or financially unable to do so. They consider the woman who continues to
            make of herself a child bearing machine a most primitive type and quite undesirable.</p>
        <p>We in this country are proud of our boasted freedom and liberty, but it is generally
            known throughout <place>Europe</place> that most of our liberties are a farce. We have a
            political and religious liberty but individual moral liberty must yet be fought for here
            before we can progress in art literature or in human understanding.</p>
        <p>We have amid us the most advanced equipment in telegraph, telephone, laboratories which
            modern science has advanced, and yet our courts continue to give out opinions and
            sentences relating to birth control as were given in the days of the sixteenth century
            when women were burned at the stake as witches because they did not comply with the
            religious opinion of the day.</p>
        <p>Birth control is the keynote to a new social awakening, an awakening of the parent to its
            responsibility toward its offspring. An awakening of individuals toward the consequences
            of their acts. Could Society want any greater morality? Is it not for this same
            responsibility in individuals that education of the past generations has been striving
            toward? Yet we find ourselves unable to advance because of laws. Laws, stupid laws, worn
            out and obsolete, useless to humanity in fact a powerful detriment. Yet we say laws are
            the creation of men. Let us change them then to suit modern times and progress. What
            folly to adhere so stubbornly to old and obsolete dogmas that were a creation of a
            preceeding generation. We might as well object to modern railways because the stage
            coach was used by our grandparents. Society must see things AS THEY ARE if it would
            progress, and <del>we</del>meet the facts of the times.</p>
        <p>I believe that birth control when disseminated among the working people who are less able
            to carry the burdens of the race than any other class, would help to reduce immediately
            the present burden upon the man and woman with their insufficient <del>small</del>
            existing wage. It would wipe out charity, an institution so destructive to self respect
            and independence in the working class. It would enable the working man and woman to be
            better educated and consequently more efficient to develop for their emancipation.</p>
        <p>It would enable the children of the workers to be better nourished and better educated
            preparing them in turn to become something better than wage slaves. It would positively
            do away with child labor. </p>
        <p>It would reduce competition among the workers, and if carried on internationally it would
            raise labor power to its rightful plane whereby the intelligent workers would be the
            controlling factors in the world.</p>
        <p>The problems of overcrowding with its serious moral and hygienic dangers would diminish
            and a solution made at least possible.</p>
        <p>In every way moral physical and spiritual society would be benefitted by the practice of
            birth control. </p>
        <p>Someone has said "<q who="UNK">A chain is only as strong as its weakest link</q>" and so
            is society and the human race it is only what its individuals are. When we make a clean
            intelligent and strong individual today, then and only then can we look for or expect a
            strong clean and intelligent society.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
