<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011-07-28 NC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-30 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1953-00-00">1953</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Some Suggestions for Japan's Future Populations Studies</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp101801</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="book">Family Planning Movement in Japan</title> (Tokyo, 1953), pp.17-18.</bibl>
            <bibl>Library of Congress Microfklm  128:283B</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
          </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>For draft versions see <title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm </title> S72:0725, 0727, and
            0729.</p><index level1="Japan" level2="population policies of"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>SOME SUGGESTIONS FOR JAPAN'S FUTURE POPULATIONS STUDIES</head>
        <byline>By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></byline>
        <p>There is an urgent need throughout the world to form an accurate picture of factors
            causing the rapid increase of World Population.</p>
        <p>Each country can cooperate in ascertaining these factors in the hope that eventually the
                <org>United Nations</org> will be instrumental in proposing a plan to its
            constituents that will improve the conditions both in physical health and economically
            for each Nation. Lacking basic data on population problems has prevented an objective
            approach to methods to be applied to solve them. If proper and adequate data relative to
            birth and death rates; attitudes toward and involved in spacing birth of children;
            limitation of size of family; methods of contraception; motivations effecting
            reproductive results. These data could afford a foundation for the formulation of a
            Population Policy, which every country should strive to attain.</p>
        <p>1. Set up a plan to extend the next five years of study in population problems.</p>
        <p>2. Compile facts contributing to the high birth rate and population increase of
                <place>Japan</place>.</p>
        <p>3. Set up a Teaching Center Clinic where graduate medical students may have
            access to films, literature, research records, and be taught the correct technique of
            contraception and sterilization.</p>
        <p>4. Recommend that an educational program by instituted by Government agencies covering
            hospitals, Public Health groups, and Welfare agencies.</p>
        <p>5. Investigate latest Research studies both chemical and mechanical, and recommend wide
            distribution of these methods most suitable to individual conditions throughout the
            country.</p>
        <p>6. All of the above should aim to be instrumental within two years in helping to form a
            basis for the inauguration of a <org>Population Advisory Board</org>, consisting of
            National experts in the studies of Demography, Population, Biology, Agriculture, Soil
            Conditions, Medical and Physiological experts. </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
