<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/06/01 CE</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/06/07 CE</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/06/20 CE</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1936-11-24">24 Nov 1936</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>The Case for Birth Control (excerpts)</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp101908</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
            <bibl><title>LCM</title>L128:641</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
        <p><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person> delivered the
            speech at the Schenley Hotel in <place
                reg="Pittsburgh, PA, United States">Pittsburgh</place> at a
            meeting sponsored by the <org>Allegheny Birth Control League</org>.
            No complete version of the speech has been found.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues"
            level3="in US"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits and risks"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation"
            level3="Federal"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="legalization of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="medical community and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="American"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="maternal"/>
        <index level1="physicians" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="quackery"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="government"
            level3="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>EXCEPRTS FROM MRS. MARGARET SANGER'S ADDRESS</head>
        <p>“I urge the immediate amendment of the present federal laws which tie
            the hands of the physician and obstruct an adequate and scientific
            national birth control program. More than 1,000 organizations, with
            millions of members, have endorsed our efforts to change these
            obsolete federal laws, and 200,000 individuals have pledged their
            support over their personal signatures.”</p>
        <p>“It is easy to boast about birth control clinics, and point with
            pride to their growth since I opened the first clinic in
                <place>America</place> in the slums of <place
                reg="Brooklyn, New York, United States">Brooklyn</place> in
            1916. This clinic, as you know, was closed as a ‘public nuisance,’
            and I and my co-workers were sent to jail. Two hundred and fifty
            clinics in forty-three states are functioning today. But for every
            woman who goes to a clinic or to a private doctor and gets birth
            control information, there are hundreds of thousands who apply to
            hospitals and doctors and are denied instruction which they need to
            preserve health and life itself. Quack nostrums, ineffectual and
            often harmful contraceptive supplies may be bought at any drug
            store, and when these fail, women can in desperation submit to
            abortions. But scientific and reliable birth control instruction is
            the privilege of the few. The great mass of American mothers ask for
            it in vain.”</p>
        <p>“Private charity can never effectively take care of this situation.
            As a part of preventive medicine and public health, it is work which
            the <org reg="United States government">Government</org> can no
            longer ignore. Let us clear away the legal obstructions which retard
            birth control work--now, at once, without further dallying. Then we
            can go forward to the inspiring and constructive program of giving
            to every mother the information which she needs, and which is her
            constitutional right.”</p>
        <p>“Statistics from <place reg="Pennsylvania, United States"
                >Pennsylvania</place> show how great is the need in your State
            for scientific and reliable birth control. Maternal deaths from all
            causes decreased from 1136 in 1930 to 931 in 1934. Deaths from
            abortion, however, increased, and of those the number caused by
            septic poisoning also increased. Of every 100 women who die during
            maternity, 95 die from abortion, and of these 25, 20 die from septic
            poisoning which generally follows abortions performed without the
            proper medical safeguards. Give women birth control information and
            they will not have to submit to abortions.”</p>
        <p>“Turning to the relief question, <org
                reg="Works Progress Administration">W.P.A.</org> figures show
            that 147,375 families in Pennsylvania were on relief in May, 1936.
            This figure is estimated to represent nearly 700,000 people--men,
            women, and children in your State. The cost of relief in <place
                reg="Pennsylvania, United States">Pennsylvania</place> for this
            month was $5,305,000, and the total cost for the <place>United
                States</place> for the month of May was $41,800,000.”</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
