<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2003/06/09 SB</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/23 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007/06/15 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/03/05 EK cleanup</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2015/01/13 EK correct proofreading</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1915-10-24">24 Oct 1915</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>The Danger of Carrying an American Passport</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp101916</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>The New York Sunday Call</title>, Oct. 24, 1915, 3.</bibl>         
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="exile, 1914-15"/>
        <index level1="World War I" level2="passports"/>
        <index level1="Europe" level2="travel in"/>
        <index level1="England" level2="views of America"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>THE DANGER OF CARRYING AN AMERICAN PASSPORT</head>
        <byline>By MARGARET H. SANGER</byline>
        <p>An American passport in <place>Europe</place> at the present is <emph rend="italics"
                >useless</emph>! In fact, it is worse than useless in helping one to get either in
            or out of <place>England</place>, to or from the Continent. To be an American today in
            England is almost as unfortunate as to be a German, but to have a passport in the
            bargain brings upon you all the cunning trickery of which the official English mind is
            capable.</p>
        <p>There is no American who is traveling in Europe who is not disgusted with the passport
            nuisance, and yet so few of them seem to blame or censure the American government for
            this torture by English officials through which they must pass. It is ridiculous that
            the <place>United States</place> makes a clashing noise
            over the <name type="ship">Lusitania</name> and <name type="ship">Arabic</name> because some of her citizens
            have suffered the fate of all on board, while hundreds, yes, thousands, of her citizens
            are suffering insult upon insult by the allied governments. It is rumored that many have
            been shot as spies. Of course, no one says an American was shot; but they do say that
            many Germans holding American passports were shot.</p>
        <p>While coming into <place>France</place> last month, via <place reg="Folkstone, England"
                >Folkstone</place>
            <place reg="Dieppe, France">Dieppe</place>, two Americans, a man and a woman, were
            arrested and taken off to be searched. Another man holding an American passport was
            ahead of me in the line. I saw the official look at him with the suspicion and cunning
            that would make the most innocent uncomfortable. He was held over, called a liar and
            insulted as few men allow themselves to be in these days. He was not allowed to proceed
            to France, and where he was taken to I cannot say. Later, on the boat, I heard he was a
            Dr. <person reg="Price, Dr.">Price</person>, of <place reg="Boston, MA">Boston</place>,
            a well-known and wealthy physician there, who had donated $75,000 to the <org>French Red
                Cross</org>.</p>
        <p>The English official in charge at Folkstone, by the way, seems to be a special species of
            animal which all England must have been scoured to find. He and others of his kind were
            chuckling in glee over their brilliant detection in finding Dr. Price a "suspect."</p>
        <p>At Hyde Park Corner, about the end of August, at a meeting of the
                <org>Anti-Naturalization League</org>, a suggestion came from one of the speakers to
            intern all the German women and children at present in <place>Great Britain</place>.
            Then came another suggestion--this one from the audience--to intern the Americans in
            England first. This was wildly cheered and the air was thick with words of "<q who="UNK"
                >swine</q>," "<q who="UNK">dirty swine</q>" and "<q who="UNK">worse than the
                Germans</q>."</p>
        <p>When I went to present my passport at the French Consul's office in <place
                reg="London, England">London</place> to get a vize--for which one pays $2--the
            official in charge only glanced at the seal and saw it was an American passport. He
            returned it to me, saying, "<q who="UNK">Do you know any English man or woman in
                London?</q>"</p>
        <p>"Yes," said I.</p>
        <p>"<q who="UNK">Well, then, go and get a letter from a British subject that you are the
                person stated on your passport and what your purpose is in going to France.</q>"</p>
        <p>I could scarcely believe my ears. I asked him to repeat the words.</p>
        <p>This he did most maliciously.</p>
        <p>I then asked, "Am I to understand you right? The American passport with the seal and
            signature of the United States government is not to receive the respect that any British
            Tommy in the streets of <place reg="Loondon, England">Londo</place>n would receive?"</p>
        <p>He bowed politely and said, "<q who="UNK">It is the regulation of the <org reg="House of Commons">House</org>,
            Madam.</q>"</p>
        <p>Are Americans to tolerate this? If the United States government issues passports, then it
            has some responsibilities toward those to whom it issues them, or it should decline to
            give them.</p>
        <p>The British government, on the other hand, takes mighty good care that anyone holding an
            English passport is not inconvenienced. For instance, for some time all applicants for
            passports for France were to call from 10 to 12 and from 2 to 4 at 20
            Bedford Square, London. Each day the scramble and push was like a wild rush of cattle.
            Often people stood there for three or four days waiting to enter. French, Belgians,
            Italians, Russians, English and Americans all stood and waited in the rain or sunshine
            outside the house like patient cattle.</p>
        <p>Finally, one rainy day, two strong and sturdy Irishmen broke in the door, were arrested,
            but released. Then the British government rented the house next door at once for all
            British subjects only, and thus secured a double staff of officers from the French
            authorities and held the doors open continuously from 9 to 5 each day. This is only one
            instance. There are many. The English government has secured for its subjects carrying
            its passports conveniences and comforts that no other people have.</p>
        <p>Even many Americans who carry British passports have stated to me that they have no
            difficulty, while their friends or relatives with them holding American passports, have
            been held over and had to undergo the greatest indignities.</p>
        <p>The American government is a laughing stock in Europe today. Every one knows that her
            population is mainly German and Irish descent and has never had particular reason to
            love England. They know, too, that another large proportion of her population are
            Russian Jews, who, in turn have no reason to bow in grateful adoration to the powers of
            the <person reg="Nicholas II ">Czar</person>. How, then, can the United States pretend
            that her people are on the righteous side of the allies--according to the press? Many
            English have stated not that they blame the United States for not "<q>coming
                in</q>," but for making the bluff that she is making, knowing that she cannot
            carry out her threats.</p>
        <p>The feeling is very bitter in England against Americans. I have not felt it in France to
            the same extent, though several Americans have said thousands have been arrested in
            France, too, during the past five months.</p>
        <p>It does seem that the American Government should demand from the European countries the
            same treatment accorded civilians carrying its passports as that of other neutrals.
            Either that, or it should cease to give passports at all. The United States should look
            into the question without delay.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
