<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Statement">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2009/04/01 CH Initial transcribe and tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-10 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2009/07/14 LL</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1931-00-00">1931</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>A Message to the Women of China</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp103187</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
                <title type="journal">Lloyd's Weekly</title>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress (LCM 12:618)</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>Margaret Sanger wrote at bottom: "For Lloyds Weekly Shanghai".</p>
        <index level1="women" level2="enslavement of"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="freedom and rights of"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="maternal feelings"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="economic benefits and risks of"/>
        <index level1="China" level2="women in"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>A MESSAGE TO THE WOMEN OF <place>CHINA</place></head>

        <p>The most significant change which has occured in the Western world in the Nineteenth
            Century has been the revolt of women against sex servility. In other worlds, it has been
            the refusal of women to consider themselves mere breeding machines which has given woman
            her place of dignity and power in the Western world. </p>
        <p>We know now that the most important force in the re-making of the world is a free and
            conscious Motherhood. As women free themselves from accidental and unvoluntary breeding
            they set free not only the women, but the children, from poverty, misery and economical
            slavery. Birth control is the first step that women must make towards the goal of their
            freedom. It is the first and most important step that labor must take towards the goal
            of its emancipation. When women own and control their own bodies they will life
            Motherhood to the plane of a voluntary, intelligent function, and re-make and
            revolutionize our social system. When the world is thus remade it will exceed any dream
            of our present statesmen, reformers or idealists. For this is the fundamental step upon
            which Society to-day is based and upon which we must reconstruct a permanent social
            system.</p>
        <closing><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">MARGARET SANGER</person>.</closing>
    </docBody>
</doc>
