<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2003/06/09 SB</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2003/08/07 CH Index</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007/06/25 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/03/05 EK cleanup</prepDate>
        
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1916-03-01">1 Mar 1916</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>"A Statement of Support for Emma Goldman"</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp106580</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
            <bibl>LCM 8:917</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>                      
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>This statement was read for Sanger at a mass meeting held for <person reg="Goldman, Emma"
                >Emma Goldman</person> at Carnegie Hall in <place reg="New York, NY">New York
            City</place>.</p>
        
        <index level1="Goldman, Emma"/>
        <index level1="free speech and free press"/>
        <index level1="birth control clinics and leagues" level2="establishment of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <p>Owing to the fact that a recurrent attack of grippe keeps me in the hospital, I am
            prevented from speaking at the meeting of protest against the arrest of Emma Goldman.
            The fight, as in my case, is for birth control as well as the broader issue of free
            speech. Birth control to me is the most fundamental issue for woman's freedom and the
            thing of which the race stands most in need. I hope that all my comrades and friends
            will work to arouse popular sentiment to such a degree that Emma Goldman cannot be
            convicted. My plan was to tour to the West Coast to establish birth control clinics in
            those States where the laws are sufficiently responsive to an intelligent public opinion
            to abdicate their authority in this regard. But if Emma Goldman goes to prison, it may
            be necessary to concentrate all our efforts against the archaic puritanism of <place
                reg="NY">New York State</place> and open the first free clinic in the lower East
            side of New York City.</p>
        <byline>Margaret Sanger</byline>
    </docBody>
</doc>
