<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2013/11/20 JK encoded</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-08-21 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1934-00-00">1934</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Mother Care in Russia</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp110554</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
            <bibl>Library of Congress Microfilm, 20:738 </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><index level1="birth control" level2="international"/>
        <index level1="abortion" level2="in Soviet Union"/>
        <index level1="Russia" level2="Birth Control Policy"/>
        <index level1="Soviet Union" level2="laws"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Mother Care in Russia.</head>
        <div>
            <p>So much has been heard outside <place reg="Soviet Union">Russia</place> of the <org
                    reg="Soviet Union Government">Soviet Government</org>’s policies on birth
                control and abortion, that it comes as a surprise to find that at the <org
                    reg="Institute for the Protection of Mother and Child">Institute for the
                    Protection of Mothers and Children</org> in Moscow in <place reg="Moscow, Soviet Union">Moscow
                </place>itself, birth control and abortion are regarded as settled questions. There
                is far more interest in other efforts to diminish infant mortality, still almost
                three times greater than in <place>England</place>, in a pure and plentiful milk
                supply, in the new developments continually being made to provide skilled care for
                the pre-school child and to educate expectant and nursing mothers in the latest
                scientific care of themselves and their infants. The whole work for maternity in
                Russia is a natural outcome of the Communist doctrines as expounded by <person
                    reg="Lenin, Vladimir">Lenin</person>. Women being, as one Communist expressed it
                to me, “the oppressed of the oppressed,” measures were taken to make her free -- free
                to work and to take her place in the community as a free citizen. Hence easy
                marriage, easy divorce, all occupations open to her, even in the <org reg="Red Workers' and Peasants' Army">Red Army</org>, equal
                pay, birth control, right to abortion, institutes, nurseries, hospitals, schools for
                babies and children to set her free to work and to play. Children too must be free,
                hence no illegitimate children, education free from the day nursery to the
                University, with maintenance allowances in nearly all cases, parents not allowed to
                give their children corporal punishment; the aim, as an intelligent girl of fourteen
                told me, is to encourage “self-conscious discipline” and to place the “discipline of
                the school in the hands of the scholars.” Punishment is replaced by the idea of
                re-education, and a naughty or tiresome child is said to need the attention of a
                pedagogue.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">No Religious Taboos.</head>
            <p>Maternity work is entirely free from religious interferences, hence there is no
                opposition to the scientific treatment of all problems. As the only serious
                opposition to birth control comes from the <org>Roman Catholic Church</org>, the
                Soviet authorities need waste neither time nor energy in trying to placate or
                circumvent those enemies of woman’s emancipation.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Science Decides. </head>
            <p>Scientific knowledge has the last word. Everywhere there is enthusiasm for education,
                for research, for the accurate knowledge on which action is to be based. When I
                discussed with one of our guides the lavish service for the children in comparison
                with the very real hardships being endured by the people in food, housing, bad roads
                and other ways, she replied: “We want to have a healthy population, and it is only
                be looking after the children well that we can get a good population.”</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Care of pregnancy. </head>
            <p>A “good population” being the aim of the Government, careful provision is made for
                the expectant and nursing mother. As soon as a woman thinks she is pregnant she is
                urged to visit her clinic to receive advice and help suitable to her condition. She
                is given two months from work before the birth of the child and two months
                afterwards on full pay. She receives a ticket which entitles her to a seat in
                tramcar or ‘bus, and also to go to the head of a queue, instead of waiting her turn.
                Propaganda is unceasing on good motherhood, as on many other activities. a poster
                for Expectant Mothers is freely displayed in clinics, factories and clubs. Among the
                point enumerated are: Visit ante-natal clinic every month. Keep your body
                scrupulously clean. Eat for the most part vegetable food, keep your digestion
                healthy. Have your teeth attended to Coitus must cease (1) during early pregnancy
                (2) on days when menstruation would have occurred (3) eight weeks before birth
                Normal work is harmless for the pregnant woman and her future child</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Go to Maternity Home for the birth. </head>
            <p>Museums for mothers and children showing in an attractive way the importance of
                proper care furing pregnancy, of the evil effects of alcohol and venereal diseases,
                talks in factories, workshops and at the Houses of Culture, all drive home the value
                of child life and good motherhood to the nation. The centre of the work in the
                cities is at the Institute for the Protection of Mothers and Children. In Moscow
                this includes many departments, such as clinics for ante-natal work, for birth
                control, for child welfare, a hospital for young children, the Museum for Mother and
                Child, and research laboratories.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Sex Education. </head>
            <p>As preparation for adult life, the importance of sex education is recognised and
                definite instruction is given in the schools to all children from 12 to 16 years of
                age. Practical applications of the teaching are provided by visits to farms where
                animals are bred, and the importance of good breeding is emphasized from examples on
                the farms. The age of marriage is 18 for men and women, and in an adjoining room to
                the marriage bureau are posters warning the newly-married against the dangers of
                alcohol and against venereal diseases. The best ways of avoiding tuberculosis, of
                the necessity of fresh air, sunshine and cleanliness of pure food and the dangers
                from flies are clearly and forcibly pointed out. Addresses where birth control
                information can be obtained and the clinics where expectant and nursing mother
                should go are given. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Railway Station Clinics. </head>
            <p>The most recent development of the work for maternity is the establishment of clinics
                at the big railway-stations in Moscow. There is an immense deal of travelling in
                   Russia, especially to Moscow, and peasants
                bringing their children with them can now have them cared for at the clinic, instead
                of dragging them about the city The writer visited a railway clinic. The children
                were received in a room above the station by a woman doctor, assisted by a nurse.
                The doctor examined the children, and those free from any infection were taken to
                one of three nurseries graded according to age-- babies, toddlers and older
                children. For the older children, those over 7 years of age, a teacher was provided
                as well as a nurse. A child with any infection was placed in a small isolation room,
                and, if necessary, transferred to a children’s hospital. The parents may call for
                the child in a few hours’ time, or it may be a few days. Moscow is so overcrowded
                that it would be almost impossible for anyone with children to find sleeping
                accommodation, and the railway station clinics are not only an immense help to
                parents, but prevent much suffering among children. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Birth Control and Abortion.</head>
            <p>are not regarded as something extraneous to the work of maternal health, but as a
                normal part of these health services. The birth control methods are similar to the
                methods used in clinics in England and <place reg="United States">America</place>.
                Contraceptives are being manufactured for export, and instruction for their use are
                issued in English, French and German. Experiments are being made with a new
                contraceptive paste prepared by the culture of the Bacillus Bulgaricus in milk. This
                is apparently giving very good results, and the women are pleased with it, but it
                has not been long enough in use for any statistics of value to be collected. The
                failures in the chief Moscow clinic have been reduced to 3 per cent., but as
                failures can be met with abortions, they have not the tragic significance they have
                with us. Abortions, carried out only after inquiry into each individual case, are
                usually performed at special hospitals. Dr. <person reg="Haden-Guest, Leslie">Haden Guest</person>, in his visit to Russia,
                made a full investigation of the abortion hospitals and published his results in
                “<title type="journal">The Lancet</title>” of December 5th 1931.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">MATERNITY A SOCIAL SERVICE.</head>
            <p>This thorough work for mothers and children, carried out apparently regardless of
                expense, is the more remarkable when contrasted with the very real hardships endured
                by the general population in order to make the five year plan successful, is of
                interest to women in all parts of the world. No woman in Russia need bear an
                unwanted child and any women who desires to bear a child will find the child as
                welcome in the society as any other child. Both parents contribute to the support of
                the child. Maternity is recognised as a social service and mothers are accorded
                recognition, encouragement and help such as is not given in countries where
                motherhood is regarded as being mainly the private concern of the individual mother.
                In many countries governments interfere to prevent birth control information, to
                forbid abortion, to label innocent babes as “legitimate” and “illegitimate,” to
                prevent cruelty in its grosser forms, and to provide education, but no country
                except Soviet Russia has as yet attempted to assume real responsibility for the
                continuance of its own existence as a society. The best test to apply to any system
                of mother-care is to examine its results on the welfare, character and happiness of
                the human beings. Time and experience alone can show what these results will be.
                Feminists, birth controllers, eugenists and humanitarians should study Soviet
                Russia’s plans of mother-care as the most important experiment now being made in the
                sphere of maternity and child welfare. </p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
