<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed draft document">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2010/03/31 AC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-11 CH clean regs and other errors</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1934-07-25">25 Jul 1934</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied>Russia</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp110550</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Library of Congress Microfilm</title>, 20:0717</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Comstock act"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation"
            level3="Postal Code and Regulations"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="State"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="continence"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="sterilization"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="safe period"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="opposition to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="religion and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="Soviet Union"/>
        <index level1="Catholic Church"/>
        <index level1="obscenity"/>
        <index level1="physicians" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="Post Office (U.S.)"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub"><add><emph rend="underline">The Saw</emph></add></head>
            <p>60 years ago, there was passed in <place reg="United States">America</place> a law
                which makes it a crime to send thru the <org reg="United States Postal Service">U.S.
                    Mails</org> or common carriers– which are our express companies– any book,
                pamphlet or leaflet which contains information, to prevent conception, or any
                article or device adapted or intended to prevent conception. The penalty <del>that
                    is</del>
                <gap reason="illegible" extent="one word"/> under this law can be five years
                imprisonment or $5000 fine, or both. In this law they also include obscenity,
                abortion, indecency, pornography, and all other titles or acts or ideas of indecency
                known in the English language. This law makes no eception for scientific books,
                literature or for medical or scientific persons using such literature. All come
                under the same category, of obscenity. In this law it also makes it a crime to tell
                    <emph rend="underline">anyone</emph> thru a letter or an advertisement <emph
                    rend="underline">where</emph> such information or such articles might be
                obtained, and you are just as severely punished for <emph rend="underline"
                    >receiving</emph> such articles or such literature as for sending them thru the
                mails or common carriers. This is the FEDERAL LAW.</p>
            <p> Aside from this we have the laws of 48 States, 47 of them within certain
                limitations, allow Doctors at least to <gap reason="illegible"/> give this
                information <emph rend="underline">orally</emph>, by word of mouth, in their private
                practice, also within certain limitations.</p>
            <p> So we have a condition in which the Federal law <emph rend="underline">will</emph>
                not allow a doctor to receive information or supplies for his patients, while the
                State law will allow him to <gap reason="illegible" extent="one word"/> tell the
                patient whatever the doctor has found out about this subject, altho just where the
                doctor is to inform himself has not been considered. The consequence of this law is
                that medical schools and universities leave the subject of contraception <gap
                    reason="illegible" extent="one word"/> out of their curricula, and many doctors
                have received all the information they know either from lay persons or
                organizations, or from their patients, and not from their medical schools.</p>
        </div>
        <div>

            <head type="sub"><emph rend="underline">Free Speech vs. Medical Question.</emph></head>
            <p> When this idea first came to me in 1912 or 1913, I thot it was simply a question of
                the freedom of speech, and of fighting for the principle that women should have the
                right to information, and that it would be sufficient to give it to them in
                pamphlets, books, or in any way so long as they obtained the information. BUT after
                going more deeply into the subject and going to Holland and studying the question of
                contraceptive technique from <person reg="Rutgers, Johannes">Dr. Rutgers</person> in
                1915, I came to the conclusion that while it every woman’s right to receive
                information and instruction, that it took <del>special knowldege of anatomy</del>
                special knowledge of anatomy and physiology in order to instruct her <emph
                    rend="underline">properly</emph>. On my return to America, therefore, there was
                a definite division, a cleavage, and change in the movement between those who
                believed it was still a question of free speech and those who believed it was a
                question of putting the responsibility of giving the information into the hands of
                the medical profession, and persuading the medical profession to include the subject
                of contraceptive technique in their practice of preventive medicine and public
                health.</p>
            <p> It was important to send out to over 150,000 Drs. in America some person who should
                tell them about this technique, and as over 20,000 Doctors had requested such
                special information from our organization, it was possible to send s physician thru
                the country to the various medical societies, and to make known to them how this
                question concerned the medical profession, in both their <gap reason="illegible"
                    extent="two words"/> public and private practice.</p>
            <p> While we have instructed thousands of physicians thruout the country, and some of ht
                emost distinguished doctors in the country are working with us to change the Laws,
                we have not yet received the offical support of the <org>American Medical
                    Association</org>, because of the influence of the <org
                    reg="Roman Catholic Church">Catholic Church</org>. Nevertheless, while the
                American Medical Association has not gone on record officially as a whole and
                endorsed our work, hundreds of County Medical and State Medical Societies, as well
                as the <org
                    reg="American Medical Association, Obstetrical and Gynecological Division"
                    >Obstetrical and Gynecological Divisions of the American Medical
                    Association</org>, <emph rend="underline">have</emph> endorsed the right and the
                principles of birth control, as it applies to the medical profession.</p>

        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">
                <del>5</del>
                <add>6</add> Reasons for Birth Control</head>
            <p>
                <list>
                    <item>1. Parents, men and women, should practice Birth Control, and in some
                        cases sterilization, when either of them have a <emph rend="underline"
                            >transmissible disease</emph> such as certain forms of insanity,
                        feeble-mindedness, epilepsy, and other diseases which are known to be
                        transmissible to the offspring.</item>
                    <item>2. Women should practice contraception of the woman’s Health is
                            <del>not</del> undergoing treatment for tuberculosis, or heart disease,
                        kidney <gap reason="illegible" extent="one word"/> disease, and other
                        temporary diseases when the healthy is further disturbed by the complication
                        of pregnancy.</item>
                    <item>3. When the Parents themselves, while apparently normal, have already
                        given birth to deaf-mutes, children with cleft palages, mental defects, or
                        children who have inherited some disease form their parents.</item>
                    <item>4. Spacing of children. There should be a period of from 2 to 3 years
                        between the births of children to give the mother a chance to recuperate her
                        health, and to give proper care of the child just born, and to prepare <gap
                            reason="illegible" extent="one word"/> herself physically and mentally
                        for the coming of the next child that she may desire.</item>
                    <item>5. Adolescence, and Marital Adjustment. We advise early marriage but the
                        postponement of parenthood until after the adolescent development has taken
                        place, which in the occidental countries is from the 12th year in the girl,
                        and the 14th year in the boy, until the 22nd of 24d year, when we believe
                        their parenthood will be more responsible; that it will be much better for
                        the children also if they are not born before their parents are developed
                        fully physically. </item>
                    <item>6. <emph rend="underline">Economic Reasons</emph>. Where
                            <del>parenthood</del> parents have been unable to support even one child
                        or two children, they should not increase the size of their family, often
                        throwing the burden upon the older children in the family and making the
                        older children take up the economic and social responsibility before they
                        are grown, as we have seen from child labor studies. These children’s lives
                        are dwarfed and stunted because they have to earn a living not only for
                        themselves, but for the other members of the family, and for their parents
                        also. <p>Marital Adjustment.</p>
                    </item>
                </list></p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">3 Methods of Birth Control</head>
            <list>
                <item>Continence</item>
                <item>Sterilization</item>
                <item>Chemical and Mechanical Means of Contraception</item>
            </list>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Clinics Established in America.</head>
            <p> At these clinics, we use mainly mechanical and contraceptive methods.</p>
            <p> Many contraceptive products are coming up on the market constantly, backed by
                commercial interests only, and as there is no control over these products, people go
                to the drug stores and ask for anything they see, regardless of the condition of
                health, etc., and therefore it is very important that the marketing of contraceptive
                products be placed under control before it gets out of hand.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Attitude of CHURCHES in America.</head>
            <p> Endorsement by the leading Protestant, groups.</p>
            <p>
                <list>
                    <item>Jewish</item>
                    <item>Congregational</item>
                    <item>Unitarian</item>
                    <item>Methodist</item>
                </list>
            </p>
            <p>Opposition of ROMAN CATHOLIC CHURCH.</p>
            <p><list>
                    <item>Continence no longer advocated entirely.</item>
                    <item>“Safe Period”</item>
                </list>
            </p>
            <p>This question could also be studied in <place reg="Soviet Union">Russia</place>,
                perhaps.</p>
            <p>Restatements of Opportunities before Russian Medical Profession and particularly
                medical women.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">CONCLUSION</head>
            <p> ANNOUNCEMENT OF GIFT OF MATERIAL TO THE <org
                    reg="Okhrana Materinstva I Mladenchestva">INSTITUTE FOR THE PROTECTION OF
                    MOTHERHOOD AND CHILDHOOD</org>
                <emph rend="underline">for research</emph>. Interested in knowing the results. </p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
