<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2010/04/14 AC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-11 CH clean regs and other errors</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1936-00-00">
            <supplied source="MSPP">1936</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>
                <supplied source="MSPP">Gandhi</supplied>
            </titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp112758</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Library of Congresss Microfilm</title>18:890</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="GANMO">Gandhi, Mohandas K.</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="population growth" level2="regulation of"/>
        <index level1="men" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
        <index level1="India"/>
        <index level1="Gandhi, Mahatma"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Gandhi</head>
        <p>And now I want to tell you a little about my visit with <person reg="Gandhi, Mohandas"
                >Mahatma Gandhi</person>, at <place reg="Wardha, India">Wardha</place>. As soon as I
            arrived at <place reg="Bombay, India">Bombay</place>, there was a message to the effect
            that Gandhi would receive me, that I should come at any time and stay as long as I
            wished. And, of course, I wanted to pay my respects to him, admiring and venerating him
            greatly and knowing that he is best loved of all in <place>India</place>. I had only
            three days to spend at Wardha, not a very long time for what we had to consider, because
            when the Mahatma was asked if he was going to be converted by <person
                reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>, he replied that he was going to
            convert her. However, I arrived at Wardha on Monday, to find that this was Gandhi’s day
            of silence, so I could not talk with him. However, I did have the opportunity of talking
            with some of the members in his household. All arose at four o’clock in the morning, and
            from five to six gathered for prayers. On the second day of my visit, starting at seven
            o’clock promptly, the Mahatma and I walked for an hour. This was very delightful, even
            though there was no “shop talk” while we were walking to the village and back. We had
            breakfast at eleven and supper at five, and in the intervals we conferred. He ate
            sparingly, but the rest of us had more than we could eat and in abundance. Of course, he
            had this <person reg="Desai, Mahadev">secretary</person> and I had <person
                reg="Shuman, Anna Jane Phillips">mine</person>, and they took down every one of our
            “golden words.” Gandhi agreed with me in principle, and I agreed with him in principle.
            He said he was a greater feminist than I was, because he believed women should have
            everything to say about babies. I said I thought it should be fifty-fifty; that the
            woman should say “<q who="GANMO">when</q>” and the man should say “<q who="GANMO">how
                many,</q>” as he has to support them. Gandhi said he was informed, that he knew what
            women had to go through. He said he did not believe that India has a particular problem
            in population. He felt that if India ever developed and fulfilled her own destiny, she
            could solve her own population problem. Of course, we disagreed on that.</p>
        <p> We discussed marriage, remarriage, and divorce; we discussed population from every
            aspect; we discussed continence, the safe period or rhythm, and birth control. He told
            me that continence would be better for the people’s spiritual development. I replied
            that until people come to that point and accepted continence in practice, it would be
            far better to use the safest methods of birth control and bring about a solution of
            their national and family problems. Incidentally, <person reg="Tagore, Rabindranath">Dr.
                Tagore</person> encouraged me greatly by agreeing on this particular question.</p>
        <p> I have just one more story to tell you before I finish. I was the guest for a short time
            at the home of a very cultured family who had three girls, but no sons. My coming had
            been discussed and the youngest child, who was very precocious, had thought over what
            she had heard. Finally she came to her father and said: “<q who="UNK">Daddy, if you had
                met Margaret Sanger before I was born, would I be here?</q>” And her Daddy took her
            up in his arms and gave her the answer which I am sure you will all feel every parent
            should be able to give his children. He said, “<q who="UNK">Joan, dear, if there were a
                hundred Margaret Sangers you would still be here, because <emph rend="underline">we 
                    wanted you!!</emph></q>”</p>


    </docBody>
</doc>
