<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2010/04/28 AC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2010/04/29 CH proof and correct</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/02/11 CH corrected date</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-11-12 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1937-08-30">
            <supplied source="MSPP">30 Aug 1937</supplied>
        </docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>
                <supplied resp="MSPP">Japanese Clinic Opening</supplied>
            </titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp113279</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
            <bibl>Library of Congress Microfilm 19:126</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>Sanger gave the keynote address at the tea reception and dedication of Baroness Shidzue
            Ishimoto’s <org>Birth Control Clinic of Tokyo</org> in Oimachi, a working class district
            of <place reg="Tokyo, Japan">Tokyo</place>. For another version of the speech see
                <title>MSM</title> S71:959.</p>
        <index level1="population" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="population growth" level2="regulation of"/>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="women in"/>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="birth control leagues and clinics"/>
        <index level1="Ishimoto, Baroness Shidzue"/>
        <index level1="Italy" level2="over-population and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="international"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Reception for opening of Clinic</head>
        <byline>M.S. remarks</byline>
        <p><person reg="Kato, Shidzue Ishimoto">Baroness Ishimoto</person>, and friends:</p>
        <p>I am very happy indeed to be in <place>Japan</place> again and to meet so many old
            friends. Some of them have been to <place reg="United States">America</place> and have
            visited us at our large <org reg="Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau">Demonstration
                Clinic</org> in <place reg="New York, NY">New York</place>, and other I met in 1922
            in Japan on my first visit. <del>So I feel</del> You all never seem to be any older.</p>
        <p>I, however, seem to be unfortunate in my visits to Japan. The first time I came with
            enthusiasm. I felt I had a message for the mothers of your country. I was not so
            hospitably received by your government. Nevertheless, the people, the mothers and the
            plain people, welcome me and gave me inspiration to carry this message on not only in
            Japan but throughout the Orient.</p>
        <p>On my second visit Japan was under martial law, and no meetings were allowed. This time
            on my way to <place>China</place> and <place reg="Manila, Philippines">Manila</place> I
            fell and broke my arm, and in view of the difficulty between China and Japan, I have
            decided to postpone my visit to China to another year.</p>
        <p>Every country has its pioneers. <place>England</place> had its <person
                reg="Wollstonecraft, Mary">Mary Wollencraft</person>, <place>France</place> its
                <person reg="Curie, Marie">Madame Curie</person>, America its <person
                reg="Anthony, Susan B.">Susan B. Anthony</person>. Many others, <person
                reg="Schreiner, Oliver">Oliver Shriner</person>, <person reg="Key, Ellen">Ellen
                Key</person> of the <place reg="Scandinavia">Scandinavian countries</place>; every
            country has men who pioneer in their line and women in others, and Japan should be
            proud, and I believe her children’s children will pay homage to one of the greatest
            women today, to Baroness Ishimoto, for Baroness Ishimoto is not only a pioneer in Japan,
            but also a <person reg="Polo, Marco">Marco Polo</person> of Japan, because thru her
            lectures and speaking to thousands and thousands of people from East to West and North
            to South, carries the message of Japan. I consider Baroness Ishimoto as really a bridge
            between Japan and the United States, brining the message of what you are doing here, and
            what we are doing there. We need many friends, both of our countries need friends. We
            need friends, and Japan needs friends in America because the world is going thru a
            chaotic, difficult time of uncertainty. Japan in particular is going thru a difficult
            time. She is one of the most overpopulated countries in the world, and it is my sincere
            belief that Japan like other countries will never solve her own problems, the problems
            of her internal relations and international relations, until she can solve her
            population problem. And population does not involve only the question of food, of rice
            and wheat and other things we eat; it concerns itself with the quality and the kind of
            people that are being brought into the world to carry on the destiny of your nation. You
            are not going to bring up the highest intelligence if you will multiply too rapidly
            because a rapid multiplication has always demonstrated that as we multiply to quickly we
            level down, but as we control our numbers and our rate of growth, we evolve to a higher
            destiny.</p>
        <p>I have great sympathy with the present situation in Japan because I know it differs from
                <place>Italy</place>. Italy is one of the greatest sinners before the Court of
            Justice. She has boosted her families by placing medals on the breasts of the fathers
            (not the mothers, note!); and in <supplied resp="MSPP">boasting</supplied> the size of
            her families she has brought upon the people greater problems to be solved by her future
            generations than can be met by her present generations. She is heaping up huge debts for
            unborn generations to meet.</p>
        <p>Japan, on the other hand, has been increasing</p>
        <p>It has been the momentum of a people that has carried on for many generations. I believe
            that your birth rate is now going down, and you will have eventually a quality
            population, and you will begin like low birth rate countries to strive for higher
            standards of living, and for peace with all the nations of the world. And someday you
            will look at this great program of peace and happiness and welfare, and see that we owe
            the beginnings to this group and to Baroness Ishimoto.</p>
        <p>And you--my friends, have a spiritual responsibility, here. You can’t believe in this and
            not support it. You cannot stand idly by and let Baroness Ishimoto and a small group do
            all the work. That can’t be done. You have a spiritual responsibility to lead the way,
            and use your intelligence and your ideals, and to try to bring them into realization. I
            think the way the birth control movement is being conducted in Japan is a wise and
            constructive way. Baroness Ishimoto has had a hard hill to climb. She needs your help
            and she needs our help because birth control is not a national problem only, but an
            international one, and we who belong to this civilization must all help each other. Her
            fight is our fight and she will need assistance from us all to send midwives into the
            homes and help those mothers who cannot come out; and to take to them the message of
            peace and hope, and give them the possibility of spacing their children and having only
            the number of children that they can decently support and take care of. This will be the
            great patriot of the future, who will be the great patriot of the future, who will be of
            benefit not only to her own nation but to the civilization of the world.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
