<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Autograph draft article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2003/05/29 JA</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/20 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007/06/15 CH Oxygen cleanup</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/03/05 EK cleanup regs</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/03/27/EK correct proofs</prepDate>

        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1915-02-00">
            <supplied resp="MSPP">February 1915</supplied>
        </docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>An Englishman's Opinion of America</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp128064</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
            <bibl>LCM 129:155</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp>
                <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
                <name id="SANMA">Sanger, Margaret</name>
            </resp>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>A revised paragraph added on a separate page has been inserted into this
            transcription.</p>
        <index level1="England" level2="views of America"/>
        <index level1="World War I" level2="U.S. Entry"/>
        <index level1="World War I" level2="anti-war efforts"/>
        <index level1="racial ethnic references" level2="to Irish"/>
        <index level1="racial ethnic references" level2="to Dutch"/>
        <index level1="racial ethnic references" level2="to Germans"/>
        <index level1="racial ethnic references" level2="to Germans"/>
        <index level1="France" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="England" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="gender roles and"/>
        <index level1="Europe" level2="travel in"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>An Englishman's Opinion of America</head>
        <p>"<q who="UNK">The Americans will do anything for money</q>" said a gray haired well
            dressed Englishman as he sat in conversation at the table on a boat going from <place
                reg="Folkestone, England">Folkstone</place> to <place reg="Bolougne, France"
                >Bolougne</place> a few weeks ago.</p>
        <p>"<q who="UNK ">Yes</q>" said his companion a young Dutchman just returned from the Dutch
            Indies. "<q who="UNK ">They care not who their bullets kill <del>if</del>
                <add>so</add> they get paid for them</q>." <add>I <del>had</del> sat across from
                them half listening to their conversation, but these words aroused my interest &amp;
                    <supplied resp="MSPP">curiosity.</supplied></add> "<q who="SANMA ">Could I
                trouble you <del>for</del> to pass the sugar</q>" said I--determined if possible to
            enter that conversation in which my country-men were being so outrageously slandered.
            This opened the way for a few further remarks &amp; a most interesting conversation
            followed.</p>
        <p>The Englishman boasted that he was as familiar with <place reg="New York, NY">New
                York</place> as with <place reg="London, England">London</place>, in fact he said he
            knew us well. Here are some of the things he knew about us.</p>
        <p>Americans were a "<q who="UNK">mixed breed</q>" "<q who="UNK ">without a soul</q>"--they
            have none of the qualities which make a nation great. They have no traditions, no
            history, no art, no music--nothing, absolutely nothing but their money-- Why they have
            to come to <place>Europe</place> for everything they have. They come to
                <place>England</place> for their laws, customs &amp; morals. To
                <place>France</place> for their fashions &amp; art, why they are human leeches on
            Europe without incentive, originality or creative ability-- They---</p>
        <p>I was getting just about "<del>filled</del>
            <add>fed</add> up" as the English say and interrupted him with an impatient gesture. "<q
                who="SANMA">What grouch have you <del><supplied resp="MSPP">Allies</supplied></del>
                English got against Americans</q>" What do they want her to do? To come into the
            war? To plunge her people into a <del>war</del> bloody conflict for England for France?
            For <place>Russia</place>? </p>
        <p>"<q who="UNK">No</q>" said he "<q who="UNK">Not for England France or Russia but for
                    <place>Belgium</place>. <place reg="United States">America</place> signed that
                    <place reg="The Hague, The Netherlands">Hague</place> treaty with the rest of us
                &amp; she has not stood by it</q>."</p>
        <p>"Perhaps <del>Uncle Sam</del><add>she</add> is too busy protecting these huge Belgian
            interests in <place>Mexico</place>" I suggested.</p>
        <p>"<q who="UNK">Yes there you are again,</q>" he turned to his Dutch friend,"<q who="UNK"
                >now they will neither go into Mexico themselves or allow any other power to go
                in--well their day is coming thats all I can say -- and personally -- I hope if the
                    <person reg="Kaiser Wilhelm II of Germany">Kaiser</person> does win this war
                that his next move will be to clean up America &amp; I tell you there's many an
                Englishman who'll shoulder a rifle to help him do it."</q></p>
        <p>At this last vindictive stroke against America all my Irish <del>atavism against England
                surged <add>leaped</add> for expression</del> blood arose in protest. "<q
                who="SANMA">I believe you," I said calmly, "England has always tried to crush those
                who would not do her bidding those who would not pull the chestnuts out of the fire
                for her -- Let us look at the situation in America more closely. You say you know
                America well -- then I do not have to tell you that the Irish population in America
                have not crossed the seas &amp; left their homes in <place>Ireland</place> because
                of their love of England or their loyalty to her. The Irish form a very powerful
                portion of the American population. The Russian &amp; Polish Jews also rate high in
                USA and no one has heard of their love of Siberia or their devotion to the despotic
                Russian <person reg="Czar Nicholas II of Russia">Czar</person>.</q></p>
        <p><q who="SANMA">Next comes the Germans who also form a large percentage of our population,
                and <del>who</del><add>which</add> of all foreigners coming into USA is the best
                equipped both physically &amp; mentally. When <place>Germany</place> sends out her
                adult population into other countries -- that adult at once becomes an asset to his
                adopted country, he is educated, mentally drilled for a commercial life with such
                qualities as accuracy, thoroughness memory, etc etc to say nothing of the knowledge
                of trades &amp; mechanical ability-- <add>For this training &amp; equipment &amp;
                    education Germany as a state has had to pay for &amp; for which she gets no
                    returns. Other countries send into other countries only the lowest element which
                    she can not use &amp; which becomes an increased expense to the adopted country
                    often from physical &amp; mental defect.</add> In foreign countries like
                    <place>Spain</place>, <place>Italy</place>, France where they seldom speak
                English it was the German who helped build up English <add>&amp; foreign</add> trade
                in all these countries through their great ability for languages. In France one
                finds the English speaking hair dresser, barber, hotel clerk, manager, etc etc
                nearly always a German and one feels it keenly today in <place reg="Paris, France"
                    >Paris</place> -- as the Germans <del>speaking English</del> are all
                interned.</q></p>
        <p>"<q who="SANMA">In every trade &amp; walk of life it was the German who helped translate.
                On the other hand the English have not learned foreign languages either. It was
                always the German as waiters, porters, clerks in hotels in London &amp; other large
                cities who welcomed the foreign guest in England &amp; helped to make his visit
                profitable to England. The <org>Commercial School of Liverpool</org> gives a record
                of salesmen going into Spain who were able to speak the Spanish language. There were
                six Englishmen -- ten Frenchmen and sixty-four Germans."</q></p>
        <p>"<q who="SANMA">It is the German who has helped to commercialize as well as to
                Internationalize the world."</q></p>
        <p>The Englishman leaned back in his chair with a would be superior smile on his lips, but I
            had the floor &amp; I intended to hold it for a time.</p>
        <p>"<q who="SANMA">In fact when one sums up the situation in America we find the Irish are a
                power politically the Jews a power financially while the German in the commercial
                &amp; industrial force upon which <del>all</del>
                <add>the</add> other <add>two</add> powers depend."</q></p>
        <p>"<q who="SANMA">Just what percentage these three nationalities are of the American
                population I cannot say, but I would venture that 60% would not be far from the
                mark. All of these three nationalities are <del>naturally</del> by nature against
                two of the Allies -- the third ally, France, perhaps they all love."</q></p>
        <p>"<q who="UNK">I see</q>," replied my antagonist, "<q who="UNK">That you are one of those
                Americans who hate England. Can you tell me just why England is so hated in America
                while France with different customs, a different language is so much liked."</q></p>
        <p><q who="SANMA">"I have my opinions on that subject,"</q> I answered, <q who="SANMA">but
                first I want to say I am not one of the Americans who hate England, but I'm Irish,
                with all the Irish atavisms <add>of my forefathers</add> in my blood-- I have spent
                the best part of a year in England amongst English people &amp; never have I had
                such charming hospitality and loyalty to my work, as <del>the</del> many of the
                English people gave me. I count many of them among my dearest friends &amp;
                    <del>claim that English</del>, nevertheless I do not think that England or any
                other country in the world should be 'swallowed whole.'"</q></p>
        <p><q who="SANMA">As to the hatred of England &amp; the love of France in America I frankly
                acknowledge I believe that feeling exists. I beleive too it can be traced back to
                out school days to our early history lessons, for we cannot teach history of America
                without telling the facts &amp; the facts were that England was our enemy &amp;
                France was our only friend -- France has always stood in the eyes of Americans as
                standing for 'liberty, equality &amp; fraternity.' While England has stood for
                oppression &amp; cunning &amp; cruelty.</q>"</p>
        <p>"<q who="UNK">Damnable outrage</q>," shouted our friend as <del>he leaped from his
                chair</del>
            <add>his hand</add>came down <add>on the table</add>. "<q who="UNK">Well the shoe is on
                the other foot just now while England is compelled to borrow their filthy dollars,
                but it won't be <del>for</del> long before they'll come begging England's protection
                against <place>Japan</place>. Where do you think England will stand then?</q>"</p>
        <p>"<q who="SANMA">Just where she always stands"</q> I said. <q who="SANMA">Where her
                biggest interests lie <add>like friendships loves &amp; hatreds</add> honor,
                liberty, freedom, treaties go up in smoke with England as well as
                    <del>all</del><add>with</add> other countries when moneyed interests are at
                stake."</q></p>
        <p>He did not deny this but turned to his Dutch friend &amp; said "<q who="UNK">Its a fact
                -- the American nation has no soul. Why the Press has sold itself to the highest
                bidder-- One million dollars was paid by the allies to one of the New York dailies
                (mentioning the name) while Germany has thrown a few crumbs to one or two other
                papers <add>to advance her cause</add>.</q></p>
        <p><q who="UNK"> They have no opinions or principles which can not be bought.</q>" This last
            assertion he flung out with a contemptuous laugh. It was my turn now to address the
            Dutchman so I turned to him trying to ignore for the present the insulting remarks of
            his English friend.</p>
        <p>"I understood your friend said he knew Americans -- well fortunately he does not speak for
            <del>the</del> England, but as an individual who has some personal bitterness which seems to have
            infected the blood of a few patriotic Englishmen lately &amp; caused their usual sense
            of fairness to be poisoned. I deny that American is soulless. I deny that <del>she
                can</del> her principle &amp; opinions can be bought &amp; sold--anymore than any
            other country--</p>
        <p>Does Freedom of Speech or Freedom of the Press exist in England today?  Does the opinion
            expressed in Englands press today represent the English people or does it represent
            English Capital? The American people are far too generous to be soulless.</p>
        <p><del>Had they</del> There exists among them the simple generosity of all great republics--  The generosity &amp; good will which
            induced France to <del>help</del> advance a tremendous war loan to Russia &amp; for
            which the blood of France is being spilled today to protect.</p>
        <p>American people are just the same -- they are opposed to war but through the guile of a war
            loan to England they will be -- like France -- dragged into a similar war to protect that
            loan--  England's diplomacy is clever -- Ill admit.  I only regret that the American people
            are not awakened to its subtleness.</p>
        <p>"<q who="UNK">Yes, great generosity--5½%</q>" laughed the older man. We all arose from
            the table as the tea had ended and as the Englishman preceeded me up the stairs to the
            deck, his friend the Dutchman called me aside in the dining room &amp; spoke to me in
            low &amp; anxious tones.</p>
        <p>"<q who="UNK ">I did not want totake part in the conversation with you &amp; my friend because I
                know not the American people but will you tell me, is it true that the husbands of
                the women in your country -- in America -- bathe &amp; dress the babies &amp; wash the
                dishes while the woman is attending suffrage meetings?</q>"</p>
        <p>I was overcome with laughter but tried to assume a serious attitude.</p>
        <p>"<q who="SANMA">Certainly,</q>" said I, "<q who="SANMA">That's the only difference in the
                English<del>men</del><add>husband</add> &amp; the American husband. The latter <del>uses
            up his</del> demonstrates his affection for his wife by 'walloping' the pots &amp; pans while
            the former 'wallops"his wife."</q></p>
        <p>"<q who="UNK">Oh but that is terrible</q>," said the Dutchman as we ascended the stairs
            together, "<q who="UNK">and very very serious.</q>"</p>
        <p>I saw them later <add>on the train to Paris </add>, talking together and I felt quite
            certain that the Dutchman <del>had</del> was now ready to believe anything about
            Americans, since the men "bathed the babies &amp; washed the dishes."</p>
        <byline>Margaret H. Sanger</byline>
    </docBody>
</doc>
