<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Draft Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011-11-09 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-26 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1929-03-15">15 March 1929</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied>Symposium on Birth Control</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp128004</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
            <bibl>Library of Congress Microfilm 129:44</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="SACSA">Sachs, Sadie</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
            <name id="POPAL">Pope, Alexander</name>
            <name id="CRAFR">Crane, Frederick</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Sanger spoke at a <org>Symposium on Birth Control</org>, held at the
                <org>Hotel Brevoort</org> in <place reg="New York, NY">New York City</place>,
            sponsored by the <org>Eastern Medical Society</org>. Other participants were <person
                reg="Dickinson, Robert Latou">Robert Latou Dickinson</person>, <person
                reg="Stone, Hannah Mayer">Hannah Stone</person>, <person reg="Mudd, Stuart">Stuart
                Mudd</person>, <person reg="Romney, A. J.">A. J. Romney</person>, <person
                reg="Brill, Abraham Arden">A. A. Brill</person>, and <person
                reg="Knopf, S. Adolphus">S. Adolphus Knopf</person>. Sanger told her son <person
                reg="Sanger, Grant">Grant</person> in a March 16, 1929, letter that her speech
            attracted so many attendees that there were "over 600 doctors turned away."</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="history of"/><index
            level1="Brownsville Clinic" level2="arrests and trial"/><index
            level1="Sachs, Sadie (story)"/><index level1="Town Hall raid"/><index
            level1="birth control" level2="in New York"/><index level1="England"
            level2="birth control in"/><index level1="Netherlands" level2="birth control in"/><index
            level1="Netherlands, the" level2="MS in"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"/><index
            level1="Sanger, Margaret" level3="exile, 1914-15"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head><add>Medical Meeting NYC</add></head>
        <dateline><date value="1929-00-00">1929</date></dateline>
        <p>
            <person reg="Cohen, Harry">Dr. Cohen</person>
            <add>Pres of Eastern Medical Society</add> has <emph rend="underline">honored</emph> me
            by asking me <del>to speak here tonight. He has suggested that I give</del>
            <add>to</add>you a brief history of the <emph rend="underline">Birth Control Movement in
                America</emph>. It is an interesting fact, of which few people are aware, that the
            person who <add>first</add>gave the greatest impetus and the most important contribution
            to the Birth Control Movement both in <place>England</place> and <place
                reg="United States">America</place> was not only an <emph>American</emph>, but a
                <emph>physician</emph>. Dr. <person reg="Knowlton, Charles">Charles
                Knowlton</person> of <place reg="Boston, MA">Boston, Mass</place>. wrote his “<title
                type="book">Fruits of Philosophy</title>” in 1832, <add>almost <emph>100</emph>
                years ago.</add> This booklet circulated the globe <add>English-speaking
            world</add>for 40 years before it challenged conventional thought and puritanical
            bigotry. Finally, in <emph>1878</emph>, <add>in</add><place>Bristol, England</place>, an
            arrest was made and the contents of the booklet were decreed <emph rend="underline"
                >obscene</emph>. <person reg="Besant, Annie">Annie Besant</person> and <person
                reg="Bradlaugh, Charles">Charles Bradlaugh</person> refused to accept the
            magistrate’s verdict in the case. <del>and</del> In the name of freedom of the press
                <add>they</add>took the case to a higher court and won a victory that enabled the
            Birth Control Movement to advance and expand <del>without legal obstruction</del> until
            the present day.</p>
        <p>When I came upon the horizon <del>of the Birth Control Movement</del> in
                191<del>9</del><add>4</add>, I knew nothing of Knowlton or of the fight that Besant
            and Bradlaugh had made. <add>I thought I had made discovery. Childhood
            influence.</add></p>
        <p>As a trained nurse working for many years in and around this city among all classes of
            people, I was constantly requested by women to tell them what could be done to avoid
            further and undesired pregnancies. <del>I a</del><add>A</add>lthough a mother of three
            children myself, <add>I</add>had the usual negative attitude in this
                matter<del>,</del><add>.</add>
            <del>until I was</del>
            <del>f</del><add>F</add>inally I was brought face to face with the question--
                <del>When</del> A <person reg="Sachs, Sadie">woman</person> whom the doctor and I
            had brought out of the Valley of the Shadow, asked us to tell her what she could do to
            prevent getting into a pregnant condition again. The <person reg="Unknown"
                >doctor</person> joked and ironically suggested that her <person reg="Sachs, Jake"
                >husband</person>
            <add>“</add><q who="UNK">sleep on the roof</q>.<add>”</add> She turned to me and
            pleaded, “<q who="SACSA">you are a woman, you understand, you will tell me won’t
            you</q>”? But I too turned away and left her to her fate.</p>
        <p>Three months later I was called to take this case again. This feeble and distressed and
            agonized woman had turned to someone <del><unclear>else</unclear></del> to help her
            terminate her pregnancy. It was fatal. I arrived too late.</p>
        <p>I saw the three little children bundled off by kindly social workers to an orphan’s home.
            I saw the husband, bewildered and stunned by this tragic happening, made homeless and
            helpless in his plight.</p>
        <p>The panorama of <del>one social</del>
            <add>one social</add>life seemed to pass before my eyes<add>.</add>
            <del>and</del> I saw as never before the vast network of philanthropic institutions
            erected for the maintenance and upkeep of human beings, whose fate was intimately bound
            up with ignorance of the knowledge of contraception.</p>
        <p>I returned to my home that hot midnight in July and as I looked out over the housetops of
            this city and watched the dawn come up I knew a new day was dawning for me as well as
            for all womankind.</p>
        <p>I announced to my family that I was through with all palliative work. I would nurse no
            more--I would never take another case until knowledge to prevent conception was
            available and accessible to the mothers of the poor. But “<q who="POPAL">fools go where
                angels fear to tread</q>”. I had no knowledge of the task I had set myself to do. I
                <add>first</add>started out to <del>invade</del>
            <add>search</add> the medical libraries <add>for practical information.</add> It was a
            shock and surprise to find almost nothing available for practical purposes. I went to
                <place reg="Boston, MA">Boston</place> and then to <place>Washington, D.C.</place>,
            even to the <org reg="Library of Congress">Congressional library</org>. I employed
                <add>French &amp; German</add>translators to help me. But after an almost fruitless
            search <add>of several months</add>I decided to go to <place>France</place> and there I
            got <add>Knowlton's Pamphlets &amp;</add>information sufficiently practical to <add>help
                me</add>start a challenge to <add><name type="law"
                    reg="United States Criminal Code, Section 211">Sec 211</name> of</add>the
            Federal law. <add>name birth control not limitation</add></p>
        <p>It was just about 100 years before this, <del>when</del>
            <add>that</add>the possibilities of a controlled population first seized the minds and
            imaginations of the Anglo-Saxon world<add>.</add>
            <del>that</del> Pioneers like <person reg="Mill, John Stuart">John Stuart Mill</person>
            and <person reg="Place, Francis">Francis Place</person> scattered <del>millions</del>
            <add>thousands</add>of leaflets from the housetops of tenements to the tenants below.
            These leaflets contained information how and why the size of the family could be
            controlled. The leaflet was known as the “<title type="book">Diabolical
            Handbill</title>.”</p>
        <p>These pioneers, like Besant and Bradlaugh <add>half a century later,</add>believed in the
            magic of the printed word and thought that all that was necessary was to distribute the
            printed leaflets to the masses and the results would be achieved.</p>
        <p>Experience is a <del><unclear resp="MSPP">bitter</unclear></del><add>wise</add> teacher.
            I too believed that the working men and women should have pamphlets made available for
            their demand. I decided to challenge the Federal law which had been instigated by
                <person reg="Comstock, Anthony">Anthony Comstock</person> forty years before. It
            seemed to me it was entirely a question of the printed word and of freedom of the press.
            That was during 1912 to 1914-- (<del><gap extent="one word"/></del>). Then I went to
                <place reg="Netherlands">Holland</place> in 1915 and studied the technique of
            contraception under Dr. <person reg="Rutgers, Johannes">Rutgers</person> of <place
                reg="Hague, Netherlands">the Hague</place>. I had spent a year in <place
                reg="London, England">London</place> in study under the guidance and direction that
            wise and venerable man <person reg="Ellis, Havelock">Havelock Ellis</person>.</p>
        <p>After Holland--I became convinced that leaflets, pamphlets, books were not the medium
            through which overburdened mothers could be educated in Birth Control. That only by
            scientific instruction received from competent physicians and nurses in clinics
            established for that purpose and for that purpose alone <add>could the best results be
                achieved</add>. When in 1916 <add>after my involuntary exile</add> I returned to
            this country <del>after my involuntary exile</del>the idea of clinics was central in my
            mind. It seemed to me that here at last was the practical solution to the
                problem<del>,</del><add>--</add><del> vis.</del>contraceptive instruction <add>to
                be</add>given by the medical profession in <del>their</del> public or private
            practice <del>and</del>
            <add>as well as</add>clinics for the poor whose social or economic status would not
            bring them into the realm of the profession otherwise.</p>
        <p>I did not realize the gigantic obstacles to overcome before that idea could be converted
            into reality. Nevertheless, I plunged into activity. My free speech friends refused to
            help me <add>further</add>because I had now insisted that the medical profession must
            give <add>this</add>advice--That we must win their support, ask that they take over the
            entire responsibilities of woman’s reproductive problems.</p>
        <p>I abandoned the Federal fight after my case was dismissed. (having been indicted on nine
            charges) and established a clinic in the Brownsville section of <place
                reg="Brooklyn, NY">Brooklyn</place>. This was for the purpose of testing the <name
                type="law" reg="New York State Penal Code, Section 1142">New York State law Section
                1142</name>. I knew that <name type="law"
                reg="New York State Penal Code, Section 1145">Section 1145</name> existed but no
            physician could be found who cared to test the validity of the law. In the meantime and
            before I had reached the decision of opening the <org>Brownsville clinic</org>-- I,
            together with two social workers, took two women, one suffering from tuberculosis, and
            the other from syphilis, to every hospital in New York and Brooklyn to ask for
            contraceptive advice. In every instance the most courteous consideration was given us,
            offers made to treat the ailment<add>s</add>of <del>the</del>
            <add>both</add>women, but in all but one case, every hospital refused to give
            instruction to prevent conception. That one agreed only because the social worker was
            known to the doctors in charge. <add>(loose Charter)</add></p>
        <p><del>The <add>average</add>physician did not interpret Section 1145 as his right to give
                such advice, especially in his public practice.</del> Because of this
                <del>confusion</del>
            <add>refusal by Hospitals</add>, I opened the Brownsville clinic and within ten days no
            less than 488 mothers crowded into our limited quarters. Then the police decended upon
            us, closed our precious clinic, and called it a “public nuisance”. In Holland it was
            called a public utility. I was convicted and carried the case to the <org
                reg="New York State Court of Appeals">Court of Appeals</org>. In 1918 a decision was
            handed down to us, justifying my conviction, but stating that “<q who="CRAFR">physicians
                lawfully practicing are permitted to give contraceptive advice for the cure or
                prevention of disease</q>.” This was our first technical victory and the first
                <add>legal</add>interpretation of the law, which cleared the atmosphere for the
            medical profession and for us all. The first <org
                reg="American Birth Control Conference, 1st">National Conference</org> was held in
            New York in 1921. It was then that the fruits of the preceding years matured and <add>be
                it her</add> to the honor of the scientists, <del>for</del>
            <add>biologists, economists that they had the</add>courage and fearlessness
                <add>to</add><del>who</del> stand staunchly behind us through all the
                ordeal<add>s</add><add>from</add><del>of</del> the <org>Town Hall</org> episode to
            the present day.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless the situation presented itself that while the physicians <add>now</add>had
            the power to <emph rend="underline">give</emph>
            <add>contraceptive</add>advice they were very confused and skeptical as to the
            efficiency of such methods as were available and known. <add>No literature, few devices
                available. Federal law. <place>Europe</place>.</add>It was important to collect and
            correlate the facts as to methods now in use.</p>
        <p><add>In 1923</add>a <org reg="Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau">Research
                Bureau</org> was established <del>in [illegible]</del> with a physician in charge.
            We have now investigated over 13000 cases and an analysis of their histories is being
            made. We have seven physicians on our staff, 5 nurses as well as a social worker and an
            assistant to do follow-up work when necessary.</p>
        <p><add>Dr.</add><person reg="Cooper, James Freyer">Cooper</person>’s book-- <add>published
                &amp; available </add><del><unclear resp="MSPP">gone</unclear> into 10,000</del> for
            profession.</p>
        <p>26 clinics in U.S.A.</p>
        <p>$150,000 lately bequeathed to <org reg="Los Angeles Mothers' Clinic"><place
                    reg="Los Angeles, CA">Los Angeles</place> clinic</org>.</p>
        <p>500 physicians visited <org>New York clinic</org>. <add>10,000 expressed interest &amp;
                solicited information</add></p>
        <p><del>Medical Societies and Universities discussing subject.</del></p>
        <p><add>4 supply houses.</add>
        </p>
        <p>The Birth Control clinic does not aim to compete with other social agencies. It does not
            act as a substitute, but it <add>must</add> precede almost every social program and
                <del>must</del> serve it as a base. Birth Control is not merely a medical question.
            It is a fundamental human need effecting every adult life. It affects also the lives of
            all children born in America, <add>it affects</add>
            <del>all the</del> our future <del>of</del> civilization. But perhaps more important of
            all it <del>is</del> fundamentally <del>a</del>
            <add>affects the</add> woman<del>’s problems</del><add>, especially poor women.</add>
            And because of the <add>my</add>knowledge of woman’s needs <add>as a woman &amp; a
                mother</add>, I entered the movement as a representative and protagonist of the
            overburdened women of this country. It is as a supplicant representative of womanhood as
            well as of motherhood that I appeal to you, the members of the most understanding and
            philanthropic profession of the world to aid us in our battle for a conscious and
            voluntary motherhood and the creation of a new <add>emancipated</add>
            <del>race of thoroughbred children</del>.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
