<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2003-07-07 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/03/04 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/23 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007/06/25 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011-11-30 CH typos</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/12-10 EK clean regs, correct proof</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1916-04-00">
            <supplied resp="MSPP">Apr-July 1916</supplied>
        </docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>
                <supplied resp="MSPP">Condemnation is Misunderstanding</supplied>
            </titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp128003</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
            <bibl>LCM 129:32</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp id="MSPP">MSPP</resp>
            <name id="SACSA">Sachs, Sadie"</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>This draft was used by <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger</person> in her <place
                reg="United States">U.S. </place>national speaking tour in 1916. Emendations to the
            text were made by handwritten by Margaret Sanger. Entire paragraphs struck out, most
            likely for shortening the speech have not been deleted from this version. For a similar
            speeches see <title type="speech">"Birth Control"</title><xref from="128002"
            >1916</xref>, and <title type="speech">Chicago Address to Women</title>, <xref
                from="236132.xml">Apr.-May 1916</xref>.</p>
        <p>A handwritten note added by MS at bottom of document reads: <q>Notes of first lecture
                tattered &amp; torn but delivered to many thousands</q></p>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="biography"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="speaking tours, 1916 (United States)"/>
        <index level1="Sachs, Sadie"/>
        <index level1="abortion" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="class-based"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="morality of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="socio-economic benefits of"/>
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Comstock Laws"/>
        <index level1="birth control clinics and leagues" level2="in the Netherlands"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, William" level2="arrest and trial of"/>
        <index level1="Woman Rebel, The" level2="legal case"/>
        <index level1="Family Limitation"/>
        <index level1="censorship"/>
        <index level1="labor movement" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="labor movement" level2="strikes"/>
        <index level1="mentally diseased and challenged" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="mentally diseased and challenged" level2="fertility of"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="infant" level3="in France"/>
        <index level1="England" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Europe" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="France" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="free speech and free press"/>
        <index level1="Germany" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Netherlands, the" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="physicians" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="enslavement of"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="freedom and rights of"/>
        <index level1="working classes" level2="women and girls"/>
        <index level1="United States Post Office"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>
            <add>Condemnation is misunderstanding</add>
        </head>
        <p>There have always been two dominant weapons which the powers of authority have used to
            beat back progress and civilization-–blasphemy, obscenity.</p>
        <p>Nearly every great discovery which is to day benefitting mankind was at the time of its
            discovery considered <del>either</del> blasphemous <del>or</del>
            <add>&amp;</add> obscene.</p>
        <p><del>It is only three hundred years ago that</del>
            <add>Take for instance</add>
            <person reg="Harvey, William">Harvey</person>s treatise on the circulation of the blood
            was considered blasphemous and wicked. One hundred years later <person
                reg="Edward Jenner">Jenner</person>s vaccination theory which has to day practically
            wiped out small pox was held to be a violation of the laws of God and nature. While only
            within the last half century <person reg="Pasteur, Louis">Pasteur</person>s germ theory
            was repudiated with the most bitter animosity by both Church and State.</p>
        <p>These and numerous other new ideas which are being advanced to day for the good of the
            many, have had and still do have to fight for their very existence against a blind and
            unintelligent prejudice.</p>
        <p>Nor has it been only scientific pioneering which has won the enmity of authority. The
            champions of political and religious liberty have endured persecutions that we look back
            upon with shame and horror. Yet we have learned very little from the experience of the
            past. For we stand to day in the midst of a fight for moral freedom–-the pivot of which
            is Birth <supplied>control</supplied> and find that we have left in the hands of our
            rulers and censors the same power of persecution, which is being exercised as
            mercilessly as at any time in the past.</p>
        <p><add>The fight for free discussion good for <unclear>other</unclear> freedoms.</add> The
            political and religious fights are over in America, but THE MORAL Fight HAS JUST BEGUN.
            ↑The fight for free discussion goes on </p>
        <p>The early revolutionists settled the first point with <place>England</place> and won for
            us the right to discuss the political question without danger of imprisonment. This did
            not give us the right to either religious or moral discussion, and not until <person
                reg="Ingersoll, Robert G.">Ingersoll</person> challenged the blasphemy laws of this
            country, and UNDERMINED their power by coming in direct contact with the people where
            the blasphemy laws made a <supplied>dead</supplied> letter and later set aside from the
            statute books of this country.</p>
        <p>
            <add>This great need has come because</add>
        </p>
        <p>And now today with women out in the industrial field working side by side with their
            brothers in the worlds work, a new demand has come forth to revise the old moral
            standards and to discuss the moral question. Freedom to discuss the moral question is
            fully as important to day, as the political and religious questions were in their
            time–the three issues are EPOCH MAKING IN THE PROGRESS OF EVERY CIVILIZED COUNTRY.</p>
        <p>
            <add><supplied>Woman</supplied> had nothing to say Politics or religion</add>
        </p>
        <p>The moral issue is the greatest concern to woman. For centuries she has gone forth with
            man to till the fields to feed and clothe the nations. She has sacrificed her life to
            populate the earth SHE HAS OVERDONE HER LABORS-– She now steps forth and demands that
            women shall cease producing in ignorance. To do this she must have knowledge to control
            birth. This is the first immediate step she must take toward the goal of her freedoms.
            It is also the first immediate step <del>the working class</del> must <del>take
                    <add>this country</add> toward the goal of its emancipation.</del>
            <add>preserve nation</add> .</p>
        <p>Those who are opposed to this are simply those who do not know. Any one who like myself,
            has worked among the people, and found on the one hand an ever increasing population,
            with its ever increasing misery poverty and ignorance, and on the other hand a
            stationary or decreasing population with its INCREASING wealth higher standards of
            living, greater freedom, joy and happiness, can not doubt that <del>BIRTH CONTROL</del>
            <add>v.m <supplied>(Voluntary motherhood)</supplied></add> is the livest issue of the
            day upon which depends the future welfare of the race.</p>
        <p>Before I attempt to refute the arguments against Birth Control, I should like to tell you
            something of the conditions I met with as a trained nurse which convinced me of its
            necessity, and led me to jeopardize my liberty in order to place this information into
            the hands of the women who need it.</p>
        <p><add>Challenge Federal laws</add>.</p>
        <p>Far back in my early childhood days, my first impression of life was that large families
            and poverty went hand in hand. I was born and brought up in a glass factory town in the
            western part of <place>New York</place> State. I was one of 11 children, so that I had
            some personal knowledge of the struggle and hardships a large family endured. </p>
        <p>When I was seventeen years old my <person reg="Higgins,Anne Purcell">mother</person> died
            from overwork and the strain of too frequent child bearing, which left me with several
            younger children to share the burdens with a lovely poetic Irish <person
                reg=" Higgins, Michael Hennessey">father</person>. A few years later I entered a
            hospital to take up the profession of nursing.</p>
        <p>There I found that 75% of the diseases of men and women were the results of ignorance of
            their sex functions. I found that every department of life was open to investigation and
            discussion, except that shaded valley of sex The explorer, scientist, inventor can go
            forth in their various fields for investigation and return to lay the fruits of their
            discoveries at the feet of society. But woe to him who dares explore that forbidden
            realm of sex. No matter how pure the motive, or what miseries he sought to remove,
            slanders, persecutions and jails awaits him who dares bare the light of knowledge into
            that cave of darkness.</p>
        <p>Have you ever stopped to think that all modern life in nearly all its departments has
            been greatly advanced or modified by electricity telegraph, telephone, but that nothing
            has been done to advance that most important of all departments, birth, sex of which we
            are as densely ignorant as were our primitive ancestors?</p>
        <p>So great was the ignorance among girls and women concerning their own bodies that
                <supplied>I</supplied> decided to specialized in woman diseases and took up
            gynecological and obstetrical nursing.</p>
        <p><del>A few years of this work gave me a shocking discovery--</del>
            <add>There I found</add> that knowledge to control birth was obtained and practiced
            among the women of wealth while the working women were deliberately kept in ignorance of
            this knowledge.</p>
        <p>I found that the women of wealth were able to have abortions performed on them if it
            became necessary, while such care and attention was given them that seldom did a death
            occur among them.</p>
        <p>I found that the women of the working class were as anxious to obtain this knowledge as
            their sisters of wealth, but were told that there are laws upon the statute books
            against imparting it to them, and the medical profession was most religious in obeying
            these laws when the patient was a poor woman.</p>
        <p>I found that the women of the working class had emphatic views on the Crime of bringing
            children into the world to die of hunger. They would rather risk their lives through
            abortion than give birth they could feed clothe and care for.</p>
        <p>It is not an uncommon thing to see a group of women forming in line out side a doctors
            office any evening after working hours between six - eight on the lower East Side of
                <place reg="New York, NY">New York City</place>. When I asked a patient what they
            were going there for, she replied simply "<q> TO GET RELIEF.</q>" To see these pale
            faced mothers, with their shawls drawn closely about their heads, their faces pinched
            and wan from overwork and worry, crowding FORWARD EAGER to face the tortures of
            abortion, rather than condemn an unborn child to poverty, to see this <del>makes</del>
            was enough to make ones blood boil with rage and indignation at the hypocritical silence
            of the medical profession who cater to the whims of the rich but ignore the TRAGEDY of
            the poor.</p>
        <p>A few simple words of advice to these women would have enabled them to avoid the horrible
            slaughter of abortion going on in this country to day.</p>
        <p>For the laws <add>stand today</add> against imparting this knowledge force these women
            into the hands of the filthiest midwives and cheapest quack abortionists (unless they
            bear unwanted children). With the consequences that the deaths from abortions are almost
            wholly among the women of the working class.</p>
        <p>NO OTHER country in the world has so large a number of abortions nor so large a number of
            deaths resulting there from as the <place reg="United States">UNITED STATES of
                AMERICA</place>. <del>The quacks and abortionists roll in wealth</del>--while our
            law makers close their VIRTUOUS EYES. <add>Discuss</add> among
                <unclear>friends</unclear></p>
        <p>A most conservative estimate is that there are <del>125000</del>
            <add>250000--1 million</add> abortions performed in US each year, with a death rate of
                    <add><unclear>25000</unclear></add>, or one out of every five cases.</p>
        <p>Again I found from records concerning the women of the underworld that 85% of them come
            from parents who average nine living children. And that 50% of these are found to be
            mentally defective.</p>
        <p>Many of them at the age of 22 or 23 years have a mentality of a child not over nine or
            ten years. CAN WE NOT SEE AT ONCE how difficult it is for this girl with an adult body
            and a childs intelligence to compete in the battle of life against the more intelligent
            and better born. <add>10000 feeble minded girls Institution</add></p>
        <p>We know too that the fertility of the mentally defective parent if our times as great as
            that of the normal parent. IS THIS NOT CAUSE FOR ALARM? IS it not time for our
            Physicians, Social workers and Scientists to face this array of facts, and stop
            quibbling over womans morality?</p>
        <p>I say this because it is these people who raise objections to BIRTH CONTROL advancing the
            argument that it MAY cause women to be come immoral.</p>
        <p>Solicitude for womans morals has ever been the cloak Authority has worn in its age long
            CONSPIRACY to keep her in bondage.</p>
        <p>When I was in <place>Spain</place> a year ago, I found that the Spanish woman was far
            behind her European sisters in readiness or even desire for modern freedom. Upon
            investigation as to the cause of this I was told that there are over 5000 villages and
            towns in Spain, with no means of transportation except donkeys over bridle paths. I was
            further told that all attempts to build roads or railroads into Spain had been met with
            the strongest opposition of the Clergy and the Government on the grounds that roads and
            railroads would make communication easy, thereby bringing the women of the country into
            the Cities WHERE THEY WOULD BECOME IMMORAL.</p>
        <p>Do we who have roads and railroads think that our women are less moral than the SPANISH
            woman? Certainly not. But we in this country are after all only just emerging from the
            fight for the higher education <del>for</del>
            <add>of</add> women, which met with the same objection a few years ago.</p>
        <p>
            <add>Razors &amp; matches knowledge can be abused</add>
        </p>
        <p>We know now that education has not done all the dreadful things to women that its
            opponents predicted were certain to result. And so shall we find that knowledge to
            control birth, which has been in the hands of the wealthy women of this country for the
            past 25 years, WILL NOT tend to lower their standards of morality. If the women of the
            upper class has withstood this test, is there any reason to suggest that the working
            woman will use it less wisely?</p>
        <p>Statistics show us that the birth rate of any quarter is in ratio to its wealth. And
            further give us figures to prove that in the large Cities the rich districts yield a
            birth rate a third of that of the poor districts. In <place reg="Paris, France"
                >Paris</place> for every 1000 women between the ages of 15 and 50 the poor districts
            yields 116 births and the rich districts 34 births. In <place reg="Berlin, Germany"
                >Berlin</place> conditions are approximately the same, for every 1000 women between
            the ages of 15 and 50 the poor district yields 157 births while the rich yield 47
            births. This applies also to <place reg="Vienna, Austria">Vienna</place>, <place
                reg="London, England">London</place>, New York and all the large cities the world
            over.</p>
        <p>It can be inferred from these figures that the women of wealth use means to control birth
            which is condemned when taught to the poor. BUT the MENACE to our Civilization the
            problem of the day is NOT the stationary birth rate among the upper classes SO much as
            the tremendous increase among the poor and diseased population of this country.</p>
        <p>Many of my friends will object to this statement, because it seems to clash with their
            economic theories. But there are always objections from some quarter. For every ideal
            born there is a <person>Herod</person> born to kill it</p>
        <p>It is difficult for me to understand how our advanced thinkers in the Labor organizations
            have attached so little importance to the question of birth control. To me it is by far
            the most important question they can touch upon. This propaganda should have gone hand
            in hand with labor organization for the past generation.</p>
        <p>
            <add>Child labor &amp; unemployed army--today</add>
        </p>
        <p>Workers are really nothing but a kind of merchandise at the mercy of the law of supply
            and demand. The man who offers himself, must be content with any wage. The man who wants
            workers must pay their price.</p>
        <p>In multiplying themselves workers become their own rivals. All work has a tendency to get
            overcrowded. Enforced idleness is the result. An army of STARVING workers present
            themselves at a reduced wage at the doors of the factories. A prolonged strike requires
            a reserve fund which the worker lacks. The strikers FIGHT AN UNEQUAL fight not only
            against their unfortunate brothers who are out of work and willing and anxious to take
            their abandoned jobs, but ALSO AGAINST their well nourished and well armed brothers--the
            soldiers--and police.</p>
        <p>
            <add>Because workers will never <unclear>advance></unclear>
                <gap extent="two words" reason="illegible"/> until BC</add>
        </p>
        <p>In SOCIAL conflicts the workers are beaten in ADVANCE by their numbers and fertility.
            They are beaten by their own children who are thrown on the labor marker thru their
            number. INNOCENT AND FRAGILE infants earn their own bread by starving their parents out
            of work, competing with them in the labor market.</p>
        <p>Factory and mill work by children is fast producing a generation of mental defectives
            among the working class, which fordooms future generations to a continued WAGE SLAVERY.
            The GREAT mass of men to day who cannot be organized or grasp the significance of
            organization are found to have a mentality NOT beyond that of a boy TWELVE years of
            age.</p>
        <p>Misery and Ignorance are not the least bit of use in the <del>revolutionary</del>
            <add>race</add> world. LET US STOP PRODUCING THEM.</p>
        <p>Aside from the economic question which has chiefly concerned the man. What about the
            woman? Is her health not to be considered? Is she to remain a producing machine? Is she
            to have no time to think to study and care for herself? Man CANNOT travel to his goal
            alone. And until woman has the knowledge to control birth, she cannot get the time to
            think and develop. Until she has the time to think, neither the Suffrage question nor
            the Social question nor the labor question will interest her, <del>and she will remain
                the drudge that she is and her husband the slave that he is just so long as they
                continue to supply the market with cheap labor <unclear>no free<unclear/> man can be
                    born of a slave mother</unclear></del></p>
        <p>It has ben my experience that a woman living on a wage of 10 dollars a week does not
            desire a large family. I have worked among thousands of them and have found them with
            five, six, eight and nine children and have never yet found one of them desire ANOTHER
            MOUTH TO FEED.</p>
        <p>ON THE CONTRARY I have found them in constant TERROR of another baby, and submitting to
            the agony of unwanted childbirth only because of ignorance.</p>
        <p>Let ME ASK YOU has the STATE any more right to ravish a woman against her will by keeping
            her in ignorance than a man has thru brute force? Has the State a better right to decide
            when she shall bear offspring?</p>
        <p>Picture a woman with five or six little ones living on the average working mans wage of
            ten dollars a week. ANOTHER baby is coming as fast as Nature can manage it. She is
            already old, broken in health and spirit a worn out shadow of the woman she once was.
            Where is the man or woman who would reproach me for trying to put into this womans hands
            knowledge to prevent giving birth to any more?</p>
        <p>Is this action on my part to be called immoral? Am I to be persecuted and classed as
            immoral because I advocate small families for the working class while Mr <person
                reg=" Roosevelt, Theodore">Roosevelt</person> can go up and down the length of the
            land shouting and urging this woman to have large families and is neither arrested nor
            molested, but considered by all society as highly moral.</p>
        <p>But I ask you which IS the More moral? To urge this class of women to have only those
            children she desires and can care for or to delude her into breeding cannon fodder for
            the munition makers and professional Jingoes? Which is America's definition of morality?
                <add>Last administration New Zealand women of France</add>.</p>
        <p>You will agree with me that a woman should be free. Yet no adult woman who is ignorant of
            the means to prevent conception, can call herself FREE.</p>
        <p>No woman can call herself FREE who cannot choose the time to be a mother or not as she
            sees fit. This should be woman's first demand. <del>And though this may scandalize some
                of the old-fashioned minds of the day, it should not be more shocking than the
                modern electrical devices in our homes, which certainly would have scandalized any
                of our great-grandmothers in their day.</del></p>
        <p>The facts are that WOMAN'S LIBERTY is shackled by the tyranny of the State, legal
            obstacles, ignorance and maternity. She may think that she can defy conventions and live
            free in her relations, all of which are purely a question of character and audacity in
            the individual woman. But the fact remains that she must have the knowledge to prevent
            conception if she is to remain free.</p>
        <p>I found that <add>For as</add> our present laws <add>are today</add> force woman into one
            of two ways, celibacy with its nervous results, or abortion. All modern physicians
            testify that both these conditions are harmful; that celibacy is the cause of many
            nervous complaints, while <emph rend="underline">abortion is a disgrace to a
                civilized</emph> community. Physicians claim that early marriage with knowledge to
            control birth would do away with both. For this would enable two young people to live
            and work together until such time as they could care for a family. I found that young
            people desire early marriage, were it not for the dread of a large family to
            support.</p>
        <p>
            <add>Why will not Society countenance &amp; advance this idea. Because it is afraid of
                the untried &amp; unknown. It would rather spend.</add></p>
        <p>I found these things and more--countless more. And what did I find that SOCIETY was doing
            to alter these conditions?</p>
        <p><del>Again</del> I <del>found</del>
            <add>saw</add> that fortunes were being spent in establishing Baby Nurseries, where new
            babies are brought and cared for while the mothers toil in sweatshops during the day. I
                <del>found</del>
            <add>saw</add> Charities establishing <org>Better Baby Leagues</org>--(not Fewer Baby
            Leagues.)</p>
        <p>I <del>found</del>
            <add>saw</add> that Society <del>and women alike</del> with all <del>their</del>
            <add>its</add> well intentioned palliatives, <del>are</del>
            <add>was</add> in this respect like the QUACK, who cures a cancer by burning off the
            top, while the deadly disease continues to spread underneath. I never felt this more
            strongly than I did three years ago, after the death of the patient in my last nursing
            case.</p>
        <p>This patient of mine was the wife of a struggling workingman--the mother of three
            children--who was suffering from the results of an attempted abortion performed upon her
            by herself. She lived on Grand Street, the Main Thoroughfare of New York's Downtown
            Ghetto. I found her in a very serious condition, and for three weeks both the attending
            physician and myself labored night and day to bring her OUT of The <emph
                rend="underline">VALLEY</emph> OF THE <emph rend="underline">SHADOW</emph> OF <emph
                rend="underline">DEATH</emph>. We finally succeeded in restoring her to her family
            circle.</p>
        <p>I remember well the day I was leaving. The physician, too, was making his last call. As
            the doctor put out his hand to say Good-bye, I saw the patient had something to say to
            him, but was timid and shy about saying it. I started to leave the room, but she called
            me back and said:</p>
        <p>"<q who="SACSA">Please don't go. How can both of you leave me without telling me what I
                can do to avoid another illness such as I have just passed through.</q>" I was
            interested to hear what the answer of the physician would be and I went and sat down
            beside her in expectation of hearing a sympathetic reply. To my amazement, he answered
            her lightly <add>&amp; jokingly put aside her question</add>.</p>
        <p>Three months later, I was aroused from my sleep at midnight. A telephone call from the
            husband of the same woman requested me to come immediately, as she was dangerously ill.
            I arrived to find her beyond relief. Another conception had forced her in to the hands
            of a cheap abortionist, and she died at four o'clock the same morning, leaving behind
            her three small children and a frantic, helpless husband. </p>
        <p>I returned home as the sun was coming up over the roofs of the Human Bee-Hive, and I
            realized how futile my efforts and my work had been. I, too, like the philanthropists
            and Social Workers, had been <emph rend="underline">dealing</emph> with the <emph
                rend="underline">symptoms</emph> rather than the <emph rend="underline"
                >disease</emph>. I threw my nursing bag into the corner and announced to my family
            that I would never take another case until <emph rend="underline">I had made it
                possible</emph> for <emph rend="underline">working women</emph> in AMERICA to have
            the KNOWLEDGE OF BIRTH CONTROL.</p>
        <p>I asked several prominent women--Suffragists, Feminists, etc. if they would not help me
            in doing this work, which would strike at the very <emph rend="underline">root</emph> of
            the <emph rend="underline">evil</emph>. I wanted to get 50 women to go on record with me
            and <emph rend="underline">make a TEST CASE</emph> through the COURTS. Could I get them?
            I was told to "<q>Wait until we get the Vote!</q>" When I asked Radical Woman Speaker
            and Writer if she would assist her reply was: "<q>WAIT UNTIL YOU BECOME BETTER
                KNOWN!</q></p>
        <p>But the cries of <emph rend="underline">thousands</emph> of <emph rend="underline"
                >suffering women would not let me wait.</emph></p>
        <p>I found, however, to my utter surprise, that there was very little <emph rend="underline"
                >scientific</emph> information on this question available in America. Although
            nearly every country in <place>Europe</place> had this knowledge, we were the only
            civilized people in the world whose postal laws would not allow of its delivery.</p>
        <p>The TYRANNY of the CENSORSHIP in the POST OFFICE IS THE GREATEST MENACE TO LIBERTY IN THE
            UNITED STATES TODAY. The Post Office was never intended to be a moral or ethical
            institution. It was intended to be mechanically efficient; certainly not to pass upon
            the opinions in the matter it conveys. If we concede this power to this institution,
            which is a Public Servant, we might just as well give to the Street Car Companies and
            Railroads the <emph rend="underline">right to refuse to carry passengers whose ideas
                they do not like</emph>. </p>
        <p>I <del>discovered</del>
            <add>was warned</add> that the penalty for violating the Post Office Laws was the most
            severe of any country in the world <add>others attempted it</add>. I need give only one
            illustration to show how they have been enforced up to the present time. This was the
            case of a physician, who resided in the Middle West. (He requests me not to use his
            name.) He received a letter from a woman a few miles out of the city where he lived. She
            stated that she was the mother of NINE CHILDREN, and that her husband was in the <emph
                rend="underline">last stages of Tuberculosis</emph>. She begged and implored him on
            the grounds of Humanity to give her some information whereby she could prevent bringing
            any more children into the world. The Doctor being a <emph rend="underline">liberal
                minded</emph> and <emph rend="underline">sympathetic man</emph>, with a conscious
            responsibility toward the future of the race, did not hesitate for a moment. He sent her
            a few simple directions to prevent conception. Two weeks later, he received another
            letter from another woman, who claimed that she had SEVEN living children and had had
            TEN abortions, and that her husband was suffering from syphilis. She, also, implored him
            to send her by return mail some information that would save her from a further
            conception. Again, the Doctor did not hesitate. He complied with her request and sent
            her simple instructions to avoid further pregnancies. </p>
        <p>One month later, he was ordered into Court and confronted by a woman, a <person
                reg="Comstock, Anthony">COMSTOCK</person> SPY, who was the writer of both letters.
            He pled guilty to the charge and was sentenced to TEN YEARS in the <org>Leavenworth
                Penitentiary</org>, and $10,000 fine. In other words, he received the maximum
            sentence of $5,000 and FIVE years' imprisonment <emph rend="underline">for each
                letter</emph>. His home was broken up, his professional standing gone, and not one
                <emph rend="underline">word of protest</emph> from the medical profession against
            this outrage. After spending SIX years in prison, last year he was released. He is now
            an old man, broken in health, and requests friends not to use his name, or to give his
            case any publicity.</p>
        <p>This is only one illustration of the methods of censorship, and although Mr. Comstock has
            passed away, the same methods are being employed as viciously under his successor as
            ever before.</p>
        <p>You all know of Mr. <person reg="Sanger William">Sanger</person>'s case, which occurred
            last year, when the FEDERAL GOVERNMENT, not being able to lay its hands on me and
            prosecute me, set a trap for William Sanger through a Comstock SPY. You have all heard
            how this man came into the privacy of his studio several times, imploring him for a
            pamphlet on "<title type="pamphlet">FAMILY LIMITATION</title>."<add> (100,000) had been
                distributed</add></p>
        <p>The same story was told of a sick wife, a large family and many abortions; that he was a
            worker in the Socialistic Movement, a friend of mind and interested in furthering the
            cause of Birth Control. As Mr. Sanger had only one copy in his possession, he gave it to
            the Spy, who turned around and arrested him for doing it. He was tried before three
                <emph rend="underline">prejudiced</emph>, clerical judges, convicted and sentenced
            to 30 days' Imprisonment. </p>
        <p>These are merely TWO EXAMPLES that have been brought close to me; but I know there are
            thousands of cases fully as outrageous, where innocent men and women are victims of the
            Censors.</p>
        <p>
            <add><person reg="Goldman, Emma">Emma Goldman</person>'s case up for trial</add>
        </p>
        <p>I am not going to take up your time to tell you about <title type="journal">"THE WOMAN
                REBEL</title>." You all know of its brief existence. You know of its suppression and
            confiscation by the Post Office authorities. You know of the indictments handed down by
            the Grand Jury against me. You know of the many postponements of my trial and the final
            dismissal of the case by the Government. I am reluctant to call it a VICTORY, for What
            has Victory meant to me in this case? It meant <emph rend="underline">months and months
                of persecution by spies</emph> and detectives, prying into every phase of my
            activity, coming into my home in the guise of comrades and friends. It meant the
            exertion of the meanest and most despicable methods in trying to suppress the message of
            Birth Control. It meant the opening of all my private letters, the <emph
                rend="underline">Invasion of every Constitutional Right</emph> we are supposed to
            enjoy in this country. It would be impossible for me to enumerate all the hindrances and
            all the tricks the benevolent Government put in my way during the months I was
            publishing the paper. The indictments were the last weapons in the strenuous campaign to
                <emph rend="underline">stamp out</emph> THE IDEA OF BIRTH CONTROL.</p>
        <p>
            <add>went to <place>Europe</place>--Family limitation</add>
        </p>
        <p>I am glad to say that the very reverse of what was intended has occurred. The same
            authorities who two years ago adjudged me lewd and lascivious now pay me the <emph
                rend="underline">pretty compliment</emph> of informing me that I am not a
                "<soCalled>Disorderly Person</soCalled>." But why did the authorities change their
            minds? Because of the thousands of <emph rend="underline">letters of protest</emph>
            which came to them from all parts of this country and convinced them that BIRTH CONTROL
            was too vital a demand in the United States today to be suppressed through the
            persecution of an individual, which proves to us again that the Courts, no matter how
            powerful, <emph rend="underline">cannot combat a strong and intelligent
            opinion</emph>.</p>
        <p>My fight with the Government has been to arouse interest in the subject of Birth Control
            in America, and in this, at least, I feel that I have been victorious. The work now
            before us is to crystallize and to organize this interest into action, not only for the
            repeal of the laws but for the establishment of FREE CLINICS in the industrial centers
                <emph rend="underline">throughout this</emph> country.</p>
        <p>In <place reg="Netherlands, the">HOLLAND</place> there are 52 Clinics with nurses in
            charge, and the Medical Profession has practically handed the work over to nurses. In
            these clinics, which are mainly in the industrial and agricultural districts, any woman
            who is married or old enough to be married, can come for information, and be instructed
            in the care and Hygiene of her body. The Dutch woman looks upon a new baby in the house
            much as we look upon an automobile or any other luxury, which we would not buy unless we
            could afford it. These clinics have been established for 30 years in Holland, and the
            result has been that the general death rate of Holland has fallen to be the lowest of
            any country in Europe. Also, the infant mortality of <place
                reg="Amsterdam, Netherlands, the">Amsterdam</place> and <place
                reg="the Hague, Netherlands, the">the Hague</place> is found to be the lowest of any
            cities in the world. Holland proves that the practice of Birth Control leads to race
            improvement, for the increase of population has accelerated as the death rate has
            fallen. <add>"Public Utility"</add></p>
        <p>In <place>England</place>, <place>France</place>, <place>Scandinavia</place>, and
                <place>Germany</place> information regarding Birth Control is also freely
            disseminated, but the establishment of clinics in these countries is not so well
            organized as it is in Holland, with the consequence that the upper and middle classes,
            as in this country, have ready access to these methods, while the poor continue to
            multiply because of their imperfect knowledge. This leads, especially in France, to a
            high infantile mortality, which, rather than a low birth rate, is the real cause of the
            decreasing population.</p>
        <p>We in <place reg="United States">America</place> should learn a lesson from this, and I
            would urge IMMEDIATE GROUP ACTION to <emph rend="underline">form clinics here at
                once</emph>. We have in this country a splendid foundation in our hospital system
            and settlement work. The American Trained Nurse is the best equipped and most capable in
            the worlds which enables us, if we begin at once, to accomplish as much in 10 years'
            time as the European Countries have done in 30 years.</p>
        <p>Can we not form here <del>to-night</del>
            <add>this City</add> the NUCLEUS FOR A BIRTH CONTROL LEAGUE? <add>better <gap
                    extent="one word" reason="illegible" resp="MSPP"/></add></p>
        <p>There are already 10 such leagues, which have been formed during the past year in the
            large cities of this country. Such a League would be the rallying point for progressive
            thought in your City, and focus interest on the local necessity for opening a
            clinic.</p>
        <p><add>My work &amp; object now tour west &amp; <place reg="New York, NY">N.Y.</place>
                Clinic</add></p>
        <p><add>Birth Control is keynote new social awakening social <unclear>principle</unclear>
                interlocked spiritual progress</add></p>
        <p>This will enable the working woman to help herself, and to do away with Charity, which at
            its best can only give temporary relief. Woman must be protected from incessant
            child-bearing before she can actively participate in social life. She must triumph over
            Nature's and Man's laws, which have kept her in bondage. Just as man has triumphed over
            Nature by the use of electricity, shipbuilding, bridges, etc., so must she triumph over
            the laws which have made her a child-bearing machine.</p>
        <p>In her triumph over these laws <add>she will free the child &amp; emancipate
                herself</add>. She will develop her Personality and Individuality, and prepare with
            man for the EMANCIPATION OF THE RACE.</p>
        <p>
            <add>
                <person>Thomas Paine</person>
            </add>
        </p>
        <p>
            <add>Telegram to E.G. bringing a child into the world the greatest
            responsibility.</add></p>
        <p><add>We must make this function a sacred gift bodies beautiful instrument possible for
                the Soul we <gap extent="one word" reason="illegible" resp="MSPP"/>to play its
                part</add></p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
