<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014-06-24 MM</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-07 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person rend="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1914-10-28">28 Oct 1914</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Letter to Women Rebel Subscribers</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp128005</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Neo-Malthusianism in the United States</title>, <title
					type="journal">The Malthusian</title> Jan. 15, 1915, pp. 3-4</bibl>
			<bibl><title type="mf">Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress Microfilm</title>,
				129:2</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name/>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>Sanger sent this letter to the subscribers of <title type="journal">The Woman
				Rebel</title> before she fled the <place>United States</place> to avoid prosecution
			for obscenity. </p>
		<index level1="Woman Rebel, The" level2="suppression of"/>
		<index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Comstock Laws"/>
		<index level1="United States" level2="Post Office"/>
		<index level1="Comstock Laws"/>
		<index level1="quackery"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<dateline>
			<place reg="New York, NY">New York</place>
			<date value="1914-10-28">October 28th 1914</date>
		</dateline>
		<p>COMRADES AND FRIENDS,-</p>
		<p>Every paper published should have a message for its readers. It should deliver it and be
			done. <title type="journal">The Woman Rebel</title> had for its aim the imparting of
			information of the prevention of conception. It was not the intention to labor on for
			years advocating the idea, but to give the information directly to those who desired it.
			The March, May, July, August, September, and October issues have been suppressed and
			confiscated by the <org reg="United States Post Office">Post Office</org>. They have
			been mailed regularly to all subscribers. If you have not received your copies, it has
			been because the <org>U.S. Post Office</org> has refused to carry them on to you. </p>
		<p>My work on the nursing field for the past fourteen years has convinced me that the
			workers desire the knowledge of prevention of conception. My work among women of the
			working class proved to me sufficiently that it is they who are suffering because of the
			law which forbids the imparting of this information. To wait for this law to be repealed
			would be years and years hence. Thousands of un-wanted children may be born into the
			world in the meantime, thousands of women made miserable and unhappy.</p>
		<p>Why should we wait?</p>
		<p>Shall we who have heard the cries and seen the agony of dying women respect the law which
			has caused their death?</p>
		<p>Shall we watch in patience the murdering of 25,000 women, who die each year in U.S. from
			criminal abortion?</p>
		<p>Shall we fold our hands and wait until a body of sleek and well fed politicians get ready
			to abolish the cause of such slaughter?</p>
		<p>Shall we look upon a piece of parchment as greater than human happiness, greater than
			human life?</p>
		<p>Shall we let it destroy our womanhood, and hold millions of workers in bondage and
			slavery? Shall we who respond to the throbbing pulse of human needs concern ourselves
			with indictments, courts, and judges, or shall we do our work first and settle with
			these evils later?</p>
		<p>This law has caused the perpetuation of quackery. It has created the fake and quack who
			benefits by its existence.</p>
		<p>Jail has not been my goal. There is special work to be done, and I shall do it first. If
			jail comes after, I shall call upon all to assist me. In the meantime, I shall attempt
			to nullify the law by direct action and attend to the consequences later. </p>
		<p>Over 100,000 working men and women in U.S. shall hear from me.</p>
		<p>The Boston Tea Party ws a defiant and revolutionary act in the eyes of the English
			Government, but to the American Revolutionist it was but an act of courage and
			justice.</p>
		<byline>Yours fraternally, Margaret H. Sanger</byline>
	</docBody>
</doc>
