<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "file:/S:/TRANSCRIPTIONS/XML%20Drafts/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed draft article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2009/08/04 LL</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2009/08/06 CH proof and correct</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/03/11 CH Entered corrections suggested by Andy Carloff.</prepDate>       
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1928-04-00">April 1928</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>
                <supplied resp="MSPP">Birth Control Refused Space at Parent's
                    Exposition</supplied>
            </titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp128018</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Papers</title>, Library of
                Congress.</bibl>
            <bibl>LCM 129:55.</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="SIMRO">Simon, Robert E.</name>
            <name id="OSHWI">O'Shea, William J.</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
        <index level1="censorship" level2="in schools"/>
        <index level1="parents associations" level2="New York, NY"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>
            <add>B.C. Refused Space at Parents Exhibiton</add>
        </head>
        <dateLine>
            <date>April - 1928</date>
        </dateLine>
        <p> Last December the <org>American Birth Control League</org> was
            invited to prepare an exhibit for the <name type="conf">Parents'
                Exposition</name>, which was held last month in the Grand
            Central Palace, in <place reg="New York, NY">New York City</place>.
            A contract was signed in February; and great care and pains were
            taken by our organization to prepare a dignified, instructive and
            inoffensive survey of our work. On the eve of the opening we
            received a letter from <person reg="Simon, Robert E.">Robert E.
                Simon</person>, president of the <org>Associated Parents'
                Association of Greater New York</org>, stating that Dr. <person
                reg="O'Shea, William J.">O'Shea</person>, <add>the
                superintendent of public schools,</add> had threatened to remove
            the exhibition prepared by the <org
                reg="New York Board of Education">Board of Education</org> if
            the American Birth Control League were permitted to exhibit.
                <add>Mr. Simon confessed </add>that he was unable to combat such
            powerful opposition, and that therefore our exhibit could not be
            shown. We then addressed a communication to the superintendent of
            schools, requesting that a committee be appointed to suggest changes
            and improvements which would make our exhibit acceptable. But, as
            was to be expected, this suggestion was refused point blank, and the
            distinguished “<soCalled>educator</soCalled>, ”in newspaper
            interviews, was quoted as asserting: “<q who="OSHWI">I won't have
                anything to do with an exhibition that teaches such stuff to our
                high school girls.... I don't want our girls to hear that sort
                of stuff while they are under the protection of the school
                system.</q>”</p>
        <p>This muddled confusion of the question, combined with Dr.
                <add>O'Shea's</add> a completely unauthorized usurpation and
            abuse of authority, was given widespread publicity in the daily
            press. As usual the attempted suppression of Birth Control resulted
            in making it for several days the focal point of public interest. It
            also showed the intelligent public of New York City that its
            superintendent of schools, affiliated with a <org
                reg="Catholic Church">Church</org> that is demanding
            broad-mindedness and tolerance among all American voters, in view of
            the presidential aspirations of Governor <person
                reg="Smith, Alfred E.">Smith</person>, is himself
            constitutionally unable to assume an adult, impartial, or
            intelligent attitude toward one of the central problems of
            parenthood.</p>
        <p><del>The exposition</del> Arranged primarily <add>to reveal
                    <del>this</del> to</add> for the parents of Greater New
            York, <del>them</del> the social agencies through which they might
            achieve happier homes, better children and wiser parenthood,
                <add>the exposition was therefore</add> was scaled down to
                <del>the</del>
            <add>
                <unclear>illegible word</unclear>
            </add> intelligence level <del>less than that</del>
            <add>below that</add> of a fourteen-year old. How is it possible to
            educate parents, when educators themselves refuse to exercise their
            intelligence?</p>
        <p>Despite the yards of newspaper publicity the incident has stimulated,
            we are too experienced in such conflicts to claim a victory. It has
            required long years of effort to educate the police of New York City
            into an attitude of forbearance and tolerance toward Birth Control
            activities. It has required an almost equally long time to arouse
            the public from its lethargy of indifference into a latently and
            even a quietly active sympathy toward our activities. And now it
            seems that we must begin to “<soCalled>educate the
                educators</soCalled>.” We have never been cynical enough to
            believe, <add>as certain observers have claimed,</add> that the
            ordinary school official is the least intelligent and most
            reactionary element in the community. But what are we to conclude
            after this exhibition of bludgeoning bigotry by Dr. O'Shea, and his
            assistant superintendent (and spokesman) <person
                reg="Campbell, Harold G.">Harold G. Campbell</person>?</p>
        <p>All that these distinguished “<soCalled>educators</soCalled>” wrote
            or said was based on the fallacious assumption that Birth Control
            was something indecent, something not quite respectable. Such an
            attitude is more <del>subnormal</del>
            <add>restricted</add> in intelligence than <add>that of</add> the
            most backward child placed under what Dr. O'Shea claims is “<q
                who="OSHWI">the protection of the school system.</q>” We wonder
            if ignorance and intolerance ever furnish any truly adequate
            protection.</p>
        <p>No: we cannot claim a victory. We are willing and ready to renew our
            fight for toleration and understanding all over again; to begin
            again our ploughing the rocky soil of ignorance and
            misunderstanding, to begin if necessary the education even of those
            who refuse to be educated, but it is difficult to find any weapon
            sharp enough and subtle enough to repair the unjust injuries done to
            our cause by deliberate misrepresentation and aggressive malice. One
            fact remains as clear as a challenge: American parents must beware
            the menace of placing the political power of their country and of
            their school in the hands of those whose attitude is determined by a
            Church which develops in its children a state of mind at complete
            variance with the essential spirit of American institutions.</p>
        <p>There <add><del>are</del> have been , however, certain</add>
            compensations for this injury <del>that was</del> done to the cause
            of Birth Control. The courageous letter of Mr. <person
                reg="Macgowan, Kenneth">Kenneth Macgowan</person>,
            vice-president of the <org>Walden School</org>, in resigning from
            the Parents' Association and refusing to make an address at the
            exposition, because of the unjust treatment of our League, has
            demonstrated that if hypocrisy and ignorance can usurp authority,
            there is, on the other hand, still active <del>in</del>
            <add>among the parents</add> of our community, a type of dynamic
            quick-thinking and quick-acting intelligence to protest against
            bigoted censorship. The protest of Mr. <person reg="Lasker, Bruno"
                >Bruno Lasker </person>was likewise gratifying, indicating as it
            did the prevalence among a <del>wide</del>
            <add>broad</add> group of New York parents of an enlightened and
            intelligent attitude concerning the central importance of Birth
            Control <del>illegible words</del> to American parenthood
                <del>illegible words</del>.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
