<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed draft speech">
<mepHeader>
<prepDate>2002-08-08 KH</prepDate>
<prepDate>2002-08-15 KH</prepDate>
<prepDate>2003/08/08 CH correcting tags</prepDate>
<prepDate>2004/10/22 CH</prepDate>
<prepDate>2014-03-07 CH clean regs</prepDate>
<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
<docDate value="1929-02-26">
<supplied resp="MSPP">26 Feb 1929</supplied>
</docDate>
<docTitle>
<titlePart>
<supplied resp="MSPP">Introduction for Owen Lovejoy</supplied>
</titlePart>
</docTitle>
<idno>msp128190</idno>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</title>
</bibl>
<bibl><title>LCM</title> 129:750</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</mepHeader>
<headNote>
<p><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger</person> introduced Owen Lovejoy's remarks at a dinner held
for the <org>Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau</org> at <place reg="New York, NY">New
York</place>'s <org>Plaza Hotel</org>. Related documents are her <xref from="234094.xml">Opening
Remarks</xref> and her introductions for <person reg="Fairchild, Henry Pratt"><xref
from="128197.xml">Henry Pratt Fairchild</xref></person> and <person reg="Hankins, Frank"><xref
from="128198.xml">Frank Hankins</xref></person>. For another version see LCM 129:750.</p>
<index level1="child welfare"/>
<index level1="women" level2="enslavement of"/>
<index level1="Lovejoy, Owen"/>
</headNote>
<docBody>
<p>
<add>Thousands of women have already been grievously wounded in the battle of life--Emergency
measures are all they ask--&amp; all they are allowed to receive. Week after week, day after day
&amp; hour after hour they come to us, appealing &amp; praying for help. Some of them come looking
furtively about, hesitant wondering how they shall be received.</add>
</p>
<p>
<add>They have run the gauntlet of various organizations &amp; been denied the information they
sought.</add>
</p>
<p>
<add>They come to us, troubled, inarticulate, like doomed souls crushed beneath the force of a
cruelly prolific nature.</add>
</p>
<p>
<add>These are the Martyrized Mothers of <place reg="United States">America</place>. They ask for
help--for the right to life, liberty &amp; the pursuit of happiness. </add>
</p>
<p>
<add>Temple of Motherhood.</add>
</p>
<p><del>The</del> Many critics of the Birth Control movement have failed to recognize how closely
the well-being of children is related <del>upon</del> to the well-being and happiness of their
mothers. To protects the children we must also protect the Mothers. It is now my great honor to
introduce a man who has fought long and bravely for the rights of <del>American</del> children
<del>born in America</del><add>to be free</add>, <del>and who has the insight and the courage to
recognize that their first inalienable right is the right to be well-born. It is my pleasure to
introduce</del>
<add>and</add> the leader in the long fight against Child Labor--Mr. <person reg="Lovejoy, Owen"
>Owen Lovejoy</person>.</p>
</docBody>
</doc>
