<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/06/29 NC</prepDate><prepDate>CH 2011/07/22 corrects</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1939-02-00">Feb 1939</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>How I Decided to Begin My Fight</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp128169</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Redbook Magazine</title>Feb. 1939, pp.36-39, 116-117 and 125.</bibl>
            <bibl><title>LCM</title>129:0597</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="YID">Yiddish</name>
            <name id="BLAWI">Blake, William</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
            <name id="SACSA">Sadie Sachs</name>
            <name id="SACJA">Jake Sachs</name>
            <name id="SANCH">Margaret Sanger's Children, Grant, Stuart, and Peggy.</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>This article is an excerpt from
            <title>Margaret Sanger: An Autobiography</title>, published
        in <title>Redbook Magazine</title></p><index level1="autobiography"
            level2="My fight for Birth Control"></index><index level1="birth control"
                level2="lack of knowledge of"/><index level1="birth control"
                level2="laws and legislation" level3="Comstock act"/><index
                level1="children" level2="unwanted"/><index level1="motherhood"
                /><index level1="nurses" level2="birth control and"/><index
                level1="pregnancy" level2="fears of"/><index
                level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="biography"/>
        </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>How I Decided to Begin My Fight</head>
        <byline>By Margaret Sanger</byline>
        <p/>

        <p>“<q who="BLAWI">Every night and every morn<lb/> Some to misery are
                born<lb/> Every morn and every night<lb/> Some are born to sweet
                delight<lb/> Some are born to sweet delight<lb/> Some are born
                to endless night.</q>”<lb/> -<person reg="Blake, William">William Blake</person></p>

        <p>During my early years in <place>New York</place> trained nurses were
            in great demand. Few people wanted to enter hospitals; they were
            afraid they might be “practiced” upon, and consented to go only in
            desperate emergencies. Sentiment was especially vehement in the
            matter of having babies. A woman's own bedroom, no matter how
            inconveniently arranged, was the usual place for her lying in. I was
            not sufficiently free from domestic duties to be a general nurse,
            but I could ordinarily manage obstetrical cases, because I was
            notified far enough ahead to plan my schedule. And after two weeks,
            I could go home again.</p>
        <p>Sometimes I was summoned to small apartments occupied by young
            clerks, insurance salesmen, or lawyers just starting out, most of
            them under thirty, whose wives were having their first or second
            baby. They were always eager to know the best and latest method in
            infant-care and feeding. In particular, Jewish patients whose lives
            centered around the family, welcomed advice and followed it
            implicitly.</p>
        <p>But more and more my calls began to come from the <place reg="New York City, NY">lower East Side</place>, as
            though I were being magnetically drawn there by some force outside
            my control. I hated the wretchedness and hopelessness of the poor,
            and never experienced that satisfaction in working among them that
            so many noble women have found. My concern for my patients was now
            quite different from my earlier hospital attitude. I could see that
            much was wrong with them which did not appear in the physiological
            or medical diagnosis. A woman in childbirth was not merely a woman
            in childbirth. My expanded outlook included a view of her
            background, her potentialities as a human being, the kind of
            children she was bearing, and what was going to happen to them.</p>
        <p>The wives of small shopkeepers were my most frequent cases, but I had
            the wives of carpenters, truck-drivers, dishwashers, and pushcart
            vendors. I admired intensely <gap extent="one word"/> consideration most of these
            people had <gap extent="one word"/> their own. Money to pay doctor and nurse had been
            carefully saved months in advance--parents-in-law, grandfathers,
            grandmothers, all contributing.</p>
        <p>As soon as the neighbors learned that a nurse was in the building,
            they came in a friendly way to visit, often carrying fruit, jellies
            or <foreign lang="YID">gefilte</foreign> fish made after a cherished recipe. It was infinitely
            pathetic to me that they, so poor themselves, should bring me food.
            Later they drifted in again with the excuse of getting the plate,
            and sat down for a nice talk; there was no hurry. Always back of the
            little gift was the request: “<q who="UNK">I am pregnant (or my daughter, or my
            sister is). Tell me something to keep from having another baby. We
            cannot afford another yet.</q>”</p>
        <p>I tried to explain the only two methods I had ever heard of among the
            middle classes, both of which were invariably brushed aside as
            unacceptable. They were of no certain avail to the wife, because
            they placed the burden of responsibility solely upon the husband--a
            burden which he seldom assured. What she was seeking was
            self-protection she could herself use, and there was none.</p>
        <p>Below this stratum of society was one in truly desperate
            circumstances. The men were sullen and unskilled, picking up odd
            jobs now and then, but more often unemployed, lounging in and out of
            the house at all hours of the day and night. The women seemed to
            slink on their way to market, and were without neighborliness.</p>
        <p>These submerged, untouched classes were beyond the scope of organized
            charity or religion. No labor union, no church, not even the
                <org>Salvation Army</org> reached them. They were apprehensive
            of everyone, and rejected help of any kind, ordering all intruders
            to keep out; both birth and death they considered their own
            business. Social agents, who were just beginning to appear, were
            profoundly distrusted because they pried into homes and lives,
            asking questions about wages, how many were in the family, and had
            any of them ever been in jail. Often two or three had been there, or
            were now under suspicion of prostitution, shoplifting,
            purse-snatching, or petty thievery; and in consequence they passed
            furtively by the big blue uniforms on the corner.</p>
        <p>The utmost depression came over me as I approached this surreptitious
            region. Below Fourteenth Street I seemed to be breathing a different
            air, to be in another world and country, where the people had habits
            and customs alien to anything I had ever heard about.</p>
        <p>There were then approximately ten thousand apartments in New York
            into which no sun-ray penetrated directly; such windows as they had
            opened only on a narrow court from which rose fetid odors. It was
            seldom cleaned, though garbage and refuse often went down into it.
            All these dwellings were pervaded by the foul breath of poverty,
            that moldy, indefinable, indescribable smell which cannot be
            fumigated out, sickening to me but apparently unnoticed by those who
            lived there. When I set to work with antiseptics, their pungent
            sting, at least temporarily obscured the stench.</p>
        <p>I remember one confinement case to which I was called by the doctor
            of an insurance company. I climbed up the five flights and entered
            the airless rooms, but the baby had come with too great speed. A boy
            of ten had been the only assistant.</p>
        <p>Many families took in “boarders,” as they were termed, whose small
            contributions paid the rent. These derelicts, wanderers, alternately
            working and drinking, were crowded in with the children; a single
            room sometimes held as many as six sleepers. Little girls were
            accustomed to dressing and undressing in front of the men.</p>
        <p>Pregnancy was a chronic condition among the women of this class.
            Suggestions as to what to do for a girl who was “in trouble,” or a
            married woman who was “caught,” passed from mouth to mouth. When
            they had word of a new remedy, they hurried to the drug-store, and
            if the clerk were inclined to be friendly, he might say: “Oh, that
            won't help you, but here's something that may.” The younger
            druggists usually refused to give advice because, if it were to be
            known, they would come under the law; midwives were even more
            fearful. The doomed women implored me to reveal the “secret” that
            rich people had, offering to pay me extra to tell them; many really
            believed I was holding back information for money.</p>
        <p>Each time I returned to this district, which was becoming a recurrent
            nightmare, I used to hear that <person reg="Unidentified">Mrs. Cohen</person> “had been
                carried to a hospital, but had never come back,” or
            that <person reg="Unidentified">Mrs. Kelly</person> “had sent the children to a neighbor and
                had put her head into the gas oven.” Day after day
            such tales were poured into my ears--a baby born dead, great relief;
            the death of an older child--sorrow but again relief of a sort. I
            shuddered with horror as I listened to the details and studied the
            reasons back of them--destitution linked with excessive
            childbearing. The waste of life seemed utterly senseless. One by
            one, worried, sad, pensive and alone, they marshaled themselves
            before me in my dreams, sometimes appealingly, sometimes
            accusingly.</p>
        <p>These were not merely “unfortunate conditions among the poor” such as
            we read about. I knew the women personally. They were living,
            breathing, human beings, with hopes, fears and aspirations like my
            own; yet their weary, misshapen bodies, “always ailing,
                never failing,” were destined to be thrown on the
            scrap-heap before they were thirty-five. I could not escape from the
            facts of their wretchedness; neither was I able to see any way out.
            My own cozy and comfortable family existence was becoming a reproach
            to me.</p>
        <p>Then one stifling mid-July day of 1912 I was summoned to a Grand
            Street tenement. My patient was a small, slight <person reg="Sachs, Sadie">Russian Jewess</person>,
            about twenty-eight years old, of the special cast of feature to
            which suffering lends a <person reg="Virgin Mary">Madonna</person>-like expression. The cramped
            three-room apartment was in a sorry state of turmoil. The man, a
            truck-driver scarcely older than this wife, had come home to find
            the three children crying and his wife unconscious. He called the
            nearest doctor, who in turn had sent for me. The husband's earning
            were trifling, and most of them had gone to keep the none-too-strong
            children clean and properly fed. But his wife's ingenuity had helped
            them to save a little, and this he was glad to spend on a nurse
            rather than have her go to a hospital.</p>
        <p>The doctor and I settled ourselves to the task of fighting the
            septicemia. Never had I worked so fast, never so concentratedly. The
            sultry days and nights were melted into a torpid inferno. It did not
            seem possible there could be such heat; and every bit of food, ice
            and drugs had to be carried up three flights of stairs.</p>
        <p><person reg="Sachs, Jake">Jake</person> was more kind and thoughtful than many of the husbands I had
            encountered. He loved his children, and had always helped his wife
            wash and dress them. He had brought water up and carried garbage
            down before he left in the morning, and did as much as he could for
            me while he anxiously watched her progress.</p>
        <p>After a fortnight, the wife's recovery was in sight. Neighbors were
            genuinely pleased that she had survived. She smiled wanly at all who
            came to see her and thanked them gently, but she could not respond
            to their hearty congratulations. She appeared to be more despondent
            and anxious than she should have been, and spent too much time in
            meditation.</p>
        <p>At the end of three weeks, as I was preparing to leave the fragile
            patient to take up her difficult life once more, she finally voiced
            her fears; “<q who="SACSA">Another baby will finish me, I
            suppose?</q>”</p>
        <p>“It's too early to talk about that,” I
            temporized.</p>
        <p>But when the doctor came to make his last call, I drew him aside.</p>
        <p>“She is terribly worried about having another
                baby.”</p>
        <p>“<q who="UNK">She well may be</q>,” replied the doctor; and then
            he stood before her and said: “<q who="UNK">Any more such capers,
                young woman, and there'll be no need for me</q>.”</p>
        <p>“<q who="SACSA">I know, Doctor</q>,” she replied timidly. “<q who="SACSA"
                >But</q>,”--and she hesitated as though it took all her courage
            to say it--“<q who="SACSA">what can I do to prevent it?</q>”</p>
        <p>The doctor was a kindly man and he had worked hard to save her, but
            such incidents had become so familiar to him that he had long since
            lost whatever delicacy he might once have had. He laughed
            good-naturedly. “<q who="UNK">You want to have your cake and eat
                it too, do you? Well, it can't be done.</q>”</p>
        <p>I glanced quickly at the wife. Even through my sudden tears I could
            see stamped on her face an expression of absolute despair. We simply
            looked at each other, saying no word until the door had closed
            behind the doctor. Then she lifted her thin, blue-veined hands and
            clasped them beseechingly.</p>
        <p>"<q who="SACSA">He can't understand. He's only a man. But you do, don't
                you? Please tell me the secret, and I'll never breathe it to a
                soul. Please!</q>”</p>
        <p>What was I to do? I could not speak the conventionally comforting
            phrases which would be of no comfort. Instead, I made her as
            physically easy as I could, and promised to come back in a few days
            to talk with her again.</p>
        <p>Night after night her wistful image appeared before me. I made all
            sorts of excuses to myself for not going back. I was busy on other
            cases; I really did not know what to say to her or how to convince
            her of my own ignorance; I was helpless to avert such monstrous
            atrocities. Time rolled by, and I did nothing.</p>
        <p>The telephone rang one evening three months later, and Jake's
            agitated voice begged me to come at once; his wife was sick again
            and from the same cause. For a wild moment I thought of sending
            someone else; but actually, of course, I hurried into my uniform,
            caught up my bag, and started out. All the way I longed for a subway
            wreck, an explosion, anything to keep me from having to enter that
            home again. But nothing happened, even to delay me. I turned into
            the dingy doorway and climbed the familiar stairs once more. The
            children were there, young little things.</p>
        <p>The wife was in a coma, and died within ten minutes. I folded her
            still hands across her breast, remembering how they had pleaded with
            me, begging so humbly for the knowledge which was her right. I drew
            a sheet over her pallid face. Jake was sobbing, running his hands
            through his hair and pulling it out like an insane person. Over and
            over again he wailed, “<q who="SACJA">My God! My God! My
            God!</q>”</p>
        <p>I left him pacing desperately back and forth, and for hours I myself
            walked and walked and walked through the hushed streets. When I
            finally arrived home and let myself quietly in, all the household
            was sleeping. I stood looking out of my window and down upon the
            dimly lighted city.</p>
        <p>Its pains and griefs crowded in upon me; a moving picture rolled
            before my eyes with photographic clearness; women writhing in
            travail to bring forth little babies; the babies themselves naked
            and hungry, wrapped in newspapers to keep them from the cold;
            six-year-old children with pinched, pale, wrinkled faces, old in
            concentrated wretchedness, pushed into gray and fetid cellars,
            crouching on stone floors, their small scrawny hands scuttling
            through rags, making lamp-shades, artificial flowers; white coffins,
            black coffins, coffins, coffins interminably passing in never-ending
            succession. The scenes piled one upon another on another. I could
            bear it no longer.</p>
        <p>As I stood there, the darkness faded. The sun came up and threw its
            reflection over the house-tops. It was the dawn of a new day in my
            life also. The doubt and questioning, the experimenting and trying,
            were now to be put behind me. I knew I could not go back merely to
            keeping people alive.</p>
        <p>I went to bed, knowing that no matter what it might cost, I was
            finished with palliatives and superficial cures; I was resolved to
            seek out the root of evil, to do something to change the destiny of
            mothers whose miseries were vast as the sky.</p>
        <p>How were mothers to be saved? I went through many revolving doors,
            looked around, and not finding what I was seeking, came out again. I
            talked incessantly to everyone who seemed to have social welfare at
            heart. Progressive women whom I consulted were thoroughly
            discouraging. “<q who="UNK">Wait until we get the vote. Then we'll take
                care of that,</q>” they assured me. I tried the
            Socialists. Here, there, and everywhere the reply came:
                “<q who="UNK">Wait until women have more education. Wait until we
                secure equal distribution of wealth.</q>” Wait for this
            and wait for that. Wait! Wait! Wait!</p>
        <p>Having no idea how powerful were the laws which laid a blanket of
            ignorance over the medical profession as well as the laity, I asked
            various doctors of my acquaintance: “Why aren't
                physicians doing something? Information does exist, doesn't
                it?”</p>
        <p>“<q who="UNK">Perhaps; but I doubt whether you can find it. Even
                if you do, you can't pass it on. <person reg="Comstock, Anthony">Comstock</person>'ll get you if you
                don't watch out.</q>”</p>
        <p>In order to ascertain something about this subject which was so
            mysterious and so unaccountably forbidden, I spent almost a year in
            the libraries--the <org reg="Astor Library">Astor</org>, the <org reg="Lenox Library">Lenox</org>,
            the <org reg="New York Academy of Medicine">Academy of Medicine</org>, the <org>Library of
                Congress</org> and dozens of others. Hoping that psychological
            treatises might inform me, I read <person reg="Forel, Auguste"
                >Auguste Forel</person> and <person reg="Block, Iwan">Iwan
                Block</person>. At one gulp I swallowed <person
                reg="Ellis, Havelock">Havelock Ellis'</person>
                “<title>Psychology of Sex</title>,” and had psychic indigestion
            for months thereafter.</p>
        <p>I read translations from the German in which women were advised to
            have more children because it could be proved statistically that
            their condition was improved by childbearing. The only article on
            the question I could discover in American literature was in the
                <title>Atlantic Monthly</title>, by <person
                reg="Ross, Edward Alsworth">Edward Alsworth Ross</person> of the
                <org>University of Wisconsin</org>, who brought to the
            attention of his readers the decline of the birth-rate among the
            upper and educated classes, and the increase among the unfit, the
            consequences of which were sure to be race-suicide.</p>
        <p>The pursuit of my quest took me away from home a good deal. The
            children used to come in after school and at once hunt for me. “<q
                who="SANCH">Where's Mother?</q>” was the usual question. If
            they found me at my mending-basket, they all leaped about for joy,
            took hands and danced, shouting: “<q who="SANCH">Mother's home,
                Mother's home, Mother's sewing</q>.” Sewing seemed to imply a
            measure of performance.</p>
        <p>I too wanted to drive away the foreboding barrier of separation by
            closer contact with them. I wanted to have them solely to myself, to
            feed, to bathe, to clothe them myself. I had heard of the clean,
            wind-swept <place reg="Cape Cod, MA">Cape Cod</place> dunes, which appeared to be as
            far from the ugliness of civilization as I could get. Socialism,
            anarchism, syndicalism, progressivism--I was tired of them all. At
            the end of the spring, thoroughly depressed and dissatisfied, I
            tucked the children under my arms, boarded a Fall River boat, and
            sailed off, a pioneer to <place reg="Provincetown, MA">Provincetown</place>.</p>
        <p>In 1913 the tip of the Cape was only a fishing village with one
            planked walk--which, I was told, had been paid for by <org reg="United States Congress">Congress</org>. Up
            and down its length walked the bellman, the last of the town criers,
            proclaiming the news.</p>
        <p>At first we lived in the upper story of a fisherman's house right on
            the water. After he went out in the morning, his wife and her
            children, and I and mine, were left alone. Then the old women
            recalled scenes from their early days on the whaling vessels. Their
            mothers had brought them forth unaided; and their own sons, in turn,
            had been born on the ships and apprenticed to their husbands. They
            fitted into life simply; but the younger Portuguese, who were taking
            over the fishing industry, were asking what they should do about
            limiting their families.</p>
        <p>The village was rather messy and smelled of fish. I was still too
            close to humanity and wanted to be more alone, so we moved to the
            extreme end of town. Our veranda faced the Bay, and when the tide
            was high, the water came up and lapped at the piles on which the
            cottage was built. <person reg="Sanger, Stuart">Stuart</person>,
                <person reg="Sanger, Grant">Grant</person> and <person
                reg="Sanger, Peggy">Peggy</person> used to sit on the steps and
            dabble their toes. At low tide they had two miles of beach on which
            to skip and run; it was a wonderful place to play, and all summer we
            had sunrise breakfasts, sunset picnics.</p>
        <p>I spent the entire season at Provincetown, groping for knowledge,
            classifying all my past activities in their proper categories,
            weighing the pros and cons of what good there was in them and also
            what they lacked. It was a period of gestation. Just as you give birth to a child, so you can give birth to
            an idea.</p>
        <p>Between interims of brooding and playing with the children, I took
            part in the diversions of the minute colony of congenial people.
                <person reg="Hawthorne, Charles">Charles Hawthorne</person> had
            a school of painting; <person reg="Vorse, Mary Heaton">Mary Heaton
                Vorse</person> and her husband <person reg="O'Brien, Joseph"
                >Joseph O'Brien</person> were there; so also were <person
                reg="Hapgood, Hutchins">Hutch Hapgood</person> and <person
                reg="Boyce, Neith">Neith Boyce</person>. <person
                reg="Ashley, Jessie">Jessie Ashley</person> had lifted <person
                reg="Haywood, William D.">Big Bill Haywood</person> out of the slough
            of the Paterson strike and brought him down to rest and
            recuperate.</p>
        <p>Big Bill was one of the few who saw what I was aiming at, although
            fearful that my future might involve the happiness of my children.
            Even he did not feel that the small-family question was significant
            enough to be injected into the labor platform. Nevertheless, as we
            rambled up and down the beach, he came to my aid with that
            encouragement of which I was badly in need. He suggested I go to
                <place>France</place> and see for myself the conditions
            resulting from generations of family limitation in that country.
            This struck me as a splendid idea, because it would also give
                <person reg="Sanger, William">Bill Sanger</person> a chance to
            paint, instead of continuing to build suburban houses.</p>
        <p>The trip to <place>Europe</place> seemed so urgent that no matter
            what sacrifices had to be made, we decided to make them.</p>

    </docBody>
</doc>
