<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed speech">
<mepHeader>
<prepDate>2002-08-08 KH</prepDate>
<prepDate>2002-08-15 KH</prepDate>
<prepDate>2003/08/08 CH Correcting tags</prepDate>
<prepDate>2014-03-07 CH clean regs</prepDate>
<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
<docDate value="1929-02-26">
<supplied resp="MSPP">26 Feb 1929</supplied>
</docDate>
<docTitle>
<titlePart>
<supplied resp="MSPP">Introduction for Henry Pratt Fairchild</supplied>
</titlePart>
</docTitle>
<idno>msp128197</idno>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
<bibl>LCM 129:750B</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</mepHeader>
<headNote>
<p>Margaret Sanger introduced <person reg="Fairchild, Henry Pratt">Henry Pratt Fairchild</person>'s
remarks at a dinner for the <org>Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau</org> at <place
reg="New York, NY">New York's</place>
<org>Plaza Hotel</org>. Related documents are Sanger's <xref from="234094.xml">opening
address</xref> that night and her introductions for <person reg="Lovejoy, Owen"><xref
from="128190.xml">Owen Lovejoy</xref></person> and <person reg="Hankins, Frank"><xref
from="128198.xml">Frank Hankins</xref></person>.</p>
<index level1="World Population Conference"/>
<index level1="population control"/>
</headNote>
<docBody>
<p>Let's not forget that Birth Control is no mere matter of overburdened mothers with babes in their
arms and hungry children tugging at their skirts. It is a problem which affects the whole
world--politics, industry, immigration, and all grave international problems. In 1927 there gathered
in Geneva a large group of authorities on these problems--<add>300</add> scientists and historians
from <del>all</del><add>many</add> countries. One of them read an illuminating and masterly paper on
"optimum Population" which received more attention from the press of <place>Europe</place> than any
other paper present at the <org>World Population Conference</org>
<del>of 1927</del>. I <del>am</del><add>was</add> proud that the author of this paper is
<add>was</add> an American resident of New York, and the professor of
<del>sociology</del><add>economics</add> at <org>New York University</org>. And I am even prouder of
the fact that he has lent his prestige and his presence to this gathering tonight. I have the great
honor of introducing Dr. <add>Henry Pratt</add> Fairchild.</p>
</docBody>
</doc>
