<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Autograph Draft Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011-08-05 NC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2013-04-23 CH Proof tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2013-04-29 AW Correct tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2013-07-23 CH corrected type</prepDate><prepDate>2014-07-10 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1953-08-19"><supplied resp="MSPP">19</supplied> Aug 1953</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Acceptance of IPPF Presidency
                Speech</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp128195</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
            <bibl>LCM 129:0746</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Sanger accepted her nomination as president of the <org>International
                Planned Parenthood Federation</org> in <place>Stockholm, Sweden</place> in August of
            1953 at the <org>Fourth International Conference on Planned Parenthood</org>.</p>
        <p>The last pages are missing.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="international conferences on"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <p>This nomination as First President of the <del>Fourth</del>International PP Federation is
            indeed a great honor. I had hoped &amp; prayed since the <org
                reg="International Conference on Planned Parenthood, Third (Bombay)"><place
                    reg="Bombay, India">Bombay</place> Conference</org> that the Presidency would be
            accepted by that charming, able woman Lady <person reg="Rama Rau, Dhanvanthi">Rama
                Rau</person>. </p>
        <p>She has given her reason why she can not accept the position &amp; hope that in the next
            two years when we meet again that these difficulties will evaporate &amp; be gone
            forever. </p>
        <p>This had been a splendid conference. I appreciate &amp; congratulate the German delegates
            for their presence here. I know what difficulties they must overcome to speak out on the
            subject. But it is not easy to keep truth buried behind laws forever &amp; I believe
            that when the general people get on their feet again -- time movement will gain
            strength. I also thank the Dutch delegation for their splendid cooperation. Their
            understanding has indeed made the work of the <org
                reg="International Planned Parenthood Federation, Steering Committee">Steering
                Committee</org> a pleasure. </p>
        <p>We must also thank the delegates from <place>Greece</place>, <place>Turkey</place>,
                <place>Japan</place> for their presence here. </p>
        <p>The splendid accommodations that the <org reg="Riksförbundet för Sexeull Upplysning"
                >Swedish League</org> has made for us. Their hospitality, their organizing ability
            give us hope that one day there may be a cooperative well ordered world where PP becomes
            a pattern of our civilization -- <person reg="Ottesen-Jensen, Elise">Mrs. Ottensen
                Jensen</person>’s great heart &amp; love has made us all feel equal to the task
            which is ahead of us as we separate &amp; return to our homes to carry on. </p>
        <p>Last may I say that we all owe a debt of gratitude for the skilled &amp; able
            demonstrations of fairness. Chairman Dr. <person reg="Blacker, C. P.">Blacker</person>,
            -- Dr. Blacker has worked long hours on the Constitution I wrote him &amp; requested
            that he &amp; the <org
                reg="International Planned Parenthood Federation, English Committee">English
                Committee</org> set up the form of an <title>International Constitution</title> for
            this <org reg="International Conference on Planned Parenthood, Fourth (Stockholm)"
                >Conference</org> which could be passed around to the various nationals for their
            opinions &amp; comments. This was done &amp; I know it took the midnight time to set it
            forth in so splendid a form for our discussions. </p>
        <p>We have all discussed every point &amp; with a few changes or additions I am pleased that
            this Constitution has been accepted. As to myself -- I can only say that my heart is too
            full to express my gratitude for this confidence &amp; honor -- that you have bestowed
            upon me. I am of the nature that I do not spread my interests. I shall be happy to take
            this Presidency for the next two years or until the next conference meets. I shall ask
            for your cooperation as well as your criticisms, your opinions &amp; what ever you think
            I may do to further the work &amp; direct its </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
