<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Draft Article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2003/08/04 SR</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2007/09/05 CH correct docdate and index</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-03-07 CH clean regs</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-08 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1920-12-00">Dec 1920</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>International Aspects of Birth Control</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp128193</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
			<bibl><title type="mf">Library of Congress Microfilm</title> 129:743.</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="UNK"> Unknown</name>
			<name id="INGWI">Inge, William Ralph</name>
			<name id="SHAED">Shackelton, Edith</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>This article was drafted for <title type="journal">The Nation</title>, but was never
			published.</p>
		<index level1="Austria" level2="birth control in"/>
		<index level1="Europe" level2="birth control in"/>
		<index level1="England" level2="population policies"/>
		<index level1="England" level2="birth control in"/>
		<index level1="France" level2="birth control in"/>
		<index level1="France" level2="birth rate in"/>
		<index level1="Germany" level2="birth control in"/>
		<index level1="Germany" level2="population policies"/>
		<index level1="World War I" level2="population and"/>
		<index level1="Giroud, Gabriel"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>International Aspects of Birth Control</head>
		<byline>by Margaret Sanger</byline>
		<p>In the present attitude of <del>continental</del>
			<place>Europe</place> toward the problem of birth control there are a number of
			illuminating contrasts. The change in the attitude of <place>France</place>
			<add>in regard to repopulation</add> is especially indicative of the corroding ironies
			of "victory". It is decidedly worth while, for instance, to compare the present official
			policy with the opinion and general practice before August, 1914. Then <add>we</add>
			discover that the present policy and propaganda of the <org reg="France, Government of"
				>French government</org> is practically identical with that of the <org
				reg="Germany, Government of">Imperial German government</org> before its downfall.
			But even more illuminating is to discover the differences between the new militaristic,
			imperialistic, <del>reactionary</del>
			<add>and "victorious"</add>
			<place>France</place> of today, <del>in this matter of "repopulation"</del>, and the
			grim necessities that confront her defeated and starving neighbors.</p>
		<p>Surely it is not without significance <del>and well worth detailed study</del> to find
			that France, where, as <del>Mr.</del>
			<person reg="Dell, Robert"><add>Robert</add> Dell</person> recently informed us,
			reaction and militarism have most firmly entrenched themselves since the Armistice, has
			renewed her great campaign for "repopulation," has moreover passed drastic laws
			forbidding the sale and circulation of contraceptives, and is making the most desperate
			efforts to stamp out all birth control agitation. Of course it was only to be expected
			that there would come, as one of inevitable symptoms of war-hysteria, this cry for a
			larger population. Even before the curtain had fallen on the vast pageant of disease and
			death and devastation, the wily <del>imperialists took</del>
			<add>militarists had taken</add> advantage of <add>the</add> country's
				<del>emotional</del> unbalance to set <del>the</del>
			<add>its</add> women to the task of aimless childbearing. Thus are sown the surest and
			most fertile seeds of future wars. One must not be blinded to the sinister Machiavellian
			wisdom of this policy <del>: except that</del>
			<add>nevertheless,</add> with the passing of the present hysteria, it is certain that
			the French will return to long established habits of prudence and foresight. France, as
			a nation, has too long been devoted to the principle of "the self-determination of small
			families."</p>
		<p>However, it is a fact that the birthrate has become enormous. French maternity hospitals
			have been so crowded that women have been delivered in the corridors, the courtyards,
			the <emph rend="underline">lingeries,</emph> even in the outsheds. But in spite of this
			unprecedented increase in the birth rate, the chauvinistic champions of "repopulation"
			are gradually discovering certain bitter truths about the futulity of indiscriminate
			fertility. <del>This</del>
			<add>The</add> answer to this fever of frenzied fertility came with the recent
			publication of the infant mortality rates. We learn that <del>out</del>
			<add>of</add> every thousand babies less than one year old at <place
				reg="St. Pol, France">St. Pol</place>, 509 have died; at <place
				reg="Halluin, France">Halluin</place>, 507; at <place reg="Mons-en-Baroeul, France"
				>Mars-en-Barzoeuf</place>, 414; at <place reg="Lille, France">Lille</place>, 294; at
				<place reg="Rouen, France">Rouen</place>, 251. In <place reg="Paris, France"
				>Paris</place>, in the words of an impartial authority, "<q>half the children die
				before they are even aware of their existence.</q>" The statistics for children of
			two, three, four and five years, are scarcely less appalling. It is a simple enough
			matter to bring children into this world: it is more difficult to keep them here.</p>
		<p>One French champion of "safe, sane and rapid repopulation" has somewhat belatedly pointed
			out that the propaganda can only be rendered fruitful by the universal establishment of
			prophylactic and sex-hygiene clinics, so that the health of both parents and child,
				<add>then</add> may be assured and the rate of survival be increased. Even the
			advocates of repopulation are thus almost forcibly led to the very door of birth
			control; and yet they refuse to recognize how organically interwoven are the ideas of
			sex-hygiene and birth control. Despite this self-evident truism, the present reactionary
			government of France has passed drastic laws against birth control and has, let us hope
			but temporarily, effected the suppression of <title type="journal">Le
				Neo-Malthusien</title>, edited so long and courageously by Monsieur <person
				reg="Giroud, Gabriel">G. Hardy</person>. With the first change of government, it is
			almost certain, the laws will be repealed. It would take at least twenty five years of
			their enforcement to reveal illegible <add>any</add> possible results. illegible In
			France at least, it is practically impossible to enforce such legislation. Nevertheless,
			one must recognize the tremendous sweep of this reaction in favor of a large
			population.</p>
		<p>Today, France has practically adopted the policy of the old imperial
				<place>Germany</place>. There, in a country "saturated" with an over-dense
			population, with a highbirth rate and ever increasing population, birth control was <gap
				extent="one word" reason="illegible"/>
			<add>discouraged</add> by the imperial government. The dire consequences are
illeg			painfully evident today. Yet evidently the politicians who are today directing the
			destinies of France are blind to any possible connection between overpopulation and war,
			and with war, starvation. Otherwise, how could they now urge their own people to
			increase and multiply and thus <del>increase</del> complicate <add>the</add> economic
			and social disorders <add>of the world.</add></p>
		<p><add>It <del>is</del> was the</add> boast of Imperial Germany that the children which
			were brought into the world at the state's behest were <add>well</add> cared for by
				<del>the state</del>
			<add>the government</add>, that under the supervision of the state <add>they</add> were
			given a sound education <add>as well as the benefits of health and welfare
				agencies</add>
			<del>and</del>
			<add>and were</add> sent out into the various countries of the <add>world</add> as
			highly efficient and valuable citizens. The difficulty was, the protagonists claimed,
			that the State which had <del>expended so much time and energy in the training</del>
			<add>invested in the health and efficiency</add> of these citizens was <del>so
				often</del> deprived, by the very limitations of her boundaries, of the fruits of
			their labors, from which alien and <add>often</add> rival governments derived the
			benefits. This, I <del>believe</del>
			<add>found</add> , was one of the arguments advanced to support the policy of expansion
			and new territory. We know today that these children who were brought into the world
				<del>under</del>
			<add>with</add> the encouragement of the state left it under the same
				condition<del>s</del>.</p>
		<p>Today in prostrate Germany and <place>Austria</place> one finds a more desperate and
			therefore less shy hypocritical state of affairs. There the only imperialism that
			remains is the imperialism of King Hunger. While little children are starving, there can
			be no <add>sincere</add> cry of "repopulation." Hunger dictates its own grim laws. I do
			not mean to recount here the monstrous details of the ravages of starvation,
			malnutrition and tuberculosis upon great populations of Central and Eastern Europe. The
			pitiful condition of the women and children has already been impressed upon America by
			those who are attempting to administer to their needs. For me, the most significant
			point is that the mothers of Germany and Austria are finally and gradually awakening to
			a consciousness of the crime of bringing children into a world that is so woefully
			unprepared to receive them. <del>It is</del> When you stop to think <del><unclear resp="MSPP">that you need too</unclear></del> that the <add>little</add> victims of cedema,
				rachitis and tuberculosis who manage to survive these
			disastrous days <del>must</del>
			<add>will</add> tomorrow become fathers and mothers, if their race is to continue,
				<del>And <gap extent="one word" reason="illegible"/> one</del>
			<add>You</add> realize <add>that</add> if some malevolent <del>God</del> 
			<add>Being</add> had deliberately decided upon the dwarfing and stunting of the human
			race for generations to come, no better method could have been devised for its
			accomplishment. Perhaps it is the painful realization of this that has crystallized into
			the movement to legalize, within certain well-defined limits, the right to abortion.</p>
		<p>In this movement to annul the laws prohibiting abortion, and in the legislation now
			before the <org>Reichstag</org>, we find the very opposite to the French cry for
			"repopulation" and the most eloquent sign of Germany's desperate outlook. It is truly
			legislation dictated by King Hunger, and much as one can understand and sympathize with
			the spirit which <del>undermines</del>
			<add>prompts</add> it, it is a <del>rather</del> clumsy <del>
				<add><gap extent="one word" reason="illegible"/> cruel</add>
			</del> and deliberate evasion of the problem of birth control. <del>In trying to find
				out why even the leaders of the movement to legalize abortion were opposed to the
				method of birth control, I came upon some interesting facts.</del></p>
		<p>Before the war there had sprung up, both in Germany and Austria, a lively birth control
			or Neo-Malthusian agitation, carried on in Germany by Dr. <person reg="Marcuse, Julian"
				>Julian Marcuse</person>, Dr. <person reg="Bernstein, Eduard">Bernstein</person>, and a
			number of laymen of the "extreme left". They were bitterly opposed by the entire
			Social-Democratic movement. They were attacked by such outstanding personalities as
				<person reg="Kautsky, Karl">Karl Kautsky</person>, <person reg="Luxemburg, Rosa"
				>Rosa Luxemburg</person>, <person reg="Zetkin, Clara">Clara Zetkin</person>, and
			others who have since become notable in the <del>socialist</del> Communist movement.
			Both in Germany and Austria, I am compelled to record the <del>Marxist</del> Communists
			have bitterly opposed the principles of birth control, and have actively combatted the
			propaganda. <del>It is a strange fact that despite the ever increasing difficulties of
				life since the overthrowal of the monarchies, that this antagonism has incresed. It
				has even led to the suppression by the "revolutionary" authorial of a small birth
				control periodical published in Berlin by Dr. <person reg="Goldstein, Arthur"
					>Goldstein</person>. Nevertheless,</del></p>
		<p>The root of this antagonism lies, of course, in the Marxian opposition to the theory of
				<person reg="Malthus, Thomas Robert">Malthus</person>, which carries with it the
				<add>unpleasant</add> implication that the working classes may be responsible for
			their own miseries. <del>The</del> German Marxians have always been the bitterest
			antagonists of Malthus; and none of them, as far as I know, <del>have</del>
			<add>has</add> ever tried to reconcile the Marxian idea of revolution with the
			principles of neo-Malthusianism. Thus unwittingly, it seems to me, in encouraging
			unrestricted <add>or "natural"</add> propagation, they <add>have</add> played into the
			hands of the imperialists and <del>illegible</del>
			<add>militarists.</add></p>
		<p>Even today, the militarists in Germany are calling loudly for more babies, even though
			millions of them are dying and starving. Thus, unless the world can somehow prevent it,
			may recommence the same old cradle competition, <del>that competition in
				conception</del> that is inevitably followed by <add>the</add> competition
				<add>in</add> armament.</p>
		<p>The most decisive action against this folly I found among the Syndicalists, whose aims
			and ideas were explained to me by their leader <person reg="Rocker, Rudolf">Rudolph
				Rocker</person> of <place reg="Berlin, Germany">Berlin</place>. With a territory
			much more restricted than before the war, with new millions sent back from <place
				reg="Alsace-Lorraine, France">Alsace-Lorraine</place> and <place>Poland</place>,
			with a total population even greater than in 1914, <del>it is now an absolute necessity
				for Germany to reduce illegible her population,</del>
			<add>the reduction of her population is now for Germany an absolute necessity</add>
			according to the Syndicalists, whose propaganda is in a large part, devoted to spreading
			the idea of birth control. If the new militarism is to be combatted, they claim Birth
			Control is the first important step. They aim deliberately at the substitution of
			quality for quantity, as the complete avoidance of any possible taint of militarism, and
			in developing gradually a country devoted to philosophy, music, arts and science.<del>
				The inspiration for this illegible for a few words.</del> It is a hopeful sign to
			realize that this <del>illegible</del>
			<add>idea</add> is growing steadily and has enlisted many of the finest spirits of
			modern Germany.</p>
		<p>Immediately after the "revolution", a movement was organized aiming at the abolition of
			the laws prohibiting abortion and seeking to bring scientifically abortion within the
			reach of hopelessly afflicted mothers. Paradoxically enough, many of the leaders of this
			movement, notably <person reg="Ferch, Johann">Johann Ferch</person>, formerly a
			typesetter and now an author, are opposed to the doctrines of prevention of
			conception.</p>
		<p>I made prolonged and widely varying efforts to probe this contradiction. After
			questioning a number of eminent gynecologists and many of the hopeless and desperate
			mothers, I have come to the conclusion that this opposition on the part of officials and
			physicians is rooted in the conviction that the moral prerogative must remain in the
			hands of the State and the community, rather than to be given to the mother-to-be
			herself. Maternity, in this view, is only secondarily the woman's affair. Birth control,
			they claim, gives women too great a power <del>of</del>
			<add>over</add> the future of the country and the race. To give her <del>a</del>
			knowledge of birth control is to give her <del>a</del> power that can never be recalled.
				"<q who="UNK">I am willing to check our population during this period of intense
				struggle,</q>" an eminent specialist confessed to me, "<q who="UNK">but merely as a
				temporary expedient. To give German women a knowledge of Birth Control would be to
				delegate to them a dangerous power, a knowledge they would not give up when better
				conditions return.</q>" It had never entered the mind of this scientist that it
			might possibly be far more dangerous to the future welfare of his country to withhold
			this knowledge from the women, that possibly even the present plight might in someway be
			connected with over-population and unrestricted breeding.</p>
		<p>In Austria, both the Church and the present state are of course, absolutely opposed to
			the <del>doctrine</del>
			<add>principle</add> of birth control. There the propaganda is carried on with
			unflinching courage <del>only</del> by the extreme left of the labor movement.
			Socialists, I am reliably informed, are either indifferent or <del>openly</del> hostile,
			while the "communists" are openly and absolutely opposed to the idea. Here at least is
			the one point of agreement <del>between</del>
			<add>amongst</add> these warring factions!</p>
		<p>Midway between the illogical and desperate extremes represented in the current attitude
			of <add>official</add> France on the one hand and <add>official</add> Germany on the
			other, the liberal open-mindedness of <place>Great Britain</place> is one of the most
			encouraging signs of the times. In <place>England</place> there is "<soCalled>wide
				open</soCalled>" discussion of birth control, allied as it is with the problem of
			over-population, state pensions and emigration. And there is growing up an enlightened
			and intelligent public opinion <add>of every shade</add> supporting the doctrine. In a
			recent address before the <org>Eugenics Education Society</org>, Dr. <person
				reg="Inge, William Ralph">W. R. Inge</person>, Dean of <org
				reg="St. Paul's Cathedral">St. Paul's</org>, a man of unquestioned intellectual
			integrity and one of the most prominent figures of the <org>Church of England</org>,
			declared: "<q who="INGWI">While eugenists understand those who say that birth control is
				forbidden by God, they have no patience with those who say that we can have
				unrestricted and unregulated propagation without disaster.</q>" He added that the
			present tax-paying classes of Great Britain were being taxed out of existence. Soon
			therefore, the dean argued, the working classes would have to pay taxes for the
			maintenance of the unfit and the incompetent; and that they would then see to it that
			all their fellow workers would adopt in regard to their families, the trade union
			principle of "restriction of output." The point is that this was widely quoted in the
			English newspapers. Papers of every variety of opinion are continually advancing
			arguments in favor of birth control. An enlightened public opinion of this type is
			indicative of a critical and <del>illegible</del> resistant attitude toward hysterical
			imperialism. Freedom of expression is absolutely necessary, it seems to me, on the
			subject of birth control, and <del>illegible</del> it is in England that one finds the
			most encouraging frankness on the subject, an open-mindedness that is well illustrated
			in an article by <person reg="Shackelton, Edith">Edith Shackleton</person>, published by
			the <title type="journal">London Daily Sketch</title>, in which she goes so far as to
			write: "<q who="SHAED">Fathers and mothers today are under the illusion that the rest of
				us believe that they brought their children into the world from a high stern sense
				of public duty--which is about as reasonable as to expect us to believe that they
				found them under gooseberry bushes.</q>" Compare this cool and <del>illegible </del>
			<add>almost</add> cynical sanity with the "repopulation" balderdash that finds its way
			even into such well-informed French dailies as <person reg="Tery, Gustave">Gustave
				Tery</person>'s <title>L'oeuvre</title>.</p>
		<p>England is at last awakening to a consciousness that the problems of population,
			parenthood and birth control are closely interwoven and practically inseperable. This is
			sufficiently evident in the second report of the <org>National Birth Rate Commission
			</org>recently published under the title of "<title type="book">Problems of Population
				and Parenthood</title>" (<org>Chapman &amp; Hall</org>). In this report we find
			ample evidence of the <del>weakening</del>
			<add>collapse</add> of the case against birth control in Great Britain, since the
			objections to the <del>doctrine</del>
			<add>principle</add> and practice are <del>
				<add>illegible</add>
			</del> based upon outworn theological dogma and traditional moral prejudice.
				<del>But</del>
			<add>Among</add> the more alive and sensitive intellects of the English clergy there are
			to be found defenders and even eloquent champions of the <del>doctrine</del>
			<add>principle.</add> To me the most significant movement in England <del>is</del> has
			been the gradual and now rapidly crystallizing spirit of true statesmanship that is
			coming to the defence of a much maligned and little understood <del>principle</del>
			<del>subject</del>. It is not too much to say that in England Birth Control is now
			enlisting in its service the most representative minds and enlightened public
			opinion.</p>
		<p>In this country we are too apt to look upon these problems of parenthood and population
			as something that only remotely and vaguely concern us. <del>illegible.</del>
			<del>Illegible sentence.</del>
			<add>One cannot view the European situations honestly without coming to the realization
				that</add> more and more directly <del>that</del> these problems are our
				<del>affairs.</del>
			<add>immediate concern</add>. We know that in her reconstruction and in her
			imperialistic activities France is looking to us for financial support and backing. We
			know that the <org>European Relief Council</org> is appealing for contributions for the
			three million five hundred thousand starving children of central Europe. We have
			received eloquent and moving appeals from the Near East. On top of all this, our
			president <add>has just</add> appointed a nation-wide committee to collect funds for the
			thirty million Chinese who are starving to death. Whether we wish it or not, the world
			has become one community; and in this community <del>illegible</del> the less crowded
			and more properous countries are called upon to ameliorate and relieve the condition of
			the overcrowded and starving. Vicariously, through our <del>rich men and women</del>,
				<del>our profiteers and politicians</del>, <add>bankers and politicians and our
				generous emotional sympathies</add> it is we who are indulging in this carnival of
				<del>illegible</del>
			<add>illegible-like</add> international charity. <del>Our emotions are stirred-- the
				symptoms of the disease.</del></p>
		<p>I do not mean to criticize the altruistic and humanitarian impulse that prompts our
			response. But since either the <org>League of Nations</org> nor any of the other
			distinguished statesmen who are at present direction the affairs of this planet find the
			matter of any importance, it is the duty of some one to point out the danger of
			unchecked and unrestricted propagation in any part of the world <add>illegible.</add> We
			may restrict immigration; we may pass exclusion laws; but the problem will
				<add>always</add> come back to us in another guise. We find ourselves
				<add>still</add> facing the vast uncontrolled and unceasing activity of the blind
			instinct of reproduction, struggling for world supremacy. Altruism, sympathy, sentiment,
			love--whatever you choose to call it--is making feeble <add>and futile</add> efforts to
			administer to the miseries created by this unrestricted propagation, <add>which is
				only</add> occasionally checked by famine, <del>a</del> war or <del>a</del> plague.
			Reason is looking on, <del>idly</del> theorizing on the situation. <del>Illegible</del>
			Until intelligence directs <add>and controls</add> not merely the effort to relieve the
			world miseries but <del>illegible</del>
			<add>also the universally</add> unrestrained propagation that lies at the root of most
			of them, <del>that we illegible may illegible expect</del> the <del>inevitable</del>
			cancellation of any world progress <add>is inevitable</add>.</p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
