<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed draft speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2010/04/07 AC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-11 CH clean regs and other errors</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1936-00-00">1936</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied>Introduction for Leon J. Cole</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp128179</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Library of Congress Microfilm</title>, 129:676</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to" level3="in remote places"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <gap extent="one page" reason="missing"/>
        <p>A fairly good record considering the material with which we must work.</p>
        <p> But we are not content to rest upon the laurels of these claims.-- We refuse to look
            back with satisfaction, rather do we look forward with impatient urgent demands.</p>
        <p> It is a curious fact that for all the hundreds of thousands of women in the more than
            300 Birth Control Clinics now operating in the <place reg="United States">United States
                of America</place> and that in the 13 years of our activity in the <org
                reg="Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau">Clinical Research Bureau</org> for the
            56,000 women it has advised, we have been forced to depend upon a method discovered and
            perfected by Dr. <person reg="Mensinga, Wilhelm">Mensinger</person> of
                <place>Germany</place> over sixty years ago! This is really an extraordinary
            situation and is precisely the reason why only a small fraction of the women in any
            country are able to benefit by contraception, <add>this condition</add> will remain
            until we find methods more suitable to the economic, social conditions of the masses. </p>
        <p> We know that we have touched only a small fraction of those millions most in need of
            contraception. We have only scratched the surface of a problem which goes beyond the
            barrier of a single nation, a single race in fact beyond the boundaries of our own
            country. For <add>with</add> the whole problem of fertility, controlled and uncontrolled
            depends not merely <add>upon</add> the future of the Human race, but the graver one of
            its salvaging and its survival.</p>
        <p> We have started to clear the way of rubbish and have uncovered many obstacles. We cannot
            go much further onward and upward without help. The submerged sections of our population
            are clamoring for cheap effective means to control the size of the family--They have
            never had a chance for they cannot come to us--So we must go to them.</p>
        <p> The Birth Control Clinics have demonstrated fairly accurately that there are methods of
            contraception which can and will give good results. They have proven over a long period
            of time to be harmless and efficacious. To get results, however, it is necessary to be
            accessible to a medical or a qualified person who is equipped to advise and
            instruct.</p>
        <p> To those millions of women on farms and homesteads, and in mining areas where the doctor
            is only an occasional visitor in times of illness, there is so far no contraceptive
            which can be recommended as efficacious and harmless. This is our great present and
            urgent need. She can not come to us. So we must go to her, but we must have for her
            use--methods suitable to her needs.</p>
        <p> We must build the future of humanity--Waste of Mother and Child life. This will continue
            in an endless chain unless we face these facts fearlessly and do something about
            them.</p>
        <p> Birth Control movement has arrived at a stage in its development to help that part of
            the population accessible to hospitals, doctors or other health service where properly
            qualified teachers are available. It has so far no answer, no reliable help, for the
            women on homesteads, farms or outlying rural districts where medical help is not
            convenient. <del>This woman</del> These millions of women are our problem--our next
            concerted effort must be on their behalf. If she can not come to us, we must go to
            her.</p>
        <p> But, before we can reach her needs with the same results as attained by the city woman,
            we must have methods of contraception: cheaper, easier to apply, as harmless as those we
            now have, have proved to be.</p>
        <p> The scientist must come to our aid. We want his cooperation, his wisdom, his impersonal
            courage and vision.</p>
        <p> We must place the Scientist on the bridge as captain of our Cause, to guide us into the
            Unknown Future. (Introduce <person reg="Cole, Leon J.">Prof. Cole</person>) </p>


    </docBody>
</doc>
