<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed draft speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2003/10/06 NS</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-16 EK clean regs</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-05-02 EK correct proof</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-12-10 CH proof tags</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1924-04-04">
            <supplied resp="MSPP">4 Apr 1924</supplied>
        </docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart type="article">
                <supplied resp="MSPP">Bertrand Russell Luncheon Speech</supplied>
            </titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp128187</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
            <bibl>Library of Congress Microfilm 129:697B</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>This short introduction was prepared for a luncheon in honor of <person
                reg="Russell, Bertrand">Bertrand Russell</person>given by <org>American Birth
                Control League</org> in the <place reg="New York, NY">New York</place> home of its
            Vice President <person reg="Delafield, Charlotte">Charlotte Delafield</person>.</p>
        <index level1="Russell, Bertrand"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <p>First I wish to express my appreciation to our gracious hostess for making it possible
            for us to meet our honored guest in this nice informal way. </p>
        <p>I can not tell you how pleased I am that Mr. Russell has <del>consented to be with
                us today</del> accepted our invitation to come here today. </p>
        <p>Most of us think of great philosophers and great scientists as remote individuals,
            eternally buried in dusty studies, poring over dry books in near sighted fashion, far
            away from the pressing problems of ordinary human beings. </p>
        <p>Here, I am happy to tell you, is one great philosopher, one great scientist, who is no
                <person reg="Crane, Ichabod">Ichabod Crane</person>. Great as his knowledge is,
            supreme as his position is, Bertrand Russell is a world figure not because of his
            learning, but because of his <del>courage</del>
            <add>vision</add> and his humanism. <add>For</add></p>
        <p>Here is a philosopher who has had the <del>courage</del>
            <add>vision</add> to bring the whole battery of his science to the service of humanity
            at large. </p>
        <p>His weapons have not been the cold steely surgical instruments of scientific analysis.
            His victories have been won by <add>courage</add>, human warmth, the idealists passion
                <del>and heroism</del>
            <add>for truth</add>. </p>
        <p>How great Mr. Russell's courage is, is shown by his daring to stand for the
                <add>unpopular</add> doctrine of birth control. </p>
        <p>I think he will agree with me that this is not a matter of troubled domestic life, to be
            dismissed with a wink, but <add>embodies</add> involves other social problems--those of
            population, international peace and the future of the race. </p>
        <p>But perhaps Mr Russell will kindly consent to tell us what he thinks on the subject, and
            how it will serve in bringing about that new civilization for which he so passionately
            pleads.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
