<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed draft article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2009/08/03 LL</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/10/18 EK </prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
       <docDate value="1929-00-00"><supplied>1929</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Motherhood Enslaved in Italy</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp129029</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Papers</title>, Library of Congress</bibl>
            <bibl>130:0166.</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="FRE">French</name>
            <name id="CARMA">Carli, Mario</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="Mussolini, Benito" level2="policy of"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="enslavement of"/>
        <index level1="motherhood" level2="conscripted"/>
        <index level1="overpopulation"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="war and"/>
        <index level1="Italy" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="Italy" level2="pro-natalism in"/>
        <index level1="Italy" level2="birth rate in"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Motherhood Enslaved in Italy<lb/>or<lb/>
            <lb/>"Mussolini's Insult to Womankind"<lb/></head>
        <byline>Margaret Sanger</byline>
        <p>The conscription of motherhood appears to be the inevitable next step in the Fascist
            policy of <person reg="Mussolini, Benito">Mussolini</person>. Benito's Napoleonic
            complex and <emph rend="underline"><foreign lang="FRE">folie de grandeur</foreign>
            </emph> have not as yet reached the point at which he compels by force every Italian
            woman to undergo the ordeal of periodic pregnancy, but he is not lacking sycophants
            ready and willing to give expression to expressed thoughts that lurk uncrystallized
            behind his noble brow. Signor <person reg="Carli, Mario">Mario Carli</person>,
                    <title><emph rend="underline">Time</emph></title> (January 21, 1929) Mario Carli
            has been making a passionate demand for the immediate conscription of Italian
            motherhood. He is directly quoted by Time: “<q who="CARMA">Every Italian woman must give
                to her country at least one son every two years. A refusal on this point will be
                equivalent to pushing men on the road to polygamy–-which, however, is contrary to
                Fascist principles. Flight in the face of maternity-–that divine maternity which
                together with some brief physical suffering, gives the loftiest and deepest joys of
                life (sic!)-–is as culpable as the desertion of soldiers in the face of the enemy,
                as the attempt of the taxpayer to escape the payment of taxes.....</q>” Furthermore:
                “<q who="CARMA">Voluntary barrenness and reducing cures to rid her miserable body of
                superfluous fat are the greatest crimes a woman can commit under the Fascist
                regime.</q>”</p>
        <p>This tyrannical threat is scracely veiled. It indicates the extent to which the impudent
            dictatorship of Mussolini has gone in <place>Italy</place>. Indifferent or easy-going
            people in this country may retort that this idea is not to be taken seriously. We wish
            that such were the case. But history of the world demonstrates that conscription of
            womanhood has been enforced innumerable times in the past, and that it is not outside
            the bounds of possibility that it can be enforced in the future. Every ambitious
            militarist in the history of the world has called upon women to undertake the rapid
            multiplication of cannon-fodder. History from the forgotten potentates of the East to
                <person reg="Caesar, Julius">Julius Caesar</person>, <person
                reg="Bonaparte, Napoleon">Napoleon Bonaparte</person> to the rulers who brought
            about the Great War, is crowded with such instances.</p>
        <p>The conscription of motherhood, and the advocacy of “<q>cradle
                competition</q>", is a policy which every dictator ambitious for his own
            glory, almost automatically advocated. Thus he attempts to assert his own godlike
            superiority over the rest of humanity. Thus he makes of all men soldiers and of all
            women slaves and breeding-machines. Even if there is no immediate danger of Mussolini's
            enforcing the dictum already expressed by his editorial sycophant, the very expression
            of this idea, and the reiterated call for an even higher birth-rate in Italy, become of
            the most sinister significance in European politics. Mussolini is demanding of his
            subjects a greater and greater over-population. He is aiming at the production in the
            Italian peninsula of an expanding and therefore an explosive population.</p>
        <p>Increased population-pressure, and eventually over-population, bring with them a lowered
            standard of living, and also a search for new territories, inevitably to be acquired by
            conquest, and therefore by war. Mussolini and his cohorts are therefore progressively
            undermining the instability of <place>Europe</place> and the entire Mediterranean zone.
            The alternatives appear to be: either Birth Control or War. Only a decade has passed
            since the signing of the Armistice and all of us are still paying, in one way or
            another, for the last international debauch of blood.</p>
        <p>Seemingly remote as we may be from the scene of Benito Mussolini's strutting theatricals,
            all of us are thus involved in this last insult cast in the face of Occidental
            civilization. While the material prosperity of Italy continues-–a prosperity dependent
            to no slight extent upon the millions of dollars annualy expended in Italy by American
            travellers and visitors-–the Fascist regime will continue to take credit for the
            country's good fortune.</p>
        <p>The insult to Italian womanhood uttered by Mario Carli is an insult to all womankind.
            American women to whom the ancient glories of Italy have made an esthetic appeal, would
            do well to consider these implications. If they would courageously decide to postpone
            all travel in Italy until that country again demonstrates its right to a place in
            Occidental civilization, an invaluable lesson in discipline and international courtesy
            would not be long in demonstrating its value. Those who respect women will stay out of
            Italy until the last act of her present tragedy has been played.</p>
        <signed><del>M.S.</del></signed>
        <signed>Margaret Sanger</signed>
    </docBody>
</doc>
