<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<doc xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="meptei3xMSP.xsd"
    type="Typed Draft Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2010/08/27 EK</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/06/07 CE</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/06/20 CE</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1936-11-24">24 Nov 1936</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>My Experiences in India</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp129033</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of
                Congress</title></bibl>
            <bibl>LCM 130:183</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp><name id="JORDA">Jordan, David Starr</name><name id="MEGJO"
                    >Megaw, John Wallace</name><name id="GANMO">Gandhi, Mohandas
                    K.</name><name id="UNK">Unknown</name></resp>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Handwritten notes and insertions by Margaret
            Sanger.</p>
        <p>Sanger was introduced by <person reg="Taylor, Jeannette">Mrs.
                Taylor</person> of the <org>Birth Control League of Alleghany
                County</org>, who read: <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret
                Sanger</person> is the President of the <org>National Committee
                on Federal Legislation for Birth Control</org>, and Director of
            the <org>Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau</org>, <place
                reg="United States">America</place>’s oldest and largest birth
            control clinic. She went to <place>India</place> as representative
            of the <org>Birth Control International Information Centre</org>,
                <place reg="London, England">London</place>, of which she is
            also the President.</p>
        <index level1="India" level2="women in"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="population rate in"/>
        <index level1="awards"/>
        <index level1="war" level2="birth control and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Radio Address by Margaret Sanger on "My Experiences in
            India"</head>
        <dateline><place reg="Pittsburgh, PA">Pittsburgh</place> PA, Wednesday 9
            A.M.</dateline>
        <p>In <place>India</place>, where I spent a good part of the past year,
            there is a proverb: "<q who="JORDA">“Wisdom is knowing what to do,
                skill is knowing how to do it but virtue is in the doing
            it.</q>" As I go from country to country, from city to city, through
            the world, I am convinced that in America today we have the wisdom,
            the knowledge and the skill, in knowing what to do and how to solve
            our problems, but we do not have the virtue <add>that thing call it
                virtue, courage or <unclear resp="MSPP"
                >initiative</unclear></add> to do it.</p>
        <p>I was invited to come to India by the <org>All India Woman’s
                Conference</org>, representing between eleven and twelve
            millions of the most intelligent women of the <place>Orient</place>.
            I was greatly surprised that so many women in India spoke English
            and were well informed about problems which we in the West are so
            futilely trying to solve. I was also surprised to find that not only
            educated Indians, particularly doctors and social workers, were
            willing and eager to find some way of dealing with overpopulation,
            but that men and women of all classes were pathetically anxious to
            learn about birth control. Women begged and pleaded for information
            about how to limit their families and space their children. </p>
        <p>This was not at all what I had been led to expect in India. People
            who claimed to be familiar with conditions, with whom I had talked
            before I landed in <place reg="Bombay, India">Bombay</place>, were
            pessimistic.</p>
        <p>“<q who="UNK">Their religion makes it an Indian woman’s highest duty
                to have children,</q>” I was told. “<q who="UNK">The more she
                has the better she likes it.</q>”</p>
        <p>One highly educated Indian man said to me: “<q who="UNK">Why, Mrs.
                Sanger, you can do nothing. We all admit that birth control is
                the only answer to India’s population problem, but the women
                themselves don’t want it.</q>”</p>
        <p>I was sure they were wrong. I have always been sure that women in all
            lands and all ages have instinctively desired family spacing. I was
            sure that in a land like India, where you find women seeking a new
            freedom, economic and social, there would be thousands of minds
            reaching out to find knowledge which would mean freedom.</p>
        <p>So I said nothing, <add>but waited.</add> I wanted to learn for
            myself whether the women of India were so different from the women
            of any other country in the world, that they wanted and would cling
            to endless childbearing if the way to voluntary motherhood were
            opened to them. </p>
        <p>Just two days after I arrived in Bombay I went to the “chawls,” the
            long rows of tenement houses where the city’s mill workers are
            crowded together in small dark rooms. Children, their naked little
            bodies bone-thin, played in the streets, or sat listlessly in the
            shadow of the buildings. Mothers stared with inert eyes. Almost
            every one had a baby or small child on her hip.</p>
        <p> I knew that of every 1000 children born in Bombay, 298 die. I know
            that it has been estimated that 100 of every 1000 mothers in India
            die in childbirth. I looked at these poor, worn out women, at their
            undernourished, undersized children.</p>
        <p>“Ask this mother how many children she has,” I said to the social
            worker who accompanied me, <add>and</add> pointed to a woman in a
            ragged sari, squatting on the street, holding a baby in her
            arms.</p>
        <p>“<q who="UNK">Six,</q>” was the answer.<lb/> “<q>And how many
                dead?</q>”,I asked.<lb/> “<q>Five</q>”, she answered.<lb/> “<q>
                And how many more do you want,</q>” I pursued.<lb/></p>
        <p>She threw out her hands in a pathetic gesture. A look of fear came
            into her tired, lined face.</p>
        <p>“<q who="UNK">Please <name type="Deity">God</name>, no more!</q>”</p>
        <p> We talked to scores of mothers, some old, some young, and they all
            echoed the words, “<q who="UNK">Please God, no more.</q>”</p>
        <p>No Bombay man can again tell me that women of this city, or any city
            in India do not want information which will free them of the dread
            of bringing children into the world to rob those they already have
            of food and clothing and care, of the very breath of life. </p>
        <p> Every moment <del>from my arrival</del>
            <add>of my stay</add> in India was crowded with meetings and
            conferences, with interviews and lectures. The problem was not how
            to meet opposition, for there are no legal restrictions, such as we
            have in America, and practically no religious opposition. The task
            was how to train doctors, midwives and nurses, to organize clinics,
            and put the movement on a firm, scientific foundation as a public
            health measure.</p>
        <p>Birth control is a burning question in India, and those best
            qualified to understand India’s problems are aware of this.
            According to Major General <person reg="Megaw, John Wallace"
                >Megaw</person>, medical adviser to the <person
                reg="Unidentified">Secretary of State</person> for India, the
            population is rapidly outstripping industrial production and the
            situation can best be summed up in words “<q who="MEGJO">They do not
                get enough to eat.</q>” Experts agree that by 1941, when the
            next census is taken, India’s population may well number four
            hundred millions. </p>
        <p>Infant and maternal mortality are tragically high, but infant welfare
            work without birth control is making matters worse, for it saves the
            infants, only to let them starve later on. As in other countries,
            welfare work without birth control is dysgenic and chaotic, cruel as
            well as planless.</p>
        <p>I have attended many meetings of women in my lifetime, but the All
            India Woman’s Conference will remain one of the outstanding
            inspirations of my life. I found among these women an outspoken
            directness of opinion, a fearlessness in facing issues as they are,
            that we in America would do well to follow. The Conference passed a
            resolution in favor of establishing birth control clinics.</p>
        <p>The <org>All India Medical Conference</org> took definite action in
            placing the subject of birth control where it belongs, as part of
            the physicians program for preserving the health of his nation. It
            passed a resolution recommending that instruction in conception
            control methods should form part of the curriculum in medical
            colleges and schools and in the training of health visitors, nurses
            and midwives.</p>
        <p>I also lectured and showed scientific films which I had with me on
            the <title type="film">Biology of Conception</title>, at the
                <org>All Indian Obstetric and Gynecological Congress</org>, the
            first of its kind in India. Indeed the movement got off to a good
            start in India, having the support of organized medicine, and of
            individual doctors everywhere.</p>
        <p>One of the highlights of my stay in India was my visit to <person
                reg="Gandhi, Mohandas K.">Mahatma Gandhi</person>, and two
            memorable conversations I had with him. Gandhi has aroused the men
            and women of India as no one else has done, and the women of India
            wanted me to se him. He turned out to be even a better feminist than
            I am. For I believe that parenthood and marriage should be put on a
            fifty-fifty basis, that the man as well as the woman should have
            something to say about how many children should be brought into the
            world. But Gandhi would leave all this to the women.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gandhi and I disagreed with mutual tolerance, and I am glad to
            say, respect. <q who="GANMO">“I think highly of your purpose,”</q>he
            said to me in parting. “<q who="GANMO">May God guide you
            right.</q>”</p>
        <p>By the time I left India, fifty teaching centers had been
            established, and supplies had been distributed to public health
            officials and hospitals. My plan on leaving India in the same as I
            make here in America: Those in authority, those in charge of public
            health, those advocating the cause of social and mental health
            should take a firm stand and include birth control knowledge and its
            practice where it is desired and needed. This is a responsibility
            that can no longer be evaded or shirked, and one which the masses
            have a right to expect.</p>
        <p><add>It is gratifying to come to Wabash Bldg <place
                    reg="Pittsburgh, PA">Pittsburgh</place> to find there is
                also a center here where mothers can go &amp; receive from
                Doctors advice to space birth &amp; control size of
                family.</add></p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
