<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Draft Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/06/28 CE</prepDate><prepDate>2011/11/28 CH correct types</prepDate><prepDate>2011/11/30 CH Correct typo</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1928-12-19">19 Dec 1928</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>The Necessity for Birth Control</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp129046</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of
                Congress</title></bibl>
            <bibl><title>LCM</title> 130:0226</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="HUGVI">Hugo, Victor-Marie</name>
            <name id="MUSBE">Mussolini, Benito</name>
            <name id="SHAGE">Shaw, George Bernard</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
            <name id="WELHE">Wells, Herbert George</name>
            <name id="MSPP">Margaret Sanger Papers Project</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Handwritten additions are by Margaret Sanger.</p>
        <index level1="abortion" level2="birth control vs."/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues" level3="in US"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits and risks"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="in marriages"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="international"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="and marriage"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="medical community and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="continence"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="instructions"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="sterilization"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="opposition to"/>
        <index level1="Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau" level2="records of"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="efforts to reduce"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="population growth and"/>
        <index level1="child labor"/>
        <index level1="child spacing"/>
        <index level1="child welfare"/>
        <index level1="children" level2="rights of"/>
        <index level1="children" level2="unwanted"/>
        <index level1="England" level2="population policies of"/>
        <index level1="eugenics" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="eugenics" level2="positive"/>
        <index level1="Europe" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="family planning"/>
        <index level1="family size"/>
        <index level1="family size" level2="class-based"/>
        <index level1="feeble-minded persons" level2="fertility and birth rate of"/>
        <index level1="physically disabled and diseased" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="France" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="heredity" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="Holland" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Germany" level2="population policies of"/>
        <index level1="Italy" level2="overpopulation and"/> 
        <index level1="Japan" level2="overpopulation and"/>
        <index level1="marriage age" level2="women"/>
        <index level1="mentally disabled and diseased" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="infant"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="maternal"/>
        <index level1="Mussolini, Benito" level2="policy of"/>
        <index level1="New York City" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="population" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="population growth" level2="natural resources and"/>
        <index level1="population growth" level2="regulation of"/>
        <index level1="population growth" level2="standard of living and"/>
        <index level1="&quot;unfit&quot; to reproduce" level2="descriptions of"/>
        <index level1="&quot;unfit&quot; to reproduce" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="population policies of"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="health of"/>
        <index level1="working classes" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="working classes" level2="children"/>
        <index level1="working classes" level2="fertility of"/>
        <index level1="working classes" level2="living conditions of"/>
        </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>The Necessity for Biirth Control</head>
        <byline>by Mrs. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret
            Sanger</person></byline>
        <p><org>Auditorium Theater</org>, <place reg="Oakland, CA">Oakland, California</place>.
                <dateline><date value="1928-12-19">December 19th 1928</date></dateline>.</p>
        <p>It was <person reg="Hugo, Victor-Marie">Victor Hugo</person> who said
                <q who="HUGVI">there was no force in the world so great as that
                of an idea whose hour had come</q>. Some of us believe that the
            hour for Birth Control has come. There are very few subjects
                <add>which have so large a </add>
            <del>of so</del> practical <del>a</del> significance which
                <add>cut</add> so deeply into the foundations of social
                <del>welfare</del>
            <add>evolution</add> as Birth Control. There are few
                <add>other</add> subjects that have been left so long in
            obscurity while, at the same time, there are few that can so
            demonstrate their importance as Birth Control has done in the past
            few years.</p>
        <p><person reg="Shaw, George Bernard">George Bernard Shaw</person> said
            that <q who="SHAGE">Birth Control is the most revolutionary idea of
                the twentieth century</q>. <person reg="Wells, Herbert George"
                >H.G. Wells</person> says <q who="WELHE">it is the most
                momentous fact of modern living</q>. I claim that Birth Control
            is <del>a</del>
            <add>the keynote of a </add> new moral responsibility, a new social
            awakening. It is not only a health and economic <del>safeguard</del>
            <add>expedient</add> but a great social <del>expedient</del>
            <add>principle</add> interlocked with the <add>spiritual</add>
            progress of the <del>human</del> race <add>and its future</add>.</p>
        <p>To define Birth Control, we say it is the conscious control of the
            birth-rate by scientific means that prevent the conception of human
            life. Prevent, remember. Prevent does not mean to interfere. It does
            not mean to destroy. There is no more interference with life through
            birth control than there is to remain unmarried or to live a
            celibate life. We also say “to control.” Control does not mean that
            you limit. When you control your furnace you do not have to put the
            fire out. When you control your motor you do not necessarily stop
            your car. To control the birth rate means that there shall be the
            same right for those who do not wish to have children as for those
            who do wish to have them. There are no objections to those who wish
            to increase the size of their families, but on the other side there
            seems to be a great deal of question and controversy as to the right
            of those who wish to limit or control the number of their children.
            Why, they say, should there be any necessity to control or limit
            population in this great land and especially out here in the west
            where there are so many large <del>spaces</del>
            <add>acres</add>of unused territory.</p>
        <p>Civilization is confronted with two problems-- pressure of population
            on the food supply <add>of the world</add> and the reconciling of
            humanitarian efforts with <del>the greatest improvement of the</del>
            race <add>improvement</add>. I believe birth control is the key to
            both. Statistics tell us that from fifteen to twenty millions of
            persons are born in this <del>country</del>
            <add>world</add> every year. That means fifty thousand a day.
            Certainly we <del>must</del> believe that something <del>must</del>
            <add>should</add> be done with this enormous <del>group</del>
            <add>increase</add> of <del>new</del> population.
            It must be controlled. There are only two ways of controlling it.
            INCREASING the death rate or DECREASING the birth rate. Which shall
            it be? History records the fact that population has always been kept
            down by war, by famine, by disease by floods and pestilence. Nature
            is most ruthless in extermination; she crushes to the wall the old,
            the sick, the demented, the diseased, the inefficient and through
            these means <del>was</del>
            <add>is</add> able to perfect her type. But civilization today will
            no longer permit those methods to operate. With the hand of charity
            and philanthropy, democracy and Christianity, we reach
            out and grapple with Nature. We take to ourselves these inefficient,
            demented, or feeble-minded persons and we tax the normal, the fit
            and the healthy members of the population for their care. Through
            these methods we are brining civilization to a queer pass. William
                <del>Sanyer</del>
            <add><person reg="Meyers, William Starr">Starr Meyer</person></add>
            of <org>Princeton University</org> tells us that out of our <gap
                reason="illegible" resp="MSPP"/>
            <add>one</add>
            <add>105,000,000</add> hundred and <del>twenty</del>
            <add>five</add> million people, only twenty million can be
            classified as intellectual. From <add>the 85 million thru</add>
            psychological, biological and other tests it is found that
            45-million are sub-normal, with intellects equal to juveniles of
            fifteen years; fifteen million were definitely feeble-minded, with
            eight year old minds; while 25-million could at best be classified
            as mediocre. Of course we all hope that we belong to the 20-million
            class. It is that enormous group of feeble-minded that gives concern
            to those of us who are socially minded.</p>
        <p>Many of us remember the two famous families, the <org
                reg="Kallikak Family">Kallikaks</org> and the <org
                reg="Juke Family">Jukes</org>. The first started by a
            feeble-minded man marrying a normal woman. We know that two
            feeble-minded persons have never been known to bring to birth a
            normal child, but here we started with a normal woman. 470 of their
            descendants were normal: 143 were feeble-minded: 36 were
            illegitimate; three were epileptics: 83 died in infancy: three were
            criminals and twenty-four died in houses of ill fame.</p>
        <p>The Jukes family had 1200 descendants; of these 130 were professional
            paupers; 135 were common criminals; 70 were thieves; the expense of
            maintaining this family was $1,300,00-- and that too, was in the
            days when we did not have to count the high cost of living. Today we
            know for a fact that the high proportion of feeble-minded in our
            population is one of the great problems of civilization.</p>
        <p>All over the country we find that institutions are not numerous
            enough or large enough to take care of our feeble-minded population.
                <place>California</place> has been one of the few States
            advanced enough to take hold of this question and try to solve it
            through sterilization. Reckoning three children for each
            feeble-minded couple, out of six thousand sterilized, California has
            saved herself eighteen thousand feeble minded persons.</p>
        <p>It is not sufficient to take only the feeble-minded who are in
            institutions; only a small proportion of them are there. Millions
            live with us-- with no regard whatever for the coming race. They
            continue to make our problems and to bring numerous children into
            the world.</p>
        <p>Our insane question is almost as serious. In <place>New York
                State</place> a few years ago there was a great deal of pride on
            the part of the <person reg="Smith, Albert Emmanuel"
                >Governor</person> and <org reg="New York State Assembly"
                >Legislature</org> because they came before the public and said
            they had been able to appropriate the sum of twenty-five million
            dollars for the care of the insane. No one seemed to ask what they
            were doing to decrease the numbers of the insane. New York has, and
            I presume California also, the practice of allowing inmates of
            asylums suffering from certain types of insanity to return home
            periodically on what is called the parole system. A man confined in
            an asylum after <del>for</del> a certain period of time is allowed
            to return to his family on certain occasions; also a mother or
            woman. There is no responsibility on the part of the State to see
            that anything is done, or any knowledge given to that inmate or his
            family to see that children do not come from that individual.</p>
        <p>We have had many cases where women, having been informed that the
            husband is returning, have come to our social agencies and begged
            that something should be done, often stating they already have two
            or three feeble-minded children or idiots. Often the women in these
            families are the bread-winner and she has begged the organizations,
            who are there to protect motherhood, to do something about this
            problem. In no case, in <place reg="New York City, NY">New York
                city</place>, have I know that these women were ever helped in a
            fundamental way. They have been told not to worry, have been cheered
            as much as they could be cheered, and told that when such a
            condition arose they could come to the pre-natal clinic and care
            given them-- and that is all. That seems to me a very short-sighted
            policy on the part of the social agencies and other groups,
            well-meaning, no doubt, but nevertheless very sentimental.</p>
        <p>Not only the feeble-minded and insane deserve consideration. There
            are two groups of people in the world-- not only in the
                <place>United States</place> but in almost all large cities of
            the civilized world. One group is what I term the small family
            group; the other is the large family group. When you look at the
            small family group you will see they have by far the best of it. It
            is there we find health, wealth, culture, education, intelligence.
            It is where there are few children, well spaced, that those few are
            brought up to full maturity. The children of this group are not sent
            to factories but to school, because of the desire of the parents to
            give them the best opportunities. They go to high school, to
            colleges, to universities. It is from this group that the best
            positions in the community are usually filled. It is from this group
            that those who desire to see large populations desire they should
            come.</p>
        <p>On the other hand is the large family group; it has a hard time. You
            find there poverty. Poverty and large families almost always go hand
            in hand. You find mothers bearing children far too frequently,
            without regard to her health or the father’s earning capacity. It is
            there we find slums, overcrowding, not only in homes but in the
            community. We find there, too, terrible infant and maternal
            mortality, ignorance, disease, unemployment, child labor, and all
            the problems we are trying today to solve.</p>
        <p>I know this group fairly well and I know the mothers here are not
            desirous of frequent child-bearing any more than the mothers of the
            other group. But seek and ask where they will there is no way for
            them to get advice or instruction on how to control the size of
            their families. All agencies are turned against them; they must turn
            to the interrupted pregnancy or bring unwanted children into the
            world year in and year out.</p>
        <p>We are known in America to be a
            very generous hearted people; we are known throughout the world as
            being very large spenders. We have in the past ten years spent NINE
            BILLION DOLLARS on what are called the four D’s-- DISEASE: DEFECTS:
            DELINQUENCY: DEPENDENCY. I have no quarrel even with that enormous
            amount if we could only be assured that it was not going to increase
            the next year and the following year. But we have no such assurance.
            In fact, judging by the past ten years, we have no reason to believe
            anything, except that we will be paying, not nine or ten but perhaps
            fifteen billion dollars to take care of the four D’s in the next ten
            years.</p>
        <p>Will all you who are interested in social work follow me for a moment
            to see how we really attack one or two of these questions.</p>
        <p>Take Maternal Mortality. It is really a disgrace that this country,
            which has so many spendid social organizations and institutions,
            should yet have its maternal mortality increased during the last few
            years. Twenty thousand mothers passed out from causes due to
            pregnancy during the past year. Twenty thousand mothers means two
            mothers for every hour, night and day. We know that tubercular
            women, or women with heart or kidney trouble should never be allowed
            to take the risk of motherhood. We know, too, that even tubercular
            women die, not from tuberculosis but from pregnancy. We know that
            the medical profession has every right, legally and morally, to
            interrupt that condition. Then what? They send her back to her home,
            to face the same conditions, in utter ignorance and with a death
            sentence hanging over her head.</p>
        <p>With Infant Mortality we have done better. It is today I believe down
            to two hundred thousand infants who died before reaching their first
            birthday. We have reduced it but oh, at such a cost, not only in
            money but a whole group of individuals have devoted the best part of
            their lives to keeping alive children who never should have been
            born.</p>
        <p>We do everything to keep our children alive but in most cases it is
            like locking the door after the horse is stolen. We have our Milk
            Stations, our Maternity Centers; we have Nurseries; we send nurses
            into the homes to tell the mothers of eight or nine children how to
            have their tenth child. What those mothers really want to know is
            how not to have that tenth or eleventh baby. Worst of all, we allow
            the 200,000 mothers and fathers of these children to remain in
            ignorance of how to prevent the birth of two hundred thousand
            children next year.</p>
        <p>The <org reg="United States Children's Bureau">Children’s
                Bureau</org> of the <org reg="United States Department of Labor"
                >Labor Dept.</org> at <place reg="Washington, D.C."
                >Washington</place> throws a light on the infant mortality of
            this country by telling us that the father’s wage has much to do
            with it. As his wage goes down, his family goes up. They also tell
            us that the spacing of children in the family has much to do with
            infant death; if there is an interval of two, three or four years
            that child has a better chance to live. They tell us also that
            number of children in the family has much to do with infant
            mortality and that the second child has a much better chance to live
            than the tenth or twelfth. For every second child born there is less
            than 100 deaths per thousand; for the fifth child, about 350; for
            the twelfth it is 600 out of every thousand Sixty per cent of
            twelfth children born do not live to see their first birthday. What
            useless waste of womanhood and motherhood. What an orgy of
            agony!</p>
        <p>I maintain that if we are ever going to do anything about infant
            mortality we have got to stop the unending stream of unwanted
            babies. We cannot sweep back the tide with the broom of organized
            charity or palliative legislation. We have to stop it at the source
            by safe and sound information to control birth.</p>
        <p>Another question concerns us. Child labor. Most of us believe there
            is no such thing. We think children are protected by the laws of
            this country from work. But that is not true. For fifty years the
                <org reg="United States Child Labor Commission">Child Labor
                Commission</org> has been trying to do away with Child Labor.
            They have not been successful. There are seven million children
            under 14 years of age who are engaged in gainful occupations. Have
            any of you seen children in the Southern mills going to work before
            the sun is up and returning after sunset? If you knew the conditions
            where these children are, you would know they are doomed to it.
            Fathers in many cases remain at home, doing much of the housework
            because he cannot get an adult man’s pay. Little ones of 6 or 7 are
            standing on boxes or benches because the machinery was made for
            their parents; here you find these little ones crowding so closely
            into the family that it is absolutely necessary for each of them as
            soon as they can to get out and compete with father and mother just
            for their daily existence. The same applies to children toiling in
            the fields, for instance, of <place>Colorado</place>. I went myself
            into the wheat fields of Colorado and it was astounding to me that
            we cannot have a little more fundamental attitude toward child
            labor; children of three and four were crawling on the ground like
            animals, putting fruit into baskets, their little backs permanently
            bent. To look into the faces of the parents of these twelve or
            fifteen children was to know that they were not capable of taking
            care of themselves, to say nothing of a large family,-- which should
            never have been brought into the world. I’d like to see the
                <org>Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Children</org>
            begin a little further back and prevent the cruelty of children
            being born in misery and disease. I should like to see the time when
            the <org>United States Government</org> would have to guarantee a
            passport of health for every child born in this country.</p>
        <p>If we could imagine it I think the children would like to take a look
            at their parents before being born and to ask them a few questions.
            If parents had to apply for children as they do for cooks and
            chaffeurs, the children might ask them for their health certificate.
            They might say: “<q who="UNK">What is the idea of having me? How do
                you live? What kind of table do you set? What are your plans for
                bringing me up? Am I to spend my childhood in a factory or a
                playground?</q>” It might even say: “<q who="UNK">Ah, Mr.
                Father, I am a potential genius: what do you know about the
                development of a genius? What kind of society have you
                constructed for my gifts to adorn</q>?” It might ask how many
            children there were already and if the answer was eight in two rooms
            and on twenty dollars a week, we can fancy it would say “<q
                who="UNK">I’ll stay where I am</q>” and interview the next
            applicant.</p>
        <p>The Government is concerned about the kind of people who come here
            from outside. Up to 1914 <name type="Character">Uncle Sam</name> was
            rather negligent about the kind of folk who emigrated here; he was
            like the parents who, although they scarcely know what they will do
            if their family is increased, yet do nothing to prevent it. Not
            until 1914 did the U.S. Government do anything much. We did not
            encourage emigration but did nothing to stop it. Not until 1924 was
            it necessary to recognize that there was a population problem and
            that SOMETHING must be done for the future of the country. So bars
            were put up at the entrance of the United States. Le mt read you
            what the Government thinks likely to be a menace and source of
            disease to her people, to the happiness and wellbeing of her
            population. Feeble-minded persons, epileptics, idiots, imbeciles,
            insane people, tubercular, those with any loathsome or contagious
            disease, paupers, professional beggars, those likely to become a
            public charge, criminals, prostitutes, or for purposes of
            prostitution in any form; illiterates, those over 16 years unable to
            read English or any other language-- all are refused admission and
            procedure for the enforcement of these measures is mandatory. I
            think it is good legislation. Unfortunately it is merely negative
            and not selective legislation.</p>
        <p>If it is necessary to keep such types out of the country why is it
            not just as important to stop their breeding? it seems to me a very
            short-sighted procedure to make laws to keep them out and laws that
            increase and multiply them within. Immigration throughout the world
            is causing a good deal of stir; the countries of
                <place>Europe</place> have looked upon America for years as the
            solution of their problems. There is a good deal of bitterness at
            the United States taking this attitude and concern as to what they
            shall do. Europe claims that she has sent into the United States
            some of her best stocks, equipped us with artisans, with man made
            ready material. She claims she has depleted her own stocks by so
            doing, also that in order to do this in the past she has now made an
            enemy <add>and a rival</add> more powerful than all Europe combined.
            Many of the countries, like <place>England</place>, are trying to
            solve their over-population problem by sending them into the
                Colonies; but the Colonies in turn say they
            cannot use the slum population which England wants to get rid of;
            they must have men of health, vigor and initiative-- so say
                <place>New Zealand</place>, <place>Australia</place> and
                <place>Canada</place>. The slum population England has sent has
            been sent back and England today has over a million unemployed. I am
            glad to say nevertheless that the <org>British Government</org> has
            been thinking seriously about <del>the</del> birth control; two
            years ago the <org>House of Lords</org> went on record and passed a
            resolution asked the Government to instruct mothers throughout the
                <org>British Empire</org> in methods of contraception at Infant
            Welfare Stations. It is an astounding thing that it was the <org
                reg="Great Britain, Labor Party">Labor Party</org> that refused
            to endorse that legislation.</p>
        <p><place>Germany</place> has also attempted to attack this question.
            When I was in <place reg="Berlin, Germany">Berlin</place> I was
            astonished to find there was legislation going on, backed up by
            aggressive organization both labor and medical, as well as womens
            organizations, trying to terminate pregnancy, up to the third month.
            They have already endorsed sterilization. Women interrupted
            pregnancy and then remained to be sterilized. Out of 80 women who
            came, 75 remained, asking to be sterilized. These women had already
            had two or more children. In almost all cases something was wrong
            with their health of the mother, heart, kidneys or other troubles.
            Sterilization on a large scale is taking place in Germany. I
            consider that rather harsh and there may be some regret later on but
            nevertheless Germany is face to face with the problem of the future
            and she feels that is the only emergency she can at present
            attack.</p>
        <p><place>Italy</place> is making a great deal of increasing population.
                <person reg="Mussolini, Benito">Mussolini</person> has said: <q
                who="MUSBE">No babies, no votes</q>. I do no know that the women
            particularly mind that; they might retort: No votes, no babies. I
            think Mussolini needs babies more than the women need votes. Italy
            is over-crowded. Everyone in Europe knows that. Italy cannot take
            care of her own population. Just two years ago six hundred thousand
            Italians and sixty thousand Poles went into <place>France</place>--
            and France herself has begun to consider population and immigration,
            as we have the last ten years. Anyone can go into France regardless
            of their condition. Not even today does France bar out of her
            country even persons with a transmissible disease. I think only one
            is not admitted-- traucoma.</p>
        <p><place>Japan</place> has seven or eight hundred thousand new souls
            born every year. Crowded into a territory the size of California is
            a population equal to half of our population. All countries, except
                <place>South America</place>, have put up the bars against the
            Japanese. South America alone has the open door for Japan’s surplus
            population. Japan, to me, is like the chick inside the shell.
            Something has got to happen. As we all know, expansive populations
            of the world have caused wars over and over again. The economists of
            Europe are convinced that the peace of the world can never be solved
            until each country takes up the question of population. Until this
            is solved intelligently they may as well throw their peace treaties
            in the waste basket. This question of birth control is not only an
            individual, a national, and a racial problem but international. Many
            people believe that we who advocate birth control do not believe in
            having any children at all. It is not necessary to deny that to this
            audience; you <emph rend="underline">know</emph> it is not true.
            Nevertheless, there are conditions in which it would be better for
            children not to be born at all. I maintain there are seven
            conditions underwhich children should never be born.</p>
        <p>First: Not of parents with a transmissible disease; with insanity,
            feeble-mindedness, syphilis or epilepsy.</p>
        <p>Second: Not of mothers with heart or kidney disease, until such
            disease is cured.</p>
        <p>Third: Not of parents who already have a sub-normal child.</p>
        <p>Fourth: I claim there should be an interval of two to three years
            between children. The mother should have an opportunity to recover
            from the ordeal of one birth, to enjoy her new baby and a period of
            time to prepare herself mentally and physically for the coming of
            the next child.</p>
        <p>Fifth: No woman should have children until she has finished her
            adolescent period, from 14 to 23 years. While we all know many fine
            children born of young mothers I maintain that is no longer
            necessary. There should be an ideal time for parenthood and that
            should be at the close of the adolescent period, when the physical,
            nervous and mental organism is developed but not yet
            interlocked.</p>
        <p>Sixth: There should not be more children than can be brought up
            decently and properly provided for. We have people for ten years who
            have been dependent upon social agencies, not only for the
            maintenance of themselves and the children they had years ago but
            for an increasing number ever since. I maintain that this is immoral
            in every sense of the word-- to have children they cannot take care
            of and to make their neighbors and others bear the consequences of
            their acts.</p>
        <p><emph rend="underline">Seventh:</emph> I maintain children should not
            be born until the young couple have have, say, two years of married
            life. I would like to see young people take two or three years to
            play together, to build up and develop their common interests before
            parenthood. I believe it is harder today for two young people to
            become adjusted to each other than it ever was in the past. We
            imagine they are going to live happy ever after, but we know their
            problems have just begun. It is not, after all, an easy thing for
            love to grow into the fine thing which it can be. It is not easy to
            strengthen the bond of love and to submit to that bond of marriage,
            unless there is time for mutual adjustment. If couples had two years
            alone together I maintain there would be more happy homes, fewer
            divorces and the possibility of the girl developing her womanhood
            before taking the responsibility of motherhood. We really see very
            little of the love-life of individuals. They are married-- and the
            next year become parents. The girl goes away on her honeymoon and
            comes back pregnant, physically and mentally disturbed. The husband
            has never an opportunity to know her as a woman; he knows her as a
            girl and then as a mother. I believe it would make for more happy
            marriages and more permanent ones if the fear of pregnancy could be
            removed or delayed, and parenthood invited instead of being an
            unwelcome accident.</p>
        <p>There are three groups of methods of preventing conception. The first
            is continence. The only organized religious body that opposes Birth
            Control does not condemn continence, but regards it as the only
            permissible method of birth control. The second is sterilization.
            The third, mechanical means of preventing conception. In our studies
            of the past five years we have found that continence cannot be a
            means of general application. Self-control, or continence, is a
            matter of one’s evolution. Sterilization is bound to play an
            important part, especially where there are transmissible diseases.
            This remedy is largely in the hands of the medical profession.</p>
        <p>It is about four years since we had the first birth control clinic in
            this country. To date, more than ten thousand women, whose histories
            we have on record, have come to us. Today we can say we know
            something about birth control. Ten years ago we could not say that.
            We could only say it had been practiced in <place
                reg="The Netherlands">Holland</place> and amongst the well-to-do
            in almost every country, but we had no positive information. We can
            today say that birth control clinics are doing a splendid thing, not
            only in giving children a better chance of life but in protecting
            mothers and reducing the enormous number of abortions. In our
            records we have 85 percent of the families going upward in the
            social scale. We know if we can get a woman before she has her
            fourth child there is every possibility of the husband bettering
            himself and the children going up the scale, instead of applying for
            work certificates before the age of fourteen. We know today, on a
            small scale (for, after all, ten thousand is a small scale) what
            birth control can do. There are twenty-five clinics in the United
            States, two in Germany, twenty in England. As to California, there
            are two in <place reg="Los Angeles, CA">Los Angeles</place>, one in
                <place reg="Pasadena, CA">Pasadena</place>.</p>
        <p>In the past thirteen years I have received over a million letters,
            written mostly by women, sometimes on scraps of wrapping paper. They
            have found my name somewhere and written to beg for information and
            help. I have recently taken a cross section of these letters and put
            them in a book called “<title>Motherhood in Bondage</title>.” If, after reading
            those letters, you still do not believe in birth control, I think
            such a person would be hopeless of reason. These are mothers who are
            asking for means to control the size of their families. And what,
            after all, are they asking for? For the right to live. For the right
            to life, liberty and the pursuit of happiness. For the right to know
            their children and to bring them up decently. For the right also to
            understand their husbands and to help him, too. These letters tell
            strange and dramatic stories of life in America, a side of life that
            is full of suffering and difficulty and that does not reach the
            public. And have not we paid a tremendous price for their ignorance?
            Have not these poor mothers paid a price that is staggering? Yet
            where is the information they need? We are paying for their
            ignorance in child labor, in infant and maternal mortality, in
            feeble-mindedness and with the large numbers of the unfit. I think
            it is time for us to wake up, to make it a right and easy thing for
            these mothers to obtain information and help of the right kind. We
            want women to have a chance to develop their own personalities, to
            rest from incessant child-bearing, to live with the fear of
            pregnancy removed from marriage. We want children to be born of love
            and conscious desire and given a heritage of sound bodies and sane
            minds. We want them to have and to have ourselves bodies that are
            beautiful, holy, fit instruments for progress towards perfection,
            temples in which the soul may take its place in the mystery of
            material being.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
