<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Autograph Draft Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/06/01 CE</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-26 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1936-00-00">1936</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied>Family Limitation Draft</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp129001</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Library of Congress</bibl>
            <bibl>Library of Congress Microfilm 130:2</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="birth control" level2="in marriages"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="condom"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="continence"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="diaphragm"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="douche"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="efficacy of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="female"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="instructions"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="male"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="pessaries"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="research"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="safe period"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="sponge"/>
        <index level1="Catholic Church" level2="birth control and abortion and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">Is Continence not the best Method of Birth Control?</head>
            <p> The above question is often asked me by people who for <del>[some?]</del>
                <add>religious</add>reasons object to the chemical or mechanical methods of
                contraception.</p>
            <p>My reply is that continence is a very certain method when strictly applied but I can
                not agree that it is the best method for married people especially during the
                    <del>years</del>
                <add>age</add>of <add>early</add> marriage up to <add>the</add> forty <del>one or
                    two</del> first or second year.</p>
            <p>Continence in marriage may be practiced providing both parties are in accord with the
                    <del>idea</del> practice &amp; when there is <add><del>creation</del></add>
                activity which sublimates the creative energies <add>of both</add> as in [work?] for
                “causes” with religious zeal <add>and</add> ardor.</p>
            <p>This condition unfortunately does not exist for millions <add>of people</add>who have
                no “cause” to espouse &amp; whose existence is <add>a</add>hum drum routine from
                year to year. True continence in marriage means no sexual contact <del>from</del>
                except when a child is desired as a result of that <del>contact</del> union.</p>
            <p>A loving couple may be strictly continent for 364 days during the year and should
                temptation or desire or <gap extent="one word" reason="illegible"/>
                <add>passion</add>overcome them on the 365th day a baby may arrive. One union a year
                can provide a couple with a large family in ten years. Besides this
                    <del>strain</del> method has been known to cause nervous strain &amp; tension,
                sleeplessness, loss of appetite &amp; many other nervous symptoms to the man &amp;
                    <gap extent="bottom of page" reason="page torn"/> the woman.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">[Reason] for Family Limitation</head>
            <p>Of all the problems that confront humanity today, in all countries climes and nations
                there is one that remains an individual problem and must be solved by the
                individuals involved – Marriage, Parenthood, love and Children (the birth of).</p>
            <p>No married man or woman is free unless knowledge of contraceptives is available for
                his and her use.</p>
            <p> What is birth control!</p>
            <p>It is assumed that you as an intelligent person, already a parent or desirous of
                being one later on, shares the above ideas and wish to obtain the best and most
                effective methods of birth control.</p>
            <p>I shall give herein the knowledge gained through many years of personal study in
                various countries and through over twenty-years of experience in clinical procedure
                in <place reg="Netherlands">Holland</place>, <place>England</place>, and <place
                    reg="United States">USA</place>.</p>
            <p>The practice of continence is a method strictly for the individual not to be advised
                without due consideration of the factors of health and experience and medical advice
                should be obtained.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">Is there a safe period?</head>
            <p>Perhaps there is. If it is true that every woman has a period when conception can not
                take place such a fact would have great scientific value. The doubt of its accuracy
                comes from the irregularity of the menstrual cycle and the fact that conception has
                taken place in precisely those days where it is supposed to be “safe.” The words of
                    <person reg="Knaus, Hermann">Knauss</person> and <person reg="Ogino, Kyusaku"
                    >Ogino</person> base their conclusions on the assumption that the first to the
                tenth and the 18th to the 28th days of the menstrual cycle are the infertile or safe
                days. The significance of this method lies in the interest it has aroused in
                medical, religious, and scientific circles. The <org reg="Roman Catholic Church"
                    >R.C. Church</org> has given its approval to this method.</p>
            <p>I do not advise a woman to depend upon a Safe period unless she is willing to take a
                risk. It has not been sufficiently established to the satisfaction of scientific or
                medical bodies yet to advise it as a general method of birth control.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">When a douche can not be had.</head>
            <p>When the convenience of a douche is not at hand, there is another method of cleansing
                the vaginal canal by simpler means.</p>
            <p>Take a piece of cotton or a small soft sponge. Dip it into a basin of warm water with
                a little soap added. Place the cotton or sponge around the first finger and cleanse
                the passage thoroughly. Discard the cotton each time, but keep the sponge for future
                use.</p>
            <p>This cleansing can be done in a squatting position over a vessel or basin. Always
                cleanse the vagina before removing the cervical or diaphragm pessary. Do not be
                afraid to introduce the cotton or sponge and assist in the cleansing of the semen
                from the folds of the membrane. You can soon tell by the feeling that it is
                sufficiently clean.</p>
            <p>A douche or swabbing as above helps to keep the parts in a health condition and
                prevents the male cell (sperm) from moving onward to the womb.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">Use of the Sheath or Condom. </head>
            <p>To overcome this difficulty is important. It can be overcome by advice and knowledge.
                Much depends upon the early education of the girl, her inhibitions and reactions
                towards sex, but more depends upon the attitude of the man toward the sex act also
                upon his attitude toward her response. Consult someone who is qualified to advise on
                this problem.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">The use of the <del>[cervical]</del> diaphragm pessary. </head>
            <p>One of the most reliable means of prevention is the diaphragm. These come in various
                sizes ranging from 50 to 100 mm. There are different makes and names, such as
                    <org>Ramses</org>, <org reg="Holland Rantos Company">H.R. Clinical</org>,
                    <org>Durex</org>, Dutch, <person reg="Mensinga, Wilhelm">Mensinga</person>,
                    <person reg="Haire, Norman">Haire</person> and numerous other trade names. Some
                made of coil and others the flat watch spring. It is the diaphragm pessary that is
                largely used in the clinics in U.S.A. and England. It has stood the test of time for
                    <del>nearly</del>
                <add>over</add> fifty years. It was invented in Holland by Dr. Mensinga and <person
                    reg="Jacobs, Aletta">Dr. Jacob</person> in 1879, but remodeled in U.S.A. by
                    <org>Julius Schmid <add>Co.</add></org> in 1918 with a coil spring and more
                flexible like rubber.</p>
            <p>Reports from various clinics give its use with a contraceptive jelly 97% success. (MS
                    <add>“first”</add> introduced it into U.S.A. in 1916.)</p>
            <p>Its chief drawback is that it must be fitted properly by a qualified person who
                understands the structure of the woman’s anatomy. It also requires instruction in
                its application and care. It is not applicable to cases with marked relaxation of
                the vaginal walls. But there is another type the [matrisolus] diaphragm that is most
                satisfactory in these cases. Frequently a cervical cap may be used with satisfaction
                where the diaphragm is not advised. Its success depends mainly upon the proper size
                being gauged by the Doctor and adequate instruction of <del>fitting it</del>
                <add>given</add> to the patient.</p>
            <p>It is adequate, reliable, and comfortable and when properly cared for by the patient
                will last one year and often two years. The American [illegible] have spent much
                time and money on research in the preparations of rubber <add>are now</add> giving
                the public an article superior in quality to what was <del>formerly</del>
                <add>ever</add> known before.</p>
            <p>Before removing the pessary, the vaginal canal should be cleaned. If a douche is
                available take a quart of warm soapy water or any other antiseptic douche and
                cleanse thoroughly. Remove the pessary and continue to cleanse the vagina until the
                parts feel absolutely rid of jelly or other secretions.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">The Cervical Cap Pessary</head>
            <p>The cervical pessary comes in three sizes and several kinds. The American mizpah and
                the Czech or French pessary. <del>The Pro Race</del></p>
            <p>At one times the cervical pessary was the only kind used in England and America.
                Owing to its frequent failures and the facts of its concerning its use
                    <del>this</del>
                <add>it</add> has been discarded in general use for the diaphragm. The cervical cap
                is applicable only in frequently in special cases where the diaphragm can not
                    <add>be</add> used as referred to on page ( ).</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">Sponges. </head>
            <p>The small net covered sponge found in most chemists shops has not been found
                satisfactory as a preventive.</p>
            <p>A sponge must act as an occlusive or barrier across the cervix or act as a carrier of
                the spermicide. In the former case the sponge must be cut out and shaped to fit so
                it will not be pushed out of place.</p>
            <p>The sponge used as a carrier has great possibilities.</p>
            <p>It should be soaked with an antiseptic jelly or powder and inserted as far back as it
                will go.</p>
            <p>Olive oil is not a spermicide. Vinegar <add>and water</add> and lemon juice and half
                water cab also be used with the sponge, but if the liquid escapes before the semen
                has been deposited there will be nothing left as a contraceptive when it is most
                needed.</p>
            <p>A recent formula of a Foam Powder <add>now being</add> tried <del>out in Miami
                    Florida</del>
                <add>by the C.R. Bureau</add> promises a hopeful safe and cheap contraceptive for
                mass use where the diaphragm cannot be applied. The <del>Pow</del>
                <add>Powder</add> is <del>used</del>
                <add>spread</add> on a rubber sponge <add>2x2½ inches ½ inch thick</add> wet with
                plain water. The powder shaken on the wet sponge until it foams. The sponge is then
                inserted into the vagina as far as it will go and left until <del>after</del> the
                next morning. When it is removed, the passage cleansed or douched and the sponge
                washed with soap and water and put away until further use. It is a cheap and clean
                method . According<del>ly</del> to the authorities using it <del>their</del> has
                been a <add>very</add> small percentage of failures. The sponge is better than
                cotton as it is resilient and holds the spermicide and releases it only on pressure.
                    <del>or</del> A small string is attached but it is tucked out of the way and is
                not noticeable.</p>
            <p>This was the method used in an experiment in <place>Florida</place> with the idea of
                providing women with a birth control method when they could not go to a Doctor.</p>
            <p>The sponge is left in place for not less than four hours and preferable all night and
                    <add>its</add> removal is followed by a soapy douche. If a jelly is used instead
                of the foam powder then the following</p>
            <p>lactic acid 1.5%</p>
            <p>boric “ ” 4.5%</p>
            <p>Chinosol 1: 10,000</p>
            <p>in a glycerite of starch base.</p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
