<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2003/05/29 RK</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2003/07/01 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/23 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/26 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/08/09 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/08/13 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007/06/15 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2009-03-04 CH Proofread with Eriok Zimmerman</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2009-03-05 CH Entered corrections</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011-03-11 CH Entered corrections suggested by Andy Carloff.</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/03/13 EK clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1915-12-05">5 Dec 1915</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Margaret Sanger Defends Her Battle For the Right of Birth Control</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp129015</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>New York Call</title>, Dec. 5, 1915, 5</bibl>
            <bibl> LCM 130:101</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>This article was introduced by a short preface by <title type="newspaper">Call, The New
                York</title> editor <person reg="Block, Anita">Anita Block</person>, detailing
                <person reg="Sanger's, Margaret">Sanger's</person> battle against the <title
                type="law">Comstock Act</title>.</p>
        <index level1="working classes"/>
        <index level1="child labor"/>
        <index level1="Woman Rebel, The" level2="suppression of"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="exile, 1914-15"/>
        <index level1="family size" level2="class-based"/>
        <index level1="labor movement" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level3="Comstock Laws"/>
        <index level1="Southern States"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Margaret Sanger Defends Her Battle for the Right of Birth Control</head>
        <byline>By MARGARET SANGER.</byline>
        <p>It is quite natural and consistent with capitalist laws that there should be a heavy
            penalty for imparting information on birth control among the workers, when we view these
            laws in the light of our present day society.</p>
        <p>In the <place reg="Southern States">South</place>, little, pale-faced children, 9 and 10
            years of age, wend their weary way to the mills early in the winter mornings, before the
            sun is up, and return, after twelve hours' toil, after it has set. These little ones are
            just "helpers" to their mothers, who work in the mills also, while the father remains at
            home, cares for the younger children, and takes the noonday meal to his wife and
            children in the mills. There are eight and nine children to a family.</p>
        <p>Almost all the stockholders of these mills are legislators, Congressmen, etc., who have
            much to do in the making of the laws. So it is to their interest that child slaves be
            born into the world, and they will enforce the laws to that end.</p>
        <p>When women have knowledge of the means to avoid producing hands, then will child labor
            cease, and the few children born to the workers will be made welcome by society, and
            given fields and playgrounds in which to spend a healthful childhood instead of grinding
            their souls and bodies into profits, as is done today.</p>
        <p>A LARGE FAMILY OF CHILDREN IS ONE OF THE GREATEST OBSTACLES FOR THE WORKING MAN AND WOMAN
            IN OBTAINING ECONOMIC FREEDOM. IT IS THE GREATEST BURDEN TO THEM IN ALL WAYS.</p>
        <p>It is the man with a large family who is most often the burden in a strike. It is he who
            is the most difficult to bring out on strike, for it is he and his who are the greatest
            sufferers through its duration.</p>
        <p>One could enumerate various instances where two or three groups of workers have broken a
            strike, and upon looking for the cause you invariably found the men in these groups or
            nationalities had many children, and could not withstand their
            <unclear>needs</unclear>.</p>
        <p>My Magazine, The <title type="journal">Woman Rebel</title>, told the working women these
            things and more.</p>
        <p>As editor and publisher of The Woman Rebel I felt a glow of hope and inspiration in the
            response which came from the working girls and women all over the <place>United
                States</place>.</p>
        <p>I saw the women of wealth, the masters' wives, obtain birth control information with
            little difficulty.</p>
        <p>I saw that, if the working man's wife refused to have more children, she was compelled to
            resort to abortion. Over 50,000 abortions are performed in the United States each year,
            and 25,000 deaths occur as the result of them.</p>
        <p>I saw that it is the working women who fill this death list, for though the master's wife
            may resort to abortions, too, she is given the best care and attention which money can
            buy.</p>
        <p>I saw that the <person reg="Comstock, Anthony">Comstock</person> laws produce the
            abortionist, make him a growing and thriving necessity, while the lawmakers close their
            Puritan eyes.</p>
        <p>I resolved to give my time and efforts to defy the law, not behind a barricade of law
            books and legal technicalities, but by spreading the information among the workers
            directly, in factory and workshop. My magazine was confiscated and I was compelled to
            flee to a place where I could carry out my work unmolested.</p>
        <p>When I have accomplished all that can be gained in this way, I shall return to take up
            the legal end of the case, ever delighting in the fact that the authorities cannot
            imprison my contempt for their stupidity, nor deprive the workers of the knowledge they
            have already received.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
