<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "file:/S:/TRANSCRIPTIONS/XML%20Drafts/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2007/06/14 CH--need to add xrefs for English methods and add these docs; deal with
            the list format at the end and the inclusion of images to edition.</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007/06/26 CH added xref for Dutch methods</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007-09-05 CH corrected doctype </prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1915-08-00">
            <supplied resp="MSPP">Aug 1915</supplied>
        </docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Magnetation Methods of Birth Control</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp129014</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
            <bibl>LCM 3:740</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp>
                <name id="EMERA">Emerson, Ralph Waldo</name>
                <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
                <name id="ONEIDA">Oneida Colony</name>
                <name id="FRE">French</name>
            </resp>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>This pamphlet was the third in a series, including "<xref from="">English Methods of
                Birth Control</xref>," 1915 and "<xref from="101920.xml">Dutch Methods of Birth
                Control</xref>," 1915. </p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits and risks"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="continence"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="male"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="religion and"/>
        <index level1="France" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="sex education"/>
        <index level1="sexuality" level2="men's"/>
        <index level1="sexuality" level2="women's"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>MAGNETATION METHODS OF BIRTH CONTROL</head>
        <byline>By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">MARGARET H. SANGER</person></byline>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">INTRODUCTION</head>
            <p>In the previous pamphlets, “<title>English Methods of Birth Control</title>” and
                    “<title>Dutch Methods of Birth Control</title>,” one finds a duplication of the
                methods given in the first pamphlet, “<title>Family Limitation</title>.” The French
                methods of Birth Control are so nearly the same that I have decided not to duplicate
                these again, but to give instead a list of the books and pamphlets issued by the<org
                    reg="Generation Consciente"> French League</org>, and also cuts or pictures of
                some of the articles they have for sale at their headquarters, 27 Rue de la Duée,
                    <place reg="Paris, France">Paris</place>. These will be found at the end of this
                pamphlet. </p>
            <p>I also find that the methods used to control births in <place>Germany</place>,
                    <place>Italy</place>, <place>Spain</place>, <place>Belgium</place>,
                    <place>Norway</place>, <place>Sweden</place>,<place> India</place>, <place
                    reg="Union of Soviet Socialist Republics">Russia</place>, and
                <place>Japan</place> all have been greatly influenced by the <org
                    reg="Malthusian League">English</org> and <org reg="Nieuw Malthuiaansche Bond"
                    >Dutch Neo-Malthusian League</org> (the two oldest Leagues). To give further
                national methods would be only a waste of time and material, and would add nothing
                to what has already been given. This does not mean that there are not many other
                mechanical devices. There are numerous ones; but I still find that there is nothing
                better, safer, cheaper, or more convenient than the pessary mentioned in
                    “<title>Family Limitation</title>.” </p>
            <p>In France, Germany, Spain, Italy, Belgium, and Sweden there are strong Neo-Malthusian
                movements advancing the Birth Control theories by lectures, literature, and
                practical means. In Russia, Japan, India, and <place reg="United States of America"
                    >United States</place> there have been recently feeble attempts to establish
                Birth Control movements; but as you they have remained embryonic.</p>
            <p>I have decided to close this series of pamphlets with the following explanation of
                the Magnetation method, and feel that I have said all that I can say of interest on
                Birth Control methods. I have gladly donated my mite toward what I consider to
                women's economic, social, and sexual freedom.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">Magnetation Methods of Birth Control.</head>
            <p>Before closing this series of pamphlets on the practical methods of Birth Control, I
                feel in justice to the many readers and subscribers of the <title>Woman
                Rebel</title> who inquired about the theories of Magnetation, Male Continence,
                Sedular Absorption, Karezza, and Zugassent's Discovery, that this series would not
                be complete without giving at least a general idea of these theories and their
                practice.</p>
            <p>It is interesting to note that the magnetation theory had its best and longest
                practice, as well as its beginning, in America, under the title Male Continence.
                This method was practised for over forty years by a group averaging 130 men and 150
                women known as the <org>Oneida Community</org>. They occupied a part of the old
                reservation of the Oneida Indians in <place>New York State</place>, and lived in a
                harmonious and prosperous form of Communistic society. <person>John Humphrey
                Noyes</person> was the head and founder of the group. Through personal experience
                and prolonged study, he discovered the theory of male continence. Since that time
                many others have come forward with the same theory under various names. Almost
                without exception, each advocate has injected some kind of religion into it. The
                Oneida Community was particularly a religious sect, and <person>Alice B.
                Stockham</person>, the author of <title>Karezza</title>, was a fervent religionist.
                However, aside from this, there are fundamental truths in the theory which bear
                thinking about and should not be discarded without some consideration. In view of
                the thousands of testimonials of the healthful results of the practise of these
                theories, I present these methods like that of the others, and for convenience shall
                classify them all under one head, “Magnetation.”</p>
            <p>There are thousands of men and women who object to the practical and mechanical means
                of Birth Control, who feel that the pessary, condom, and douche are gross and
                sordid, and take away the artistic and spiritual beauty of the act. It is those whom
                the magnetation method will interest most. There are others who will claim that this
                method is “not satisfying,” and can find no enjoyment in its practice. But so there
                are thousands of men and women who can pass a beautiful painting and receive no
                inspiration from it, or listen to a charming selection on a musical instrument and
                receive no emotion from it. So are there many whose natures are not so constructed
                that they can enjoy or benefit by this method. There is no doubt that the successful
                attainment of this method is dependable upon a free spiritual bond between the two
                who enjoy its practice. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">THE THEORY</head>
            <p>The advocates of the magnetation method ask you to first analyse sexual intercourse.
                They claim that you will recognise in it two distinct acts, i.e., the social (or
                amative) and the propagative. Those who practise the magnetation method content
                themselves with and prefer the social act, unless the procreative act is desired. It
                is usually held that the sexual organs have two distinct functions, viz., urinary,
                propagative, and amative, i.e., they are conductors firstly of urine, secondly of
                semen, and thirdly of social magnetism. Each one separate and distinct in itself. </p>
            <p> The organs of propagation are physiologically different from the organs of union in
                both sexes. The testicles are the principal organs of reproduction in the male, and
                the uterus in the female. Sexual conjunction of male and female no more involves the
                discharge of semen than of the urine. The discharge of semen, instead of being the
                main act of sexual intercourse, is really the sequel and termination of it. Sexual
                intercourse pure and simple is the conjunction of the organs of union, and the
                interchange and flow of magnetic influences through that conjunction. The seminal
                discharge can be voluntarily withheld in sexual intercourse, or it can be produced
                without sexual intercourse, as in masturbation, which demonstrates the fact that the
                discharge of the semen, and the pleasure associated with its discharge, is not
                social, since it can be produced in solitude: it is a personal and not a social act.</p>
            <p>The physiological analysis of the procreative act shows that the pleasure of the act
                is not produced by contact and interchange of life with the female, but by the
                action of the seminal fluid on the internal nerves of the male organ. The desire and
                that which satisfies it are both within the man, and may be obtained without sexual
                intercourse. The amative function, or the simple union of two persons, is a distinct
                and independent function, giving a medium of magnetic interchange superior to the
                ox, and it is the stimulating, retaining, and absorbing the semen in the man, and
                directing it into other creative channels, which make the amative act of greater
                benefit and more healthful and vitalising than the procreative act. </p>
            <p>Most of us know that creative energy expressed through the sexual nature is an
                instinct to perpetuate life; that it has its origin in and is co-existent with life
                itself; that it is the power back of all purposes and plans; that it is the
                self-pushing force that gives the individual the ability and desire to do and to
                perform; that it is the impelling factor and inventive genius in all man's
                handiwork. That this force operates in the multiplication of atoms and molecules, in
                the attraction of germ to sperm cells. The process of growth and fulfilment of
                functions is propelled by this energy, which is operative throughout all Nature. It
                is the force back of and expresses itself through the physical life of man and
                animal.</p>
            <p>Atoms, cells, and plants are unconscious of this force, and animals are conscious of
                it only in a slight degree. But man is conscious of this energy, and is capable of
                developing a greater consciousness of it all and of its operations and utilisation
                to a remarkable degree. Like the engineer who masters the engine by his knowledge of
                its construction and the force that runs it, so can man master this creative energy
                and direct it where he wills. Creative life can be expressed in other ways besides
                parenthood.</p>
            <p><person reg="Emerson, Ralph Waldo">Emerson</person> says, “<q who="EMERA">Work your
                    passion into poetry.</q>” Passion is the sign of creative power; it is the voice
                of creative life. If it were understood and its powers realised, it would be
                elevated and worshipped instead of lowered and debased, as the Comstocks would have
                us do. As creative energy becomes understood and applied, men and women will grow in
                strength of character and in strength of love, and will naturally devote these
                powers to the interests and development of the human race.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">THE PRACTICE</head>
            <p>Each of these theories involves sedular absorption through intercourse without
                culmination. No discharge is allowed, but by a superior control is retained, thereby
                making the act an amative (love) act, and uplifting it from an exhaustive, abrupt
                fertilising function into a quiet magnetic charm, producing health and increased
                happiness.</p>
            <p>The act of sexual intercourse has a beginning, a middle, and an end. Its beginning or
                first stage is simply the presence of the male organ in the female. The middle or
                second stage is a series of reciprocal motions. The end or third stage is the
                ejaculatory crisis, or the termination of the act. The advocates of male continence,
                Zugassent's discovery, sedular absorption, and magnetation claim that the whole
                process up to the third stage is entirely voluntary and can be stopped at any point.
                It is compared to a stream in the three conditions of a fall, a course of rapids
                above the fall, and still water above the rapids. The boatman may decide if he will
                remain in still water or venture down the rapids, or run his boat over the fall.
                They contend that experience will teach him the wisdom of remaining where the rowing
                is easy, unless the object is worthy of going over the falls. Karezza advises to
                content onself with the simple presence in the first stage until the magnetic thrill
                passes off. They are all similar and all aim at the same result. I head them under
                one method - “magnetation.”</p>
            <p>Those who practise it claim the highest possible enjoyment, with no loss of vitality
                and a perfect control of the fecundating power. Its practice greatly involves the
                art of love by a prolonged intercourse preventing that which puts an end to
                intercourse - the ejaculation. The seminal fluid, it is claimed, has an immense
                immanent value; and if kept in the system and magnetised, and reabsorbed by the
                blood, adds enormously to a man's mental and magnetic force, which through the
                ordinary sexual act is constantly being expended. That its practice by some men will
                be difficult there can be no doubt; but it can be no more difficult or need a
                greater power of control than that required of the man in the act of “coitus
                interruptus” (withdrawal). Those who practise magnetation claim that it is far
                removed from “repelling asceticism”; that it gives ample exercise to the affections,
                and opportunity for the exchange of sexual magnetism; but that its greatest benefit
                is that its practise conduces to a higher love development. It is the attainment of
                this control that raises the sexual passion in man and woman to its proper place by
                the side of music and poetry. </p>
            <p>The strongest objection which is put forth against its practice is that it is
                “unnatural”; that it is unauthorized by the examples of other creatures of the
                animal kingdom, and therefore must be wrong. But the answer comes that cooking,
                wearing clothes, and all modern life is far removed form natural living; and were we
                to remain in close adherence to Nature, we would go on all fours and remain dumb. </p>
            <p>When we realise we are living in an age when nearly all departments of life have been
                greatly modified and advanced by recent discoveries of steam, electricity, the
                telephone, telegraphy, the microscope, and other agents of enlightenment, is it not
                surprising that there has been almost no discovery or improvement in the vital
                department of the sex relations? The explorer, the pioneer, the discoverer may
                pursue his way into every department of life, and return to lay his riches at the
                feet of Science, Art, or Invention; but woe to him who dares to explore that shaded
                valley of sex. No matter how pure the motive, or what agony and miseries one sought
                to alleviate, dungeons, persecutions, slanders, and jails await him who ventures to
                bring treasures from its hidden depths. Yet there is no other department of life
                which needs so much instruction and education as the sex department.</p>
            <p>A healthful sexual stimulation has a beneficial effect on both men and women,
                especially when the loved one is accessible and some demonstration of sexual feeling
                allowed, as in the restrained yet ardent caresses of an affianced pair. Here we
                often see not only the happiest but the most productive and healthful period of a
                man's life. It is said this is particularly true of man's intellectual activities.</p>
            <p>We see a year later this same happy pair experience a great falling off in their
                affection. Women have experienced this so often that they begin to hate the sexual
                relation, and look upon the act either with a fear of pregnancy or with an
                unconquerable loathing. Of course, a great deal of this aversion which women
                experience is the result of their former training. The girl is taught before
                marriage that the act is a most degrading thing, and is told that it is the
                accomplishment of this one thing for which man desires her before marriage.
                Afterwards all is supposed to be changed. She is expected to have an entirely new
                philosophy as soon as the marriage certificate is in her hands. The average young
                man knows little of the art of love, and is consequently unably to beautify their
                relations or to teach her a new psychology. The first year is spent in secret misery
                on her side, and ruptures and misunderstandings between them both. The average woman
                will tell you she loves to be caressed and to express her affection for her husband,
                but could be quite satisfied without intercourse. This is especially true of the
                intellectual woman, who is acknowledging her lessening interest in the sex relation,
                and even repulses affectionate demonstration, fearing it must terminate in sexual
                intercourse (mainly the fear of pregnancy). </p>
            <p>Surely this is something to be squarely faced by every intelligent man and woman, and
                serious enough to deserve our untiring interest. Something must be wrong. What is
                it? Does this theory offer a solution to any? It may. Nearly all women who practise
                it testify to its benefits, while few men complain of it. Those who do, sat that to
                control the ejaculation to-day means a seminal loss later during sleep. The
                advocates, however, say this will occur at first, but after the organs become
                accustomed to their new functions this will wear off, and there will be no seminal
                loss. </p>
            <p>All men in the Oneida community realised that this control was a necessary attainment
                if they would be regarded with favor by the women in the group. Its accomplishment
                was necessary to their mutual happiness, and they had to learn it. If there is a
                method which in practice expresses the highest mutual affection and reveals one's
                own strength and power, then by all means let mankind know it.</p>
            <p>There is no earthly reason why men and women should not study the laws of sex
                expression as any other science is studied, and it should be a study not only
                intellectual, but of experience and adjustment. If, as is claimed, the experience of
                this method must be practised on a higher plane of thought than the purely physical,
                then certainly it must tend toward a finer companionship and understanding between
                men and women than the fleeting physical gratification prevailing at present. If
                there is anything which controverts the traditional uncleanliness previously
                attached to the sex relation, if there is anything which brings a blending of body
                and spirit or an ennoblement of the character of the individual, then by all means
                let us have it in its fullest detail, and let this revolting ignorance and prudery
                holding sway over men and women's minds so long be swept away for all time. Let us
                have light, through discussion, experience, and adjustment. </p>
            <p>There are few men who desire to expose the object of their affection to the burden of
                bearing children faster than her health will permit. They realise a women's strength
                is greatly undermined and her beauty and grace fast ebbing away; but ignorance and
                tradition have him in their grip. He knows nothing about the means to prevent it,
                and allows the one he loves best to wither and fade before his eyes.</p>
            <p>It is especially necessary for the woman to be free from the mental dread of
                pregnancy. There is nothing so productive of nervous disorders or so likely to
                decrease the sexual attraction or magnetation as fear and anxious thought. Perfect
                confidence in the man's ability to control himself is essential to the perfection
                and desired results of these methods. Just as one beings, so can one develop. Young
                men and women about to enter alliances and desirous to establish a lasting affection
                and higher bond between themselves can easily put this method into practice and
                control the sex functions. The more magnetic the individual, the greater the sex
                attractions between those two who love, and the stronger the bond will grow between
                them, through this “magnetation” method.</p>
            <p>The expression and adjustment of all theories is so largely personal that special
                regulations can scarcely be given. The road to science and the great natural laws
                are discovered through experience: there is no education but that of experience.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">TESTED THEORIES AND PRACTICAL TRUTHS. </head>
            <head type="sub">FROM THOSE WHO HAVE PRACTISED THIS METHOD</head>
            <p>
                <q who="UNK">I am a young man twenty-four years of age, enjoying the most vigorous
                    health. For two years after becoming engaged I delayed marriage, simply because
                    I did not think my income sufficient to support a wife and the children which I
                    regarded as an inevitable consequence. Happily for me, a friend who knew my
                    circumstances wrote me about male continence. The ideas contained in this
                    discovery were so different from all my preconceived ideas of what constituted
                    martial happiness that I was inclined to reject them as utterly impracticable
                    and absurd. But the more I thought of the matter, the more clearly I saw that if
                    there was a possibility of these new ideas being true, they were exactly adapted
                    to a man in my circumstances, and that they made my marriage immediately
                    practicable.</q>
            </p>
            <p><q who="UNK">The wholly new thought, that retaining the vital seminal secretion in
                    the body, instead of spending it recklessly, might make a man stronger, cleaner,
                    and better, also seemed to me not irrational. With some misgivings, therefore, I
                    ventured upon marriage; and, thanks to this practice, it has been found a
                    complete success. I have has a continuous honeymoon for four years, besides
                    having the daily use of my wife's invaluable services in my business, and have
                    never been conscious of any irksome constraint or ascetism in my sexual
                    experience, and my self-control and strength, mental and physical, have greatly
                    increased since my marriage. In the light of my own experience, I regard the
                    idea that seminal fluid is a secretion that must be got rid of as being the most
                    pernicious and fatal one that can possibly be taught to young people. </q>F. G</p>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub">FROM A MAN OF SEVENTY</head>
                <p>
                    <q who="UNK">My age is seventy years, and, thanks to male continence, my health
                        is good and I am as vigorous sexually as I ever was. My only regret is that
                        I was not informed of it earlier in life. It is not only a splendid sanitary
                        measure, but is a promoter of pleasure and the greatest harmoniser of
                        domestic life that I know. It is my decided opinion that where this practice
                        is adhered to, except where reproduction is desired, strife and contention,
                        separation and divorce would never occur. It seems to me that no one who is
                        seeking improvement would, after experiencing this practice, ever wish to go
                        back to the crude sensual practice in whose wake follow satiety, exhaustion,
                        disgust, and remorse.</q>
                </p>
                <p><q>The waste of vital and nerve force attending the usual custom of intercourse
                        is, in my opinion, a leading cause of the craving for alcohol and tobacco;
                        while in this new practice both parties, if magnetism exists, experience a
                        renewal of life force that is in the highest degree wholesome. If young men
                        would abide by this practice they would find that their self-control would
                        be immensely enhanced in every department of life, and that they would
                        retain the vigor and enjoyment of their sexual nature long after the
                        generality of men have become impotent.</q> W. S. F. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="UNK">FROM A WOMAN</head>
                <p>
                    <q who="UNK">Since my husband became acquainted with this new theory he has
                        endeared himself to me a hundredfold; and although our so-called “honeymoon”
                        was passed five years ago, it was no more real and far less lasting than the
                        ecstatic, the unspeakable happiness which is now continually mine. My
                        prosaic and sometimes indifferent husband has changed by a heavenly magic
                        into an ardent and entrancing lover, for whose coming I wish with all the
                        tender raptures of a schoolgirl. His very step sends a thrill through me,
                        for I know that my beloved will clasp me in his arms and cover me with
                        kisses, such as only the most enthusiastic lover could give. And through the
                        years lapse, I cannot see or feel any change in the way he cherishes me. To
                        each other we are continually objects of the deepest reverence and the most
                        sacred mystery. Our affection deepens, our romance seems as sure and as
                        enduring as the stars. I date my marriage from the time that he became a
                        student of Zugassent, for that was the beginning of out assured happiness.
                    </q>
                </p>
                <p><q who="UNK">But it is not alone as a cherishing lover that my husband has become
                        the crown of my happiness. He has grown perceptibly nobler in character, in
                        purpose, and in strength; so that besides a lover I have a strong friend, a
                        wise councillor, and my happiness is complete. </q>L. S. T. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub">A HUSBAND OF FIFTEEN YEARS.</head>
                <p><q who="UNK">It gives me happiness to testify to the beneficial effects of this
                        method, because I am earnestly convinced that no other discovery in physical
                        science has ever been made which is of such importance to the welfare of the
                        human race. In proportion as I have followed this method life has become
                        wholesome and happy. It avoids the opposite evils of ascetism and
                        self-indulgence, and does more than <emph rend="italics">any other single
                            thing</emph> to make the marriage relation a perpetual courtship. I am a
                        husband of fifteen years, and speak of matters that I know.</q> F. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub">A LETTER TO J. H. NOYES.</head>
                <p><q who="UNK">This Yankee nation claims to be a nation of inventors, but the
                        discovery of male continence puts you, in my mind, at the head of all
                        inventors. There has been no higher conservation of force than that realised
                        by this method, and I am confident that the blessings which will flow from
                        it cannot be measured by those which have followed the steam engine and the
                        electric telegraph. Your truly</q>, – – – – </p>
            </div>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">A FRIEND.</head>
            <p>
                <q who="UNK">A school friend of mine who lived in a large manufacturing town in New
                    York State, and has been married five years, had learned during the first months
                    of marriage this method of birth control. She was radiant with happiness; did
                    not desire a child until they had made provision for the future. Husband worked
                    ten hours in the electrical works, after which he played a cornet in a concert,
                    which kept him until after midnight every night. Such long hours of labor would
                    deplete and exhaust the average man, but this fellow was a s radiant and as
                    strong as one could picture. Both claimed it is the practice of this method to
                    which they owe their health, strength, and happiness.</q>
            </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">A GRANDMOTHER.</head>
            <p>A grandmother came from <place reg="San Francisco, California, USA">San
                Francisco</place> to assist at the birth of a grandchild. Had been married
                thirty-five years, but looked like a girl of twenty-eight in figure and color. I was
                amazed at the vivacity and eagerness and joyous health of this woman. Every day she
                received one or two letters from her husband, who had remained in San Francisco; and
                form part of them which she read to me one would think he was some ardent and
                forlorn lover of eighteen. She claimed she had always practised this method, and
                knew of a few others who practised it, and found its practice superior to any other.
                She was the most beautiful sexually alive woman I have ever known, and the most
                modest. “<q who="ONEIDA">True modesty is a sentiment which springs, not from
                    indifference or aversion to the sexual offices, but from a delicate and reverent
                    appreciation of their value.</q>” </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub" rend="bold"><foreign lang="FRE">CATALOGUE DE LIBRAIRIE</foreign>.</head>
            <p rend="center"><person>EUGENE HUMBERT</person>, DIRECTEUR.<lb/> 27 Rue de la Duee,
                Paris.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="center">BROCHURES.<lb/> (1 fr. = 20 cents; 10 c. = 2 cents. Postage is extra.)</p>
            <p>
                <foreign lang="FRE"><title>Essai sur la vasectomie</title> (Sterilisation de
                    l'homme), par <person reg="Hardy, G.">G. HARDY</person>. – 0 fr. 10 c.</foreign>
            </p>
            <p>
                <foreign lang="FRE"><title> Le mal de vivre</title>, par <person rend="Huot, Marie"
                        >MARIE HUOT</person>. – 0 fr. 10 c.</foreign>
            </p>
            <p>
                <foreign lang="FRE"><title>Le mariage, l'amour libre et la libre maternite</title>,
                    par <person rend="Marestan, Jean">JEAN MARESTAN</person>. – 0 fr. 10
                c.</foreign>
            </p>
            <p>
                <foreign lang="FRE">
                    <title>La societe mourante et le neo-malthusisme</title>, par <person
                        reg="Kolney, Fernand">FERNAND KOLNEY</person>. – 0 fr. 10 c.</foreign>
            </p>
            <p>
                <foreign lang="FRE"><title>La greve des ventres</title>, par FERNAND KOLNEY. – 0 fr.
                    10 c.</foreign>
            </p>
            <p>
                <foreign lang="FRE">La chair a canon, par MANUEL DEVALDES. – 0 fr. 15 c.</foreign>
            </p>
            <p>
                <foreign lang="FRE"><title>Le probleme de la population</title>, allocution de Mme.
                        <person reg="Roussel, Nelly">NELLY ROUSSEL</person> et conference faite par
                        <person reg="Faure, Sebastian">SEBASTIEN FAURE</person>. – 0 fr. 15
                c.</foreign>
            </p>
            <p>
                <foreign lang="FRE"><title>Le probleme sexuel</title>, par <person
                        reg="Meric, Victor">VICTOR MERIC</person>. – 0 fr. 15 c.</foreign>
            </p>
            <p>
                <foreign lang="FRE"><title>Entre proletaires</title>, par <person reg="Dixelles, ?"
                        >DIXELLES</person>. – 0 fr. 15 c.</foreign>
            </p>
            <p>
                <foreign lang="FRE">
                    <title>Le neo-malthusisme est-il moral?</title> – 0 fr. 20 c.</foreign>
            </p>
            <p>
                <foreign>
                    <title>Defendons-nous! Pour le neo-malthusisme; contre l'immoralite des
                        moralistes</title>. – 0 fr. 20 c.</foreign>
            </p>
            <p>
                <foreign>
                    <title>Neo-malthusisme et socialsme</title>, par <person reg="Naquet, Alfred"
                        >ALFRED NAQUET</person> et G. HARDY. – 0 fr. 20 c.</foreign>
            </p>
            <p>
                <foreign lang="FRE">
                    <title>La grande utopie: l'impuissance de la repopulation</title>, par <person
                        reg="Lericolais, Eugene">EUGENE LERICOLAIS</person>. – 0 fr. 25 c.</foreign>
            </p>
            <p>
                <foreign lang="FRE"><title>Socialisme et population</title>, par <person
                        reg="Marinont, Leon">LEON MARINONT</person>. – 0 fr. 40 c.</foreign>
            </p>
            <p>
                <foreign lang="FRE"><title>Socialisme et malthusisme</title>, par <person
                        reg="Ernest, Victor">VICTOR ERNEST</person>. – 0 fr. 60 c.</foreign>
            </p>
            <p>
                <foreign lang="FRE"><title>Malthus et ses disciples</title>, par G. HARDY. – 0 fr.
                    50 c.</foreign>
            </p>
            <p>
                <foreign lang="FRE"><title>La loi de Malthus</title>, par G. HARDY. – 0 fr. 75
                c.</foreign>
            </p>
            <p>
                <foreign lang="FRE">
                    <title>Population et subsistances</title>, par <person reg="Hardy, G.">G.
                    GIROUD</person>. – 1 fr.</foreign>
            </p>
            <p>
                <foreign lang="FRE">
                    <title>Aux jeunes hommes, aux jeunes filles. Ce qu'ils dovient apprendre sur la
                        vie sexuelle</title>, par <person reg="Grandjean, Valentin">VALENTIN
                        GRANDJEAN</person>. – 1 fr.</foreign>
            </p>
            <p>
                <foreign lang="FRE"><title>Valeur scientifique du malthusianisme</title>, par le
                        <person reg="Gottschlak, Dr.">Dr. GOTTSCHALK</person>. Deux brochures (1 re
                    et 2e parties). Ensemble, 1 fr. 50 c.</foreign>
            </p>
            <p rend="bold">
                <foreign lang="FRE">POUR EVITER LA CONCEPTION</foreign>.</p>
            <p>
                <foreign lang="FRE">
                    <title>Ayons peu d'enfans! Pourquoi? Comment? </title> par <person
                        reg="Chapelier, Emile">EMILE CHAPELIER</person>. – 0 fr. 20 c.</foreign>
            </p>
            <p>
                <foreign lang="FRE"><title>Moyens d'eviter les grandes families, par les docteurs</title>
                    <person reg="Rutgers, Johannes">J. RUTGERS</person> et <person
                        reg="Mascaux, Fernand">F. MASCAUX</person>. – 0 fr. 30 c.</foreign>
            </p>
            <p>
                <foreign><title>Generation consciente</title>, par <person reg="Sutor, Franck"
                        >FRANCK SUTOR</person> – 0 fr. 75 c.</foreign>
            </p>
            <p rend="bold">VOLUMES.</p>
            <p>
                <foreign lang="FRE">
                    <title>Moyens d'eviter la grossesse</title>, par G. HARDY. – 1 fr. 25
                c.</foreign>
            </p>
            <p>
                <foreign lang="FRE">
                    <title>L'education sexuelle</title>, par JEAN MARESTAN. – 2 fr. 50 c.</foreign>
            </p>
            <p>
                <foreign lang="FRE">
                    <title>Peu d'enfants. Porquoi? Comment?</title> par EUGENE LERICOLAIS. – 3
                fr.</foreign>
            </p>
            <p>
                <foreign lang="FRE"><title> Le breviaire de la femme enceinte</title>. – 4
                fr.</foreign>
            </p>
            <p>
                <foreign lang="FRE">
                    <title>La pauvrete. Sa seule cause, son seule remede, par le Dr. <person
                            reg="Drysdale, George">GEORGE DRYSDALE</person></title>. – 1
                fr.</foreign>
            </p>
            <p>
                <foreign lang="FRE"><title> La procreation volontaire</title>, par le Dr. <person
                        reg="Klotz-Forest, Dr.">KLOTZ-FOREST</person>. – 2 fr.</foreign>
            </p>
            <p>
                <foreign lang="FRE">
                    <title>Elements de science sociale, par le Dr. G. DRYSDALE</title>. – 3
                fr.</foreign>
            </p>
            <p>
                <foreign lang="FRE"><title>L'initiation sexuelle</title>, par <person
                        reg="Bessede, G.">G. BESSEDE</person>. – 3 fr.</foreign>
            </p>
            <p>
                <foreign lang="FRE">
                    <title>La vie sexuelle et ses lois</title>, par le Dr. <person
                        reg="Nystrom, Anton">ANTON NYSTROM</person>. – 6 fr.</foreign>
            </p>
            <p>
                <foreign lang="FRE"><title>Notions d'hygiene feminine populaire:
                    l'Adolescente</title>, par le Dr. <person reg="Martial, Rene">RENE
                    MARTIAL</person>. – 2 fr.</foreign>
            </p>
            <p>
                <foreign lang="FRE">
                    <title>La fonction sexualle</title>, par le Dr. <person
                        reg="De Plauzoles, Sicard">SICARD DE PLAUZOLES</person>. – 6 fr. </foreign>
            </p>
            <p>
                <foreign lang="FRE"><title>La generation humaine</title>, par le Dr. <person
                        reg="Witkowski, G. J.">G. J. WITKOWSKI</person>. – 8 fr.</foreign>
            </p>
            <p>
                <foreign lang="FRE"><title>La question sexuelle</title>, par <person
                        reg="Forel, Auguste">AUGUSTE FOREL</person>. – 10 fr.</foreign>
            </p>
            <p>
                <foreign lang="FRE"><title>De l'avortement. Est-ce un crime?</title> par le Dr.
                    KLOTZ-FOREST. – 3 fr 50 c.</foreign>
            </p>
            <p>
                <foreign lang="FRE"><title>De l'amour physique</title>, par <person
                        reg="Mauclair, Camille">CAMILLE MAUCLAIR</person>. – 3 fr.</foreign>
            </p>
            <p>
                <foreign lang="FRE"><title>La physique, de l'amour</title>, par <person
                        reg="De Gourmont, Remy">REMY DE GOURMONT</person>. – 3 fr</foreign>.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <p>
                <foreign lang="FRE">Generation Consciente.<lb/> Organe de propagande pour la
                    limitation volontaire<lb/> des naissances. Neo-malthusisme. Eugenisme.<lb/>
                    EUGENE HUMBERT, Directeur.<lb/> ADMINISTRATION: 27 rue de la Duée, Paris
                (XX.).</foreign>
            </p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
