<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed draft speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2010/02/03 ac</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-10 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1932-04-00">Apr 1932</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">American Woman's Association Medal
                Speech</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp129022</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
            <bibl>LCM 130:0114</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">For the final version see Address at the <xref from="101793.xml">American
            Women's Association</xref>. 
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Federal"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <p>MISS <person reg="Morgan, Alice">MORGAN</person> [illegible] <add>Chairman</add></p>
        <p> FRIENDS:</p>
        <p> My heart is too full to express my gratitude in words.</p>
        <p> I have bene sitting here listening to all these beautiful tributes, but I have had to
            ask myself: “IS THIS ONLY A DREAM OR AM I REALLY AWAKE?”</p>
        <p> After nearly twenty years of INDICTMENTS, SUPPRESSIONS, PATROL WAGONS, RAIDS, COURTS,
            JAILS, <del>PERSECUTION and RIDICULE</del>, it is hard to believe that I would receive
            any <emph rend="underlined">reward</emph>
            <del>beside</del>
            <add>except</add> a <emph rend="underlined">warrant</emph>!</p>
        <p>
            <del>As I press this medal in my hand,</del>
            <add>I shall always prize this medal</add> it seems to me <hi rend="underlined">much
                more</hi> than a reward. It is <emph rend="underlined">your</emph> action-- <emph
                rend="underlined">your GESTURE</emph>-- that I value <add>so</add> much <del>more
                than the recognition of <emph rend="underlined">my</emph> efforts.</del>
            <add>because it</add> symbolizes <del>the</del>
            <emph rend="underlined">public</emph> recognition by a <emph rend="underlined"
                >representative</emph> group of <del>the</del>
            <hi rend="underlined">enlightened women</hi> of <del><place reg="United States"
                    >America</place></del>
            <add>this country</add> of the basic importance of Birth Control as a necessary
            instrument in the making of our civilization.</p>
        <p>
            <del>You are </del>In expressing <emph rend="underlined">your</emph> belief in <emph
                rend="underlined">me</emph>, and in <add>you are joining the battle for</add> Birth
            Control. That is the important thing! This medal will go with me into the thick of the
            fight! In moments of fatigue or discouragement, it will reassure me, whisper to me: “You
            are not alone in this fight. Intelligent and courageous women are standing behind you,
            standing with you in spirit!”</p>
        <p> I am just back from five months on the firing line in <place rend="Washington, D.C."
                >Washington</place>, five months,-- if I dare say so without disrespect-- in the
            Congressional trenches; five months at the head of a valiant little band of shock
            troops, trying to get a bill through Congress which will enable women of America to have
            free access to scientific knowledge of their own bodies.</p>
        <p> These last, busy, hectic five months have taught me one thing: <emph rend="underlined"
                >beliefs</emph>, <emph rend="underlined">convictions</emph>, <emph rend="underlined"
                >ideas</emph> mean nothing unless they are brought out into the open, enunciated
            boldly, expressed challengingly, and courageously. Passive acceptance is not enough. It
            is just as unhealthy to hoard an idea as to hoard dollars-- much more so, in fact. Put
            your <del>ideals</del>
            <add>connections</add> into circulation, or they wither and die..</p>
        <p> Just as the organs of our bodys atrophy if not exercised, so our belief in <gap
                extent="one word" reason="illegible"/>
            <add>an</add> idea must be <emph rend="underlined">actively</emph> expressed, if it is
            to mean anything to ourselves of the world. If you are ashamed of your belief, if you
            are afraid to express it in public-- it will fester and rot and die miserably <add>--
                and so will your spirit!</add></p>
        <p> In presenting this medal to me, who less than twenty years ago was denounced and
            indicted and run out of this great free enlightened country as a representative of the
                <emph rend="underlined">devil</emph> himself, you are acting with courage and
            independence. You are championing a cause that is still unpopular, that is still
            denounced and blocked at every step by its bitter and fanatical enemies.</p>
        <p> I am not EXAGGERATING.</p>
        <p> While the intelligent and enlightened elements in this country content themselves with
            remarking casually: “Of course I’m for Birth Control-- everybody is!” our opponents are
            ACTIVE in blocking our every move, Dont think for a moment that their opposition is a
                <emph rend="underlined">Passive</emph> one.</p>
        <p> Let me tell you something of our fight in WASHINGTON.</p>
        <p> We arrive there to find the very air surcharged with the great problems of the day: WAR
            DEBTS, MORATORIUMS, REPARATIONS, UNEMPLOYMENT RELIEF, THE PEACE CONFERENCE, THE WAR IN
                <place reg="Manchuria, China">MANCHURIA</place> AND <place>CHINA</place>: NEW TARIFF
            WALLS: SALES TAXES, SOAKING THE RICH, THE BUDGET TO BE BALANCED, BEER AND
            PROHIBITION.</p>
        <p> The mind of each Representative, each Senator, was alike a busy telephone switch
                <add>board</add> with his or her secretary the telephone operator. All the wires are
            busy. How to PLUG in with a subject like BIRTH CONTROL-- To the busy legislator, it
            comes like a message from Mars or some <gap extent="one word" reason="illegible"/>
            planet even more remote.</p>
        <p> One morning I called upon forty Congressmen and succeeded in obtaining interviews with
            only TWO of them. <add>But that was a good day’s work.</add> But in the past. five
            months, we have interviewed no less than TWO HUNDRED AND TWENTY representatives and
            FORTY-FIVE Senators. These gentlemen for the most part expressive a POLITE, PASSIVE
            Sympathy. But they are dominated by Fear-- fear of their constituents, fear of public
            opinion, fear of prejudice, fear most of all of the opponents of Birth Control. For
            these opponents are skilled in the tactics of blocking all progress. They may be--
            undoubtedly they are-- in a minority. But by the TIRELESS ACTIVITY, they give the
            impression of being twice as strong as they actually are. While the adherents of BIRTH
            CONTROL may on occasion come to our aid, the OPPONENTS spring into double and intense
            activity, knowing that they must exercise eternal vigilance to prevent the freedom of
            women.</p>
        <p> One <person reg="Unknown">Senator</person> finally confessed: “<q who="UNK">If I sponsor
                this bill, I’LL MAKE ENEMIES: if I do not sponsor it, it will make no difference to
                my popularity.</q>” Thus, though the PASSIVE supporters of Birth Control measures
            may be actually more numerous, they never protest against this type of refusal. They
            acquiesce; they forget at the next election. We can stir them into sporadic activity;
            but <del>they</del>
            <add>their</add> attention, is easily distracted, and led astray by other problems which
            seem on the surface more pressing, but actually are not so.</p>
        <p> We were told by our political advisors-- we women are of so trusting a nature-- that our
            Bill would come before the Judiciary Committee. We spent months interviewing,
            persiading, educating the twenty-five members of that Committee. Finally, after the Bill
            was introduced in the House-- and that was in itself a strenuous, collassal task-- it
            was referred to the Ways and Means Committee. All that work gone for nought-- and yet we
            refuse to be discouraged.</p>
        <p> Once I asked the advice of a <person reg="Unknown">Congresswoman</person>. She was
            popular, well-liked, intelligent apparently. Yet she exclaimed to me bitterly: “<q
                who="UNK">For <name type="deity">God</name>’s sake, dont send any of that Birth
                Control literature to my office! My <person reg="Unknown">stenographer</person> is
                bitterly opposed to Birth Control, and any day, any of this Birth Control matters
                comed in the day’s mail to my desk, she goes up in the air-- and makes it too hot
                for me the rest of the day.</q>” I found out that secretaries and stenographers
            wield a vast unseen power behind the scenes in Washington-- and the Congressman, already
            dominated by fear and afraid to ruin his own political futures-- dare not act contrary
            to the advice of the secretary.</p>
        <p> Another <person reg="Unknown">Woman Congressman</person> said to me: “<q who="UNK">For
                Heaven’s sake, don’t ask women to touch this bill! It’s too controversial!</q>”</p>
        <p> Opponents of Birth Control <del>have</del>
            <add>use</add> only the negative TACTICS OF PROTEST, but because they are so
            diabolically vigilant, even blocking our moves before we have had time to complete our
            plans. Yet in spite of these odds, we have accomplished much. Our bill is introduced.
            But we need your support. We need ammunition. We need reserve troops.</p>
        <p>
            <gap extent="two words" reason="illegible"/> ACTIVE, DYNAMIC public opinion,
            concentrated, focussed, mobilized, that has brought <add>produced</add> this desired
            result. <gap extent="one word" reason="illegible"/> Few American citizens
                <del>have</del> realized that the Federal Laws concerning the transportion of
            preventives do not merely concern the use of the United States mails and common
            carriers. Do you realize that Section 312 of the federal Penal Code makes it a CRIME
            PUNISHABLE BY TWO YEARS IMPRISONMENT and a FINE of $2,000 even to have in your
            possession any article or information designed to prevent conception?</p>
        <p> It was this that aroused the people of <place reg="Winston-Salem, NC">Winston-Salem
                North Carolina</place>. We sent workers there, and aroused the determined support of
            the enlightened voters of Representative <person reg="Hancock, Frank ">Frank
                Hancock</person>’s constituency. They made him “Birth-Control-conscious” in a week’s
            time. Their dynamic, determined, persistent activity, courageously, challenging <gap
                extent="one word" reason="illegible"/>, expressed in letters, phone calls, visitors,
            could not turned away with any conventional polite dismission. of Representative
            Hancock, they demanded pointblank: Would he introduce this bill? And knowing their
            earnestness he replyed that he would. And he has.</p>
        <p> We have since been working to get the Bill in the <org reg="United States Senate"
                >Senate</org>. The hearing before the <org
                reg="United States Senate Ways and Means Committee">ways and Means Committee</org>
            is set for . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
        <p> Most of the economic and social muddles which the <org reg="United States Congress"
                >Congress</org> is trying to clear up have been the results of mistakes of the past.
            Clean them up, we all cry; but in doing so, do not neglect the great, basic, problems of
            humanity-- the problems of MOTHERHOOD And of Childhood. Therefore we are convinced that
            it is our right and our duty to compel Congress to erase from the <name type="law"
                reg="United States Criminal Code, Section 211">Criminal Code of this Country those
                Sections 211</name>, <name type="law" reg="United States Criminal Code, Section 245"
                >245</name> and <name type="law" reg="United States Criminal Code, Section 312"
                >312</name>, which are an insult to American Womanhood and a disgrace to the Country
            which permits them to remain there to block our path to freedom and realization.</p>
        <p> I accept this medal as your pledge that you are with me in this battle to the
                <del>bitter</del>
            <add>victorious</add> end; <del>and that as</del> Your gesture has been a public one and
            a courageous one. It is likewise a challenge to the opponents of Birth Control. Let your
            interest continue in the Active Tense, not the Passive. Join me in the <add>is</add>
            glorious battle for American womanhood and childhood, in the creation of a newer, better
            civilization for to-morrow. You will thank me then, as I thank you know-- for Life
            active, dynamic, <del>fighting</del>
            <add>crusading for a cause</add>, I assure you, is more joyful and <add>thrilling</add>
            than life passive, inhibited, fearful. I have been in for twenty-years, and this medal
            gives me the inspiration to go on for twenty-years more, but I hope that Women will be
            freed long before that. Help us to make that hope become a fact. I thank you. </p>

    </docBody>
</doc>
