<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2009/07/14 LL</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2001/03/11 CH Entered corrections suggested by Andy
            Carloff.</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <prepDate>2011/11/28 CH correct typos</prepDate>
        <docDate value="1931-01-17">Jan. 17 1932 </docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>My Way to Peace</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp129037</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>MSM</title>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress
                130:198</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>Sanger delivered this speech to the New History Society, part of a
            series on "My Plan for Peace." For other versions, including one
            published in the <emph rend="Underline">Birth Control Review</emph>,
            see MSM S71:336, 338, 341, 345, and 348.</p>
        <index level1="eugenics"/>
        <index level1="fertility limitation"
            level2="of physicaly disabled and diseased"/>
        <index level1="sterilization" level2="candidates for"/>
        <index level1="&quot;unfit&quot; to reproduce" level2="descriptions of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>MY WAY TO PEACE</head>
        <byline>Margaret Sanger</byline>
        <p> Science has been applied to the various channels of life’s needs
            especially to our environment. Industry, commerce, education,
            hygiene, surgery, agriculture, dairy, factory, mining and even war
            have had the benefits of the best that science could command; but it
            has not yet been applied to improving the quality of life itself nor
            to the maintenance of PEACE.</p>
        <p>MY WAY TO PEACE would be First, to put into action the fourteen
            points of President <person reg="Wilson, Woodrow">Wilson</person>’s,
            upon which <place>Germany</place> and <place>Austria</place>
            surrendered to the Allies. Second, to have <org
                rend="United States Congress">Congress</org> set up a special
            department for the study of population problems, and appoint a
            Parliament of Population Directors representing the various branches
            of science.</p>
        <p>This body to direct and control the population through Birth rates
            and immigration, and direct its distribution over the country
            according to national needs consistent with the taste, fitness and
            interest of the individuals.</p>
        <p>The main objects of the Population Congress would be:</p>
        <p>(a) to raise the level and increase the general intelligence of our
            population.</p>
        <p>(b) to increase the population slowly by keeping the birth rate at
            its present level of fifteen, <emph rend="Underline"
                >decreasing</emph> the death rate below its present mark of
            11.</p>
        <p>(c) keep the doors of Immigration closed to the entrance of certain
            aliens whose condition is known to be detrimental to the stamina of
            the race, such as feeble-minded, idiots, morons, insane, syphiletic,
            epileptic, criminal, professional prostitutes, and others in this
            class barred from entrance by the <name
                reg="Immigration act of 1924 (Johnson-Reed Act)">Immigration
                Laws of 1924</name>.</p>
        <p>(d) apply a stern and rigid policy of sterilization, and segregation
            to that grade of population whose progeny is already tainted or
            whose inheritance is such that objectionable traits may be
            transmitted to offspring.</p>
        <p>(e) to insure the country against future burdens of maintenance for
            numerous offspring as may be born of feeble-minded parents, the
            government would pension all persons with transmissible disease who
            voluntarily consent to sterilization.</p>
        <p>(f) the whole dysgenic population would have its choice of
            segregation or sterilization.</p>
        <p>(g) there would be farm lands and homesteads where these segregated
            persons would be taught to work under competent instructors for the
            period of their entire lives.</p>
        <p>The first step would thus be to control the intake and output on
            morons, mental defectives, epileptics.</p>
        <p>The second step would be to take an inventory of the secondary group
            such as illiterates, paupers, unemployables, criminals, prostitutes,
            dope-fiends; classify them in special departments under government
            medical protection and segregate on farms and open spaces as long as
            necessary for the strengthening and development of moral
            conduct.</p>
        <p>Having coralled this enormous part of our population and placed it on
            a basis of health not punishment, it is safe to say that about
            fifteen or twenty millions of our population would then be organized
            into soldiers of defense–defending the unborn against their own
            disabilities.</p>
        <p> The third step would be to give special attention to the mothers’
            health, to see that women who are suffering from tuberculosis, heart
            or kidney disease, toxis goitre, gonorrhea, or any disease where the
            condition of pregnancy disturbs her health; place these mothers
            under public health nurses to instruct them in practical scientific
            methods of contraception in order to safeguard their lives–thus
            reducing maternal mortality.</p>
        <p>There would be a careful follow-up in the homes where infants have
            died, to ascertain the causes and to prevent when possible the
            further increase of children until the causes have been
            removed–reducing infant mortality.</p>
        <p>While the above steps seem to be emphasis on a health program instead
            of on tariffs, moratoriums and debts, I believe that national health
            is the first essential factor in any program for universal
            peace.</p>
        <p>With the future citizens safeguarded from hereditary taints, with
            five million mental and moral degenerates segregated, with ten
            million women and ten million children receiving adequate attention,
            we could then turn our attention to the basic needs for
            international peace.</p>
        <p>There would then be a definite inexorable ruling that the population
            should increase slowly at a specified rate, in order to accommodate
            and adjust the increasing numbers to our social and economic
            system.</p>
        <p>The Birth Rate in the <place>United States</place> in 1931 was 15.0
            and the death rate about 11, which allowed for a survival rate of
            4%, or an increase in the population, including immigration, of over
            20%.</p>
        <p> Immigration: Open the gates of the U.S.A. to those countries whose
            inhabitants have the inherent talents and national characteristics
            desirable, eliminating entirely those countries whose subjects have
            already been difficult to assimilate.</p>
        <p>This plan to be in operation for ten years. In the meantime we shall
            organize and join an International League of Low Birth Rate Nations
            to secure and maintain WORLD PEACE.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
