<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2010/24/02 Initials</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/03/10 EK clean regs</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-11 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1933-09-28">Standard Date</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Address of M.S. at Women's Arts and Industries Exposition</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp138035</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Library of Congress, Margaret Sanger Papers</bibl>
            <bibl><title>LCM</title> 52:117</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Federal"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Address of M.S., at <org>Women's Arts and Industries Exposition</org>, <org>Hotel Astor</org></head>        
        <p>It is ever a source of feminine pride and satisfaction to witness the rapid strides made
            by women in the arts, industries, sciences and professions during the past decade.</p>
        <p> Woman has had an age-long struggle to free herself from the superstitions and dogmas of
            the Dark Ages in order to prove her ability and to compete with man in the affairs of
            the world.</p>
        <p> Nature has not been altogether kind to woman, in that she has not distributed equally
            the biological task of child-bearing. In this in equality we find the greatest handicap
            that woman has had to overcome in order to develop her talents and to express her
            individuality. A few of them have dared and challenged and defied the laws and canons
            and moved forward toward their emancipation; but in the main the larger number of women
            have been and still are conscripted to the task of child-bearing.</p>
        <p> It was President <person reg="Roosevelt, Franklin D.">Roosevelt</person> who had the
            courage, foresight and vision to raise his voice on behalf of the forgotten man, and is
            it not time for the enlightened women of this country to raise a voice in unison on
            behalf of the most forgotten of all living creatures, the overburdened child-bearing
            woman?</p>
        <p> Why not a new deal for the 45 million women of child-bearing age in this country whose
            future life, liberty and pursuit of happiness depend absolutely upon the knowledge of
            how to control the physiological function of motherhood?</p>
        <p> We ask a “new deal” for the mother immortalized in poetry but <add>(neglected)</add>
            forgotten in fact--</p>
        <p> A New Deal for the mother whose life is shadowed by constant fears of unwanted
            pregnancies--a New Deal for the mother who goes down into the valley of the shadow of
            death for every baby born--</p>
        <p> A new consideration for the women who appeal for contraceptive knowledge to hospitals,
            clinics, and(social)agencies, and are denied this by priest and politician alike.</p>
        <p> The solidarity of woman is as noble as the brotherhood of man, and the opportunity is
            here today for all of us whose lives have been benefited by such knowledge to pass that
            right and privilege on to the underprivileged woman who is too poor, too weak, too
            inarticulate to battle for her own rights.</p>
        <p> There is now pending in <org reg="United States Congress">Congress</org> a Bill which,
            if passed, will automatically open the way to thousands of hospitals, dispensaries and
            public health agencies throughout the country, and will make it possible for these
            poor,troubled, anxious mothers to go to these institutions for medical help and to
            receive the proper medical advice suitable to their individual needs. Today such
            knowledge is refused them because of our Federal laws which were passed by Congress just
            sixty years ago.</p>
        <p> The passage of this Bill will give the poor mother the right that the well-to-do mother
            has had for the past generation. It will enable her to obtain special scientific
            knowledge through the source of the medical profession, and this is the wisest and
            safest way to obtain it.</p>
        <p> Congressmen will listen to this appeal when sufficient numbers of men and women make
            their voices heard. We learn on all sides from women coming to us to seek advice and
            that relief agencies in this and other cities are advising women who appeal to them for
            aid that they should get themselves in a condition of pregnancy in order to obtain
            immediate and substantial relief.</p>
        <p> What kind of justice and vision is this--when already millions of men are unemployed and
            other millions dependent upon them for life and maintenance?-- What sort of vision is
            this to encourage the birth of children at this time of uncertainty--at this time when
            we know that millions are born into homes so wretched that not only are their bodies
            denied proper nourishment but many of them can never grasp a perception of life’s
            beauty, nor will they ever be able to participate in the moral or spiritual activities
            of our civilization.</p>
        <p> In fact, I should say it was the patriotic duty of men and women to refrain from
            bringing children into this complex and confused age until there is a new code
            established by the Federal Government which will insure for every child born the
            heritage of a sound body and a sound mind.</p>
        <p> When this is done, we can indeed know that we are on the road to permanent recovery, and
            then indeed shall woman take the first step toward the goal of a real emancipation. </p>


    </docBody>
</doc>
