<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Draft Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/06/10 RT initial tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/06/13 CH proof</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/06/24 RT corrections</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-26 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1937-04-02">2 Apr 1937</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Birth Control - A Changing World
                Attitude</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp141309</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
            <bibl>Library of Congress Microfilm 174:74</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
            <name id="MRX">Mr. X. (fictional)</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>This <place reg="Phildelphia, PA">Philadelphia</place> radio address
            was opened with the following announcement: "Margaret Sanger, leader of the birth
            control movement will debate with an imaginary oponent, Mr. X, on the question "Will
            birth control promote family welfare?". <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Mrs. Sanger</person> is the president of the
                <org>National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control</org> and director
            of the oldest and largest birth control clinic in <place reg="United States"
                >America</place>, the <org>Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau</org>. Mrs.
            Sanger......"</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="opposition to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Comstock act"/>
        <index level1="child spacing"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="health of"/>
        <index level1="United States Children's Bureau"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <p>In debating with Mr. X on the question <q>Will birth control promote family welfare</q> I
            am discussing a matter of deep concern to everyone. For love of home, of family life, of
            children is a love which we all share. You may be wondering about Mr. X. It is hard to
            find an actual opponent of birth control. There is disapproval, misinformation,
            prejudice. But when it comes down to cases, it is almost impossible to find a man or
            woman who will voice that disapproval in open debate.</p>
        <p>Let me say at the start that I have the utmost respect for the opinions of others, and
            that I want others to have that same respect for the opinions of others, and that I want
            others to have that same respect for mine. Here I want to lay at rest the first
            misconception about birth control. It is permissive, not obligatory. To put it plainly,
            noone is being forced, or even persuaded to use birth control. Noone is being coerced.
            But.. and the but is important. . people who want to use it, people who plead and beg
            for this information should not be denied.</p>
        <p>Do people ask for birth control? The records of over three hundred birth control clinics
            in all parts of the country show that they do. The thousands of letters which I receive
            every year are mute and tragic evidence. Last month the editor of a woman’s page of a
            mid-western newspaper published a letter about birth control in which the writer stated
            that mothers in need of this advice should write to me. Within three days more than 500
            women had opened their hearts to me, had sent letters asking for help. And lest you
            think that this was perhaps only a local need, I want to make clear that these letters
            came from almost every state in the union.</p>
        <p>From the drought section of <place>Montana</place>, from the fruit valleys of
                <place>California</place>, from the mill towns of <place>New England</place> and the
            mining districts of your own state, <place>Pennsylvania</place>, came stories which
            wring the heart and fire the mind to action.</p>
        <p>A mother <del>mother</del><add>woman</add> of twenty-five, married at 15, and already the
            mother of seven children; a young bride who wants to postpone having a family until her
            husband is able to take care of children; a worn out mother of ten, who has been bearing
            and rearing and burying children for more than twenty years. These are the people who
            ask for birth control advice.</p>
        <p>Birth control means using the discoveries of science to plan and control, to take this
            subject out of the realm of blind chance into the realm of reason. It means spacing
            children, so that they are not born too close together. When one pregnancy follows
            another without the mother having time to recover her strength the children and the
            mother suffer. Maternal and infant mortality mounts. Our maternal death rate is a
            national disgrace. It is higher than that of any other country recording vital
            statistics, with the exception of <place>Scotland</place>, <place>Lithuania</place> and
                <place>Northern Ireland</place>. More mothers die every year in America than in
                <place>Canada</place>, <place>Germany</place>, <place>Japan</place>,
                <place>Sweden</place>, <place>Switzerland</place>. . . and what makes this shameful
            record truly tragic is the fact that two mothers’ deaths out of three are
            preventable.</p>
        <p>Out of every three women who die from causes related to childbearing, two could have been
            saved. Too frequent and too many pregnancies are responsible for a large number of these
            preventable deaths. And abortion, that tragic substitute for reliable birth control, is
            the cause of 25 per cent of maternal deaths.</p>
        <p>Let me pause here to clear up another misconception. The records of birth control clinics
            and of hospitals show that it not the young and unmarried girls who seek abortions and
            are responsible for the thousands and thousands of <del>criminal</del> cases. <del><gap
                    extent="several words" reason="illegible"/></del> The number of abortions
            performed yearly in America is conservatively estimated at 700,000, and some authorities
            place the figure as high as two million. It is married women with three or more children
            who, in the main, take this desperate way out. Death and permanent injury to health, and
            sterility are the aftermath. How much better for mothers, for their children, for family
            welfare, if these overburdened women had known how to prevent pregnancy, rather than
            destroy life after it had begun. How much better from every point of view if women were
            given reliable birth control advice.</p>
        <p>Do women plead for birth control advice? Yes.</p>
        <p>Will reliable advice cut down our disgracefully high maternal mortality rate? Yes.</p>
        <p>Will it SAVE children’s lives? Again the answer is “Yes.” The <org
                reg="United States Children's Bureau">Children’s Bureau of the United States
                Government</org> made a study, some years ago, of the causes of infant mortality. It
            wanted to find out why babies die, so that something could be done about it. The Bureau
            discovered that when children are born one year apart 147 out of every thousand die
            before they are one year old. But when there is a two year interval between births, this
            number is cut almost in half. By giving mothers information so that they can wait even
            two years between one birth and another, all these infant lives can be saved. And as the
            interval increases the picture brightens.</p>
        <p>Each one of you who is listening to this talk probably know of some family where tragedy
            has talked, where the young mother has been cut off in her prime, where babies have died
            needlessly. Would the welfare of THAT family have been promoted through birth
            control?</p>
        <p><add><q who="MRX">Birth control is immoral. It is tampering with nature, it is giving
                    license to the pleasure loving. Birth control will destroy our civilization, it
                    will lead our nation along the downward path, as similar indulgence caused the
                    fall of <place>Greece</place> and <place reg="Rome, Italy">Rome</place>. Birth
                    control is responsible for sterility, it brings about insanity.</q></add></p>
        <p>I am not a very good ventriloquist, so I must announce that this is again Margaret Sanger
            speaking. You may think that the objections I have put into the mouth of Mr. X are
            exaggerated. But they were voiced as recently as last week in a California radio debate,
            and they are the echo or the objections that are retarding the development of birth
            control as a public health measure. I say retard, please note, not obstruct, for I
            believe that nothing can obstruct the truth. I believe that though misunderstanding can
            slow things up, it cannot permanently stop something as fundamentally right as birth
            control.</p>
        <p>In the radio debate to which I referred a moment ago, one objection was raised, so
            fantastic, that I could not believe it were it not in the stenographic record. <q
                who="UNK">“Better a baptized idiot than a child unborn,”</q> said the opponent of
            birth control. You are doubtless drawing in your breath in amazement. Well, to every man
            his own opinion, as I said in the beginning. Let those who <del><gap extent="one word"
                    reason="illegible"/></del>
            <add>hold</add> even this amazing and truly awsome view have the right to their own
            opinion. But for the rest of us. . we need not be and should not be coerced.</p>
        <p>“<q who="MRX">Birth control is immoral,</q>” says Mr. X. It is immoral to save women’s
            lives so that they may rear their children to adulthood? Is it immoral to produce happy,
            healthy wanted children, who can be born into homes able to welcome them?</p>
        <p>“<q who="MRX">Birth control is tampering with nature?</q>” says our opponent. So is
            heat for our houses in <del><gap extent="one word" reason="illegible"/></del> winter,
            clothing, cooked food, medicine, all civilization. I need not enlarge this point. I
            think you will all agree with me.</p>
        <p>To the charges that birth control is responsible for sterility and insanity, I can answer
            emphatically: there is not a shred of evidence to support this view. Hospital and clinic
            records, cases in the files of provate physicians fail to disclose any evidence that
            reliable birth control methods as prescribed by physicians ever cause sterility. Quite
            the contrary is true. Bootleg and quack methods can due immeasurable harm. Abortion,
            which could be largely wiped out by birth control, is a major cause of sterility.</p>
        <p>In regard to insanity. . . again the opposite is true. No one has ever been able to
            estimate accurately the <del><gap extent="one word" reason="illegible"/></del> amount of
            hereditary insanity which could <del>have been</del>
            <add>be</add> avoided , if people with hereditary taint <del>had known</del>
            <add>knew</add> how to keep from having children. We are seeing now, in America, a
            splendid campaign of public education on the control of syphilis. “Conceive only when we
            say you may,” the doctor tells afflicted women. This means that women must be given
            birth control information, as one of the fundamental ways of controlling syphilis, which
                    [<del><gap extent="several words" reason="illegible"/></del> sends so tragically
            large a number of people to our hospitals for the insane.</p>
        <p><add>“<q who="MRX">Well, over and above all these things, which are perhaps matters of
                    opinion, here is a straight fact. Birth control is illegal. The law forbids
                    it.</q>”</add></p>
        <p>But Mr. X is wrong. We are celebrating this year an epoch making making victory in the
            birth control movement. On November 30th, 1936, the <org>United States Circuit Court of
                Appeals</org> for the second Circuit unanimously upheld a decision of the lower
            courts, liberating the medical profession, hospitals and health agencies from the legal
            restrictions under which birth control had suffered.</p>
        <p>In 1873, more than sixty years ago, please remember, <org reg="United States Congress"
                >Congress</org> passed the so-called obscenity laws prohibiting the use of the mails
            and common carriers, meaning express, for items which were then considered lewd and
            obscene. To the eternal disgrace of that period, and of <person reg="Comstock, Anthony"
                >Anthony Comstock</person> who urged the law on a bewildered Congress, articles and
            information relating to the prevention of conception were put in this category. It was a
            serious crime to send such articles or information through the mail or by express or to
            import them.</p>
        <p>The birth control movement spent years of effort to right this mistake. For with the law
            thus tangled and confused, many doctors hesitated to give advice, hospitals and
            dispensaries were afraid to include this service in their activities.</p>
        <p>I saw clearly many years ago that we would never reach our goal until this matter was
            clarified. With this in mind I formed the National Committee on Federal Legislation for
            Birth Control, to seek an amendment to the obscenity statute, exempting physicians from
            its restrictions. Support both in Congress and in the outside public grew by leaps and
            bounds. Each year we introduced a bill and each year we gained more and more
            support.</p>
        <p>Finally there came the chance of clearing the matter up through a test case. Some birth
            control materials, sent by a physician to a physician for research purposes, were held
            up in the <org reg="United States Customs">Customs</org>. The Court decision in this
            case has given the medical profession what we were seeking through legislation. The
            rights of the American physician in regard to birth control have been established.</p>


    </docBody>
</doc>
