<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2003/05/27 RK</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2003/07/01 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/23 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007/06/27 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2001/03/11 CH Entered corrections suggested by Andy Carloff.</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011-11-28 CH correct typos</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011-11-30 CH typos</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-01 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2015-01-14 EK correct proof</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1917-03-00">Mar 1917</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Voluntary Motherhood</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp143450</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>"Voluntary Motherhood," National Birth Control League, 1917.</bibl>
            <bibl><title type="mf">Library of Congress Microfilm</title>, LCM 131:104</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>For a partial draft version, see "Address from Prison,"see <title type="mf">Margaret Sanger Microfilm: Smith College Collection</title>
            S70:775.</p>
        <index level1="quacks and quackery"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="and war"/>
        <index level1="abortion" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="socio-economic benefits of"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret " level2="arrests and trials"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="and nursing"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="charity in"/>
        <index level1="poverty"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="freedom and rights of"/>
        <index level1="physicians" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="Brownsville Clinic"/>
        <index level1="Brownsville Clinic" level2="arrests and imprisionment"/>
        <index level1="World War I"/>
        <index level1="war" level2="and birth control"/>
        <index level1="children" level2="unwanted"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>VOLUNTARY MOTHERHOOD</head>
        <byline>By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">MARGARET SANGER</person></byline>
        <p>Birth Control when based on the theory of voluntary motherhood becomes the new moral
            standard and social principle which shall be the foundation of a new glorified
            womanhood.</p>
        <p>Long has woman been called the gentler and weaker half of humankind; long has she borne
            the brunt of unwilling motherhood; long has she been the stepping stone of oligarchies,
            kingdoms and man-made democracies; too long have they thrived on her enslavement. The
            time has come at last when she demands her physical and spiritual freedom,--and her
            liberty.</p>
        <p>When woman becomes conscious of her ego, her inner self, then shall she become a pivot in
            the world's advanced thought, and shall hold within her hands the reins of human
            destiny. Those who have opposed her development and progress are simply those who refuse
            to accept this new Moral Standard for her.</p>
        <p>They do not realize that Birth Control, which shall place woman in possession of her own
            body, is an epoch-making process in racial development.</p>
        <p>They do not realize that this new social principle, born out of the hearts and desires of
            womankind, shall be the <emph rend="italics">medium</emph> to bring to the light of day
            the <emph rend="italics">sorrows</emph> and <emph rend="italics">sufferings</emph> that
            have afflicted humanity; and shall point the way to their elimination.</p>
        <p>Those who have opposed Birth Control have overlooked the fact that <emph
                rend="italics">woman alone has endured the pangs of childbirth</emph>, and has gone
            into the Valley of the Shadow of Death for every baby born.</p>
        <p>For centuries she has populated the earth in ignorance and without restraint, in vast
            numbers and with staggering rapidity. She has become not the mother of a nobler race but
            a mere breeding machine grinding out a humanity which fills insane asylums,
            feeble-minded institutions, hospitals and penitentiaries, and provides cannon fodder
            that despots and tyrants may rise in power on the sacrifice of her offspring.</p>
        <p>Now in this very day we witness a world tragedy unequalled in all time. We see the flower
            of European manhood sacrificed on the altar of Tyranny. We see the nations of Europe on
            bended knee, begging, imploring, crying to woman, using every subterfuge to induce her
            to breed again in the old time submission to man-made laws.</p>
        <p>To all these entreaties the Modern Woman answers: No!</p>
        <p>She denies the right of the State or Kingdom to hereafter make her a victim of unwilling
            motherhood.</p>
        <p>We hear so much of sacred motherhood. Have the forces of oppression ever cared for her
            poignant grief? Have they not turned in callous indifference from her tears while her
            flesh and blood reddened every battlefield in history?</p>
        <p>There are statues in plenty to kings, statesmen and generals who have led her sons off to
            the universal shambles of slaughter. But where are the monuments to Motherhood?</p>
        <p>Woman is bearing the result of her ignorance of Birth Control.</p>
        <p>She is bearing it in the fact of poverty, in the fact of unemployment, in the fact of
            emigration, in the fact of maternal and infantile mortality. The whole history of the
            world is on <emph rend="italics">her</emph> side. The side of ownership over her own
            body and Birth Control.</p>
        <p>The history of Labor is the history of an every-unsuccessful effort on the part of man to
            bring his productive ability as a worker up to the same level as his reproductive
            ability.</p>
        <p>It has been a losing battle all the way.</p>
        <p>Of course, under the pressure of hungry mouths asking to be fed, miracles have been done
            in relieving distress, through charities and philanthropies, but never has the actual
                <emph rend="italics">cause</emph> been touched, never have we been able to secure
            peace, never to provide plenty, never to fully satisfy the demand, never have we been
            free from disease, misery and crime.</p>
        <p>With the millions yearly spent upon these bottomless pits called charities, never once
            has anyone attempted to cure the disease. They have treated with the symptoms but the
            deadly disease has been allowed to spread underneath.</p>
        <p>It was the reproductive capacity of mankind that produced the first poverty; it created
            want; it goaded mankind into industrial frenzy, into theft and warfare.</p>
        <p>It is the big battalions of undesired babies that have made of human life <emph
                rend="italics">an endless burden of heavy work and misery</emph>.</p>
        <p>The world is full of undesired babies and every undesired baby represents a terrible
            infringement of the <emph rend="italics">personal</emph> rights of a mother. Women do
            not desire to spend the whole of their adult lives in bringing children into the
            world.</p>
        <p>They yield only because of ignorance of how to prevent it. They do not know how
            reproduction can be avoided; when they do seek for medical advice they are told that
            laws prevent their getting it.</p>
        <p>For moral turpitude and human indifference it shall remain a dark chapter in the annals
            of the American medical profession that physicians have not availed themselves of
            knowledge to give relief to these poor women that they may be saved from too frequent
            childbearing and saved from the horrors of frequent abortions.</p>
        <p>When we view it as an institution, I feel it has done more than any other single body to
                <emph rend="italics">prolong</emph> the <emph rend="italics">misery</emph> and <emph
                rend="italics">degradation</emph> of womankind.</p>
        <p>What has been the result? Owing to our obscenity laws and the stubborn silence of the
            medical profession we have the appalling spectacle of 250,000 abortions performed every
            year in this country, while it is said over 50,000 deaths result therefrom. No other
            country in the world has so large a number of abortions, nor so large a number of deaths
            resulting from abortions, as the <place>United States</place>. </p>
        <p>No other country has produced so large a number of quacks and abortionists who feed on
            these unfortunate women, on their ignorance produced by these archaic and inhuman
            laws.</p>
        <p>For no other country in the world except the <place>United States</place> makes it a crime to impart
            information to prevent conception.</p>
        <p>The <person reg="Comstock, Anthony">originator</person>  of these laws has long since passed from public notice but his work
            remains, <emph rend="italics">forty years after</emph>, a living monument to ignorance
            and oppression seemingly <emph rend="italics">to wreak out vengeance upon
                womankind</emph>.</p>
        <p>My experience as a trained nurse convinced me that these laws are the most outrageous
            piece of legislation on the statute books today. What was the motive of those who framed
            these laws? Were they not inspired by narrow religious morality and bigotry?</p>
        <p>Were they not the outcome of those who aspire to be our moral censors? Are they not
            enforced by the most cruel and unintelligent censorship and exercise of police power in
            the annals of the State? Have they not remained on the statue books and been unassailed
            since their inception? And have not the legislature, medical profession and courts
            maintained a death-like silence while the inhuman slaughter of the innocents has gone
            on?</p>
        <p>My constant thought was: How can I arouse the people and the women of this country
            especially to what I know so that these laws will be challenged and changed?</p>
        <p>I felt so powerless. I had no influence, no money, few friends. I had only one way of
            making myself heard. I felt as one would feel if, on passing a house which one saw to be
            on fire and knew to contain women and children unaware of their danger, one realized
            that the only entrance was through a window. Yet there was a law and a penalty for
            breaking windows. Would any one of you hesitate, if by so doing you could save a single
            life?</p>
        <p>In trying to test the constitutionality of this law, every barrier was placed in my way
            and that of my attorneys. Medical testimony of four physicians was refused, who wished
            to state that there are thousands of women today suffering from tuberculosis, pelvic
            deformities, heart disease, etc., to whom pregnancy would mean almost certain death, but
            whose lives might be saved and their health preserved through knowledge of how to
            prevent conception. <person reg="Byrne, Ethel Higgins">Mrs. Byrne</person> and I were
            denied the privilege of paying a fine pending the decision of our appeal and were
            ruthlessly cast into prison like the lowest cut throat and degraded prostitute. There
            was no consideration shown us or understanding of what we were trying to do. No
            recognition that we are both married women and mothers of children. No recognition of
            the pains we took to give the information in a private place, by word of mouth and to
            mothers only. No recognition of the congested neighborhood, and the need in it for
            family limitation, or the women who testified of their distress and poverty and horror
            of pregnancy, and of the great relief and help and new hope in life that the clinic
            brought to them. The spirit of the Inquisition reigned supreme in the court and held a
            piece of parchment more sacred than human life, womanhood, and motherhood.</p>
        <p>I hope you will see with me that this statue, and all such statues, is against all the demands of
            modern thought and civilization.</p>
        <p>Women of <place reg="United States">America</place>: Have we not paid for it? Has not the poor woman especially paid for it?
            Has she not staggered under its inhuman mandate? Has she not paid for it in high infant
            mortality? Has she not paid for it in child labor?</p>
        <p>Have we not paid for it by the multiplication of the unfit? By the diseased? By the
            feeble minded? And by the hordes of unwanted babies? Have we not paid for it in the
            widespread practice of abortion? In untold misery? It is time for us to awaken.</p>
        <p>Far back upon the road of Today millions of women are trudging along overburdened with
            too many children, bowed, bent, broken, they stumble along. They call to you to listen
            to their piteous cry? What will your answer be?</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
