<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2009/07/15 LL</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-10 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1931-07-27">July 27, 1931</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Introduction to the Zurich Proceedings</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp143494</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> 131:0489</bibl>
            <bibl><title type="article">Introduction</title> in <title type="book">Practice of
                    Contraception</title>, eds. Margaret Sanger and Hannah Mayer Stone (Baltimore,
                1931). pp. xiiix-viii.</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="FRE">French</name>
            <name id="GER">German</name>
            <name id="FOR">Fortune Magazine</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"> The <org>Seventh International Birth Control Conference</org> was held in
        Zurich, Switzerland from Sept. 1 to 5, 1930. A selection of papers were edited by Sanger and
        Hannah Stone as <title type="book">Practice of Contraception</title>. <index
            level1="conferences" level2="International Birth Control Conference (7th)" level3="1930"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="research"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="international"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="international conferences on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="goals and strategies"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>INTRODUCTION<lb/>ZURICH PROCEEDINGS</head>
        <byline><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger Slee</person><lb/>16 St.,
            N.Y.C.</byline>
        <dateline>July 27, 1931.</dateline>
        <p>On September 1, 1930, an earnest group of experts--men and women--from various parts of
            the civilized world gathered quietly together in <place>Zurich, Switzerland</place>.</p>
        <p>These men and women were delegates to the Seventh International Birth Control Conference.
            They came together in the interest of the scientific quest for contraceptive
            knowledge.</p>
        <p>For five days, more than one hundred scientists, physicians and clinicians discussed the
            technical problems of contraception. They compared notes, reported progress made in
            research laboratories and birth control clinics, and proved beyond doubt that the much
            troubled subject now universally known as Birth Control had entered a new phase of
            development.</p>
        <p> All theories, all propaganda, all moral and ethical aspects of the subject were left in
            abeyance--practically forgotten--in the unanimity of cool scientific conviction that
            today contraception as an instrument in racial progress is on the way to be reliable and
            efficient and may in the very near future be perfected.</p>
        <p>As the first international conference of its kind ever organized in the history of
            humanity, the Zurich conference represents a milestone in the history of modern
            civilization. For this reason, I believe that it is highly desirable that the record of
            this conference be preserved in the present pages.</p>
        <p>This may indeed seem to the superficial reader an exaggerated claim. “A little gathering
            of a hundred or so men and women,” he might scoff, “unheralded by the press, comparing
            notes on contraception--that a milestone in the progress of humanity? Ridiculous!”</p>
        <p>To which promptly retort that today civilization is being remade not in parliaments, not
            in the conferences of international financiers on the <place
                reg="Quai d’Orsay, Paris, France">Quai d’Orsay</place>, but by obscure scientists in
            laboratories, by earnest workers in clinics, by the silent victories of modest
            physicians in preventive therapy. Just as the great spectacular achievements in
            aviation--the transatlantic and round-the-world flights--would never be possible without
            the vastly increased perfection of design which insures reliability and efficiency, so
            today contraception as an instrument of individual and racial well-being would not be
            possible without the efforts of these scientists, the bio-chemists and the clinicians
            through the agency of whose laboratories new methods, new materials, new processes can
            be effectively developed and proven.</p>
        <p>A milestone and landmark this Conference must remain, because it has lifted the whole
            problem out of the troubled atmosphere of theory where previously it had been battered
            by the winds of doctrine and the brutal attacks of prejudice into the current of serene,
            impersonal, scientific abstraction. That such a gathering, widely international in
            character, cooly yet compassionately humanitarian in temperature, could become a reality
            in my own time, instead of a wish hoped for yet hardly to be attained, indicated to one
            soldier at least in the long battle that a new orientation in race welfare had indeed
            arrived.</p>
        <p>For many years past I had been acutely congnisant of the fact – to me distressing and
            seeming insurmountable – that many of our most able physicians were absolutely lacking
            in knowledge of the technique of contraception. Even those who were familiar enough with
            the methods available recognized that the percentage of efficiency and safety were
            widely fluctuating. Such was the condition of affairs in the <place>United
                States</place> which impelled me to call together the men and women actually working
            on the problem in the various scattered clinics of <place>Europe</place> and
                <place>Asia</place>.</p>
        <p>It was a sad commentary on the progress of medical science, with its recent emphasis on
            preventive therapy, that the methods of contraception had not been advanced since the
            days of <person reg="Mensinga, Wilhelm">Mensinga</person>. It is roughly estimated that
            the number of abortions performed annually in this country amounts to no less than one
            million. The medical attitude toward contraception has only recently changed. Its
            difference may have been to a large extent, influenced by the early crusaders for birth
            control, which until my own advent in the field hid under the name of Neo-Malthusianism,
            had for almost a century been fighting in the fields of economic and social doctrine.
            Implicitly they had assumed that the known methods of contraception were already
            one-hundred percent effective and required only to be disseminated by the written or
            spoken word.</p>
        <p>That this was a fallacy was soon discovered but the first necessity was to ascertain
                <emph rend="Underline">what</emph> methods were being advised; <emph
                rend="Underline">how</emph> the method was applied; what percentage of success or
            failure attended the various methods. This was demonstrated in the experience with the
            diaphragm pessary as used in the clinics by Dr. <person reg="Haire, Norman">Norman
                Haire</person> and Dr. <person reg="Stone, Hannah Mayer">Hannah Stone</person> – two
            different phases of technique by two competent students of gynecology through the means
            of the same pessary. This and other differences will be noticed as brought out in the
            papers as well as in the discussion.</p>
        <p> It is of interest to note from the Proceedings of this conference that greater advances
            in scientific contraception has been made in America and <place>England</place> then in
            European countries (not excepting <place reg="Netherlands">Holland</place> and
                <place>France</place> where the practice of birth control has long been a part of
            family life). This is the result of directing the movement along professional lines,
            where emphasis has been placed on the keeping of records as well as on a greater
            consideration of contraception, keeping it separate and apart from sex hygiene and
            abortion.</p>
        <p>Just as demand and supply are related to all economic questions, so is propaganda a
            related part of scientific research in the realm of sex psychology.</p>
        <p>The next and most important step in the progress of the movement is to perfect a method
            of contraception giving a greater security and confidence to those workers in the
            field.</p>
        <p>In the early days <person reg="Bradlaugh, Charles">Charles Bradlaugh</person> and <person
                reg="Besant, Annie">Annie Besant</person> had been tried in <place
                reg="London, England">London</place> for circulating Dr. <person
                reg="Knowlton, Charles">Charles Knowlton</person>’s “<title>Fruits of
                Philosophy</title>”, a pamphlet written by the <place reg="Boston, MA"
                >Boston</place> physician about half a century previous and detailing in the
            sketchiest fashion crude methods upon which it would today be folly to rely.</p>
        <p>The following year--1878--<person reg="Truelove, Edward">Edward Truelove</person>, a
            London publisher, was sentenced for selling a similar book, <person
                reg="Owen, Robert Dale">Robert Dale Owen</person>’s “<title>Moral
            Physiology</title>” which was far more innocuous, from the point of view of
            contraception, than its advocates supposed. From the first publication of <title
                type="journal">The Malthusian</title>, which began its work in 1879 with the
            sub-title of “<title type="journal">A Crusade against Poverty</title>”, the advocates of
            birth control unconsciously assumed that methods of contraception were already reliable,
            effective, and practically perfected. Statistics were unavailable; clinics which might
            have kept records, were either forbidden by law or unheard of; and the medical
            profession, as a whole, remained antagonists or at best indifferent to this vast and
            complicated problem of human life.</p>
        <p>However, it would be unjust to minimize the progress made by the courageous physicians
            and pioneers of the movement. Dr. <person reg="Stille, Gustav Wilhelm Bernhard"
                >Stille</person>, a physician of <place reg="Hannover, Germany">Hannover</place>, as
            well as <person reg="Hausmeister, Max">Max Hausmeister</person> and <person
                reg="Letter, Karl">Karl Letter</person> who in 1889 founded the <org><foreign
                    lang="GER">Social Harmonische Vererin</foreign></org> in <place
                reg="Stuttgart, Germany">Stuttgart</place>, devoted themselves mainly to theoretical
            and economic aspects of the small family system. We may read of the enormous decline of
            the birth rate in certain German towns; but it is impossible to definitely correlate in
            a precise scientific manner, the two phenomena. In <place>France</place>, the birth rate
            had indeed been declining since 1831, and more sharply since 1871, although the late
                <person reg="Robin, Paul">Paul Robin</person> had not founded his <org>
                <foreign lang="FRE">Ligue de la règèneration humaine</foreign>
            </org> until 1896.</p>
        <p>In 1900 the <org>first International Neo-Malthusian Conference</org> was held in <place
                rend="Paris, France">Paris</place> – in the office of M. Robin’s League. Delegates
            from four countries--England, France, Germany and Holland – took part in what for those
            days was considered a thorough discussion of technical methods of contraception. Dr.
                <person reg="Rutgers, Johannes">J. Rutgers</person> of Holland in particular, we are
            informed, presented a discussion of such methods, both historical and contemporaneous.
            This, it seems, was the <org reg="Second International Neo-Malthusian Conference">second
                international conference</org> on methods, the first having taken place at an
                <org>International Medical Congress</org> in 1879 in <place
                reg="Amsterdam, Netherlands">Amsterdam</place>.</p>
        <p>Paul Robin had proposed the formation of an <org
                reg="International Federation of Neo-Malthusian Leagues">international federation of
                Neo-Malthusian leagues</org>, and Dr. <person reg="Drysdale, Charles Robert">C. R.
                Drysdale</person> was elected president of this organization. A second international
            conference was called in <place>Liège, Belgium</place>, in 1905. Records of this meeting
            indicate the swing of interest away from technical aspects of contraception to the
            problems of propaganda and popularisation. At Liège the meeting, the Neo-Malthusians
            came into sharp conflict with the Marxians, who were the advocates of larger and larger
            families as the surest method to precipitate social revolution. This clash of ideas had
            the effect of propelling public interest away from the technical and hygienic aspects of
            contraception to the social aspects of population pressure.</p>
        <p>Subsequent international conferences followed: in <place reg="The Hague, Netherlands">the
                Hague</place> (July, 1910); participation in the <org>International Congress of
                Hygiene</org> in <place reg="Dresden, Germany">Dresden</place> (1911) in which
            representatives of thirteen countries participated. Two German women pioneers, Dr.
                <person reg="Stöcker, Helene">Helene Stöcker</person> and Frau <person
                reg="Stritt, Marie">Marie Stritt</person>, acted as organizers. It was not until
            1922 that the <org reg="Fifth International Neo-Malthisian and Birth Control Conference"
                >Fifth International Conference</org> was held. In 1914 I had initiated the
            so-called Birth Control movement in the United States, and this movement, with its
            emphasis on the personal and racial aspects of contraception had in less than ten years
            become a world movement. In 1922 in London, not only Europe, but the Americas,
                <place>Japan</place>, <place>China</place> and <place>India</place> were represented
            by delegates. In 1925 the <org>Sixth Neo-Malthusian and Birth Control Conference</org>
            was held in <place reg="New York, NY">New York City</place>, and delegates from sixteen
            countries attended.</p>
        <p>Since 1914, in ever increasing numbers we had gradually succeeded in effecting the
            adherence of economists, sociologists, biologists and geneticists, the effect of which
            was to convert intelligent laymen to the principle of birth control. In this field
            indeed, the battle seemed to be won. Because public opinion supported birth control, it
            was possible, despite the still strenuous opposition, to open and to maintain
            contraceptive clinics--except in such countries as France and <place>Italy</place>,
            engulfed in waves of post-war reaction.</p>
        <p>More and more it became apparent to me that a new direction was necessary. The theories,
            the ramification, the racial aspects of birth control had been thoroughly threshed out.
            It was but a matter of time that these fundamental ideas should percolate to the masses
            – the masses indeed were already crying aloud for “safe and harmless” methods. But since
            the opening of the century, Medicine itself has evolved from its dogmatic stage.
            Prevention indeed was the cry--the prevention of epidemics, the prevention of disease,
            the conquest of the great scourges like tuberculosis or syphilis, instead of their
            alleviation. Medicine indeed was fast becoming, as a penetrating observer recently
            expressed it, the most personal of our sciences, and was advancing from the art of
            curing to the art of prevention. Science was effecting a veritable revolution in
            sanitation and general health education. But as the same writer points out (Fortune:
            May, 1930): it had “<q who="FOR">not by any means taken the third step of showing how it
                is possible to improve upon the natural endowments of man, to create greater
                capacities for work, growth and pleasure.</q>”</p>
        <p>From the beginning, I had insisted upon the establishment of birth control clinics as the
            swiftest, most effective, and most scientific method of advancing the cause of
            contraception.</p>
        <p>Yet all of this work going on in various countries, under the most diverse conditions,
            must be correlated, coordinated, unified into a common human ideal. For this reason,
            after organizing the first <org reg="World Population Conference (1927)">World
                Population conference</org>, assembled in <place reg="Geneva, Switzerland"
                >Geneva</place> in 1927, I began work on the problem of bringing the scientists, the
            research workers, and the directors of clinics together. The success achieved is
            recorded in the accompanying pages.</p>
        <p>Not without significance, to me, was the quiet earnestness of this unheralded gathering.
            The press did not intrude upon the deliberation of the men and women assembled in the
            charming little town in the Alps. No publicity was sought. The most important as well as
            the most delicate of all human relationships was discussed without shame and without
            prejudice, and problems most deeply affecting the well-being of every individual man and
            woman, the health of all future generations, and the stability of nations, were brought
            closer to satisfactory and permanent solution.</p>
        <p>Here indeed, the impartial observer might have discovered the true spirit of
            internationalism, the fundamental brotherhood of man, rather than in the bickerings and
            disagreements of the <org>League of Nations</org> at Geneva, or the truces in the
            warfare of governmental finances. For these reasons, the records of the Zurich
            Conference demand permanent place in the annals of human progress.</p>


    </docBody>
</doc>
