<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/06/13 CE</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-18 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1937-10-25">25 Oct 1937</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Women Free</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp143488</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Library of Congress Microfilm</title>, 131:0433</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="STOHA">Stone, Hannah M., Dr.</name>
            <name id="STOJO">Stokes, John H., Dr.</name>
            <name id="WHCCHP">White House Conference on Child Health and Protection</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to" level3="in remote places"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues" level3="in US"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits and risks"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="in marriages"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Comstock act"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="legal cases"
            level3="U.S. V. One Package of Japanese contraceptives'"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="medical community and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="continence"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="sterilization"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="American"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="rights associated with"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="war and"/>
        <index level1="Birth Control Clinical Resarch Bureau"/>
        <index level1="censorship" level2="in United States"/>
        <index level1="child spacing"/>
        <index level1="child welfare"/>
        <index level1="children" level2="unwanted"/>
        <index level1="family planning"/>
        <index level1="motherhood" level2="consripted"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="infant"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="maternal"/>
        <index level1="National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control"
            level2="birth control bills"/>
        <index level1="New York City" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="obscenity"/>
        <index level1="poverty" level2="family size and"/>
        <index level1="pregnancy" level2="fears of"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="government" level3="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="government" level3="public health programs"/>
        <index level1="United States Children's Bureau"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Women Free</head>
        <byline>by Margaret Sanger</byline>
        <div type="section">
            <p>“<q who="UNK">Won’t you please in <name type="deity">God</name>’s name help
                me?</q>”</p>
            <p> “<q who="UNK">I milked six cows at 6 a.m., had a baby at 9 that morning and five
                    days later was working in the fields</q>.”</p>
            <p>“<q who="UNK">I am thirty years old, have been married fourteen years, and have
                    twelve children. Every one is defective</q>.”</p>
            <p>“<q who="UNK">I didn’t even have enough for my babies to eat. Oh, how I cry to see my
                    babies in this way</q>.”</p>
            <p>“<q who="UNK">We live 100 miles from the railroad. I have five children and am all
                    alone when my babies come</q>.”</p>
            <p>“<q who="UNK">Oh! Tell me how to keep from having another. I feel like it’s more
                    important to raise the eight I have than to bring more</q>.”</p>
            <p>“<q who="UNK">I live in constant fear, so please have pity on me and tell me what to
                    do as I have to live for the children’s sake</q>.”</p>
            <p>“<q who="UNK">I’m just tired of living and bringing those children into this world to
                    suffer</q>.”</p>
            <p>“<q who="UNK">The pitifullest sight on this earth is more children than can be cared
                    for</q>.”</p>
            <p>“<q who="UNK">Is there anything in this world I can do to keep from having any
                    more?</q>”</p>
            <p>“<q who="UNK">Oh! If I could only have a little peace before I die!</q>”</p>
            <p>These are keynotes of more than 250,000 letters which have come to me since I began
                the fight to free women from the bondage of excessive and untimely child bearing.
                Why have such poignant pleas gone up from literally millions of women in <place
                    reg="United States">America</place>?</p>
            <p>Because in 1873 <org reg="United States Congress">Congress</org> gave in to pressure
                by a misguided “reform” group led by <person reg="Comstock, Anthony">Anthony
                    Comstock</person> and passed a law which put contraceptive information in the
                same class with obscene pictures and writing. That law prevented the giving of birth
                control information even by a physician and barred it from the mails.</p>
            <p>For nearly 65 years the law remained on the statute books, interpreted by the courts
                as binding. It put motherhood in bondage. It enslaved millions of mothers to
                ignorance and prejudice and sentenced them to bearing more children than their
                health, strength and ability to provide for them warranted.</p>
            <p>This and similar archaic laws unjustly linking contraceptive information with filth
                stopped the clock of progress and denied to the women of the United States
                dependable, scientific information on family limitation and protection of motherhood
                and childhood. Mothers were cruelly denied the facts needed to protect their own
                lives and those of their offspring. Countless thousands of children have been born
                sick, weak, unwanted and unprovided for. It is estimated that these laws were
                responsible, directly or indirectly, for the deaths of a million mothers from
                abortions and from bearing children too frequently and when not in healthy physical
                condition for motherhood. They were responsible for the widespread bootlegging of
                contraceptive devices and quack remedies, and denying to the poor information
                generally available to the rich.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">IT COULD HAPPEN HERE</head>
            <p>Looking back today, a year after that law was finally interpreted by an enlightened
                court as <emph rend="underline">not</emph> prohibiting contraceptives under medical
                direction, does it seem possible that women with tuberculosis, heart and kidney
                disease, epilepsy, and other ailments, or in need of surgical operations, could not
                be given contraceptive information?</p>
            <p>Doe sit seem possible that women could not have information which would permit them
                to space the arrival of their children in the interests of the health of both mother
                and child and with some regard to the ability of the parents even to clothe and feed
                their children, to say nothing of giving them an education and advantages?</p>
            <p>Could information which was available to rich women able to pay the fees of private
                physicians be denied to millions of poor women who needed it most?</p>
            <p>Could quacks go on year after year exploiting the miseries of mothers?</p>
            <p>Is it possible that people went to jail in the effort to end such an intolerable
                situation?</p>
            <p>Such things can’t happen here, you say? <emph>But they did happen!</emph></p>
            <p>I myself was one of those who went to jail in 1917 and served a month’s sentence for
                testing the law by opening a clinic in <place reg="Brooklyn, NY">Brooklyn</place> to
                aid poor mothers.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">WHAT BIRTH CONTROL IS AND IS NOT</head>
            <p>Exactly what do we mean by the term birth control? It has been the subject of so much
                misinformation and misrepresentation that a definition is needed. I am credited with
                originating the term. I did, but it almost originated itself. It means <emph
                    rend="underline">control</emph>, not merely preventing births. In many instances
                contraceptive measures promote births, properly spaced, by mothers who otherwise
                would not have been in a condition to bear children.</p>
            <p>Birth control is the conscious control of the birth-rate by scientific means which
                    <emph rend="underline">prevent</emph>
                <emph rend="underline">conception</emph>. It does not mean interference with life
                after conception has taken place. Indeed, one way to understand the significance and
                social values of birth control is to state clearly what birth control <emph
                    rend="underline">is not:</emph> Birth control is <emph rend="underline"
                    >not</emph> abortion. It is <emph rend="underline">not</emph> against the laws
                of nature. It is <emph rend="underline">not</emph> a means of promoting sexual
                promiscuity and immorality. It is <emph rend="underline">not</emph> an immoral
                practice. It does <emph rend="underline">not</emph> endanger growth in population.
                It is <emph rend="underline">not</emph> harmful to mothers. It does <emph
                    rend="underline">not</emph> cause sterility. It is <emph rend="underline"
                    >not</emph> to be classed with filth and obscenity.</p>
            <p>Birth control is the proper use of scientific knowledge to remove chance as the chief
                factor in the birth of children and to promote voluntary, planned parenthood. The
                aim is to have the number of children consistent with the mother’s health, the
                child’s possible heritage, the father’s earning capacity, and decent standards of
                living and education.</p>
            <p>There are various means of birth control. <emph rend="underline">Continence</emph>
                (complete abstinence from the sexual relation) cannot be recommended because it
                implies the abandonment of the natural marriage relationship, which too often
                results in the break-up of family life, in divorce, and promiscuous sex relations
                outside the family.</p>
            <p>Birth control permits normal sex life in marriage. It eliminates fear and the
                uncertainty of pregnancies when an addition to the family is unjustified on
                economic, moral or medical grounds. As <person reg="Stone, Hannah Mayer">Dr. Hannah
                    M. Stone</person> has pointed out, “<q who="STOHA">we cannot overlook the role
                    which birth control plays in married life generally. The fear of pregnancy, when
                    a pregnancy must be avoided for medical, social or economic reasons, is a source
                    of recurring anxiety in many families. It often leads to physical and emotional
                    strains which make a satisfactory marital adjustment difficult to attain.
                    Obviously, the sexual relation in marriage cannot be limited to the few
                    occasions when a child is desired. Marital continence for the purpose of
                    preventing conception is neither feasible nor desirable. It is an ascetic ideal
                    which is unsound both physiologically and psychologically and which tends to
                    destroy the finest qualities of the marital union</q>.”</p>
            <p><emph rend="underline">Sterilization</emph> is sometimes recommended by physicians in
                extreme cases where other forms of temporary contraception are not advisable or
                possible, especially in cases of mental or physical deficiency, or venereal
                disease.</p>
            <p>Chemical and mechanical methods of contraception suited to each individual case and
                used under medical direction are best adapted to the needs of most mothers.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">WHY BIRTH CONTROL IS NEEDED</head>
            <p>Let us see why birth control is needed. It is common experience that nearly every
                married couple in average circumstances passes through a time when the birth of
                another child- or of several children in close succession- is a family disaster. The
                mother’s strength is sapped, her health impaired, children are born weak or sick,
                and their arrival taxes the ability of the family to provide for them and to give
                them the heritage of health and security and the advantages of education, protection
                and opportunity for development which should be the right of every child.</p>
            <p>Many women suffering from tuberculosis, heart disease, kidney disease and other
                ailments die as a result of pregnancy, or bring weak, sick, or dead children into
                the world. In the case of most of these unfortunate children their capital of life
                has been used up before they were born! Many mothers die needlessly from pregnancy
                when ill, and from abortions. Thousands would have been alive today if contraceptive
                information had been available to them.</p>
            <p>Many children are born to parents suffering from venereal disease. There are
                approximately 500,000 new cases of syphilis in this country every year, according to
                reports of the Public Health Service.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">BIRTH CONTROL AND POVERTY</head>
            <p>In families of poverty, the burden of too many children, born at too frequent
                intervals, is crushing. It often reduces the whole family to the level of mere
                animal subsistence. Lack of sound, effective means of birth control is a tragedy to
                such families at all times. During the depression the higher birth rate among the
                families of the unemployed, which studies revealed, aggravated the problem of
                supporting millions of persons unable to provide for themselves by still further
                increasing the number of the dependents. Not only is the quality of family life- the
                realization of the higher values of family life- at stake, but the resources of
                society are being taxed to support children born to families who do not want and
                cannot support them.</p>
            <p>One report indicated that in a group of families studied in 1932 “<q who="UNK">the
                    birth rate in families without employed workers was 197 as compared with 154 in
                    families with part-time workers only, and 134 in families with one or more
                    full-time workers. Thus, the families without any employed workers in 1932 had a
                    birth rate during the depression 48 per cent higher than those which had one or
                    more full-time workers in 1932</q>.”</p>
            <p>Birth control is perhaps the most immediate factor in reducing preventable infant
                mortality. A report to the <org>White House Conference on Child Health and
                    Protection</org> indicated that some 80,000 infants a year are born too weak to
                live even one month. Almost as many more are still-born. Studies of the <org
                    reg="United States Children's Bureau">U.S. Children’s Bureau</org> revealed that
                infant mortality rates increase with the order of birth; there is a rapid rise from
                the fourth child on.</p>
            <p>Lack of birth control information has driven vast numbers of distracted mothers to
                seek abortions. There has been a notorious increase in the number of abortions, now
                estimated at more than a million a year in the United States. Aside from the moral
                issue involved, abortions cause many deaths of mothers, and ill health and
                disability among thousands of others.</p>
            <p>A report submitted to the White House Conference on Child Health and Protection
                stated: “<q who="WHCCHP">It is appalling to note that in the childbearing years from
                    fifteen to forty-five, in that epoch when mothers are most needed for the care
                    of their young children, this scourge of abortion is responsible for deaths
                    almost equalling those from childbirth</q>.”</p>
            <p>The death rate among American mother is abnormally high. Abortions are a major factor
                in the maternal death rate, and a large proportion of them have been due to lack of
                contraceptive information and hygiene. Many studies have been made to ascertain the
                prevalence and causes of maternal mortality. The most extensive inquiry was made by
                the Children’s Bureau. It was a case-by-case check of 7,500 maternal deaths
                occurring in two years in fifteen states. It revealed a startling toll of deaths
                from abortions. Almost exactly a fourth of these women had died after some form of
                abortion.</p>
            <p>Every year thousands of mothers seek relief in bootleg contraceptive devices. They
                are victimized by unscrupulous purveyors of unreliable, ineffective and dangerous
                devices, quack remedies and advice without a sound scientific basis. In tests of
                more than one hundred commercial “contraceptives,” so-called, undertaken by the
                    <org>Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau</org>, <place reg="New York, NY">New
                    York</place>, forty-five were found wholly unreliable.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">PROGRESS OF BIRTH CONTROL</head>
            <p>I was working as a trained nurse among the poor in the slums of New York when I first
                realized the need for birth control. That was in 1914. From the day when I saw a
                poor woman die needlessly because information of how to prevent her becoming
                pregnant was denied her, I decided what my life work was to be. It was to bring to
                such women the information which they had every right to have from the standpoint of
                their health, their children, the welfare of their families and the public good. The
                fight lasted for 25 years. It has been won at last. A great host of men and women
                joined me in assailing the outmoded law, in breaking through the barbed wire
                entanglements of legalism, prejudice and opposition.</p>
            <p>Finally victory came through public opinion and a liberal court. The end of that
                dark, dismal, disgraceful chapter was written when an enlightened court saw beyond
                the dead letter of a law, which never should have gone on the statue books and which
                had already become dead and obsolete in the light of modern science, medicine and
                morality, and refused longer to interpret it as preventing physicians from giving
                contraceptive information in good faith where the need for it was clearly
                indicated.</p>
            <p>Birth control under medical direction finally became legal throughout the United
                States on November 30, 1936, when the <org>United States Circuit Court of Appeals
                    for the Second District</org> rendered a decision in a <name
                    reg="United States vs. One Package of Japanese Contraceptives">test case</name>
                brought by Dr. Hannah M. Stone that the Federal obscenity laws do not apply to the
                legitimate activities of physicians, and that they may prescribe contraceptives in
                the interests of the health and general well being of their patients. This momentous
                decision signed by <person reg="Hand, Billings Learned">Justice Learned
                    Hand</person>, <person reg="Swan, Thomas Walter">Thomas W. Swan</person> and
                    <person reg="Hand, Augustus Noble">Augustus N. Hand</person>, marked the end of
                the long fight against the outmoded Comstock law. It brought the birth control
                movement to the goal which it had sought through legislation.</p>
            <p>Within a few months, too, the <org>American Medical Association</org>, representing
                the physicians of the country, which had appointed a special committee to study
                birth control, adopted it as an integral part of medical practice and education.
                Thus, both legally and ethically, the way is now open for physicians in private
                practice to give contraceptive information for the health and welfare of their
                patients, and for medical college to give instruction to their students in this
                branch of medicine.</p>
            <p>The court’s decision was the emancipation proclamation of American motherhood.
                Motherhood is no longer in bondage. It is also a Bill of Rights to the medical
                profession in the field of contraception. Thus it marks the dawn of a new era. It
                guarantees to mothers the legal as well as the moral right to have something to say
                about how many children they shall have, how often, and under what conditions.</p>
            <p>The future is one of hope. The next steps are to actually put into practice what is
                now legally permissible and desirable from the standpoint of mothers, children,
                family welfare and the public good.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">THE NEXT STEPS</head>
            <p>In addition to making contraceptive information available to mothers through
                physicians in private practice, the doors of hospitals, clinics, dispensaries,
                health centers and other sources of medical counsel and help must be opened,
                especially to the poor. It is also most important to help mothers who do not have
                easy access to doctors and clinics. There are today 500 or more birth control
                clinics in this country. This number should be increased ten-fold. We need at least
                3,000 such clinics. We should also send visiting nurses into isolated homes remote
                from medical service to teach contraceptive measures to forgotten mothers.</p>
            <p>Only by adequate effort to save the lives of women and to promote maternal and child
                health can the community atone for the deaths of a million mothers during the six
                decades while the Comstock laws were in force. Those who won the legal fight for
                birth control must now move fast- and keep moving- for women and children still are
                needlessly dying. Their lives may be saved if contraceptive facilities become
                adequately available in every community.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">CONTRACEPTIVE CARAVANS</head>
            <p>Especially must we help the mothers who as yet are not reached through public health
                channels. We need contraceptive caravans of education and help for mountain women,
                farm women, mothers on distant homesteads, mothers in all districts, city and
                country, who are now neglected. They are the ones who should now be reached and
                helped. Thousands of letters have testified where these women are and that they are
                untouched by the social service of either community or state. There is a vast
                number, thousands, tens of thousands, doubtless millions of such women who cannot or
                do not come to a clinic, women who never come out of their own restricted areas, who
                seldom leave their homes.</p>
            <p>We should send an organization of birth control instructing nurses to visit the homes
                of these underprivileged mothers. Just as the members of the American Visiting
                Nurses Association have gone into the homes to help through bedside work, so we need
                an army of quipped, sympathetic, understanding nurses to take up this task of
                educating and instructing mothers in contraceptive techniques and thus free them
                from the constant fear which haunts their lives.</p>
            <p>Means must also be provided for testing contraceptive products and standardizing
                those offered for sale. Research looking toward simpler and cheaper methods
                (suitable to the poorest and least educated women) must go forward, and experimental
                methods must be carefully studied.</p>
            <p>For the benefit of women in the larger centers within reach of medical service, we
                must move with all our might and force to influence the public health authorities of
                the city, county, state and nation to see that birth control instruction is carried
                on under medical auspices as a part of their program.</p>
            <p>Social service agencies and workers should be awakened to the need of birth control.
                Many such agencies have been asleep or have refused to act. In many cases the
                workers have been more alert and progressive in this field than the managing boards
                of such organizations. Often the Boards of Directors, the officials who dictate the
                policies of philanthropic organizations, tie the hands of the actual workers. They
                are the ones who sacrifice constructive work, progress and the very lives of those
                in their care, in order to maintain a neat structure of harmony and pleasantness
                among themselves.</p>
            <p>Birth control clinics substitute competent medical attention for quackery and
                bootlegged advice and devices. There are about 7,000 hospitals and 10,000 other
                agencies where medical aid is sought by mothers, which are now legally free to give
                contraceptive advice and information to women who apply. We must induce them
                actually to provide such service. Women everywhere should help to get their own
                communities to provide birth control facilities. The <org>General Federation of
                    Women’s Clubs</org> have made birth control a part of their public welfare and
                health activities.</p>
            <p>We should also aid the nation-wide campaign to check venereal diseases, especially
                syphilis, which is now being carried on by the United States Public Health Service
                and State and local public health authorities.</p>
            <p>As long ago as 1932, <person reg="Stokes, John H.">Dr. Stokes</person>, testifying in
                behalf of a birth control bill, said:</p>
            <p>“<q who="STOJO">Syphilis stands somewhere between first and fourth among the causes
                    of death in the world... a major cause of insanity, of death from heart disease,
                    of infant mortality...Given the physician’s power to prescribe clearly and
                    exactly the use of contraceptive and disinfectant measures... there will be a
                    radical change in our situation with respect to one of the most tragic aspects
                    of syphilis, the helplessness of the innocent</q>.”</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">BIRTH CONTROL RESEARCH BUREAU</head>
            <p>With birth control legalized, the <org>National Committee on Federal Legislation for
                    Birth Control</org> finished its work and disbanded. The <org>Birth Control
                    Clinical Research Bureau</org>, New York, founded fourteen years ago, continues,
                however, and will increase both its clinical work and its services of research and
                counsel to aid other clinics and organizations. It will provide clinic research,
                serve as a clearing house of information about the establishment and operation of
                clinics and promote new centers throughout the country.</p>
            <p>More than 58,000 women have received contraceptive instruction at the Bureau,
                representing every walk of life, every diversity of race, religion and education.
                Additional thousands have benefitted through other services of the Bureau.</p>
            <p>As the first large center for contraceptive counsel, it has long since become
                internationally known and is now the largest clinic of its kind in the world.
                Doctors and scientists from many countries have visited it for technical training.
                Representatives from nearly every European country, as well as from
                    <place>Japan</place>, <place>China</place> and <place>India</place>, have sought
                information about the Bureau’s methods, along with innumberable visitors from all
                parts of the American continent. In many other countries similar work has been
                started.</p>
            <p>As the Bureau has had an experience and has collected a mass of data paralleled
                nowhere in the world, it is logical that it should be the center with which other
                contraceptive clinics should be allied. It is the only large birth control teaching
                center in the United States. It is the only center doing research in a variety of
                methods. It is the only center which has published any considerable number of
                reports on its work so that members of the medical profession could be informed on
                more than a series of a few hundred or possibly a few thousand cases.</p>
            <p>More than 145 clinics throughout the country are affiliated with the Bureau in a
                mutual effort to maintain and improve clinical service and contraceptive methods.
                The number of clinics needs to be greatly increased. If mothers everywhere in the
                land are to have contraceptive information, it must be within reach in their own
                communities, not alone in the headquarters of some distant city.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">WARNINGS</head>
            <p>A few words of warning against misuse of birth control are in order. It is for
                married women - for mothers- <del>not unmarried women</del> and women about to be
                married. It is not a negative but a positive force. These clinics servce as centers
                of maternal and child health. They provide medical examination of and counsel to
                mothers in the hygiene of conception and child bearing - in conception as well as
                contraception. They substitute competent medical attention for quackery and
                bootlegged advice and devices.</p>
            <p>Perhaps no other question is asked so frequently as this: “Is birth control the same
                as abortion?” No. It is <emph rend="underline">entirely different</emph>. Abortion
                destroys the already fertilized ovum or interferes with its development. Birth
                control or contraception prevents by mechanical and chemical means the union of the
                two cells, therely <emph rend="underline">preventing</emph> the conception from
                taking place. Birth control <emph rend="underline">prevents</emph> the conceiving of
                a life. Abortion is the <emph rend="underline">interruption</emph> of pregnancy,
                after a life has been conceived.</p>
            <p>It cannot be too strongly emphasized that responsible birth control clinics do not
                perform, counsel or countenance abortions. Their work is wholly preventive. When a
                competent medical examination indicates that a mother is pregnant, the case is
                wholly outside the clinic field and becomes a matter of obstetrical care from the
                patient’s own physician.</p>
            <p>Birth control is not forced on any woman. Legalizing it does not make contraceptive
                information compulsory; it is permissive and optional- available to those who wish
                it. No physician will be compelled to give such information. The court decision
                permits contraceptive information and supplies to be sent to doctors, to hospitals
                and clinics and to druggists for use in legitimate prescription business.</p>
            <p>Finally, we may appropriately sum up again the reasons why birth control is needed.
                They are clear and compelling. The main reasons are:</p>
            <p>To insure to every child the heritage of a sound mind in a healthy body.</p>
            <p>To assure children who are wanted and welcome.</p>
            <p>To safeguard the health of women who should postpone or refrain entirely from
                motherhood.</p>
            <p>To space births so that each child may have adequate care and the mother any
                recuperate from childbirth before starting another pregnancy.</p>
            <p>To enable parents to bring into the world only the number of children they can afford
                to rear.</p>
            <p>To prevent over-population-- a major cause of war.</p>
            <p>The practice of birth control affords opportunities for the development of the higher
                qualities of personality on which the future and progress of the race on the higher
                levels depend. It makes for a real “survival of the fittest.” Fitness is not merely
                physical strength, but also involves the mental and spiritual attributes which
                enrich life and assure the spiritual advancement and rounded development of the
                race.</p>
            <p>The time and opportunity for birth control to take its proper place as a way of life
                have come. It will reduce suffering, fear, misery, ill health, abortions and deaths.
                It will make for healthier and happier mothers, fathers, and children. It will
                promote the welfare of the race as well as the family.</p>
            <p>Women are free-- at last.</p>
            <p># # #</p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
