<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed draft article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2012-04-17 AW</prepDate><prepDate>2014-04-10 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="0000-00-00">N.d.</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Foundation for
                Marriage</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp143428</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
            <bibl>Library of Congress Microfilm 131:008</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>No final version was found.</p>
        <index level1="adolescence"/>
        <index level1="hormones"/>
        <index level1="human body"/>
        <index level1="marriage"/>
        <index level1="marriage age" level2="men"/>
        <index level1="marriage age" level2="women"/> 
        <index level1="sexuality"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <p>In any plan for building, one of the first things to consider is
            the laying of the foundation. This is especially true in Marriage,
            and strange as it may seem to you to say it, but the foundation of a
            happy married life usually is made during that period of youth
            called the adolescent period, or the age in the girl from twelve to
            twenty-two, in the boy fourteen to twenty-three.</p>
        <p>This is the period when the girl or boy pack away into their bodies,
            into the sinews, bones, nerves and blood cells, all the essential
            qualities of body building they will need for use later on. It is
            the period for conserving and developing the life energy and power
            of the vital functions.</p>
        <p>If these powers are wasted and dissipated by premature use, it will
            be impossible to bring them to their highest potentialities in
            marriage.</p>
        <p>For after all every girl and every boy hopes and dreams of the day
            when he or she shall enter that state called marriage and in terms
            of the usual love story “live happily every after.”</p>
        <p>In life, however, the real love story does not end with marriage. It
            begins with it.</p>
        <p>A certificate of marriage does not guarantee happiness to any of us.
            Neither love nor happiness are prizes found in the package of the
            marriage license.</p>
        <p>Enduring happiness in marriage can be attained by all of us if we
            know the rules of the game. The game of life, the game of courtship,
            the game of love.</p>
        <p>As love is essential to marriage, virility is essential to love.
            Mastery of the power and forces of our bodies, as instruments of our
            desires, instruments for our expression in love, is essential.
            Youth, adolescence or early manhood is given the race, not only as
            periods of preparation, but as periods to develop and build. It is a
            mistake to hurry through the age of adolescence. Youth must not try
            “a short cut” to manhood. Life will be and can be more fully
            realized by the prolongation of this period of preparation for
            maturity by the conservation of these vital powers making for
            manhood and womanhood.</p>
        <p>All activity--mental and physical--during the adolescent period, when
            the foundations of happiness are being laid, should be determined by
            the knowledge that the very architecture of the body, the bones,
            muscles, nerves, brain is dependent upon the internal secretions of
            the body and these are intricately tied up with the sexual system,
            its powers and potentialities.</p>
        <p>During the period of growth and development between the age of twelve
            and twenty-two, the co-ordination of those secretions hormones or
            chemical messengers absorbed directly into the blood stream, model
            and shape the bony structure that makes for virility, strength, and
            beauty.</p>
        <p>In all this vital process of body and brain building in the
            adolescent, the sex glands play a part of equal importance with the
            other directless glands, the importance of which, modern science
            tells us cannot be overestimated. </p>
        <p>The strength, beauty, vigor, shape of the body with its bones, its
            sinews, delicately coordinated muscles, its internal organs, heart,
            lungs, liver, is dependent upon the harmonious activity of these
            glands. Thus we see that human bodies are both dynamos and motors.
            We must not tamper with or interfere with the normal development of
            any organ, for to do so throws the whole process of construction out
            of balance.</p>
        <p>No one can go back and build his life over again. We must go on with
            what we have, but often, alas too often, a discord in early youth
            has entered to defeat the well rounded development or our physical
            and mental powers.</p>
        <p>Before the nervous and emotional force can be directed and expended
            properly and sanely--it must first be created--and stored away. The
            more power you store up in bones, nerves, glands and blood cells,
            the greater the force of its expenditure during maturity. The later
            its use, the longer the period of virility. To store away vitality
            and sex energy in youth means a greater power and fuller use of it
            in maturity and old age.</p>
        <p>Each process, each period of life, has its own reason. Its own use.
            Life is a chain, each period a link. Each link dependency upon the
            preceding link for its strength. We must not hurry through, neglect
            or shorten them. Sex energy is not only controlled but stored up for
            without this deep reservoir, this latent force, love cannot, at the
            great period of marriage, express its power, nor the overwhelming
            poetry of life find full expression.</p>
        <p>It is thus generated, and in a miraculous way acknowledged and ready
            to be converted as the mysterious miracle of sex love, into
            ambition.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
