<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed draft speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2012-04-04 AW Initial Tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2012-05-15 CH Proofed Tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2012-05-16 AW Corrected Tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-10 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-05-02 EK correct proofs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1917-01-29"><supplied>29 Jan. 1917</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied>Carnegie Hall Speech Notes</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp143430</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Library of Congress, Margaret Sanger Papers</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Library of Congress, Margaret Sanger Papers Microfilm,</title> LCM
                131:24</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>A portion of a draft speech, prepared for her rally at <org>Carnegie Hall</org>, held to
            support Sanger during her trial for opening the <org>Brownsville birth control
                clinic</org>. No published version was found. For newspaper coverage of Sanger's
            speech, see <xref from="321954.xml">"Carnegie Hall Mass Meeting Address, Jan. 29,
                1917."</xref></p>
        <p> At the bottom of the second page, <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret
                Sanger</person> wrote: "Part of speech at Carnegie Hall. Judges furious at reading.
            Perhaps for <title type="journal">BC Review</title> on conscripts."</p>
        <index level1="birth control movement"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="war and"/>
        <index level1="motherhood"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <byline>Mrs. SANGER <add>Radio</add></byline>
        <p>Undoubtedly many of you present in this audience have heard me speak before on this vital
            subject of Birth Control. <del>I don’t want to travel over old ground by any repetition
                of what already has been said but I must emphasize that Birth Control is the keynote
                of a new social program. It is interlocked with the future of our nation, in fact
                the future of all nations.</del></p>
        <p>Interest in the Birth Control movement has arisen in response to a real need of thousands
            and thousands of wives and mothers, many of whom have been grievously wounded in the
            battle of life. Today these mothers refuse to be thoughtlessly wasteful of their more
            precious possessions--mother power and child life. Thinking men too realize more fully
            that child bearing is a costly venture -- as costly in life as it is in money. (Insert
            here paragraph on infant and maternal mortality figures)</p>
        <p>Birth Control means an end of this pathetic picture. It means mothers will not be drained
            of vitality and happiness by incessant child bearing, particularly when parents know
            they cannot give the child even a fighting chance for a life of health and happiness
                <del>and the development it has the right to expect. Women want to bring to the
                creation of children a sense of joy and the full flowering of womanhood.</del> They
            demand and have a right to demand the legal application of at least as much of science
            and <del>of brain possessed</del> of thought and of intelligence in the rearing of
            children as the government applies to the rearing of horses, pigs and <del>goats</del>
            <add>poultry.</add> I feel that the day of smug hypocracy has passsed and that the youth
            of the nation, of reasoning age, has a right to look the facts of nature squarely in the
            face. <add>&amp; apply</add> these facts to the <del>happiness</del> fulfillment of
                <del>their lives</del>
            <add>its life</add>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="page(s)"/> a land of bondage and slavery, it steals the
            husband from his wife and children, it starves the poor while it fattens the rich.</p>
        <p> Women of <place reg="United States">America</place>, have not the offspring of womankind
            reddened every battlefield in history? Have we not carried the burden of universal
            slaughter? Have we not drunk the cup of tears to the very dregs, so that dynasties and
            governments the world over have prospered on the blood of our offspring?</p>
        <p>The time has come to show that American women shall not be driven or coerced and they
            shall demand that the money kings may lend their ill-gotten wealth at high interest to
            the allied despots of <place>Europe</place> but that our people will not be
            conscripted,-- come what may!</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
 