<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Autograph draft article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2001-08-30 MH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2001-09-05 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2002-08-22 KH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2003-07-28 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/02 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007-05-30 CH Oxygen cleanup</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2001/03/11 CH Entered corrections suggested by Andy Carloff.</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-18 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1912-00-00">
            <supplied resp="MSPP">1912</supplied>
        </docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Wanted--A Bigger Motherhood</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp143451</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
            <bibl>Library of Congress Microfilm 131:0108</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="ANON">Anonymous</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
        <p>For a draft version of this article see <title type="article">"A Crying Need for a Greater
                Motherhood</title>," ca. 1912 [LCM 131:46].</p>
        <index level1="child labor"/>
        <index level1="prostitution"/>
        <index level1="working classes" level2="children"/>
        <index level1="working classes" level2="women and girls"/>
        <index level1="poverty"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Wanted--a Bigger Motherhood.</head>
        <epigraph>
            <q who="ANON">"<unclear>O</unclear> friends and sisters gliding down the
                years-<lb/>Humanity is calling each and all;<lb/>In tender accents, born of grief
                &amp; tears:<lb/>I pray you listen to the thrilling call;<lb/>you can not in your
                cold &amp; selfish pride <lb/>Pass guiltlessly upon 'the other
                    side'"</q>
        </epigraph>
        <p>Mothers of today <add>let us</add> keep that last line ever before our eyes. "<q
                who="ANON">Pass guiltlessly upon the other side.</q>" For as the children of today
            are the society of tomorrow holding full sway over all--we must stand back &amp;
                <del>see the</del> view the passing generation of our creation and we can not shut
            our eyes to the good or wrong we have done them. Accordingly shall we be judged. Wonder
            &amp; exclaim as we stand back &amp; review the passing people of our creation, why so
            many are in jails &amp; prisons, so many paupers and prostitutes so many thieves &amp;
            murderers and so <del>few having the flag of his country</del> many marred &amp; sick
            &amp; dead--</p>
        <p>The problems of the children, of sex of education, in fact are problems of life, are the
            mothers problems and the mothers of today have been too long shifting her
            responsibilities on her single sister &amp; passed upon "<q who="ANON">the other
                side</q>." On the child of today is moulded <del>so will</del> that form will
            our future Society take and so will they call us to account for the neglect toward
            them.</p>
        <p>Only a few days ago <supplied>Im</supplied> talking to a farmers wife and was greatly
            impressed by their attitude of "<q who="ANON">passing on the other side.</q>" In
            relating some of the experience I had on the lower East Side in homes of poverty and
            sickness, where a father and mother work side by side in the factory, leaving the family
            of five children to the care of the oldest girl in years--the children remain in the
            streets all day getting their <del>meals</del>
            <add>lunch</add> as best they can out of garbage pails or gutter until the parents come
            home at night. After I had related a few such stories which had come directly under my
            care, tears glistened in her eyes, she drew both her children close to her and said "<q
                who="UNK">Oh City Woman Im so glad my children have their mother, &amp; good food,
                &amp; plenty of air &amp; sunshine, Im so happy that they are out of those harried
                cities &amp; here where they can chase the butterflies gather daisies &amp; romp
                &amp; play to their hearts desire</q>"--She dashed a tear from off her nose, braced
            herself in her chair and began, "<q who="UNK">but after all its no use in our worrying
                about these things, they are there, &amp; they can't be helped &amp; I just won't
                think about them.</q>"</p>
        <p>This good kind human was as deserted wife &amp; mother as we could find today to her own,
            but no other little waif ever stood even in the shadow of that love, she would not think
            of the waifs so she "<q who="ANON">passed upon the other side.</q>" Mothers of today
            is this not what millions of us are doing. Are we not afraid to meet the cruelties of
            our own neglect. Are we not afraid to face the four millions of little toilers returning
            at night fall from the mills &amp; factories with faces pale &amp; worn &amp; bodies
            bent and old, they have been making the clothing for us, for ours, which gives us more
            time for culture &amp; education, they return old in experience and weary with life at
            twelve years--to their huts to eat their scanty food &amp; throw their frail and tired
            forms upon heaps of rags on the floor, to prepare for the next day's toil: Are we not
            afraid to face the thousands of little ones spending their daytime from sunrise to
            sunset in the dark cellar picking over old rags &amp; doing so called "easy
                work" emerging at night fall thinly clad, tired and pale not a ray of sun
            to kiss their features for months.</p>
        <p>Are we not afraid to face the thousands of "little mothers" ranging
            in years from 9 to 12 weighed down with the burdens and cares of the younger children,
            shoulder bent and whole body tending toward deformity with carrying the little ones.</p>
        <p>Think of allowing the future men and women to be reared by Children not much older than
            themselves-- how many accidents is due to this neglect, How easily Society passes on the
            other side &amp; smiles at the "little mother" &amp; praises them,
            but does nothing to preserve their health for the future big mothers.</p>
        <p>Are we not afraid of the thousands of little girls whose power of motherhood has been
            taken from her on account of diseases of gonorrhea etc. contracted in filthy toilets in
            the tenements, hundreds of little girls contract this disease &amp; are neglected--
            mothers are away at work, the "little mother" knows nothing of this
            ailment, and so the baby of three years is being slowly eaten away by this dreadful
            disease and unless death relieves her she lives deprived of the most beautiful gift of
            this life-- the gift of motherhood.</p>
        <p>Mothers of today let us look at each other unmasked--let us tear this mask of
            indifference &amp; hypocrisy from off our eyes, &amp; face these conditions &amp; meet
            them squarely. These children who work in the mills &amp; factories, &amp; cellars,
            these neglected &amp; starved children of the slums; these diseased &amp; deformed
            children of neglect. <del>Even</del> the children who are pushed about in the streets by
            every one, the children of the reform schools and jails, yes even the children who walk
            the streets at night to sell their bodies are all ours--they are ours. Mothers-- yours
            &amp; mine. Our sisters are their mothers they are &amp; all belong to us-- for we are
            mothers of the <add>human</add> race-- These children cry out to us for protection
                <add>These creatures of our creation</add>
            <del>They</del> are the products of our neglect. And the time has come for mothers of
            today to face this neglect.</p>
        <p>Children are creatures of environment as all mothers know and yet walk through the
            streets of any city from 9am to 3pm when the older children are in school &amp; see what
            environment the children of today, the men &amp; women of tomorrow, are spending their
            little lives, waiting for the time to go to school.</p>
        <p>From the time a baby can toddler from its mothers side until its ready for the
            kindergarten it receives its first lessons of life-- and thousands yes, millions learn
            this first lesson in the street. There is no place for them, they are in the way on the
            roads on the side walks on the steps in the houses. No place in this beautiful world of
            ours for <name type="deity">God</name>s most perfect creation the little child. &amp; our future
            Society taken its first lesson eating from garbage cans, stealing from grocers lying,
            fighting, swearing, and we will wonder &amp; exclaim as we stand back &amp; review the
            passing people of our creation, why so many are in jails &amp; prisons, so many paupers
            &amp; prostitutes, so many thieves &amp; murderers and so <del>few bearing the flag of
                his country</del> many marred &amp; sick &amp; dead.</p>
        <p>The problems of the children, of sex of education, in fact all problems of life, are the
            mothers problems, and the mothers of today have been too long shifting her
            responsibilities on her single sister &amp; passed upon "<q who="ANON">the other
                side</q>" as the child of today is moulded <del>so will</del> that form will
            our future Society take, and so will they call us to account for the neglect toward
            them.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
