<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/06/08 CE</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/06/20 CE</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1937-05-25">25 May 1937</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>What Margaret Sanger Thinks of Mussolini</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp143477</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Plain Talk Magazine</title>May 25, 1937</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of
                Congress</title>131:0310</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="FGC">Fascist Grand Council</name>
            <name id="MUSBE">Mussolini, Benito</name>
            <name id="SHABE">Shaw, George Bernard</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <p>An editorial introduced this article, stating: "Mrs. Roberta Campbell
        Lawson, president of the General Federation of Women's Clubs, told what
        the American women think of Mussolini in May PLAIN TALK, in response to
        Il Duce's own article on the small estate in which he holds the opposite
        sex.</p>
    <p>Mrs. Margaret Sanger, best known advocate of scientific birth control,
        who has been to Italy, is telling here what the women of Italy think of
        Mussolini, as well as her own interesting personal opinion of the
        world's most aggressive breeder of cannon fodder.</p>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>For another version, see S71:0944</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="international"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="opposition to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="rights associated with"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="decline in"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="efforts to increase"/>
        <index level1="Italy" level2="population policies"/>
        <index level1="Mussolini, Benito Amilcare Andrea"/>
        <index level1="population growth" level2="regulation of"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="freedom and rights of"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="gender roles and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>What Margaret Sanger Thinks of Mussolini</head>
        <byline>By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">MARGARET
            SANGER</person></byline>
        <p>Item for item and paragraph for paragraph, <person
                reg="Mussolini, Benito">Mussolini</person>'s ideas about women,
            as set forth in the article “<title>What Mussolini Thinks of
                Women</title>”, which appeared in the last issue of <title>PLAIN
                TALK</title>, are shot through with prejudice.</p>
        <p>They are a confession of his own limited personal life. His fanatical
            male egotism is a threat to the development of the women of
                <place>Italy</place>, to the advancement of all women, and to
            the peace of the world.</p>
        <p rend="blockquote"><emph rend="bold">“<q who="MUSBE">The modern woman
                    is liable to forget the primary duties she owes to
                    civilization, and therefore I am not in favor of woman's
                    dabbling in politics</q>,” Mussolini writes.</emph></p>
        <p>Women realize poignantly the obligation and privilege they carry as
            race bearers because they are the mothers of the race, and it is
            because of this that they must, perforce, enter the political arena.
            For only by so doing can women make the world a fit place for
            children to live in.</p>
        <p>“<q who="MUSBE">Women never created anything</q>,” writes Mussolini.
            “. . . <q who="MUSBE">you cannot point to any single instance where
                a woman has created anything that has been passed down to
                posterity</q>.”</p>
        <p>Ludicrous--were the implications Mussolini's bigotry not so fraught
            with danger and tragedy. Women never created anything? What about
            babies? What about you, Signor Mussolini. You would not be here to
            rant and shout, nor we to read and fight, if women had never created
            anything.</p>
        <p>As to women not being creators--shame on Mussolini!</p>
        <p>Has he forgotten his history? Where are his religious teachings?</p>
        <p><emph rend="italic">Does he not know that the <person
                    reg="Mary, Virgin, Saint">Virgin Mary</person>, all by
                herself and without assistance of man (according to legend)
                created the leader and founder of Christianity. This was an act
                of creation which has changed our civilization for the past 2000
                years.</emph></p>
        <p>Is this not enough?</p>
        <p>What are the mutterings of a vain egotistical war lord compared with
            this achievement?</p>
        <p>Why waste time in listing other names of women of history, of
            science, of art, of music, of literature?</p>
        <p>Women of the world are united in loathing and despising Mussolini's
            egotism. Consequently his knowledge of women of brain, personality,
            talent and ability has been curtailed, and such women do not exist
            for him.</p>
        <p rend="blockquote"><emph rend="bold">“<q who="MUSBE">Women in
                    parliament are meddlers and muddlers. Women cannot look
                    after the future of the human race in the home and in the
                    nursery and govern at the same time. . . the governing of
                    the community should be left to the male sex</q>,” Mussolini
                continues.</emph></p>
        <p>And a fine mess the male sex has made of it. We, the mothers, look
            today upon a world threatened by war, upon nation arming against
            nation. We look upon poverty in the midst of plenty, upon millions
            of able bodied men unable to find work, upon hunger and disease. We
            see men, women and children without adequate food, shelter or
            clothing, while billions are spent for armaments and the upkeep of
            armies.</p>
        <p>Women cannot look after the future of the human race without taking
            an active part in shaping their nation's laws, without entering the
            fields of politics and government. I am no rabid man hater who
            thinks that women should rule the world. But I do believe, and my
            belief is grounded in a study of history, that our problems must be
            met by men and women acting together, by a fusion of male and female
            power, by cooperation between the sexes.</p>
        <p>As truly as these <place>United States</place> could not exist half
            slave and half free, so truly today the nations cannot build a
            better world while male dominates female, while man enslaves his
            womenfolk.</p>
        <p>“Emancipation of women has imperilled the domestic security of the
            home and the safety of the world from the point of view of
            eugenics,” Il Duce states.</p>
        <p>What, I ask, is the greatest threat to domestic security, to the
            safety of the world?</p>
        <p>War.</p>
        <p>And men are responsible for war. Women, because they know the glory
            of motherhood, because they are the life bearers, the creators of
            men, feel a horror unknown to mere man at the spectacle of thousands
            upon thousands of young men mowed down, maimed and crippled in the
            glory of their youth. It is women who champion the cause of peace,
            who have made articulate the voiceless protest of the masses.</p>
        <p>Does Mussolini, with the rape of <place>Ethiopia</place> still vivid
            in the minds of a horrified world, dare to talk of security? Does
            this arch leader of marching cohorts, bent on further aggression,
            presume to tell women about “<q who="MUSBE">the safety of the world
                from the point of view of eugenics</q>?”</p>
        <p>War, which claims the best and the youngest, the choicest flower of
            the race, is the deadly enemy of eugenics. <place>France</place>, to
            cite on example, still bears the scars of the ruthless slaughter of
            the Napoleonic wars, fought over a century ago.</p>
        <p>Plot the population curve of any nation, and it will show a tragic
            dip, after each war. Study the make-up, physical and psychological,
            of that population, and it will show the next generation, and the
            next, paying for the insanity of war.</p>
        <p rend="blockquote"><emph rend="italic">“<q who="MUSBE">I have always
                    said that women are inferior to men</q>,” continues
                Mussolini. “<q who="MUSBE">But to give them their full due I
                    will say that despite their physical frailty they are very
                    often more courageous</q>.”</emph></p>
        <p>Inferior--what yardstick is used here? What of the loyalty, the
            steadfastness, the ability to meet sudden emergencies, and long
            years of suspense and unhappiness?</p>
        <p>Hear the life story of any mother, it matters not what nationality or
            what station in life. Listen, and marvel at the acts of heroism, the
            unsung deeds which make men's feats seem like child's play.</p>
        <p><person reg="Shaw, George Bernard">Bernard Shaw</person> once said
            that <q who="SHABE">if men bore the children there would be but one
                child in every family, for no man, having once gone down into
                the valley of suffering to give birth to a child, would
                willingly and knowingly undertake it again</q>. But women freely
            suffer the agony, because (even Mussolini grudgingly admits it) they
            are more courageous than men.</p>
        <p rend="blockquote"><emph rend="italic">“<q who="MUSBE">Women do not
                    want to enter politics. . . . they are unwanted and
                    unnecessary in public life</q>,” Il Duce states
                blandly.</emph></p>
        <p>Perhaps they do not WANT to enter politics; perhaps they would rather
            still depend upon their males as did their primitive sisters who
            stayed at home while the male went forth to stalk his game.</p>
        <p>But since man today does not, and perhaps can not, provide for all
            women, they must go out and fend for themselves and their children.
            Woman has entered public life, industry, politics, in order to
            FULFIL, not to ESCAPE, her biological function, in order to be able
            to bear and bring up children, and make the world a fit place for
            them.</p>
        <p>It is because man has failed to use the power he has held through so
            many centuries intelligently, that women are in public life today.
            But with wisdom we can turn that failure into good.</p>
        <p>The unmarried woman, the woman who is childless through no fault of
            her own, the woman whose childbearing and child rearing tasks are
            behind her, and whose years of highest mental and psychological
            activity stretch ahead, are needed in the affairs of public
            life.</p>
        <p>They have a contribution to make, and thoughtful men will be glad of
            their cooperation. Male and female together must work should to
            shoulder if we are to achieve the best for future generations.</p>
        <p>Woman, set free, given the power of decision over her biological
            functions--that is, given birth control knowledge--is ready and
            willing to be not only a wife and mother, but a comrade and fellow
            worker.</p>
        <p>But birth control, under Mussolini, is ruthlessly forbidden in Italy.
            While, increasingly the world over, birth control is seen as a
            necessary part of public health, the women of Italy are doomed to
            needless suffering and death because scientific information about
            how to space their children and plan their families is
            forbidden.</p>
        <p rend="blockquote"><emph rend="italic">More babies is Mussolini's
                command, and he does not even bother to hide the reason for his
                orders. According to a recent press report, the <org
                    reg="Gran Consiglio de Fascismo">Fascist Grand
                Council</org>, Italy's highest advisory body, is “<q who="FGC"
                    >taking steps to increase the birth rate, is considering the
                    need for more children for Italy's armies of the
                future</q>.”</emph></p>
        <p>This is no new move. Professor <person reg="Salvemini, Gaetano"
                >Gaetano Salvemini</person>, one of Italy's most distinguished
            historians, exiled for anti-fascist views, has pointed out that
            though Mussolini has pursued his campaign for more babies with all
            the showmanship and facilities of high pressure salesmanship for
            more than ten years, the Italian birth rate has declined
            steadily.</p>
        <p>In 1927 Mussolini issued the command to the women of Italy to breed
            him not less than fifty million subjects by 1950. While waiting for
            the desired 50 million, he demanded six million men of fighting age
            between 1935 and 1940, when European history will reach its crucial
            point.</p>
        <p>We have already seen in Ethiopia to what use he has put these
            fighting men. His command for more babies was backed up by
            reductions and exemptions from taxation and other privileges for
            large families, by heavy couples and by suppression of all birth
            control propaganda and practice.</p>
        <p>What happened? In 1926, despite peremptory orders to increase and
            multiply, the women of Italy produced 20,000 less children than in
            1925; in 1927 they produced 50,000 less children than in 1926. In
            1930, the birth rate was lower by 56,000 than in 1929.</p>
        <p>In 1902, when Italy's population was 32,500,000, 1,100,000 children
            were born. In 1925, with a population of 40 million, only 1,150,000
            children were born. Population increase has come, not from an
            increase in births, but from a decrease in deaths through better
            sanitary conditions.</p>
        <p>Italy looks toward war, and must have fodder for the cannon of the
            enemy. But the women of Italy are doing their own thinking, despite
            the fact that, according to Mussolini, they have no initiative, no
            brains, no function save to amuse and charm and soothe their men
            folks, and bear children.</p>
        <p>While the general trend throughout the civilized world is to raise
            the legal age of marriage, Mussolini has lowered the marriage age
            for boys from 18 to 16 and for girls from 16 to 14. He says, in
            effect:</p>
        <p rend="blockquote"><emph rend="italic">“<q who="MUSBE">Hurry up and
                    get married and have a lot of babies. Its cheaper. If you
                    don't we’ll tax the shirt off your back. If you do, you can
                    have a state loan as a wedding present, reduction in taxes,
                    free passes, bonuses and a lot of glory</q>.”</emph></p>
        <p>But the women of Italy aren't interested. The birth rate declines
            steadily.</p>
        <p>In 1932 I visited Italy. I went, not as a birth control advocate, but
            as a private American citizen, under the name I use in private life.
            While I didn't get to <place reg="Rome, Italy">Rome</place>, the
            news of my arrival leaked out elsewhere and I was overwhelmed with
            requests from women's clubs for secret meetings, for information and
            help.</p>
        <p>There is, I believe, a great underground movement for birth control
            in Italy, and this is perhaps, in large measure, responsible for the
            fall in the birth rate. Truth and freedom cannot be killed nor
            entirely suppressed. It lives, submerged, to do its work and rise
            again.</p>
        <p>The women of Italy are silently telling Mussolini WHAT THEY THINK OF
            HIM. They are telling him that there can be no life unless they will
            it, and that, with their sisters the world over, they will not bear
            children to be slaughtered on the battlefield.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
