<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed draft article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2009/08/04 LL</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2009/08/06 CH proof and correct</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/03/10 clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1928-05-28">28 May 1928</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>
                <supplied resp="MSPP">An Open Letter to Cardinal Patrick J.
                    Hayes</supplied>
            </titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp143710</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Papers</title>, Library of
                Congress.</bibl>
            <bibl>LCM 130:0435</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="HAYPA">Hayes, Patrick J.</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="Catholic Church" level2="political influence of"/>
        <index level1="Catholic Church" level2="birth control and abortion and"
        />
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Open Letter to Cardinal Hayes</head>
        <byline>by Margaret Sanger</byline>
        <p>My attention has just been called to your statement to the delegates
            at the <org type="conference">18th Annual Convention of the
                Catholic Press Association</org>, reported in the <place
                reg="New York, NY">New York</place>
            <title>Evening Sun</title> of May 25th, 1928.</p>
        <p>You are quoted as saying, in your welcome to the delegates on behalf
            of the Diocese of New York, that you are “<q who="HAYPA">in full
                agreement that the church should be kept out of politics-- And
                at the same time let us have the Catholic press keep out of
                politics.</q>”</p>
        <p>The <org>American Birth Control League</org>, Inc. is deeply
            interested in this statement. Every year the League sponsors a bill
            at <place reg="Albany, NY">Albany</place> which, if passed, would
            permit physicians to give Birth Control advice to married persons.
            Every year the only opposition comes from the <org>Roman Catholic
                Church</org>, through the <org reg="Catholic Diocese of Albany"
                >Dioceses of Albany</org> and <org
                reg="Catholic Diocese of New York">New York</org>, and from the
                <org>Associated Catholic Charities</org> of the state of New
            York.</p>
        <p>When our representatives were interviewing members of <org
                reg="United States Congress">Congress</org> at <place
                reg="Washington DC">Washington</place> two years ago, they
            found Catholics, directed by the <org> National Catholic Welfare
                Council</org>, lobbying against any change in the Federal law
            governing the distribution or importation of Birth Control
            information or materials.</p>
        <p>Does your statement mean that in future the Catholic Church will keep
            out of politics where legislation on Birth Control is concerned, and
            will your Church cease its policy of intimidation of those members
            of Congress and of the <org>New York Legislature</org> who do not
            think as you do, but who have been threatened, in the past, with
            defeat if they voted for our bills?</p>
        <p>We entirely agree with your reported statement that “<q who="HAYPA"
                >the church should be kept out of politics.</q>” Is the
            statement attributed to you correct, and what does it imply? Many
            thousands of married people in New York State are interested in your
            answer. </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
