<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Statement">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2007-07-16 CH-research questions pending</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-03-07 CH clean regs</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-22 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1927-00-00">1927</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Preface to the Proceedings of the World Population
					Conference</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp143773</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>Margaret Sanger, ed. <title type="book">Proceedings of the World Population
					Conference</title> (London, 1927).</bibl>
			<bibl>Library of Congress Microfilm 130:725A</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<index level1="conferences" level2="World Population Conference" level3="1927"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>PREFACE.</head>
		<byline>by MRS. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">MARGARET SANGER</person></byline>
		<p>The problems of population have been looming upon the horizon of international thought
			for the past ten years, and with the advance of scientific application to social
			problems it was only natural that some of us should turn to the scientists with the
			possible hope that from them might be gleaned the solution.</p>
		<p>It was with this idea in mind that the <org>World Population Conference</org> was
			initiated and organized. It was the first time that biologists had been invited to
			participate with sociologists in the solution of economic problems and, as has been
			seen, the biological principle played a very large part in the discussions.</p>
		<p>The result of this gathering was the recognition of the need and desire for further
			study, and a permanent <org
				reg="International Union for the Scientific Study of Population Problems">Union for
				the study of Population</org> in various countries was formed.</p>
		<p>It has long been my desire to have the population question discussed from an
			international scientific standpoint, and it is with a feeling of some satisfaction that
			I am at last able to present to the public so complete and comprehension a volume on
			this great question as it was discussed at the World Population Conference.</p>
		<p>I trust that the valuable information and data submitted herein may prove a source of
			help and inspiration to those who ceaselessly work towards the solution of the
			population problem.</p>
		<p>My thanks are tendered to Mr. <person reg="Chance, Clinton">Clinton Chance</person>, who,
			with Mrs. <person reg="How-Martyn, Edith">Edith How-Martyn</person>, cooperated with me
			throughout and devoted over a year to the preliminary preparation for the
			Conference.</p>
		<p>Thanks are due to Professor <person reg="Pearl, Raymond">Raymond Pearl</person> and also
			to Sir <person reg="Mallet, Bernard">Bernard Mallet</person>, who accepted the
			chairmanship of the Advisory Council, and also to the members of the Advisory Council
			for their valuable help.</p>
		<p>I wish to make special mention of Professor <person reg="Huxley, Julian">Julian
				Huxley</person>, whose cooperation and active participation from the outset has been
			one of the determining factors in the success of the Conference. He, together with
			Professor <person reg="Carr-Saunders, Alexander">Carr-Saunders</person> and Dr. <person
				reg="Crew, Francis Albert Eley">Crew</person>, has given valuable assistance and
			advice in the editing and completion of these Proceedings.</p>
		<p>My warmest thanks are given also to Mrs. <person reg="Hodson, Cora">Cora Hodson</person>,
			Miss <person reg="Green, Susan">Susan Green</person>, Mrs. <person reg="Kennedy, Anne"
				>Anne Kennedy</person>, Miss <person reg="Comstock, Anita">Anita Comstock</person>,
			Miss <person reg="Breed, Mary ">W. Breed</person>, Mrs. <person
				reg="Martin, Alice Marjorie">Marjorie Martin</person> and many voluntary workers for
			their wholehearted assistance in the arrangements for the Conference.</p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
