<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Autograph Draft Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2003/06/25 JA</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/23 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007/06/25 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-18 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/12/11 EK Correct Proofs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1916-01-00"><supplied resp="MSPP">Jan</supplied> 1916</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Notes on Address before the Woman Rebel Trial</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp143701</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers Microfilm, Library of Congress, L130:0342</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="EB">The Encyclopedia Britannica</name>
            <name id="PAITH">Paine, Thomas</name>
            <name id="PLA">Plato</name>
            <name id="ARI">Aristotle</name>
            <name id="ZEN">Zenophon</name>
            <name id="CICMA">Cicero, Marcus Tullius</name>
            <name id="TERQU">Tertullian, Quintus Septimus</name>
            <name id="AUG">St. Augustine</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote><p>A handwritten note by <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger</person> reads:
                "<q>Notes on address when contemplating trial re <title type="journal">Woman
                    Rebel</title> 1916.</q>" At the top of the 4th page, Sanger wrote "<q>buck
                up.</q>" Portions of this text were used again in the stump speech she gave on her
            1916 national tour. For an example see <title type="speech">Condemnation is
                Misunderstanding</title>
            <xref from="128003.xml">Apr.-July, 1916</xref>.</p>
        <index level1="abortion" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="class-based"/>
        <index level1="working classes" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="biography"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="morality of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="opposition to"/>
        <index level1="censorship"/>
        <index level1="family size" level2="class-based"/>
        <index level1="free speech and free press"/>
        <index level1="law-breaking and direct action"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="infant"/>
        <index level1="obscenity"/>
        <index level1="Scotland" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Woman Rebel, The" level2="suppression of"/>
        <index level1="Woman Rebel, The" level2="legal case"/>
        <index level1="working classes" level2="women and girls"/>
        <index level1="United States government" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="Post Office"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">HISTORY OF EDUCATION.</head>
            <p>It <del>would</del>
                <add>might</add> be surprising to me that in the year 1916 a woman who is a trained
                nurse and a mother, must be brought into this Court as a criminal and plead with you
                for her liberty,<add>because she</add> advances a subject of the greatest importance
                to womankind. Were I not acquainted with the long struggle education has had against
                the powers of government and the tyranny of Authority. As we look back to the past
                we find from the beginning of time governments persistently sought to stifle all new
                ideas as well as to suppress all attempts of their expression. We look back with
                horror at the persecution, champions of new ideas have endured at the hands of
                authority. Only thirty years ago <person reg="Besant, Annie">Annie Besant</person>
                was prosecuted in <place>England</place> for vindicating ideas of liberty and for
                publishing literature which was then deemed obscene. The results of her educative
                work were to give the English people <add>and the English Press</add> the utmost
                liberty for the free discussion of subjects which the <org
                    reg="United States Post Office">Post Office</org> authorities in this country
                deem to be <add>obscene</add>" <del>non-mailable matter.</del>" To what extent the
                right of the press is <add>now</add> recognized in England may be seen by the
                following extracts from the summing up of <del>immigrants</del>
                <add>idealists</add> caused a change in conditions here and a second battle took
                place for the freedom of religious expression and now to-day with our rapidly
                increasing commercial lives, with women out in the industrial field, standing side
                by side with their brothers in the world's work, a new demand has come forth for the
                freedom of moral discussion.</p>
            <p>The three events are epoch-making in the history of the moral progress of every
                country and you are indeed privileged men that you have the opportunity to be
                instrumental in saying <del>that</del>
                <add>whether</add> the <place reg="United States">United Statesof America</place>
                shall go on the map beside other civiliszd nations or whether it shall still lag
                behind in all moral issues as it has continuously done for the past fifty years.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">WOMAN AND MORALITY.</head>
            <p>The moral issue is mainly of greatest concern to women. For centuries woman has gone
                forth with man to till the fields, to feed and clothe the nation. She has shared
                with him the struggles and hardships of his efforts. She has sacrificed her life to
                populate the Earth. She has overdone her labors. She has entrusted Man with the
                wealth of her offspring. He has failed her. He has allowed <del>their</del>
                <add>her</add> children to die by the thousands in the social system he has
                constructed and maintains. Woman at last steps forward to demand that she have a
                word to say in her function of Motherhood and her first request is that woman cease
                to produce children in ignorance.</p>
            <p><del>For this</del>
                <add>Because</add> twentieth century sees woman emerge from the cave of ignorance
                into the light of knowledge. She demands that she shall have control over her own
                body; that she shall be a mother when she desires to be one, consciously and
                voluntarily. In order to do this she must have the knowledge to control birth. Man
                has seen fit to place the most sacred function of her body on a footing with
                pornography and he calls any education bearing upon it as "<q>Filthy, vile,
                    obscene</q>". Woman must undo that crime. She must raise Man's standards in this
                as she has done in the past to a still higher level and place the function of
                motherhood and its physiology where it rightly belongs. She can only do this through
                education. And this paper, the "<title type="journal">Woman Rebel</title>" was a
                pioneer attempt to give her that education.</p>
            <p>It has been said that the issue advocated in this paper is fifty years ahead of the
                times. But this I deny. Rather is it a few narrow-minded officials who are fifty
                years behind the times, for I have found that the great mass of people desire this
                    <del>education</del> knowledge, and it is only the existence of an anti-social
                law inspired by the late <person reg="Comstock, Anthony">Mr. Comstock</person> that
                is keeping them in ignorance. From all over this country letters have come to me
                from women in all departments of life's work, expressing their opinions that the
                knowledge to prevent conception is a great social necessity and is far removed from
                obscenity.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">DIFFERENCE IN INTERESTS.</head>
            <p>As a trained nurse and mother of three children I have reason to consider my views on
                this question far superior to those of the prosecution whose interest in this
                question are so removed from mine, for he is not concerned with the fifty thousand
                women who die each year from abortion in this country. He is not concerned with the
                150,000 abortions that occur each year. He is not concerned with the fact that 95%
                of them are performed on women of the working class; neither is he concerned with
                the tremendous number of babies who die each year before they are one year old. He
                is concerned only in winning a verdict in this case while my interests are prompted
                by the most piteous cry <del>of</del>the women of this country have ever
                uttered.</p>
            <p>What can Man know of the mental agony of carrying beneath one's heart a little life
                which every instinct tells the mother it cannot survive? Little can he know of the
                mental agony and fear of unwanted pregnancy. Why then should he dictate to her in a
                function which chiefly concerns her.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">CHARGES.</head>
            <p>The indictments charge me with publishing and circulating <add>indecent</add> obscene
                literature. What is the meaning <del>obscenity</del> of this word "<q>Obscene</q>"?
                The average <del>men and wo</del>citizen is not familiar with the definition given
                in law books but must rely upon the only available source, that is in dictionaries
                and encyclopedias. I refer you to a standard authority <title type="book">The
                    Encyclopedia Britannica</title> which <del>defines</del> says of
                    "<q>obscenity</q>":-</p>
            <p>"<q who="EB">The precise meaning of the word is decidedly ambiguous. It has been
                    defined as something offensive to modesty or decency or expressing or suggesting
                    unchaste or lustful ideas or being impure, indecent or lewd, or <del>tends</del>
                    tending to deprave and corrupt those whose minds <add>which</add> are open to
                    immoral influences.</q>"</p>
            <p><del>I deny the charge.</del> I deny that there is one word or sentence or article in
                any of these papers, which can be termed obscene or which in any way violates this
                law or the intent of this law. I have read Section 211 many times and by the wildest
                stretch of the imagination there is nothing from the pages of "<title type="journal"
                    >The Woman Rebel</title>" which in any way incites to passion or immorality. The
                law distinctly says that no one shall give any information to prevent conception or
                to produce abortion and nowhere in the columns of this paper has this information
                been given. The law does not prohibit a discussion of these questions, but that is
                what Mr. <person reg="Content, Harold A.">Content</person> wants you to believe. I
                advocate that the knowledge to prevent conception be placed in the hands of women. I
                advocate small families for <add>the</add> working <del>mothers</del> class mothers
                and have encouraged them not to have more children than they can feed, clothe and
                care for. Is this obscene? Why is it that I am indicted for advocating small
                families when others quite prominent in the world's affairs are allowed to go up and
                down the length of the land advocating large families. Certainly if the picture
                brought to <add>a</add> young girl's mind by telling her not to have <del>many</del>
                children is in any way inciting to immorality, what must it be to be told that it is
                her duty to have many children? Which is the most moral? Is it obscene
                    <add>indecent</add> to help educate people; to have a responsibility towards
                their actions and towards their offspring or is it not more obscene to keep them in
                ignorance, misery and poverty. This law does not say that one cannot advocate small
                    <add>families</add> and therefore nothing that has been read to you from the
                pages of "<title type="journal">The Woman Rebel</title>" violates that law.</p>
            <p>Is it moral for two adult people to bring children into the world knowing that there
                is no possible provision made for their survival? Is it moral to leave the welfare
                and health of your offspring to the charity of a few kindly and well-intentioned
                philanthropists or is it not the duty of two people to be responsible for
                    <del>and</del> the consequences of their acts, securing to the best of their
                ability all advantages for their children's development? Is this not the greatest
                moral step forward which the working people of this generation are desirous of
                taking. For it is a noted fact that as soon as a woman raises herself out of the
                lowest stages of poverty and ignorance <del>where the present system of society has
                    placed her</del>, her first step is to seek knowledge whereby she shall have
                control over the size of her family? Where can she go for this knowledge? She knows
                that the woman of the upper-class has this information, which she in her poverty
                cannot afford to pay for. Consequently she must bring forth children who either die
                in infancy <del>or</del> grow up to fill the reformatories jails and poor-houses,
                    <emph rend="underline">or she must resort to abortions</emph>! Abortions and
                their horrible consequences are unnecessary. The "<title type="journal">Woman
                    Rebel</title>" has said this and the District Attorney has chosen to call it
                    "<q>obscene</q>" <add>indecent</add>.</p>
            <p>I trust you do not feel that I would have the impertinence to go into a work of this
                kind without realizing the responsibility which the dissemination of such knowledge
                brings; without a thorough study of the question from all points of view. For the
                past four years I have studied this subject and visited <del>different
                    countries</del>
                <place>France</place>, <place reg="Netherlands, the">Holland</place>, England and
                    <place>Spain</place> where the subject is considered from the family, the moral,
                the individual and the racial point of view, and before I go any further I should
                like to give you a brief summary of my life's work and the conditions that I met
                with which made me study this question and has brought me here today.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"><add>intent</add></head>
            <p>For in bringing in a verdict it will not be enough for you to decide whether these
                papers are obscene in character but it will also be necessary to get at the intent.
                The prosecution in drawing up the indictment has used great cunning in carefully
                extracting parts of the paper which do not dwell on the bigness of the Cause. He has
                said that the intent was good but that the intent does not matter. I claim that the
                intent is a very vital part of this charge. I further claim that these indictments
                should never have been brought against me, and were those who are back of this
                prosecution really interested in the welfare of the people as they pretend to be,
                they would not be wasting your time here to-day and piling up <del>the</del>
                enormous costs <del>on the people's backs</del> by such proceedings. The intent is
                the very essence of the character of this paper. It may be defiant; it may be bold;
                it may be much that you do not approve of but <add><unclear>you do not want to
                        agree</unclear></add>. <del>the intent is certainly not obscene!</del>
                <add>The question you are to decide is-- Is it obscene?</add>
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">HISTORY.</head>
            <p>Far back in my early childhood days, my first impression of life was that large
                families and poverty went hand-in-hand. I was born and brought up in a small factory
                town in the western part of <place>New York</place> State. I was one of eleven
                children, so that I had some personal knowledge of the struggles and hardships which
                a large family endures. At the age of seventeen my mother died from the results of
                overwork and the strain of too-frequent child-bearing which left me with the care of
                four younger children to share the burdens with a lovely poetic Irish father.</p>
            <p>A few years later I entered a hospital to take up the profession of nursing. It is
                impossible for any<del>one</del>
                <add>woman</add> to go through a general training without realizing that <add>she
                    must revalue ideas of life--</add> 75% of the diseases of men and women are the
                results of their sex lives. This discovery decided me to specialize in women's
                diseases and I devoted myself to gynecological and obstetrical work. A few years of
                work in this special line gave me a still greater discovery, i.e. that knowledge to
                prevent conception was obtained and practiced among the women of wealth while the
                working women were kept in ignorance of this knowledge. I found that the women of
                wealth were able to have abortions performed if it became necessary and such care
                and attention was given them by the medical profession that seldom did a death occur
                among them. I found that the women of the working-class were as anxious to obtain
                this information as their sisters of wealth but that there were laws upon the
                statute book against imparting this information, and the medical profession was most
                religious in obeying the laws when the patient was a poor woman. I found that the
                women of the working-class had emphatic views on the crime of bringing children into
                the world to die of hunger and were willing to risk their lives through abortions
                rather than give birth to unwanted offspring. I found that 300,000 children die each
                year from poverty and neglect, while the parents remain in ignorance of the means of
                preventing 300,000 more from coming into the world to die the following year. I
                found that the children who toil in factories and mills all come from parents who
                average 9 living children. I found <del>that</del>
                <add>from</add> the records concerning the woman of the underworld; the so-called
                prostitute--that 85% of them come from parents who average 9 children. I found that
                the laws against imparting knowledge to prevent conception had forced women into the
                hands of filthy midwives and quack abortionists unless they would bear unwanted
                children, with the consequences that the deaths from abortions were almost wholly
                among women of the working-class. I found that no other country in the world has so
                large a number of abortionists nor so large a number of deaths resulting therefrom,
                as the United States of America, and that the quacks and abortionists were rolling
                in wealth while our law-makers were closing their virtuous eyes. What did I find
                that Society was doing to alter these conditions. I found that it was treating with
                the symptoms instead of the <del>disease</del>
                <add>causes</add>. They founded the <org>Little Mother Leagues</org>, Babies
                Nurseries, <org>Better Baby Leagues</org>, and hundreds of well-intentioned
                philanthropic and charitable organizations <del>are trying to</del>
                <add>tried to</add> cure a social cancer by burning off the top instead of getting
                at the root. These conditions I found resulting from ignorance and I decided to
                arouse the people of this country to these conditions and to put into action some
                means of removing them.</p>
            <p>Before doing this it was necessary to make a thorough study of the special question
                involved. Learning that this information can be obtained in every other civilized
                country in the world except the United States, I decided to go abroad to study it
                there.</p>
            <p>My first visit was to <place reg="Glasgow, Scotland">Glasgow</place> where I spent
                several weeks trying to find out what twenty years of municipal ownership had done
                for women and children. I was disappointed in finding that the benefits resulting
                from this system were for those who had few children; the model tenements owned by
                the municipality were constructed for families having not more than three children,
                while working people with more than this number were compelled to huddle in the
                surroundings of their industry. From here, disgusted and disappointed with these
                municipal reforms, I went to Holland, where I found that the Dutch women through the
                knowledge to prevent conception had done more for themselves and their children in
                one year than was done during the whole twenty years of municipal administration in
                Glasgow. I will not dwell upon the conditions I found there but suffice it to say
                that children are loved and cared for in Holland as perhaps in no other country in
                Europe because those who are born are desired and the knowledge of how to prevent
                births is given to all <add>married</add> women, or women old enough to be married,
                in clinics conducted by nurses <add>&amp; Doctors</add>.</p>
            <p>These conditions so impressed me that I was convinced that we in the United States
                cannot advance either morally or socially until we take up the study of the
                knowledge to control births. On my return to this country my desire was to inform
                women of the conditions which I had found. I wanted their opinions on the
                advisability of imparting this information. The best way to find out the opinions of
                people is through the Press. I issued this publication (<title type="journal">The
                    Woman Rebel</title>) to the thinking women of the working-class. The first issue
                was suppressed by the Postal Authorities. <del>Let us look again at the first
                    issue.</del> We find here two counts which show definitely that the discussion
                to prevent conception was the objection the censorship had to this issue. This was
                March and the May, July, September and October issues were in turn suppressed and
                confiscated by the <org reg="United States Post Office">Post Office</org>
                authorities in this <place reg="New York, NY">City</place>. <add>Alth'o the paper
                    was mailed as first class matter</add> all of the articles except the one on
                assassination (with which I shall deal later) are on the discussion of small
                families and the question for you to settle to-day is: Are the working women of
                America to have the use of the mails for the purpose of their moral education and in
                language they can understand; simple, plain, without technical covering, or if the
                mails are only for the use of special people with college or university diplomas.
                When <org reg="United States Congress">Congress</org> was authorized to establish
                post-offices it was never intended that it should pass judgement on the political,
                religious or moral opinions of the matter to be conveyed. It was intended to fetch
                and carry printed matter regardless of these opinions. If we concede this
                constitutional <del>guarantee</del>
                <add>right</add> to this institution we might as well concede the same right to the
                    <org>Interboro Rapid Transit Co.</org>, or any other company of public utility.
                There is little doubt that the law was never intended to interfere with serious
                discussions carried on with dignity <add>&amp; for a high purpose special
                    purpose</add> but was for the suppression of pornographic pictures and
                writings.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">RESULTS OF PUBLICATION.</head>
            <p>The publication of the "<title type="journal">Woman Rebel</title>" brought me
                    <del>an</del> enthusiastic support from prominent men and women throughout this
                country. It aroused physicians and educators alike to the necessity of Birth Control
                as a national issue and has brought to the notice of all social workers the
                much-neglected question of large families. (Articles have appeared in <title
                    type="journal">Harper's</title>, <title type="journal">The New Republic</title>,
                    <title type="journal">The N.Y. American</title> and the <title type="journal"
                    >Tribune</title>). <del>Those</del>
                <add>My</add> articles on Birth Control have received the approval and support of
                the most eminent authorities in <place reg="England">Great Britain</place>
                <add>as you may see by</add> the following communication signed by <person
                    reg="Wells, H. G.">H. G. Wells</person>, <person reg="Murray, Gilbert">Gilbert
                    Murray</person>, <person reg="Bennett, Arnold">Arnold Bennett</person>, <person
                    reg="Ames, Percy">Percy Ames</person>, <person reg="Carpenter, Edward">Edward
                    Carpenter</person>, <person reg="Ashwell, Lena">Lena Ashwell</person>, <person
                    reg="Stopes, Marie C.">Marie C. Stopes</person>, <person reg="Maude, Aylmer"
                    >Aylmer Maude</person> and <person reg="Archer, William">William
                Archer</person>, was forwarded to President <person reg="Wilson, Woodrow"
                    >Wilson</person> and reads as follows:-</p>
            <p rend="blockquote">"TO THE PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES, WHITE HOUSE, <place
                    reg="Washington, D.C.">WASH. D.C.</place></p>
            <p rend="blockquote">Sir:- We understand that Mrs <person reg="Sanger, Margaret"
                    >Margaret Sanger</person> is in danger of criminal prosecution for circulating a
                paper on birth control. We therefore beg to draw your attention to the fact that
                such work as that of Mrs Sanger's received appreciation and circulation in every
                civilised country except the United States of America, where it is still counted as
                a criminal offense.</p>
            <p rend="blockquote">We in England, passed a generation ago, through the phase of
                prohibiting the expressions of serious and disinterested opinion on a subject of
                such grave importance to humanity, and in our view, to suppress any such treatment
                of vital subjects is detrimental to human progress.</p>
            <p rend="blockqote">Hence, not only for the benefit of Mrs Sanger, but of humanity, we
                respectfully beg you to exert your powerful influence in the interests of free
                speech and the betterment of the race.</p>
            <p rend="blockquote">We beg to remain etc.</p>
            <p>Those who signed this communication have as you doubtless know, made a life-long
                study of Birth Control, and strongly endorse its practice for the benefit of the
                human race.</p>
            <p>I will now take up the article on Marriage which treats of a different subject. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">THE MARRIAGE BED.</head>
            <p><add>Gentleman what do we find here.</add></p>
            <p>There is nothing here which has a tendency to deprave. On the contrary the language
                and intent of this article show the highest moral purpose, for it is a protest
                against that form of sex-slavery which woman too often has to submit to in married
                life. It is a plea for love in wedlock as opposed to brute force. It appeals to man
                to develop the finer qualities of his sex-nature to <emph rend="underline"
                    >win</emph> the object of his affection instead of taking for granted that a
                wife's duty is to submit herself at all times to his needs.</p>
            <p>The fact that there are 85,000 divorces granted each year in the United States goes
                to prove that there is some discordant note in the marriage bond of today which
                needs serious discussion and investigation. In order to do this, as with birth
                control women must have a medium for their discussion.</p>
            <p>On the shelves of my library I have dozens of books dealing with <del>the</del>
                marriage problem in the language similar to that used in this article. All of these
                books pass through the U.S. mails and no action is taken against their publishers. I
                need only to mention <person reg="Shaw, George Bernard">G. Bernard Shaw</person>'s
                preface to his play "<title type="play">Getting Married</title>" <del>in which he
                    says that</del>
                <add>extracts which I will read giving the same ideas</add></p>
            <p>This book also is forwarded through the U.S. mails but the censorship does not dare
                attack so prominent an author.</p>
            <p><add><del>I submit</del> I deny that</add>
                <del>In</del> this article on "<title type="article">The Marriage Bed</title>" there
                is anything obscene, lewd or depraving. <add>The title may be obnoxious to some but
                    you must judge the article by its content &amp; I believe that the coarsest mind
                    could find nothing filthy vile obscene</add></p>
            <p>If the <org>United States Government</org> have indictments out for the Publishers of
                    <person reg="Phillips, Wendell">Wendell Phillips</person>
                <add>or <person reg="Roosevelt, Theodore">Roosevelt</person>'s</add> Books as well
                as three of the books mentioned above--then we might consider the justice of this
                accusation, but here again as with the subject of marriage, the petty officials of
                this city dare not attack or indict Publishers or Authors who are well known.</p>
            <p>Now, gentlemen, I have tried prove to you that the language of this Article is
                impartial, clear and cool, appealing to logic and the cold <del>day</del> light of
                reason and I trust you will agree with me that this is so, but I have not told you
                the reason why I published this Article on "<title type="article">The Defense of
                    Assassination</title>."</p>
            <p>When the March issue was suppressed, I wrote at once to the Post Master requesting
                him to inform me what Articles, words or sentences in the issue were objectionable,
                so that I could either alter them or have some guide by which I could be directed.
                His reply was curt and short, but I was no wiser than before. The next issue was
                suppressed and again I requested to be informed what was the special objection to
                the paper, and again the same unintelligent reply.</p>
            <p>I resolved then and there to bring the "nigger out of the wood pile" and to make the
                authorities cease suppressing and confiscating a publication without giving the
                reason and forced them to come out into the open and tell the public where they
                stand.</p>
            <p>I am glad to say this article did it, not because there is anything inciting either
                to murder or immorality at all, but because of the very word "Assassination". This
                indictment is based on a head line alone, for tho one does approve of an act,
                approval does not necessitate inciting others to approve. This man gives us his
                reasons WHY he approves or defends assassination and I claim he has a right to be
                heard.</p>
            <p>I am not going to go further into this defense, I am not going to "sum up" all the
                proof I have placed before you, I am going to conclude by asking you to try and look
                out upon the World with me, as I have tried to tell you what I have seen and to ask
                you to consider the Age, the century, this year 1916--the Country where we have the
                most advanced electrical devices and comforts and construction engineering--we are
                here in what is called the most advanced country in the world and yet within these
                walls in this same age and year here is a woman pleading with you, as if it was
                three hundred years ago. I ask you gentlemen to consider, as Justice <person
                    reg="Coleridge, Bernard John Seymour">Coleridge</person> says in his summing up
                in a case similar to this a year or so ago etc.</p>
            <p>Gentlemen, I have not dwelled upon the personal inconveniences that these indictments
                have caused me, I have not told you of the hardships, the financial outlay, the
                sacrifices, the separation from my children for over a year, the imprisonment of my
                husband and the death of my little girl which have been caused of these indictments,
                all which I lay at the door of the government which has caused me to be insulted,
                slandered and my name and work tainted with that foul
                        <del><supplied>stigma</supplied></del>
                <add><unclear>tag</unclear></add> "<q>OBSCENITY"</q>.</p>
            <p>I have not dwelt on these personal matters because I want you to consider my
                innocence from a impersonal view, but I cannot refrain from impressing you with the
                inconvenience and the hardships unless I can leave this room acquitted by you of
                these charges, which otherwise a life time cannot wipe from one's name and work.</p>
            <p>And in conclusion let us remind ourselves again of the Appeal to our forefathers by
                that worthy Veteran of liberty, <person reg="Paine, Thomas">Thos. Paine</person>
                when he said: "<q who="PAITH">O ye who love Mankind, ye who dare oppose not only the
                    tyranny but the tyrants stand forth. Liberty has been chased around the
                    globe--receive ye oh the captive, and let us here in United States prepare an
                    asylum fit for mankind.</q>"</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">DEFENSE OF ASSASSINATION.</head>
            <p>You have had this article read to you by the prosecution and must realize that it has
                been presented with great care and caution. The subject is <del>a</del>
                <add>no doubt a disagreeable</add> painful one but what connection this article has
                with obscenity it would take something more than a legal mind to grasp. Before I go
                any further with this matter I want to draw your attention to the editorial page of
                    "<title type="journal">The Woman Rebel</title>" where you will see printed a
                notice to the effect that "The Editor does not necessarily agree with all signed
                articles." I am not here today to defend the principle of assassination but I do
                come to defend the right of the <person reg="Thorpe, Herbert A.">author of this
                    article</person> to express his views in the press in this way. The article in
                question is an academic, scientific, <del>and</del> impartial and logical discussion
                on methods and tactics which may possibly arise in a given society for the removal
                of certain individuals who may have put themselves beyond the reach of
                constitutional law. There was no recommendation made here to slay or assassinate any
                special individual or tyrant and as this article was published over a year ago and
                no one has been assassinated as a result of reading this, I submit these facts bear
                out my contention and judgement that <add>it</add> is a pure academic defense,
                appealing to the intellect and reason and not to the <add>passions</add> emotions of
                my readers.</p>
            <p>(Inciting or Appealing to emotions.)</p>
            <p>Were I defending the principle of assassination I could mention hundreds of
                celebrated writers of moral and political economy who have argued the necessity of
                putting the law of nature in force against tyrants who have the power and desire to
                set themselves above all laws made for the welfare of the society in which they may
                live, but I am defending the freedom of the press <add>on this issue.</add> I could
                have brought here dozens of volumes from the best authorities; authorities whom no
                man in this court would decry, to support the necessity and propriety of putting
                tyrants to death if no other means <del>of</del> for their removal present
                themselves.</p>
            <p>All of these volumes <del>extracts from <add>some of them</add> which I shall
                    read,</del> are allowed to be sent through the U. S. mails and when you shall
                have heard the opinions of these writers, you gentlemen will, I am sure, acquit me
                of either malicious intent or of inciting to assassination. I was not the author of
                the article. The <del>article</del> author is a man whose scientific knowledge
                justifies an opinion which I, as editor and publisher, believing in the freedom of
                the press, had every reason to believe he had the right under our constitution to
                express.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"><add>Extracts from the Classics</add></head>
            <p> You can read again the article in question and I submit to you it is not one
                    <del>whit</del>
                <add>bit</add> more cruel or inciting to murder than the dozens and hundreds of
                articles written in our daily papers dealing <add>&amp; inciting to</add> with the
                war. I <add>further</add> submit this article is more moral and <add>would have a
                    better</add> effect upon a community than the sporting page of any daily paper.
                I wish to read you some extracts from the classics.</p>
            <p>I will begin with the philosophers of <place>Greece</place> and <place
                    reg="Rome, Italy">Rome</place>, whose opinions are supported by authorities from
                the <title type="book">Bible</title> and which, I trust, will fully exculpate me
                from the charge upon the record.</p>
            <p><person>Plato</person>, in his plan for a <title type="book">Republic</title> (a
                volume which may be purchased at <org>Brentano's</org> on Fifth Ave and sent through
                the U.S. Mails to your address for the sum of $2.00) says, in part:-</p>
            <p>"<q who="PLA">The longer a tyrant lives, the more tyrannical humor increases in him,
                    like those beasts who grow more vicious as they grow older.</q>" Again he says:-
                    "<q who="PLA">The ordinary course they took with tyrants in Greece was to
                    dispatch them secretly, if there was no opportunity of expelling them by
                    accusations before the citizens</q>".</p>
            <p><person>Aristotle</person> also says:-"<q who="ARI">Tyranny is against the law of
                    human society, in which human nature is preserved.</q>"</p>
            <p><person>Zenophon</person> says:-"<q who="ZEN">The Grecians would not allow murderers
                    to come into their temples yet in those very temples they erected statues to
                    those who killed tyrants thinking their deliverers fit companions for their
                    gods.</q></p>
            <p>Then there is that beautiful book on <gap extent="four words" reason="illegible"/>
                written by <gap extent="two words" reason="illegible"/> the great <unclear>scholar
                    and prophet</unclear> of freedom.</p>
            <p> Cicero, in extolling the assassination of <person reg="Julius Caesar"
                    >Caesar</person> says:-"<q who="CICMA">What act, O <name type="deity"
                        >Jupiter</name>, more glorious; more worthy of eternal memory hath been
                    done, not only in this city but in the whole world. All good men killed Caesar.
                    Some wanted capacity, some courage, others opportunity but none wanted the will
                    to do it.</q>"</p>
            <p><person>Tertullian</person>:- (who was one of the Fathers of the Church, says) "<q
                    who="TERQU">Against common enemies and those who are enemies of the
                    commonwealth, every man is a soldier.</q>"</p>
            <p><person>St. Augustine</person> says:- "<q who="AUG">Is it not incongruous that the
                    laws of Nature and society as well permit a man to kill a thief if he be found
                    breaking into his house at night and that a tyrant who is a common robber of
                    mankind, to whom nothing is sacred, and whom no law can bind, should be
                    considered inviolable.</q>"</p>
            <p>I will conclude with an approval of <del>tyrannists</del>assassination written by
                    <person reg="Roosevelt, Theodore">Theodore Roosevelt</person> in his "<title
                    type="book">Life of Cromwell</title>" published by <add>Scribner &amp;
                Son</add>Quote. . . . . </p>
            <p>The article I have published, gentlemen, you will observe does not
                    <del>necessarily</del>
                <add>so emphatically or enthusiastically</add>approve of assassination, as Mr.
                Roosevelt's <del>quotation</del> does. In the <title type="journal">Woman
                    Rebel</title> the Article deals with the question in an impartial way, viewing
                it from both the moral and biological standpoints. About a third of the article
                consists of a quotation from <person reg="Phillips, Wendell">Wendell
                    Phillips</person> and the remainder deals with the subject in the general way I
                have described to you.</p>
            <p><add> If the <place reg="United States">U.S.</place> govt have indictments out for the publishers of Wendell Phillips
                    &amp; Theodore Roosevelt's books as well as Those of the books mentioned
                    above--then we might consider the justice of this accusation.</add></p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
