<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Autograph draft article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2003/05/27 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/20 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007/06/14 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-07 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/03/20 EK proof</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1915-04-00">
            <supplied resp="MSPP">Apr-Sept 1915</supplied>, p. 145 </docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Opinions of American Women in Europe</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp143711</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
            <bibl>LCM 130:427</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp id="MSPP">MSPP</resp>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="Europe" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="Europe" level2="travel in"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level3="exile, 1914-15"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="freedom and rights of"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="gender roles"/>
        <index level1="Netherlands, the" level2="women in"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="women in"/>"
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Opinions of American Women in <place>Europe</place></head>
        <p>It was four oclock <del>on</del>
            <add>of</add> an April morning <del>on</del> as the train from <place
                reg="Paris, France">Paris</place> pulled into <place reg="Cebère, France"
                >Sebere</place>
            <del>in the south</del> that station in the south of <place>France</place> where the
            French Police view with caution &amp; mistrust all passengers going over the border into
                <place>Spain</place>. "<q who="UNK">Sebere</q>" shouted the guard--"<q who="UNK"
                >Passaportes--show all passports</q>" shouted an official following closely behind
            him!</p>
        <p>If any of you who read these words &amp;<del> hear that word "passport"</del> have
                <del>been</del>
            <add>traveled</add> in Europe since this war began--you will <add>sympathize &amp;</add>
            understand <del>with</del> me and the confusion &amp; hysterical emotions that word
            "passport" <del>caused</del>
            <add>aroused</add> in me. I had been asleep since I had left <place
                reg="Perpignan, France">Perpiginnon</place> where I had had to go to get my passport
            vized by the Prefecture of Police before I could leave French soil. I had arrived at
            this same station Sebere at this same time the preceding morning at four oclock &amp;
            not having the required documents I was made to descend &amp; after a confused &amp;
            excited discussion in a language neither French or Spanish--the train moved out of the
            station leaving me &amp; my baggage a very desolate but wiser person.</p>
        <p>After great difficulty of several interviews with various officials I made it out that my
            passport had to have another signature and Perpignon was the nearest station where this
            could be done. I therefore took my bags &amp; baggage &amp; wandered my weary &amp;
            sleepy way back to Perpignon at 5 am just in time to see the beauty of the Pyrennese in
            early dawn &amp; with the rising sun my first glimpse of the Mediterrenean with its
            wonderful magic waters of blue repaid me in pleasure for all the trouble I had been put
            to my the stupidity of the French police.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless I had no intention to repeat the operation and I had telegraphed my friends
            in Spain "live or die sink or swim Ill be in <place reg="Barcelona, Spain"
                >Barcelona</place> the next day".</p>
        <p>I had finally after a days delay secured the necessary signatures &amp; paid the
            exorbitant prices for same, had boarded the train with a light heart and my
            passports--three of them clutched tightly in my hand. There were four other people in
            the compartment, but I managed to squeeze out enough room to curl <del>up</del> myself
            up and go to sleep.</p>
        <p>I awakened with a start <del>to</del>
            <add>on</add> hearing the word "<q who="UNK">Sebere passports</q>" &amp; found the
            police in the compartment already examining those of my fellow passengers. I looked in
            my bag where I had always carried the passport for mine but it was not there--the
            knowledge of this &amp; the shock threw me into such a state of confusion. I began to
            turn everything upside down-- It was only a minute when my turn had come &amp; the
            officer stood waiting for me to present the document which would allow me to
                <del>leave</del> enter Spain.</p>
        <p>I spoke to him &amp; said "I have a passport all signed but I can not find it go on to
            the others &amp; when you return Ill have it."</p>
        <p>He did so but as they have several officers at the work he was back in no time &amp;
            demanded my passport so the order could be given for the train to move on.</p>
        <p>I looked in my small hand bag--it was not there, I looked in my valise--not there--I
            looked in my hat box-- I knew it was not there--and the officer stood sarcastically
            smiling down on me &amp; said "<q who="UNK">Have you a trunk madam perhaps its in
                there</q>". This remark only confused me more &amp; I began turning things out
                <del>in</del>
            <add>on</add> the seat, papers, books &amp; pamphlets of all description &amp; kinds
            were scattered over the compartment while <del>my</del> the passengers gazed on with
            great sympathy.</p>
        <p>At last another officer appeared &amp; consulted together then said "<q who="UNK">madam
                we can not wait any longer for you, you will please get off the train so we can
                    <del>get</del> move on.</q>"</p>
        <p>"No Ill not" I answered "Ill not get off this train. Move on your train &amp; Ill have my
            passport before the train reaches <place reg="Port Bou, Spain">Por Boa</place> and if I
            do not find it by that time Ill of course get off but not now."</p>
        <p>At this defiance of his plea he blew a whistle shrill &amp; loud, at which five great big
            men came running to the car. He spoke to these in Catalan &amp; the biggest of the
            five--stepped up in the car &amp; threw open the door to make me understand I must get
            off.</p>
        <p>I kept right on talking to them in English, which I knew they did not understand so
            finally they called one of the passengers in another car to translate their decision to
            me--that I must get off at once. The train was already late on my account &amp; these
            people wanted to catch the Barcelona Express at Par Bou "So do I" I exclaimed. "Why
            don't they move on Ill find the passport in a few minutes but Ill not get off this train
            alive--and it won't be well for any one to put a hand on me to put me off." I stood up
            facing the big burly one with his long black cape thrown across his shoulders &amp; I
            saw him make an attempt forward as if to touch me--when the translator who was a young
            Spanish student stepped in front of me &amp; said to the officer.</p>
        <p>"<q who="UNK">Theres no use in doing that. She'll do as she says, she's an American woman
                &amp; she'll never come down. You had <del>better</del>
                <add>best</add> move on.</q>"</p>
        <p>The officers <del>all</del>
            <add>silently</add> left the car &amp; the train moved slowly out of Sebere
                <del>&amp;</del>
            <add>while</add> I began to look for my passport, which I found immediately to the great
            joy of all the sympathetic passengers who shook hands with me saying "Its only
                <add>the</add> American woman who can act like that--they're always right." I was
            greatly amused at this, but found there was a general opinion among European men that
            American women are "fearless &amp; have a mind of their own." In most of the Latin
            countries all English speaking women are spoken of as "English ladies" and <del>if</del>
            even when you stop to explain that you are not English but an American. The Latin shrugs
            his shoulder as much as to say--whats the difference?</p>
        <p>In <place reg="Netherlands, the">Holland</place> while waiting in <place
                reg="Amsterdam, Netherlands, the">Amsterdam</place> for the blockade to cease across
            the channel I spent several evenings with Dutch, English &amp; German <del>
                <unclear>illegible</unclear>
            </del> men <del>playing billiards</del> conversing on the usual topic, the war. One
            evening I was invited to play a <add>game</add> billiards &amp; accepted the invitation
            as naturally as I would accept an invitation to enter a game of whist. After the game a
            conversation followed in which several views were expressed on women of all countries,
            &amp; the <add>American</add> woman <del>question</del> in particular.</p>
        <p>The Dutch man said that in Holland an American woman can do anything &amp; be respected.
            She minds her own business &amp; pays her bills-- If she is seen on the streets late at
            night alone everyone <del>thinks</del>
            <add>knows</add> she has business which keeps her out &amp; her action is not
            misunderstood. It is not the same with a Dutch woman--no respectable Dutch woman is seen
            alone on the streets at night. No <add>Dutch</add> woman in Holland could play billiards
            in that room tonight without being molested or insulted later on--while the fact that an
            American woman does it makes it all right.</p>
        <p>Then the Englishman spoke and said that that is just what the American woman has done for
            the women of Europe. She has pioneered a way on the continent quite alone. She has come
            over here in her summer vacation, travelling either one woman alone or two or three
            together, you find her in all kinds of out of the way &amp; often questionable places
            but you need only look into her face to find <del>your</del> an answer to what she is
            doing there.</p>
        <p>She has done a great deal for Europe in the last twenty years. In France especialy is
            this noticeable. While in England it is a most common sight to see the most respectable
            women smoke cigarettes in all fashionable restaurants &amp; Hotels just like <place
                reg="United States">America</place>-- "America"? I gasped "<q who="SANMA">"Do you
                think women smoke in fashionable restaurants &amp; hotels in America? Your quite
                mistaken gentlemen. It's only a few of the very bravest who dare defy conventions to
                such a degree-- Someone tries it occasionally &amp; is requested by the waiter to
                stop-- 'ladies' are not supposed to smoke in America! So they have that freedom
                which they are credited with giving to others, to gain for themselves.</q>"</p>
        <p>This seemed to be a "shocking" surprise to them all but the German, who considered it "<q
                who="UNK">not nice</q>" for women to smoke, and said he found the American woman "<q
                who="UNK">too bossy</q>"--<q who="UNK">"Why you can always tell an American couple
                in Europe--the woman leads the way, she does all the talking &amp; ordering while
                the man trails on behind her &amp; <add>silently</add> pays the bills.</q>"</p>
        <p>"<q who="SANMA">I must have seen him when he was on his good behaviour"</q> I suggested.
                "<q who="SANMA">For at home he is not so silent about paying the bills.</q>"</p>
        <p>"<q who="UNK">Nevertheless</q>" said the Dutchman "<q who="UNK">she is the best dressed
                woman in the world</q>." "<q who="SANMA">What</q>" said I "<q who="SANMA">What about
                the Parisian woman?</q>"</p>
        <p>"<q who="UNK">I except none</q>" said the Dutchman decidedly.</p>
        <p>"<q who="UNK">I have been over half the globe I have paid particular attention to
                foreigners, their news, their customs their education their tastes and I have
                    <del>long</del> been convinced that today the Parisian woman has had to take a
                back seat with the American woman in regard to clothes &amp; fashions.</q>" </p>
        <p>"<q who="UNK">It is true the Americans may buy their gowns in Paris, but the American
            women wear them while the French woman designs &amp; makes them for her to wear. <del>Why look</del> The French woman is neat &amp; trim &amp; jaunty but it takes a
                woman of wealth in France to be in fashion while in <place reg="New York, NY">New
                    York</place> the same ultra fashion is copied &amp; reproduced in cheaper
                qualities so that every shop girl in New York wears what only the wealthiest lady of
                fashion in Paris can afford.</q>"</p>
        <p>The German was deep in thought all during this with his chin resting on his hand he became
            aroused by the striking of the clock &amp; said-- "<q who="UNK">my brother who has long
                lived in America says the woman there is the head of the house, that she manages
                all, her word is law. Is this true</q>"? He seemed greatly disturbed over this and I
            was about to answer but the Englishman answered instead.</p>
        <p>"<q who="UNK">Of course she is</q>" he said "<q who="UNK">because she's far superior, why
                the American <del>men have</del><add>man has</add> nothing in common with the women
                there. They are coarse, blunt, rude, while the woman is finely sensitive,
                    <del>decided</del>, exquisite &amp; courteous. The man has nothing to give her
                but his money, he comes home at night &amp; talks business, introduces into his home
                only friends who will help him in his business &amp; when his wife talks of music,
                art or literature, he falls asleep &amp; snores.</q>"</p>
        <p>At this we all laughed &amp; arose to part, but the Englishman had not finished.</p>
        <p>"<q who="UNK">The American woman is quite a different species to the American man, thats
                why she brings her fortune into Europe for a husband. She finds her equal in the
                French, the Italian the Spanish but particularly in the English, for every
                Englishman is a gentleman while every American woman is a
                'lady'</q>."</p>
        <p><del>Later that night</del>It was past midnight that night as I sat looking
                <del>down</del> from my window down into the lighted streets below that I renewed in
            my thoughts the various opinions expressed by the three men <del>of</del>
            <add>on</add> American women. My thoughts travelled back again to Sebere--to the Spaniards
            opinion who said "<q>She means what she says she's an American woman, she'll never come
                down</q>." It was strange that in Spain where she has traveled less their opinion of
            her is the strongest. And I think I like it best of all.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
