<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011-07-21 NC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-25 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1941-10-16">16 Oct 1941</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>On the 25th Anniversary of the Brownsville Clinic</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp143785</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Library of Congress Microfilm</title> 130:0767</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="WELHG">Wells, H. G.</name>
            <name id="HUGVI">Hugo, Victor</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger</person> gave this speech on
            October 16, 1941 at the <org>Hotel Roosevelt</org> to commemorate the 25th Anniversary
            of the <org>Brownsville Birth Control Clinic</org> in <place reg="Brooklyn, NY"
                >Brooklyn, New York</place>. An excerpt of this speech can be found in the article
                "<title type="article">Birth Control and Civil Liberties</title>" which appeared in
            the <title type="journal">Churchman</title>. This article also includes excerpts from
            the speeches of Canon <person reg="Trowbridge, Cornelius P.">Cornelius P.
                Trowbridge</person> and <person reg="Fernsworth, Lawrence">Lawrence
                Fernsworth</person> who also spoke that night. For draft versions see S72:0285,
            0287, 0289, 0301, 0308, and 0317.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="American"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="history of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="goals and strategies"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <p>On October 16, 1916, a gray day with overcast skies, the first birth control clinic was
            started in Brownsville, Brooklyn. Its purpose was to test the <place>New York</place>
            State law, and to free mothers from the slavery of ignorance and fear. This clinic also
            marked the first effort to place this subject in medical and public health channels, and
            to give it the scientific approach which it emphatically deserved and must have.</p>
        <p>Twenty-five years ago there was no organization and no organized public opinion behind
            this idea. To the ignorance of the general public was added the wilful effort of our
            opponents to confuse the issue through misrepresentation <del>of the meaning</del> of
            the meaning of the term “birth control”. There was sarcasm from the public press,
            opposition from religious groups, and criticism from the medical profession. One must
            remember that there existed no scientific data in <place reg="United States"
                >America</place> from which to draw conclusions and prove our facts. There were no
            books, no literature, on the subject. There were no adequate methods available in the
            United States to guarantee a certain percentage of success. Medical magazines scarcely
            dealt with any phase, not even the medical aspects of the subject. Most difficult of all
            was the legal opposition, both State and Federal, which represented the barbed wire
            entanglements that had to be cleared from our path.</p>
        <p>What then gave us the faith and strength to carry on? Only our (tormenting) knowledge of
            the needless waste of life and misery that women everywhere were enduring. We who worked
            closely with these mothers, especially the sick, the poor, the indigent, we know the
            facts. We know the infant death rate was terribly high and the maternal death rate also
            shamefully high. Records of that period revealed that over 2 million women were
            terminating their pregnancies illegally because they did not know how to prevent them.
            Thousands of these mothers died. Thousands more became invalids. Out of this single fact
            the birth control movement sprang into life.</p>
        <p>We advocated birth control to enable mothers to space the births of their children to
            safeguard their own lives and health. We advocated it to save the lives of babies; to
            raise the standard of child life and childhood; to make parenthood a conscious
            responsibility-- with children wanted before they are conceived-- with no unwanted
            children born who all too often become a burden upon the community. We maintained that
            no mother should be forced through ignorance to bring a crippled, defective or sickly
            child into the world, and that parents should have the right to determine the size of
            their family according to the family income and the earning capacity of the father.</p>
        <p>The Brownsville clinic attempted to <del>put</del>
            <add>translate</add> these ideas into practical service. Previous to its opening, a
            little group of us had little leaflets printed which we slipped into the mailboxes of
            that crowded, poverty-stricken community. They read; in English, Yiddish and
            Italian:</p>
        <p>Can you afford to have a large family?</p>
        <p>Do you want any more children?</p>
        <p>If not, why do you have them?</p>
        <p><emph rend="underline">Do not kill; do not take life</emph>, but <emph rend="underline"
                >prevent</emph></p>
        <p>Safe harmless information can be obtained of trained nurses at 46 Amboy Street</p>
        <p>From these circulars 450 mothers came to Amboy St. within the next few days, with a new
            hope in their hearts. This army of women, assembling in a single block, with baby
            carriages and babies in their arms could not help but attract the attention of the
            police. As a result, despair soon replaced hope among these women, as 9 days after it
            opened its doors, the clinic was closed by the police. And this first American clinic,
            which in <place reg="Netherlands">Holland</place> would have been honored as a great
            public utility, was described in the Brooklyn court order which closed it as “a public
            nuisance”!</p>
        <p>But we refused to accept this verdict without a fight. We challenged the decision and
            carried the case to the <org reg="New York State Supreme Court">Supreme Court of New
                York State</org>, with the result that in 1918 a decision was handed down which
            broke through the wall of legal confusion surrounding the birth control movement. It
            clarified and established the <add>legal and medical</add> right of doctors in this
            Empire State to give contraceptive information “for the cure or prevention of
            disease”.</p>
        <p>While this decision was rendered in 1918, we had to wait almost 5 years, from 1918 to
            1923, before we were able to find a physician who would stand beside us in
            re-establishing a practical program of service, from which we could build up a
            scientific background of medical case histories that would prove even to the most
            skeptical the importance of birth control in saving lives and promoting public
            welfare.</p>
        <p>We now have the medical data. Our clinical methods have been tested by competent medical
            and scientific authorities. We have the records of nearly 100,000 patients at one center
            alone, plus the records of more than 600 other birth control centers, to support out
            claims. We know today what birth control will do; what it has done; and what it can do.
            We know that it has saved countless lives of mothers and children. We know that we have
            helped to keep intact the respect and affection and love of parents for each other
                <add>[</add>a necessary factor in happy marriages and permanent homes<add>]</add>
            <add>, we know we have helped to strengthen family life</add>. </p>
        <p>We can look back over these 25 years with a grateful heart that the vision we had in 1914
            has remained steadfast throughout the years. It has not been influenced by this or that
            group to change its course. It has not made the mistake of aligning itself with those
            advocating this or that panacea. It has steadily clung to its original program which had
            two major objectives:</p>
        <p rend="blockquote">1. That every woman, rich or poor, regardless of race of creed, should
            be entitled to harmless scientific knowledge that would make planned parenthood
            possible.</p>
        <p rend="blockquote">2. That she should receive such information only from those medically
            qualified to give it.</p>
        <p>While we <gap extent="one word" reason="illegible"/> that there are over 600 centers now,
            this is not enough to take care of our 32 (?) million mothers of childbearing age in
            this country. Birth control is not and cannot be a thing apart. It must be recognized as
            an important factor by all health and social welfare organizations dealing with the
            human family and its problems. It belongs as a part of every pre-natal and post-natal
            program, in every hospital, in every public health service for mothers, in the cities,
            counties and states of this nation.</p>
        <p>Birth control is today recognized as one of the most revolutionary ideas of the century.
            It does not mean to limit families to one child or two children, but it does mean to
            have only the number of children that can be raised with due consideration for the
            mother’s health, the father’s income, and decent standards of living. It does not meant
            to take life or to interfere with the development of life, for by preventing conception
            there is no life to destroy. </p>
        <p>Properly taught, and made equally available to all classes, birth control will balance
            our differential birth rate as it did in Holland and as it is doing in
                <place>Sweden</place> and other countries today. It is only in countries where such
            information is available to the intelligent and well-to-do but denied to the poor and
            indigent that we see this dysgenic unbalanced birth rate, so deplorable as well as
            dangerous to the future of our country and its defense. This unhappy situation we lay
            straight at the doors of the opponents of this movement who use their political
            influence to intimidate public officials and prevent them from doing their duty.</p>
        <p>In closing it is pertinent on this occasion to refer briefly to the statement of
            President <person reg="Roosevelt, Franklin D.">Roosevelt</person>, following the
            Conference on the high seases between himself and Prime Minister <person
                reg="Churchill, Winston">Churchill</person> in which he set forth the four (?)
            freedoms for which nations must fight:</p>
        <p rend="blockquote">Freedom of speech and expressions everywhere in the world-- page Lt.
            Gov. <person reg="Poletti, Charles">Mr. Poletti</person>, please!</p>
        <p rend="blockquote">Freedom from want-- everywhere in the world. Freedom from being
            unwanted here in the United States. This would solve a lot of our future problems--and
            if followed everywhere in the world would certainly lay the foundations for world peace. </p>
        <p rend="blockquote">Freedom from fear-- At last the world is waking up to the agony of
            fear-- a agony suffered by women for centuries-- fear hanging over their lives like a
            sword, fear, day after day, month after months, fear from year to year. Freedom from
            fear-- for women everywhere in the world.</p>
        <p><person reg="Huxley, Julian">Julian Huxley</person> has stated that birth control will go
            down in history as one of the great achievements of the human intellect, that it will
            class with those great advances, such as the invention (?) <add>making</add> of the
                <add>first</add> stone hammer, the discovery of electricity and the use of the
            printing press.</p>
        <p>It is indeed an honor and a privilege to have had on our side from the beginning of the
            movement some of the greatest intellects of the English-speaking world, but we who have
            had the historic privilege of leadership in this movement, cannot be content or
            satisfied by the achievements of the past. There is a grave responsibility still
            remaining to guide this movement into those channels where the greatest good will come
            to the greatest number. We must stay on the battlefield to hold what we have gained; we
            must continue to carry our banners high until the ideals they proclaim shall have become
            firmly established in practice in our civilization. <add>words</add> May I close with a
            message just received in a cable from Mr. <person reg="Wells, H. G.">H. G.
                Wells</person>:</p>
        <p>(quote)</p>
        <p>It is pertinent to quote here a message just received by cable from Mr. H.G. Wells.</p>
        <p>“<q who="WELHG">The Birth Control Movement has revolutionized human life. It has
                emancipated men and women alike from involuntary animal parentage. Women can not
                possess their own lives and be the willing and deliberate mothers of our renascent
                world.</q>”</p>
        <p>(possible last page?)</p>
        <p>Bit by bit we invaded the opponent’s territory. We threw light where there was darkness.
            We brought hope where there was resignation and despair. Through logic, reason,
            knowledge and factual evidence, condemnation, injustice, criticisms, arrests and
            persecution gave way. Through patience and more patience we have brought the intelligent
            forces of the English speaking world to support our cause. For as <person
                reg="Hugo, Victor">Victor Hugo</person> said: “<q who="HUGVI">There is no force in
                the world so great as that of an idea whose hour has struck.</q>” The hour had
            struck for women to free themselves from age long bondage. Now let us move forward to a
            new world with planned parenthood as its foundation.</p>
        <p>(another bit for insertion)</p>
        <p>We thank our enemies. . . Our opponents. . . for the good they have done to our cause.
            When in 1921 the <org>Town Hall</org> was closed by a <org reg="Roman Catholic Church"
                >religious organization</org> which
                <add>commandeered and gave its orders to</add> the Police force of <place
                reg="New York, NY">New York City</place>, the resulting protest enabled us to give
            the public a far clearer idea of what we were doing, and established that right shall
            triumph as long as a free press endures here.</p>


    </docBody>
</doc>
