<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2001-08-21 MH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2001-09-05 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2002-08-09 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2002-08-15 KH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2003/08/08 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/08/13 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-07 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1936-06-00">June 1936</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Planning Your Children</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp143717</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Voice of Youth</title>, June 1936, 1- 2</bibl>
            <bibl>LCM 130:473</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="FAIHE">Fairchild, Henry Pratt</name>
            <name id="USCE">United States Commissioner of Education</name>
            <name id="USCC">United States Criminal Code</name>
            <name id="CRAFR">Crane, Frederick Ewen</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
        <p>For other versions see <title>MSM</title> S71:0852, S71:0856.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="federal"
            level4="Comstock act"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="federal lobbying"/>
        <index level1="public health" level3="" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="parenthood" level2="MS on"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Planning Your Children</head>
        <byline>By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></byline>
        <p>PARENTHOOD, when it is responsible, can be a noble trust, a proud commission, an honored
            assignment. But this can be accomplished only by taking it out of the sphere of accident
            and placing it in the sphere of conscious responsibility.</p>
        <p>When this is done every child will be a wanted child, born to its rightful heritage of
            love, care, and comfort.</p>
        <p>Science has taught us how to take parenthood out of the sphere of accident, how to plan
            for the number of children in a family, and the intervals between their births. The idea
            that this should be done in accordance with the health of the mother and the income of
            the family seems obvious. But our adult world has been too dull, too timorous, and too
            bigoted to take advantage of this knowledge. We have hedged it in with taboos and legal
            restrictions; we are directly responsible for the present deplorable situation in which
            the well-to-do can secure birth control information, but the poor who need it most, are
            deprived of it.</p>
        <p>The Youth of <place reg="United States">America</place>, and of the world, however, gives
            evidence of viewing the matter more sanely, and more courageously. They apparently
            realize that birth control, the knowledge of how to make parenthood a responsible,
            voluntary trust, rather than a blind accident, is one of the most fundamental issues
            before the world today. It can make or mar a marriage. It can, I venture to say, help us
            solve our present tragic unemployment and relief problem, and it can profoundly affect
            international relations and world peace.</p>
        <p>"<q who="FAIHE">A century of stationary population,</q>" writes Professor <person
                reg="Fairchild, Henry Pratt">Henry Pratt Fairchilds</person> of <org>New York
                University</org>, "<q who="FAIHE">would do more to promote the cause of peace and
                prevent international wars than all the peace treaties and disarmament conventions
                that have ever been signed, or ever will be signed.</q>"</p>
        <p>One of the most significant indications of youth's interest in birth control comes from
            the office of the <org reg="United States Department of Education">U.S. Commissioner of
                Education</org>. In connection with a nation-wide <org>Public Forum</org> project, a
            conference of youth leadership, representing from one to one and a half million young
            people, was asked to vote on topics for forum discussion. The question "Should birth
            control information be permitted to be sent through the mails and disseminated through
            clinics?" was given second choice out of 115 topics and was placed first within its own
            category, Social Problems. Incidentally, economic problems were voted first place in the
            general divisions and social problems second.</p>
        <p>At present, as a result of laws passed in 1873 at the instigation of <person
                reg="Comstock, Anthony">Anthony Comstock</person>, "<q who="USC">the prevention of
                conception</q>" is classed with obscenity. The <name type="law">United States
                Criminal Codes</name> make it a serious crime, carrying a penalty of $5,000 or five
            years in prison or both, for anyone, even a physician to send through the mails or
            common carriers any information or article "<q who="USC">designed, adapted or
                intended</q>" to prevent conception. The situation is further complicated and
            rendered paradoxical by the fact that the laws of more than forty states permit
            physicians to prescribe contraception to their patients. But how, may I ask, can a
            doctor prescribe birth control if they are not permitted to receive data and
            supplies?</p>
        <p>The birth control bill now before <org reg="United States Congress">Congress</org>,
            introduced into the <org reg="United States Senate">Senate</org> by Senator <person
                reg="Copeland, Royal S.">Royal S. Copeland</person> of <place>New York</place>, and
            into the <org reg="United States House of Representatives">House</org> by Representative
                <person reg="Gassaway, Percy L.">Percy L. Gassaway</person> of
                <place>Oklahoma</place>, would permit the use of the mails and common carriers for
            sending contraceptive information and supplies only to the medical profession in states
            where physicians are already permitted to prescribe contraception.</p>
        <p>This seems little enough to ask. The number of men in Congress willing to support the
            bill has increased greatly, and this support is matched by ever increasing numbers of
            individuals and groups in the public at large. But the bill has not yet been enacted
            into law.</p>
        <p>In 1916 I opened a birth control clinic in <place reg="Brooklyn, NY">Brooklyn</place>,
            which was promptly closed as a "public nuisance." In 1923, following a test case and a
            decision permitting physicians to give birth control advice for the "<q who="CRAFR">cure
                and prevention of disease,</q>" the <org>Birth Control Clinical Research
                Bureau</org>, of which I am the director, was opened. It has functioned continuously
            since that time and is now the largest in the world as well as the oldest in America.
            Since then clinics have sprung up all over the country, until there are now
            approximately 250, taking care of poor mothers who cannot afford to go to private
            physicians.</p>
        <p>Splendid as is the work being done by these clinics, it is only a drop in the bucket
            compared with what needs to be done. Every hospital and dispensary in the land should
            have a birth control clinic. Birth control should be part of the public health work of
            the <org>United States government</org>. Every young mother, as part of her postnatal
            care, should be given scientific birth control advice in order that her next child need
            not come before she has fully regained her strength. Every newly married couple should
            have this advice so that they can plan their family, allowing, in general, some time to
            adapt themselves to each other before the coming of children.</p>
        <p>All this will be possible if the absurd law, placed on the statute books over fifty years
            ago is changed. The bills now before Congress, <name type="law">Senate bill No.
                4000</name> and <name type="law">House bill No. 11330</name>, should be passed.</p>
        <p>Some sort of birth control is being practiced everywhere today, and will continue to be
            practiced, for birth control is here to stay. You cannot get people to "unlearn" the
            knowledge that there is some way of planning families. America's youth has a right to
            ask their parents, teachers, doctors, ministers, and congressmen which is better;
            bootleg, uncertain and often harmful methods promoted by commercial concerns for profit,
            or scientific, harmless, efficient methods prescribed by physicians for the best
            interests of young married people and their children.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
