<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011-07-15 NC</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1944-06-20"><supplied resp="MSPP">20 Jun
            1944</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Marriage</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp157942</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
            <bibl><title>LCM</title>116:0667B</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><index level1="war" level2="marriage and"/><index
            level1="birth control" level2="war and"/><index level1="marriage"
        /></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <p>“<q who="UNK">Marriage is both a concession and a demand, and in
                order to thrive there must be constant thought for the other
                ‘partner’</q>”. To belong, to cooperate, mutual interest, a
            oneness. These are the means of defense against the peril of mental
            and psychic alienation in marriage. Any work, play, or endeavor
            which keeps two people close together will help keep mutual
            understanding fresh and active.</p>
        <p>Then too, considering that medical science has advanced beyond the
            physical manifestations of pain and anguish into the psychiatric --
            it behoves intelligent men and women to tackle the problems of
            marriage and love, to put intelligence, brain, and science to work
            fair and square and adjust accordingly. It can be done.</p>
        <p>A man with a physical handicap, a blind eye, a lost arm or leg, a
            patched up face, is likely to be more gentle and kind in his
            marriage than the man who suddenly finds himself impotent. His
            limitation causes resentment and in a blind rage he seeks relief in
            striking out, in accusation, in reproach and complaint of his
            beloved. His pride, his vanity are fighting for survival. This is a
            situation where the woman’s love and knowledge and infinite patience
            must endure and bridge the gap to his recovery.</p>
        <p>Usually this impotence is temporary but to him, who has been pent up
            for months, he sees the end, and becomes impatient, irritable,
            negligent, thoughtless, violent, unstable, easily exasperated.</p>
        <p>A change from military life to civilian life will not be as simple as
            just removing the uniform.</p>
        <p>The problem of preserving the happiness in marriage as it was before
            he went away.</p>
        <p>There may be mutual repulsion upon his return, or the honeymoon may
            have been one of blissful rapture and all too short -- you wait and
            wait for his return.</p>
        <p>By knowledge the girl may have revealed the manifold possibilities of
            achieving or recapturing or enhancing that happiness and not allow
            marriage to decline into a morass of disillusion, ending in
            divorce.</p>
        <p>Marriage cannot be confined to the sexual physiological factors
            alone. There are joys and griefs even in a happily married life.</p>
        <p>The living husband who went off to war may return and look upon his
            marriage with a certain serene detachment, too bitter for “follies”
            of youth and yet too young to forgo them all. It can be a hell of
            torment to the living partner who has waited and dreamed of a
            happily married future and finds herself grappling with shadows. A
            vigorous and harmonious sex attitude in marriage is indispensable to
            happiness. The loneliness of mind and heart to which this absence
            has confined him can be more devastating than all the brutality,
            waste and death he has witnessed.</p>
        <p>Women must also remember that the man who has entered the army has
            had to undergo a complete training to reverse the training given him
            as a boy and young man in his home -- by his parents and teachers.
            His training is not to hurt others or to needlessly kill animals or
            to fight -- all these aggressive urges have been repressed.</p>
        <p>Fear.</p>
        <p>Psychiatrists are now facing the problems in the army of men raised
            by parents and teachers no to hurt other people, and certainly not
            to kill animals or men -- except in self defense. These boys and men
            being placed where they had to kill soon became loaded with
            unexpressed feelings of remorse and guilt. Officials soon became
            aware of this conflict and had to break down the home or parents
            teachings and substitute for it a different education and attitude
            toward group experience -- so the re-education has taken place in
            him as army morale, but it cannot hold when he returns to civilian
            life and home and loved ones.</p>


    </docBody>
</doc>
