<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2007-08-30 ek</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2010-04-06 CH proof</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2010-04-07 AC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-21 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1934-06-13">13 Jun 1934</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Catholics and Birth Control </titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp158426</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
                <title type="journal">New Republic</title>, LXXIX:1019 (13 June 1934): 129</bibl>
            <bibl>Library of Congress Microfilm 134:354A</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>

    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>This letter was drafted for <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person> on
            May 8, 1934 by the editors of <title type="journal">New Republic</title> based on her
            14th Newsletter of the <org>National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth
                Control.</org> Sanger approved it for publication on May 10 and it was published
            under the heading "<title type="article">Catholics and Birth Control</title>" in the June 13, 1934 issue of the
                <title type="journal">New Republic</title>.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="safe period"/>
        <index level1="Catholic Church" level2="birth control and abortion and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="opposition to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="morality of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation"
            level3="Postal Code and Regulations"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>

        <p>SIR: The Catholic opponents of birth control are evidently unaware of the dissatisfaction
            among the intelligent men and women of their own faith regarding the attitude their
            Church has taken on birth control. To satisfy this element there was recently published
            a book called “<title type="book">Rhythm</title>,” loudly praised by Catholic prelates and press,
            which explains in detail, and to the hour, when conception <emph rend="italics"
                >cannot</emph> take place. Most of us have long ago discarded the safe-period theory
            as a method available for general application. This book, however, was written by a
            physician and is published with “Ecclesiastical Approbation,” which
            means that it has the approval of the <org>Roman Catholic Church</org>.</p>
        <p>Our opponents are evidently unaware of the contents of this book, for every argument they
            have ever used against contraception is supported in the book on behalf of the
            safe-period method. All the ballyhoo of “race suicide,” “the race dying out,”
            “immorality,” is answered by the author with fearless intelligence and in a spirit that
            one respects.</p>
        <p>On the general principles of limiting or controlling the size of the family-- on the
            needs, rights and morality of the practice, we seem to be in perfect agreement. <emph
                rend="italics">On methods we entirely disagree</emph>. The Catholic opponents
            advocate a safe period. The non-Catholic proponents desire to place all responsibility
            concerning methods in the hands of the medical profession.</p>
        <p>The federal laws, however, state clearly that “<emph rend="italics">any</emph>”
            information to prevent conception sent through the United States Mails is illegal. The
            Post Office has informed us that “<title type="book">Rhythm</title>” by <person reg="Latz, Leo">Dr.
                Latz</person> is mailable, but that "<title type="book">Contraceptive Practices</title>,” by
                <person reg="Stone, Hannah Mayer">Dr. Hannah M. Stone</person>, is unmailable. </p>
        <p>The twenty million members of the Catholic faith now have a method of Birth Control
            legally sanctioned by the <org reg="United States Post Office">Post Office</org> authorities and
            morally sanctioned by the hierarchy. But what about the one hundred and four millions of
            non-Catholics who prefer <emph rend="italics">other</emph> methods of birth control or
            who do not think the safe period is safe?</p>
        <dateline>
            <place reg="Washington, DC">Washington, D. C.</place>
        </dateline>
        <byline>MARGARET SANGER.</byline>
    </docBody>
</doc>
