<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2012-03-27 AW</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2012-03-28 AW</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-04 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1959-07-21">21 July 1959</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Eulogy for Abraham Stone, M.D.</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp203671</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S72:0985</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="Stone, Abraham"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head rend="underline">ABRAHAM STONE, M.D., 1891-1959</head>
        <p>The extent of the shock and grief we feel at the sudden passing of our co-worker, Dr.
                <person reg="Stone, Abraham">Abraham Stone</person>, cannot be told in writing. He
            came early into the Birth Control Movement, accompanying his wife, Dr. <person
                reg="Stone, Hannah Mayer">Hannah Stone</person>, whom I met in 1921, and who became
            the second medical doctor serving in my <org
                reg="Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau">Clinic</org> in <place
                reg="New York, NY">New York</place> in 1924. Through the years from that time, Dr.
            Stone developed from a specialist in urology to become an outstanding teacher and leader
            in family counseling and birth control throughout the world.</p>
        <p>As we all know, he was an indefatigable traveler in the interest of our cause, and his
            work in so many countries will be sorely missed. He achieved a successful and happy
            professional and personal life, even though it was cut short so suddenly. He was founder
            and President of the <org>American Association of Marriage Counselors</org>, Special
            Consultant to the <org>World Health Organization</org> on Family Planning, a member of
            the General Council of the <org>International Union of Family Organizations</org>, and
            Vice-Chairman of the Council of the <org
                rend="International Planned Parenthood Foundation">IPPF</org>.</p>
        <p>He received the <name type="award">Lasker Award</name> for <name>Planned
                Parenthood</name> in <place reg="United States">America</place> in 1947. His
            writings for professional publications and popular periodicals were numerous. He wrote
            extensively and fluently on birth control and family planning, as well as about marriage
            counseling, and at his death was writing his autobiography. A naturalized citizen of the
            United States, Dr. Stone was born in <place>Russia</place> in 1891 and came to this
            country in 1905 where he obtained his medical education in New York. During his studies
            he met a bacteriologist, Hannah Mayer, a beautiful woman with a face and head sculptors
            and painters look for, who became his wife. After their marriage, he served in World War
            I as a Lieutenant in the <org reg="United States Army Medical Corps">Army Medical
                corps</org>, during which time his wife became a medical doctor. Their only child,
            who survives with three grandchildren, is <person reg="Aitken, Gloria Stone"
                >Gloria</person>, a pediatrician, married to a physician, Dr. <person
                reg="Aitken, Gerard">Gerard Aitken</person>, of <place reg="Bound Brook, NJ">Bound
                Brook, New Jersey</place>.</p>
        <p> Dr. Stone is a member of many professional organizations, including the <org>American
                Medical Association</org>, the <org>New York Academy of Medicine</org>, and <unclear
                resp="MSPP">was</unclear> a Fellow of the <org>American Society for the Study of
                Sterility</org>. He had been an instructor of urology in the <org>New York Post
                Graduate Medic School and Hospital</org> early in his career. At his death he was
            Associate Clinical Professor of Preventive Medicine at the <org>New York University
                Bellevue College of Medicine</org>, and a member of the Faculty of the <org>New
                School for Social Research</org>.</p>
        <p>The scope of his work and recognition in the world is large indeed, but not so large as
            the great personal friendships he inspired in every country he visited. We will miss
            Abraham Stone deeply and forever.</p>
        <byline><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></byline>
    </docBody>
</doc>
