<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2003-10-23 amc</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/01 CH</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1925-08-00">Aug 1925</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>One Week's Activity in England</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp205948</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>The Birth Control Review</title>, August 1925, 219-20</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title>S71:30</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="DAWBE">Lord Bertrand E. Dawson</name>
            <name id="THOAL">Alexander Thompson</name>
            <name id="QUI">Miss Quinn</name>
            <name id="SOCFR">Society of Friends</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="birth control" level2="medically controlled"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods and devices" level3="continence"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="opposition to"/>
        <index level1="Catholic Church" level2="birth control and abortion and" level3="in England"/>
        <index level1="Church of England" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="England" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="National Conference of Labor Women (England, 1925)"/>
        <index level1="National Council of Public Morals (1925, England)"/>
        <index level1="Quakers (Society of Friends)" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="Royal Institute of Public Health (England)"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>ONE WEEK'S ACTIVITY IN ENGLAND</head>
        <div>
            <p>Inspiring reports come to us from <place>England</place> indicating that Birth
                Control is now accepted, not merely by a small group, but by men and organizations
                exerting powerful influence, as a national problem to be faced and solved by the
                English people as a whole. The record of one week's activity, for instance, is most
                encouraging, illustrating as it does that the tireless and often unrewarded
                activities of our British comrades have been productive of the most fertile results.
                Birth Control has entered the national consciousness of England. The little seeds of
                thought sown by the Neo-Malthusians and Birth Control advocates have not fallen on
                sterile ground. The one week we speak of was the first in June. Let us summarize
                that crowded week of Birth Control activity:</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">I. At the Congress on Public Health</head>
            <p>The <org>Congress of the Royal Institute of Public Health</org> met in <place
                    reg="Brighton, England">Brighton</place>. One session was devoted to the
                question of Birth Control. The chair was taken by Mrs. <person>Cooper
                Rawson</person>, who in her opening speech urged the limitation of offspring, not
                alone on the ground of the danger to the nation but in the name of humanity. Our
                friend, Dr. <person>Norman Haire</person> developed this point of view in his
                quietly effective manner. But the supreme event of this Congress on Public Health
                was the sermon delivered to the delegates in the Brighton Parish Church by the
                Bishop of Birmingham (Dr. <person>E. W. Barnes</person>). I say supreme because this
                sermon, so outspokenly courageous, provoked a response from the Vicar of Brighton
                (Canon <person>F. C. D. Hicks</person>), expressing disagreement with the Bishop,
                and this incident stimulated a widespread and healthy discussion in the press. It
                evoked, especially from <person>Harold Cox</person> and <person>Alexander M.
                    Thompson</person> ("Dangle" of the <title>Sunday Chronicle</title>), eloquent
                and readable defences of the doctrine of Birth Control.</p>
            <p>If space permitted, we would reprint for the benefit of our readers all of these
                splendid utterances. We shall content ourselves with quoting on another page of the
                    <title reg="Birth Control Review">REVIEW</title>* a bit of Bishop Barnes'
                sermon, expressing with a fine sense of the ethics of Christ, the profound morality
                of contraception. Let us hope that the courageous example of Bishop Barnes may
                inspire influential American churchmen to similar unequivocal utterance on the
                subject of Birth Control.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">II. National Council of Public Morals</head>
            <p>Another event which stimulated discussion and nation-wide publicity was the report,
                (published on June second, the Tuesday following Bishop Barnes' sermon) of the
                special committee appointed by the <org>National Council of Public Morals</org>.
                Lord <person reg="Bertrand E. Dawson">Dawson </person> of Penn had submitted a
                report advocating its endorsement of contraception. After declaring that
                    "<soCalled>conception control</soCalled>" demands a much fuller investigation
                from the medical, economic and religious standpoints, the committee came to the
                amazingly sterile conclusion that "<q who="DAWBE">the ideal method of Birth Control
                    is self-control.</q>" "<q who="DAWBE">Such self-control must be agreed upon by
                    the husband and wife and carried out in a spirit of service and sacrifice....
                    The line of real advance lies in a deeper reverence, a return to a greater
                    simplicity of life, and, not least, a drastic reformation of our social and
                    economic conditions.</q>" </p>
            <p>The value of our movement is not in the report of this committee, but the replies it
                has stimulated by its impossibly stilted and absurdly fantastical conception of
                ordinary human nature. "<q who="THOAL">While they wait a hundred years or so for
                    that reformation,</q>" exclaimed Alexander Thompson, hitting "<soCalled>the nail
                    on the head</soCalled>" in the <title>Sunday Chronicle</title>, "<q who="THOAL"
                    >husband and wife... are to model themselves on St. Francis of Assisi, and
                    practise self-control in the spirit of service and sacrifice! Imagine it.... If
                    you think for one little moment of the conditions under which conjugal relations
                    are conducted in the <gap extent="word missing"/> sties of our big cities, you
                    will realize that one might as well hope to grow roses from the thistle down or
                    teach the earthworm to sing like the nightingale. My word! Think of it.
                    Continence, chastity, service, sacrifice, as the text of a heart-to-heart chat
                    with <person>Bill Sikes</person>!</q>"</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">III. National Conference of Labor Women</head>
            <p>Birth Control caused stormy scenes at the <org>National Conference of Labor
                Women</org> in <place reg="Birmingham, England">Birmingham</place>, held at the same
                time as the Brighton Congress on public health. A resolution had been introduced to
                the effect that physicians in public service should be permitted to give
                contraceptive information to married people who requested it. <person>Miss
                Quinn</person>, a Catholic delegate from <place reg="Leeds, England">Leeds</place>,
                protested against Birth Control being taken up by the Socialist movement. "<q
                    who="QUI">I represent thousands of working women... to whom this doctrine and
                    this insidious propaganda spells impurity. I protest with all the vehemence I
                    possess against the suggestion that working women want instructions in impure
                    and unchaste methods. It is a crime against God and humanity!</q>" </p>
            <p>It is reported that this speech provoked great dissension, and Miss <person>Ellen
                    Wilkinson</person>, M.P., the chairman, interposed that she had allowed Miss
                Quinn a good deal of latitude, but she would not allow her to insult the rest of the
                delegates. "<q who="QUI">I represent the sentiments of thousands of Catholic
                women,</q>" retorted Miss Quinn. Other women might hold different views, quite
                honestly, replied the chairman, and Miss Quinn should not impute impure motives to
                them. Bravo, Ellen Wilkinson, M.P.! </p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">IV. Quakers Approve of Birth Control</head>
            <p>This active week closed with another significant event–the publication by a committee
                of the <org>Society of Friends</org> of a pamphlet entitled "<title>Marriage and
                    Parenthood–the Problem of Birth Control.</title>" While this pamphlet does not
                bind the Society of Friends as a unity to our doctrine, it may be said to represent
                the enlightened attitude of the English society. </p>
            <p>"<q who="SOCFR">There can be no doubt that Friends, like others, have accepted the
                    idea of the small family,</q>" assert the signatories of this pamphlet. "<q
                    who="SOCFR">There must be many young couples who long to have children and yet
                    have no margin to meet the incidental cost of child-birth.</q>" Further: "<q
                    who="SOCFR">The method of complete abstinence does not seem to us to be
                    necessarily right for most married people. To lay down as a standard for all
                    married people a rule of life that can only be attained by a few is in itself an
                    error in moral direction.</q>"</p>
            <p>This expression is significant, indicating as it does without confusing the issue
                that the Society of Friends is brave enough, as all other Protestant bodies should
                be, to announce publicly its independence from the domination of the <org>Roman
                    Catholic Church</org> in this all-important problem, in that it refuses to rule
                out the discussion and the spread of knowledge concerning Birth Control.</p>
            <p>These four important incidents, coming almost within the compass of seven days, give
                some indication of the widespread and intense interest our British cousins are
                taking in Birth Control. May it inspire all of us to renew our activities to keep
                our own country abreast in the march toward the new civilization!</p>
        </div>
        <trailer>* See page 228</trailer>
    </docBody>
</doc>
