<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2003/06/04 SB</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/26 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/08/09 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007/06/27 CH Oxygen update and table formatting</prepDate><prepDate>2011-11-30 CH typos</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1918-09-00">Sept 1918</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>How Nature Gets Even</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp206333</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>The Birth Control Review</title>, Sept. 1918, 13</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S70:800</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits and risks"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="socio-economic benefits of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>HOW NATURE GETS EVEN</head>
        <byline rend="italics">By Margaret Sanger</byline>
        <p>When you have read this page, tear it out and put it into your handbag. Show it to the
            next crank who denounces birth control as "<soCalled>criminal</soCalled>" or
                "<soCalled>against nature</soCalled>."</p>
        <p>Out of the <org>Queens County (<place>New York</place>) Penitentiary</org> comes a
            startling reply to the constant question: What has Nature to say about birth control?</p>
        <p>Natures answer is just this:</p>
        <p>Control your birth-rate in a sane, scientific way in this generation, or in the next I
            will control it no less effectively, but at an untold cost of money and misery.</p>
        <p>Look for a moment at the tragic table printed below. In it you will find summed up in
            cold figures the misery of several hundred lives.</p>
        <p>Thirty-one of those lives are those of women in the Queens County penitentiary. What
            existence must mean to them is readily guessed by the fact that they have been in
            prison. </p>
        <p>Note that by far the larger proportion of this number came from families that were too
            large--families denied the knowledge of birth control.</p>
        <p>Note that the mothers of the unfortunate thirty-one gave birth to 217 children. Now note
            also that the thirty-one gave birth to 53 children. Of these 53, only 38 survive.
            Fourteen of the thirty-one women prisoners have no children.</p>
        <p>While the mothers of the thirty-one women prisoners averaged seven children each, the
            prisoners themselves averaged one and a fraction.</p>
        <p>The two generations of these thirty-one families had this choice:</p>
        <p>They could control births in the first generation or Nature would control them in the
            second, while society would send at least one child of each family to the penitentiary
            in the process.</p>
        <p>That is Nature's answer to the argument that birth control is
            "<soCalled>unnatural</soCalled>." Incidentally, the crime that society committed in
            preventing the overburdened mothers from avoiding their load of misery, comes home hard
            to that same society in the cost of taking care of the unfortunate offspring in prisons
            and in hospitals for the insane. That sordid fact stands out like a frightful signpost
            from this table:</p>
        <p>NAME NUMBER OF CHILDREN<lb/>Mary None<lb/>Rose 2<lb/>May 2 -- (1 dead)<lb/>Clara
            9<lb/>Rose 2 living<lb/>Mary 1 son<lb/>Freda None<lb/>Sadie None<lb/>Annie
            Single<lb/>Ruth Single<lb/>Josephine 3 -- (all dead)<lb/>Violet 2 -- (1 dead)<lb/>Agnes
            None<lb/>Elizabeth 5 -- (2 dead)<lb/>Elsie 1<lb/>Minnie 11 -- (4 living)<lb/>Ida
            1<lb/>Olie 1<lb/>Minnie 1<lb/>Dora None<lb/>Tessie None<lb/>Annie 4<lb/>Eleanor
            None<lb/>Irene None<lb/>Rose None<lb/>Ethel None<lb/>Bessie None<lb/>Pearl 1<lb/>Ruth
            1<lb/>Lily None<lb/>Alice 6 -- (1 dead)<lb/>Total 53</p>
        <p>NUMBER OF CHILDREN MOTHER HAD<lb/>5, 1 miscarriage<lb/>9, 7 living, 2
            dead<lb/>1<lb/>5<lb/>1<lb/>1 died<lb/>11, 7 living<lb/>4<lb/>8<lb/>4<lb/>11, 3
            miscarriages<lb/>1<lb/>17<lb/>8, 4 miscarriages<lb/>4<lb/>14<lb/>8<lb/>13, 2 or 3
            miscarriages<lb/>3 (in 3 years), died in childbirth<lb/>15, 10 living<lb/>6, 2 or 3
            miscarriages<lb/>7<lb/>6, 5 living<lb/>2<lb/>13, 8 living<lb/>4<lb/>1<lb/>1<lb/>13, 4
            living<lb/>11, 8 living<lb/>10<lb/>TOTAL 217</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
