<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2003/06/02 SB</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/26 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/08/09 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007/06/27 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-07-10 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1918-08-00">Aug 1918</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>A Statement of Facts--An Obligation Fulfilled</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp206332</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title>, Aug 1918, 3-4</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S70:798</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="BLOFR">Frederick Blossom</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="birth control" level2="propaganda and publicity"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="disputes within"/>
        <index level1="Birth Control Review, The"/>
        <index level1="Blossom, Frederick A."/>
        <index level1="New York Women's Publishing Co."/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>A STATEMENT OF FACTS--AN OBLIGATION FULFILLED</head>
        <byline rend="italics">By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></byline>
        <p>This is the twelfth issue of <title type="journal">The Birth Control Review</title>, and
            as such marks the fulfillment of an obligation. To me a dollar given for the support of
            any movement such as ours–-is more than one hundred cents, it is a pledge for the
            betterment of the world–-of the human race. Thus it is doubly the attitude of those
            chosen to administer the monies contributed for such funds, to see to it that every cent
            of every dollar is rightfully expended and rightfully accounted for. Governed by this
            conviction I have issued the twelve numbers of The <title type="journal">Birth Control
                Review</title>, and have succeeded in bringing the magazine to a point where its
            future usefulness is assured. Before, however, forgetting the obligations of the past in
            the greater promises of the future, I consider it my duty to make plain to the
            subscribers of this magazine certain following facts: In October, the year of 1916, the
            task of stimulating the birth control movement through a monthly publication was
            undertaken by me with the assistance of <person reg="Blossom, Frederick A.">Frederick A.
                Blossom</person>, former manager of the <org reg="Cleveland Associated Charities"
                >Associated Charities</org> of <place reg="Cleveland, OH">Cleveland, Ohio</place>.
            He came to me in Cleveland during the month of July, 1916, and volunteered his services
            to the movement for a period of six months. Despite the fact that he had had no previous
            experience in any modern or progressive movement nor scarcely any knowledge of the
            physical, historical or economic facts of birth control, I accepted his offer, for I
            believed that with his experience and assistance as manager much of the routine work
            would be taken off my shoulders, and that I would be able to devote more of my time to
            agitation, to lecture work, to the opening of clinics and to organizing more intensely
            some of the many details which had to be neglected because of lack of time. I also hoped
            to be of more general service in bringing together in closer and more constructive
            operation the various birth control centers which I had just organized in the
                <place>United States</place>. In October of the same year, Frederick Blossom was
            placed in full charge of the <place reg="New York, NY">New York</place> office, of all
            the books, of monies received and spent, and generally of all financial affairs of
                <title type="journal">The Birth Control Review</title>. In fact, he was given a
            confidence usually earned by years of toil and sacrifice and accomplishment. </p>
        <p>It was expected that the first issue of the magazine would be issued immediately, but it
            was not until February of the following year, five months later, that the first number
            came from the press. The third issue and incidentally the last of his eight months of
            management of the magazine came in May of that year. Then, to my utter surprise, he
            proposed to abandon the publication, although he had accepted almost two thousand
            paid-in-advance subscriptions and had therefore incurred an obligation to continue the
            issuance of the magazine to the end of the twelfth month. His explanation was he had
            spent on three issues all the moneys collected, a sum which by his own calculations
            should have been sufficient for twelve months. He also claimed the magazine owed him
            several hundred dollars. In May, 1917, Frederick A. Blossom resigned as manager of
                <title type="journal">The Birth Control Review</title> and was asked to discontinue
            his activities on my behalf. In leaving he took with him all the furniture and
            furnishings of the office that had been bought in the name of the <title type="journal"
                >Review</title>, all books, vouchers, checks and business or financial records of
            every sort, leaving me with none of the equipments necessary to carry out the obligation
            to the subscribers of <title type="journal">The Birth Control Review</title>, with nine
            issues out of twelve yet to be published, and not one cent in the bank account of the
                <title type="journal">Review</title>. When Frederick Blossom thus abandoned his
            responsibilities as manager of the <title type="journal">Review</title>, I asked him to
            give me a complete report or statement of receipts and expenditures. This request was
            never complied with nor have I to this day been able to obtain the books from him,
            although this request was made at various times covering the period of a year, sometimes
            as often as once a week. I needed and asked for the following: </p>
        <p>1. The total amount received from subscribers.<lb/>2. The names and amounts received from
            contributors.<lb/>3. Moneys received through cash sales of the <title type="journal"
                >Review</title> other than through subscribers.<lb/>4. Total amount received from
            sales of the "<title type="book"><rs reg="What Every Girl Should Know"
            >Girl</rs></title>" and "<title type="book"><rs reg="What Every Mother Should Know"
                    >Mother</rs></title>" books and other literature; also</p>
        <p>1. The dates and amounts paid for printing the various issues.<lb/>2. Amount spent for
            postage, wrappers and other incidental disbursements.<lb/>3. Amount paid for "<title
                type="book">Girl</title>" and "<title type="book">Mother</title>" books.</p>
        <p>HIS ANSWER WAS that I could "<q who="BLOFR">count the number of subscribers on file and
                send to the printer for the printing bills</q>" for any information. I then
            requested him, as I had not received a statement, to send to me by return mail the book
            or books in which a full account of receipts and contributions had been kept, also the
            bank book, check book and vouchers of the <title type="journal">Review</title> account,
            saying that I would prepare a statement and submit it to him for correction before
            taking it to the committee of friends who were willing to help me. He refused flatly to
            do this, and I then placed the matter in the hands of my attorney. Finally, one year
            after his resignation as manager of <title type="journal">The Birth Control
                Review</title>, he sent to my attorney not a financial statement of receipts and
            expenditures, nor the books, vouchers, etc., but what purported to be a statement of
            bank deposits and withdrawals by checks which amounted to $4,816.25. Upon obtaining a
            transcript of this account from the bank, it was found that their account showed
            deposits and withdrawals to the amount of $5,185.50. That discrepancy is a question
            between Frederick Blossom and the bank. Much as the money involved is needed in the
            movement, its loss, if loss there be, is overshadowed by the difficulties, the
            embarrassment and injury to the movement from his failure to return to <title
                type="journal">The Birth Control Review</title> its documents and to give an
            accounting of his financial transaction of his stewardship. All that we have to show
            covering that stewardship of eight months is the report of deposits and withdrawals,
            which does not agree with the banks and three numbers of <title type="journal">The Birth
                Control Review</title>. This meeting was finally brought to a head by the
            interjection of the <org reg="Birth Control League of New York">B.C.L. of New York</org>
            in the matter. An annual meeting of the B.C.L. of New York was called in Frederick
            Blossom's apartment on May 11th to elect officers. The newly elected officers, of which
                <person reg="Myers, Hiram">Hiram Myers</person> was president, <person
                reg="Stone, Margaret Grant">Mrs. Eugene Stone</person>, vice-president; <person
                reg="Goldstein, Jonah J.">Jonah J. Goldstein</person>, treasurer; <person
                reg="Stuyvesant, Elizabeth">Elizabeth Stuyvesant</person>, secretary, requested
            Frederick Blossom, former treasurer of the League, to pass over to its newly elected
            officers all books, accounts, etc., of the League. This he refused to do, and the
            treasurer and president issued a complain against him in the district attorney's
            office.</p>
        <p>IN THE MEANTIME the <org>New York Women's Publishing Co., Inc.</org>, had been formed to
            take over the publishing of the <title type="journal">Review</title> and assist me in
            fulfilling my obligations to subscribers. This statement would have been made earlier,
            but it could not be made until absolute proof had been given that all obligations
            included in a year's subscription had been discharged. <title type="journal">The Birth
                Control Review</title> has made good its obligations to its supporters and to the
            movement--so far as we have been able to ascertain them--even in the absence of the
            records which Frederick Blossom has as yet not surrendered. If anyone who has paid for a
            subscription to the <title type="journal">Review</title> has not received it,
            information should be sent to this office at once in order that the unavoidable omission
            may be made good. Whatever the outcome of the disagreement--personal, petty in the
            extreme, it does not conflict with the work nor obstruct the goal that is to be reached.
            Everywhere throughout the country, from the Atlantic to the Pacific, the birth control
            idea is progressing and the future of the movement is assured.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
