<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2003/07/15 SR</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2003/07/23 SR</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/02 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014--03-07 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1923-01-00">Jan 1923</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Facing the New Year</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp210661</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title>, Jan. 1923, 3-4</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Smith College Collections</title> S70:956</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="funding"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="goals and strategies"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="opposition to"/>
        <index level1="Catholic Church" level2="birth control and abortion and"/>
        <index level1="censorship"/>
        <index level1="First American Birth Control Conference (1921)"/>
        <index level1="Ohio" level2="birth control in"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Facing the New Year</head>
        <p>No year has been more eventful, more crowded with drama and significance than the twelve
            months just finished. The <org>first American Birth Control conference</org>; the
            illegal breaking up of the <org>Town Hall</org> meeting and our subsequent exposure of
            the powers of darkness; our triumphant completion of the meeting in the <org>Park
                Theatre</org>; our successful incorporation of the <org>American Birth Control
                League</org>; the increasing support and championship of Birth Control by the finest
            contemporary intellects of the world; the organization of State leagues and the
            awakening of public interest in this profound and immediate problem--such are only a few
            of the events that should inspire us to new and increased endeavor. The year 1922 also
            marks the successful circling of the globe by the doctrine of Birth Control. Despite the
            efforts at suppression by the Imperial Japanese government, <person
                reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person> was warmly greeted in the leading
            cities of the island empire; and the Birth Control movement has struck roots in the
                <place reg="Japan">land of the Mikado</place>. We should also mention the dignified
            conference held in <place reg="London, England"> London</place> last July, and the
            adhesion to our movement of so distinguished a figure as that brilliant economist
                <person reg="Keynes, John Maynard">John Maynard Keynes</person>. But if we have
            succeeded in impressing public opinion, in awakening interest, we face at the beginning
            of 1923 great difficulties.</p>
        <p>The year 1922 marked for us the renewed efforts of our arch-enemies to hinder the
            progress of enlightenment. The seat of this opposition is to be found in the <org>Roman
                Catholic Church</org>. This enemy is ceaselessly active and openly determined to
            exterminate the Birth Control movement in <place reg="United States">America</place>.
            The incident of the Town Hall meeting illustrates the extent our opponents may go. The
                <place reg="Cincinnati, OH"> Cincinnati</place> episode, recounted elsewhere in this
            issue, shows the attempt of the <org>Roman Catholic Church</org> and such subsidiary bodies as the
                <org>Knights of Columbus</org>, to use the weapon of boycott to stop the progress of
            Birth Control. Last month we invited our enemies to come out into the open. The Knights
            of Columbus threatened the managers of the <org>Hotel Gibson</org> with the cancellation
            of their annual banquet, if they permitted the use of the Hotel Gibson ballroom for the
            Birth Control conferences. To the everlasting credit of the managers of the hotel and
            the <person reg="Carrel, George">Mayor of Cincinnati</person>, they stood firm. They upheld the
            law and the Constitution. They refused to be intimidated by this blustering mob,
            directed by the wily directors of Church politics. The conference was held, the <org>Knights
            of Columbus</org> banquet was cancelled. Let us not fail to record here our deep gratitude and
            appreciation for this noble support of the sacred American traditions of free speech and
            free thought. Cincinnati is to be congratulated for the fine courage and steadfastness
            of her mayor, her citizens, and the management of the Hotel Gibson, in resisting the
            threats of the Catholic machine. Our movement is an educational one in more ways than
            one.</p>
        <p>Our handicaps are great. They seem greater than ever before. We have the equipment for
            the greatest single movement on the earth--almost. No one can deny that we have the
            vision, the fighting energy, an ever-growing knowledge of the cause from its scientific
            and practical aspects. Every day we are receiving letters of encouragement from the most
            enlightened men and women in every country. We have workers eager to dedicate their
            lives to the movement. We have the support of the best authorities in the fields of
            social service, of the churches and of scientific research. There seems in truth only
            one aspect in which we are weak, and in that so deplorably weak that our hopes seem
            impossible of realization. <emph rend="italics"> We have no definite and dependable
                financial resources.</emph> Without this foundation we cannot continue our fight.
            Our workers should have some assurance that they are supported by enlightened public
            opinion. They should be relieved of the ignoble task of collecting penny by penny. This
            burden at least should not be heavy upon the shoulders of those who are on the fighting
            front. In this war for <emph rend="italics">true civilization</emph> we should stand
            back of our little army of the vanguard. Vague purposeless charities are generously
            supported; philanthropic schemes get millions from intelligent Americans. This great
            experiment, this effort to educate the educators, which is now gradually bearing fruit,
            is assumed to be able to live on nothing a year. Years of study, research, labor and
            sacrifice have gone into the effort to crystallize the Birth Control movement. We are
            just successfully beginning to penetrate the social consciousness of our age. Our effort
            to accomplish this is absolutely dependent upon financial support. People buy pictures
            racehorses, aeroplanes and motor cars. They support charities, museums, schools, the
            opera. They are interested in breeding thoroughbred live stock. Why are they so little
            interested in our effort to improve the human stock, to introduce efficiency, health and
            nobility into the coming generations? Here is the great experiment, the most fascinating
            of all, the most important of all social efforts to bring order out of chaos, the most
            interesting and exciting fashion, in short, to create the future civilization of America
            and of the world! The line for millionaires forms at the right. Step forward please!</p>
        <byline>M. S.</byline>
    </docBody>
</doc>
