<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2003/07/30 SR</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-04-17 EK clean regs</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-19 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1924-02-00">Feb 1924</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>A Personal Glimpse of Havelock Ellis</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp211149</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title>, Feb. 1924, pp. 40-41.</bibl>
			<bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Smith College Collections</title>,
				S70:1043</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name/>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<index level1="Ellis, Havelock"/>
		<index level1="Ellis, Havock" level2="and birth control"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>A Personal Glimpse of Havelock Ellis</head>
		<byline>By Margaret Sanger</byline>
		<p>I can never think of <person reg="Ellis, Havelock">Havelock Ellis</person> except as one
			of the outstanding heroes of contemporary civilization. His heroism is not of the
			spectacular, melodramatic type so easily recognized and rewarded by the world at large,
			quick to acclaim and quick to forget. It is not the heroism of a single, decisive
			action. It is a more profound heroism, quite indefatigable heroism, a heroism that has
			been expressed through a lifetime of loving devotion to humanity at large. Havelock
			Ellis is the type of hero who is serenely and calmly indifferent to rewards. The world
			has beaten a path to his door; but it has not forced an entrance into the inner
			sanctuary. A man heroic enough to endure years of misunderstanding and even attack, a
			man who early in life of self-reliance, who, resolutely and without compromise,
			undertook, carried through and completed a task, Herculean in its immensity--surely such
			a man cannot now be vastly impressed with the empty applause which our English-speaking
			world heaps indiscriminately and with equal enthusiasm upon the memory of a great
			life-giver like <person reg="Pasteur, Louis">Pasteur</person>, or upon any of the
			blundering destructive strategists of the World War.</p>
		<p>Silhouetted like a saint against the horizon of the dawning day, the great figure of
			Havelock Ellis assumes benignly gigantic proportions in comparison with our lesser
			prophets and teachers-- noisy busy men stridently shouting doctrines and propaganda into
			our ears. For, in his quiet, never insistent, never emphatic, yet never halting fashion,
			Havelock Ellis has, more than any other voice in contemporary life, changed our whole
			mode of seeing, of thinking, of living. Long before the advent of the newer schools of
			psychology, schools, let me point out in passing, which owe him a great debt, Havelock
			Ellis had begun his great task of searching in the common, often forbidden, fields of
			universal human experience for the great treasures of spiritual truth. Without the
			penetrating vision of inspired genius, without that bottomless reservoir of dynamic
			idealism, never could he have carried on through the long years of loneliness, of
			misunderstanding and even of isolation. For we must not forget that he initiated this
			great work of exploring the dark jungle of human passion in an age that was solidly
			Puritanical and firmly entrenched in the Victorian traditions.</p>
		<p>In "<title type="book">The Dance of Life</title>" Havelock Ellis shows us how closely
			allied, how practically identical in some ways, is the spirit of the artist and the
			scientist. He is himself the most brilliant living example of this union of art and
			science. In the deepest and most complete sense, Havelock Ellis is a great creative
			artist. When we write "<emph rend="italics">creative</emph>," we mean that actually for
			an ever increasing number of men and women he has created newer and truer values of
			life. He has taught us how to think and feel; he has taught us how to live. In this
			respect he is comparable to a great novelist of poet, except that his influence has been
			more direct and more profound in bringing light and love into our actual lives. If in
			this sense Havelock Ellis is a great imaginative and creative artist, he is no less a
			scientist-- a scientist in his respect for the truth, in his refusal to evade or to
			conceal or to shirk those facts about which it has become the cowardly tradition to
			enforce a polite silence.</p>
		<p>Beautiful in its growth and fruition as some majestic tress, his life is the living proof
			that true greatness is not a quality that exists in watertight compartments. Little men
			cannot write great books. Greatness--beauty, truth and love,--suffuse this life, radiate
			not merely on the reader of his books, but on those he has honored with his friendship.
			With the same enthusiasm which has enabled him to throw such flaming ardor and such
			indefatigable courage into his research, with the same catholicity which makes him today
			one of the most erudite of living men, Havelock Ellis has expressed himself in the
			difficult art of friendship. Many men and women, he has never seen, reverently name him
			as close friend. But there are few who are received intimately. To those few he gives
			generously, gives himself, gives freely his all too precious time. He has not chosen his
			friends because of their prominence, nor because of their interest in his work, but
			because of his appreciation of profound human qualities. Secluded and lonely as his life
			might seem to those who have been unable to strike root at all in the shifting sands and
			currents of contemporary life, it has often struck me that through these friendships
			Havelock Ellis has never lost touch with the busy workaday world from which, at first
			glance, he seems so serenely remote. If he speaks of the latest experiments of the <org
				reg="Ballet Russe de Monte Carlo">Ballet Russe</org> or of the novel sensations of
			aeroplane travel, he does so from first hand personal experience. He would shun as a
			plague the doubtful pleasures of a public dinner given in his honor--it was once
			suggested and as promptly vetoed--but he is a skilled epicure in the art of the cuisine
			and a connoisseur of fine wines.</p>
		<p>In the humbler field of everyday life, I mean to suggest; Havelock Ellis exhibits an
			all-embracing sympathy and discrimination. In short, he is an artist in life,--the very
			artist we would expect of the thinker and teacher who can so skillfully vitalize for us
			the ancient and undying truths of the Chinese sage, <person reg="Laozi"
			>Lao-tze</person>, or receive with such cordial enthusiasm the challenging heresies of
			an <person reg="Einstein, Albert">Einstein</person>. This all-embracing hospitality of
			intellect was exhibited earlier in his career when so justly so discriminatingly and yet
			so sympathetically, he interpreted such diametrically opposed prophets as <person
				reg="Francis of Assisi (St.)">St. Francis of Assisi</person> and the <person
				reg="Nietzsche, Friedrich">author</person> of <title type="book"><rs
					reg="Thus Spoke Zarathrustra">Zarathrustra</rs></title>."</p>
		<p>No single factor contributes more to our courage or proves a more unfailing source of
			strength to us who, with the weapon of Birth Control, are seeking to liberate the
			mothers and children of <place reg="United States">America</place> from the bondage of
			enforced maternity and abnormal infancy, than this staunch allegiance and warm
			friendship of Havelock Ellis. That he is "with us," that he has, on the basis of his
			monumental erudition and penetrating vision, expressed himself in clear, unequivocal
			terms concerning the wisdom of this practice; that in his written words we may find
			guidance; that we may learn from him the lesson of patience, of tolerance, of
			understanding; and that in so doing we may share, no matter in how small a part,
			something of his greatness, of his all-embracing understanding and love of
			humanity--these are the things that give us the courage to go on in our work, hoping
			that, like this great man, the world may to some extent recognize the justice and the
			truth of our cause.</p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
