<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
<mepHeader>
<prepDate>2003/06/25 SB</prepDate>
<prepDate>2004/04/26 CH research added and errors checked</prepDate>
<prepDate>2004/07/27 CH</prepDate>
<prepDate>2004/08/09 CH</prepDate>
<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
<docDate value="1920-01-00">Jan 1920</docDate>
<docTitle>
<titlePart>A Birth Strike to Avert World Famine</titlePart>
</docTitle>
<idno>msp211400</idno>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl><title>The Birth Control Review</title> Jan. 1920, 3</bibl>
<bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S70:831</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</mepHeader>
<headNote resp="MSPP">
<index level1="Martens, R. C."/>
<index level1="population" level2="excess"/>
<index level1="population" level2="food supply and" level3="in Europe"/>
<index level1="population control" level2="government policies"/>
<index level1="Vanderlip, Frank A."/>
<index level1="women" level2="reprodutive choices and decisions"/>
</headNote>
<docBody>
<head>A Birth Strike To Avert World Famine</head>
<byline rend="italics">An Editorial by <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret
Sanger</person></byline>
<p>Every reader of <title>THE BIRTH CONTROL REVIEW</title> should study carefully the interview with
Mr.<person reg="Marten, R. C.">R. C. Martens</person>, one of the world's foremost authorities on
food supplies, which is published in this number. Then every reader should call that interview to
the attention of one or more friends.</p>
<p>As long ago as last July, the editors of this publication drew public attention to the situation
into which the world has gotten itself through industrial overpopulation. The text used at that time
was an address made by <person reg="Vanderlip, Frank A.">Frank A. Vanderlip</person> the banker. Mr.
Vanderlip pointed out the dangers entailed by the financial condition of Europe. Now comes Mr.
Martens, a man who conducts a world-wide business, one who has had, perhaps, through his
connections, particularly those with <place>Great Britain</place>'s food controller, the late
<person reg="Thomas, David Alfred">Lord Rhondda</person>, a better opportunity of knowing the
condition of the world's food supply than any other man in <place reg="United States"
>America</place>. And he too sounds a note of warning. His warning is to be more gravely considered
than that of Mr. Vanderlip, for his knowledge is more comprehensive and exact than Mr. Vanderlip's
could have been. Moreover, he deals with the most vital subject of all--the food supply. Mr.
Martens' long-considered and carefully weighed opinion is that many millions of Europe's population
will starve before next year's crops arrive.</p>
<p>Let us consider for a moment the world's situation as reflected by facts known to all thoughtful
persons. First, the world's greatest war and a score of lesser ones, still being waged, resulted
from the pressure of populations, as reflected in commercial rivalries. As one of the fruits of the
war, and therefore of this same industrial overpopulation, we have, according to all reports,
millions of people (mostly children) suffering from lack of food or actually starving in Europe
today. As the result of families too large to subsist upon the earnings of a single wage-earner, we
have more than 2,000,000 of child workers in the United States and other millions in Europe and
Asia--all of them doomed, in a greater or less degree, to broken lives.</p>
<p>On top of all this misery comes the breaking down of Europe's productive system, of her means of
transportation, and a resulting shortage of fifty per cent of her cereals, potatoes and the like, to
say nothing of the shortage of other foods, which will be discussed by Mr. Martens in forthcoming
issues of <title type="journal">THE BIRTH CONTROL REVIEW</title>. <place>Europe</place>, according
to this authority, has on the average enough food to last until February, after which the aged and
the young will begin to die of starvation by the millions!</p>
<p>The world faces its greatest crisis. It approaches the greatest disaster of all time. And even
before the arrival of that disaster, children are being worked to death in American factories; they
are being starved in countless numbers in Europe.</p>
<p>Hunger has not yet gripped the United States as a nation but we are no longer a nation to
ourselves. We must feed Europe, and Europe's hunger is bound to reflect itself upon us. Already we
have felt the first nip of deprivation in high prices and the scarcity of a number of food products.
And as Europe's condition gets worse, so too will ours grow worse.</p>
<p>What shall we women, as citizens of the nations, and of the world, do in this crisis? Shall we
continue to bring children into a world that does not, seemingly cannot provide food for them? Shall
we continue to build up populations to die in war, of plague, and hunger?</p>
<p>We do not invite guests to our homes if the pantry and purse are empty? Shall we bring children
into a world that is bankrupt and starving? All of our mother instincts, all of our humane feelings,
all of our common sense must cry out against such a course. There are too many children in the world
now. They are being broken in factories and they are dying of hunger. More of them are to
die--millions more, say those who are best informed as to the real situation.</p>
<p>The governments have been short-sighted in dealing with this problem, and their measures have
been pitifully inadequate. They have failed. It is time for the women of the world--for each
individual woman to accept her share of this problem. <emph rend="italics">In this hour of crisis
and peril, women alone can save the world. They can save it by refusing for five years to bring a
child into being. And there is no other way.</emph></p>
<p>For the next five years no woman who understands the present situation should bear a child. Not
only should she refuse to bring another human being into a starving and disordered world, but she
should see to it that she enlightens as many of her sisters as possible as to their duties under the
existing circumstances. Each woman who is awake to the true situation should make it her first task
to encourage and to assist her sisters in avoiding child-bearing until the world has had an
opportunity to readjust itself.</p>
</docBody>
</doc>
