<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed draft article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2009/07/20 LL</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/06/03 EK</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1930-00-00">1930</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>One Million Letters from Mothers</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp214082</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>MSM</title> S73:0128</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="WELHG">Wells, H. G.</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="family size" level2="class-based"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"
            level3="negative consequences of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="class-based"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="rights associated with"/>
        <index level1="motherhood"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="enslavement of"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="freedom and rights of"/>
        <index level1="working classes" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="Pope Piux XI"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>
            <add>1 million letters from mothers</add>
        </head>
        <p>Some of us <del>illegible</del>, <add>who</add>, are familiar with the subject as a whole
                <del>we</del> realize our responsibility as human beings and <del>illegible
                fight</del><add>are fighting</add>fight<add>ing</add> for the poor woman's freedom
            and rights, <del>and</del><add>we want to</add> see <del>that</del>her position as
            mother <del>to</del>elevated to one of dignity, through knowledge of birth control. Such
            knowledge, <person reg="Wells, H. G.">H. G. Wells</person> says, “<q who="WELHG">marks a
                new and happier phase in the history of our civilization</q>”. <del>Working</del>
            <add><unclear>Military</unclear></add> and professional classes have the lowest birth
            rate. They also however have the lowest death rate. In other words, while they bring
            into the world only a few children, they provide and care for those children so well
            that the large majority of them live to full maturity.</p>
        <p>It is in my estimation far more patriotic and considerate of the race to have a
            responsibility in the function of child bearing, than to consider it an act of
                <name>God</name> thereby casting the responsibility upon him.</p>
        <p>Theorizing--Let them ask the mothers, frantic with worry, old and broken on the wheel of
            maternity, Hopeless and devitalized with endless childbearing, let these mothers speak
            and tell us what they think of such cruelty on the part of church or state, that makes
            the perpetuation of death-doomed infants a necessity, that makes women submit to
            ignorance and kept in fear of knowledge, that with harmless information
                <add>conscripted</add> available through medical and scientific sources these
            mothers of the race must bind their hands and continue to call in vain for relief from
            maternal bondage.</p>
        <p>The mothers in <place reg="United States of America">America</place> who cannot avail
            themselves of such medical advice are indeed enslaved. They have less consideration than
            the cattle on our farms. They are more enslaved than their husbands in industry or the
            black race in the days of yore.</p>
        <p>The women of wealth have available knowledge and are able to control the number of
            children in their families. Through it, they have time and leisure to develop and
            understand their children.</p>
        <p>Every argument is on this side.</p>
        <p>
            <add>43 million women of child bearing years.<lb/>Pontifical Dictator in foreign land,
                dictates how many children American women shall have.</add>
        </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
