<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011-07-29 NC</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1952-11-26"><supplied resp="MSPP">26 Nov 1952</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>The Humanity of Family Planning</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp214408</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Third International Conference on Planned Parenthood, Report of the
                    Proceedings</title>(Bombay: 1952), p. 12, 54-55.</bibl>
            <bibl><title>MSM</title>S72:0776</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="GANMA">Gandhi, Mahatma</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Margaret Sanger gave this speech at the <org
                reg="International Conference on Planned Parenthood, Third (Bombay)">Third
                International Conference on Planned Parenthood</org> in <place>Bombay,
            India</place>.</p>
        <index level1="family planning"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="speaking tours" level3="1935-1936 (India)"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="and war"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="and natural resources"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="neo-Malthusian arguments for"/>
        <index level1="World War II" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="sterilization" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="Gandhi, Mahatma"/>
        <index level1="population control" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="physicial justifications for"/>
        <index level1="child spacing"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>The Humanity of Family Planning</head>
        <p>We have seen during the past decade, that those for and those against birth control or
            the control of the size of the family live in different mental climates. We must realize
            psychologically that ignorance attracts ignorance, faith attracts faith, intelligence
            attracts intelligence. We know, too, from experience, that no reasonable discussion is
            possible with minds still focused in the dark ages, where scientific advances are
            ignored. We cannot wait for these minds to evolve as they eventually do but we must go
            ahead with all the courage and understanding we possess to overcome their prejudices in
            the interests of life, liberty, and the pursuit of happiness. </p>
        <p>My first visit to <place>India</place> was from November, 1935 to March, 1936. I came at
            the invitation of the <org>All India Women's Conference</org>, requesting me to address
            their Congress in <place reg="Travancore, India">Travancore</place>. Arrangements had
            been made for me to visit your great leader and, to many, the world's greatest living
                Saint--<person reg="Gandhi, Mahandas">Mahatma Gandhi</person>--at <place
                reg="Wardha, India">Wardha</place>. I spent three days there as a guest of the
            Mahatma's. Needless to say these three days were not ever to be forgotten or paralleled
            in human experience. I could spend all the time allotted to me this evening relating our
            conversation--enough for me to say that neither of us convinced the other that we were
            wrong. Gandhi's conclusions, however, were interesting and had already been given
            publicity. He said that India was then (in 1935) overpopulated--“<q who="GANMA">it was
                this condition of overpopulation that enslaved her</q>”-- that four children should
            be the limit born to a couple--after that, separation or continence. I am not going into
            the birth and death rates of that period. The leaders of India are aware of a population
            problem and will doubtless attempt in every way to solve it. </p>
        <p>Every one who thinks will realize that people must and should be fed. When too many
            people occupy the land and use up its resources faster than they can be replaced these
            problems begin--and often increase at a faster rate than the solution to solve them.
            This is the condition in many countries today and all the “ifs” and “buts” do not solve
            the immediate problem of feeding, clothing and sheltering the vast populations
            constantly increasing all over the world.</p>
        <p>The vast essential problem of almost all nations today, including political problems,
            could be greatly alleviated by the national encouragement and practice of birth control.
            Nearly every country is overtaxed to pay for enormous armament. The cry for babies is
            the cry for armament, the cry for war. There is also the tremendous expense of care of
            defective mentalities and the army of delinquents. There is also the problem of poverty,
            of child labor, of unemployment, of crime and enormous maintenance of prisons, and
            asylums; the standards of public education with the demands of more and more from the
            tax-payer; demands to support charities, community chests, <org>Red Cross</org>, all of
            these mount year by year in nearly every country in the world. Everyone who has studied
            the advance of science and of technical progress is aware that machinery in all
            industrial pursuits can take the place of manpower, that more can be produced with less
            hours and fewer men, so that there is not the need of vast populations for industry as
            in former years.</p>
        <p>As population increases in any given territory, it enroaches upon all natural
            resources--forests, grasslands, soil fertility, water levels and water sheds. The
            increasing population threatens not only the food, clothing and shelter of the present
            living people, but the living standards of the present population lower as naturally as
            the night follows the day. Cultural, educational, and scientific advances remain in the
            background or are relegated to the past.</p>
        <p>Sir <person reg="Sansome, George">George Sansome</person> in a recent <org
                reg="British Broadcasting Corporation">B.B.C.</org> broadcast said that he was
            alarmed by the magnitude of the problem of population throughout <place>Japan</place>
            and India where he had recently traveled. He said “The Japanese, the first in
                <place>Asia</place> to use modern technology for the increase of their resources,
            have not solved it. Their population has grown faster than the means for its support and
            their economic situation gives cause for anxiety.”</p>
        <p>While it is right to extend all possible means of science to cultivate land as a means of
            food supply, it is also right to use intelligence and apply it to the individual family
            and its responsibility of adding numbers to the already overcrowded land. Family
            limitation is the intelligent approach to problems of housing, of marriage, of
            education, of medical care, of high taxes as Governments take over the philanthropic
            attitude toward people too poor to provide for themselves, and of the problem of War or
            Peace. </p>
        <p>In World War Two, over 21 million young men were killed in battle; 15 to 20 million
            woman, children and old people killed in air raids; 30 million wounded, mutilated, or
            incapacitated for work; 45 million people evacuated, deported or interned; 30 million
            homes reduced to ashes; 150 million people left without shelter, prey to famine and
            disease. Up to 1946, the Second World War cost three times as much as the First. This
            money could have provided a $30,000 house, $12,000 worth of furniture and $6,000 cash
            present to every family in the United States, <place>Canada</place>,
                <place>Australia</place>, <place reg="Great Britain">Britain</place>,
                <place>France</place>, <place>Germany</place>, <place>Ireland</place>, the
                <place>Soviet Union</place> and <place>Belgium</place>. In addition, every town of
            over 200,000 inhabitants could have been given a cash donation of $75,000,000 for
            libraries, $75,000,000 for schools, $75,000,000 for hospitals. These are the actual
            sordid facts of war.</p>
        <p>We must break down prejudices against sterilization--we must enlighten and educate our
            people as to its harmlessness.</p>
        <p>Abortions break down the health of the mother without preventing renewed pregnancy at an
            early date. Abortions are the very worst way to prevent increase in the population. Let
            us make an end to all this suffering, waste, enfeeblement and despair.</p>
        <p>Anyone who has a free mind and the welfare of the nation at heart will recognize that one
            single principle should stand first and foremost in the solving of these problems, which
            is birth control. This subject concerns everyone of us in its more remote consequences
            it affects the life of every man, woman and child of the nation, as well as the future
            of the race.</p>
        <p>The first object in population control is to achieve cultural progress rather than
            military advance.</p>
        <p>Second--research institutions to be established by scientists classifying basic factors
            in eliminating harmful dysgenic births in the nation.</p>
        <p>Third--co-operation in educating the population to consider the cultural qualities of
            offspring and efface the egotistic desire to perpetuate the self in offspring.</p>
        <p>Basic principles of the planned parenthood movement will help to achieve these results,
            as follows:--</p>
        <p>1. Any adult having a transmissible or hereditary disease should not have children.
            Marriage may be contemplated, but only if the person submits willingly to sterilization
            as a safeguard against propagating offspring carrying such diseases.</p>
        <p>2. Women afflicted with temporary diseases, where cure is retarded because of pregnancy,
            should practise contraception until cured. Tuberculosis, heart disease, kidney disease,
            goitre, and other ailments not transmissible, put a definite strain on a woman's health
            when conception has taken place.</p>
        <p>3. No more children when parents, though showing no affliction themselves, have given
            birth to offspring with mental and nervous disease---morons, cleft palate, Mongolian
            idiots. Somewhere in the heredity there is the cause of these conditions.</p>
        <p>4. Spacing of children in a family where husband and wife are in good health should be
            from two to three years. If the family is planned for four children, the first two could
            be a year or 18 months apart. Then a spacing of two years before another pregnancy is
            contemplated. Two more children 18 months apart. Then a spacing of two years before
            another pregnancy is contemplated. Two more children 18 months apart bring both groups
            together with fair spacing, to consider the mother's health, the father's earning
            capacity, and the standards of living the parents are ambitious to maintain.</p>
        <p>5. Early marriage can be helpful to young people with the postponement of parenthood.
            Twenty-two years is a good age for a woman to bear her first child. Children born of
            young mothers in the teen ages are more frequently neglected. Infant mortality is
            highest where mothers are under twenty-two years of age.</p>
        <p>6. Economic conditions should be seriously considered. Certainly the father whose
            wage-earning power can properly feed, house and educate three, even four children,
            should not have eight, ten or twelve children. Records for delinquency of children in
            poor, large families fill the courts, jails and penitentiaries.</p>
        <p>7. Parenthood should be considered a privilege, not a right. It should be considered an
            assignment, and those about to, or desiring to be parents should be examined physically
            and mentally as to their responsibility and knowledge of the care of infants. There
            should be compulsory education by the State for parents to be able to cope with problem
            children and the changes occurring yearly in childhood and puberty.</p>
        <p>In voicing the above principles it is well to realize that responsibilities are twofold.
            First, the individual couple, who have the intelligence, insight and wisdom to plan the
            number of children desired who can be cared for, can be considered the cultural group in
            every country. Second, there is the responsibility of our officials in public health and
            social welfare. It should be their duty to the State, to the public and to our future
            civilization to see that those who do not have the individual initiative and
            intelligence to plan and control the size of their families should be assisted, guided,
            and directed in every way to eliminate the undesirable offspring, who usually contribute
            nothing to our civilization but use up the energy and resources of the world. </p>


    </docBody>
</doc>
