<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">

    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-03-12 JK initial tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-19 CH proof tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-26 JK correct tags</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1937-02-24">24 Feb 1937</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Speech on Opening a Birth Control
                    Clinic in El Paso</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp214912</idno>
        <sourceDesc>

            <bibl><title type="article">350 El Pasoans Meet To Hear Mrs. Sanger
                    On Birth Control</title><title type="journal">El Paso
                    Times</title> Feb. 25, 1937, p. 1-2</bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="EPT">El Paso Times</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger</person> spoke
        at the <org>Hotel Paso del Norte</org>, after the original location, the
            <org>Hotel Hilton</org>, backed out. <index
            level1="population growth" level2="regulation of"/><index
            level1="Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau"/>
        <index level1="birth control clinics and leagues"/><index
            level1="birth control movement"/><index level1="birth control"
            level2="morality of"/><index level1="birth control"
            level2="socio-economic benefits of"/><index level1="child labor"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="suppression of"/><index
            level1="sex education" level2="birth control and"/><index
            level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Federal"/><index
            level1="&quot;unfit&quot; to reproduce" level2="social burden of"
            /><index level1="transmissible disease"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>350 El Pasoans Meet To Hear Mrs. Sanger On Birth Control</head>
        <head type="sub">She Says Clinic Here Would Cost $1500 Annually</head>

        <p>
            <q who="EPT">Mrs. Sanger said it would cost $1500 a year to operate
                a clinic in <place reg="El Paso, TX">El Paso</place>. Support of
                El Paso clinics is favored through memberships in the local
                committee. A small fee will be charged patients unless it is
                known that the patient has no funds.</q>
        </p>

        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Ask Doctors To Help. </head>

            <p>A committee of physicians will be asked to work at the clinics,
                which Mrs. Sanger hopes will be established on El Paso’s north
                and south side. Clinic equipments costs little, and supplies are
                furnished by the demonstration clinic of the <org
                    reg="Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau">Birth Control
                    Clinical Research Bureau</org>, she said. </p>
            <p>“El Paso people are the first in the <place>United States</place>
                to take advantage of the December 7, <org
                    reg="United States Court of Appeals for the Federal Circuit"
                    >United States Circuit Court of Appeals</org> ruling that
                physicians might send contraceptives by mail- an act considered
                hitherto illegal,” Mrs. Sanger said. </p>
            <p>“Birth Control is conscious means of control that prevents the
                conception of life, and people who say ‘murderer or killer,’ are
                wrong. One cannot kill what has not yet lived. Now doctors need
                not fear a $500 fine, or five years in the penitentiary for
                administering a simple, scientific preventive to a woman who is
                not able to bear a child.”</p>
        </div>

        <div>
            <head type="sub">Sees Finer Type. </head>

            <p>“Birth control is old, but methods are new, and because of this,
                the key note of a new social era, a sound era, that will advance
                the spiritual welfare of the people is born. Birth control will
                mean a new and finer type of human race.”</p>
            <p>
                <q who="EPT">Mrs. Sanger declared that many types who are
                    diseased and brutal are not fit to be parents. </q></p>
            <p> “I would like to live to see the day,” she said “when parents
                will be made to apply for a child or children. When the parents,
                in ill health, and possessing sordid or moronic characteristics
                stood before the child, many a youngster would say, no thank
                you, I will wait for the next applicant. </p>
            <p>“The advance of Christianity, of charity, or humanitarianism,
                will not allow the natural order of nature to function, to
                dispose of the feeble-minded, the diseased, the insane, the old
                as it should. Though it may sound cruel to say they should die,
                if they live they will, in the majority of cases, reproduce
                their kind, which is to throw upon the social order of the world
                certain types who are illiterate, deformed, and diseased, from
                birth. </p>
            <p>“You build palatial palaces to keep them alive, while you are
                taxed to provide the means. A survey shows in one state that
                each person is highly taxed for every inmate in the state’s
                insane asylum. At various times these charges are allowed to go
                home on parole, to reproduce their kind, and I think that every
                official in every state and city heading an insane asylum should
                bear the greater part of the responsibility of such an act.”</p>
        </div>

        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Mentions Four Children. </head>

            <p> “The average man cannot take care of more than four children,
                and after that it is someone else who must bear the burden. We
                must get to the source of the fault. The externals are not
                enough. Do not think that because the Child Labor Laws have been
                recognized that child labor will be abolished. It will exist as
                long as certain types are reproduced.”</p>
            <p>
                <q who="EPT">Mrs. Sanger submitted seven reasons for birth
                    control. They were: Transmissible disease of parents; women
                    suffering with temporary ailments should be informed;
                    parents that seem normal, but have children that are
                    sub-normal in any respect, should not be allowed to
                    reproduce more of this type; there should be a three-year
                    spacing of children, so that the mother might recover from
                    the birth, a year to enjoy the newcomer, and another year to
                    prepare spiritually and mentally for the next baby should
                    she want another; and, although </q>“I strongly favor young
                marriages, I do not believe that children should be born during
                adolescence.”</p>
        </div>

        <div>
            <head type="sub">Urges Get Acquainted. </head>

            <p> “Young marriages are wonderful, but babies should not be born
                during these years, as neither the boy nor the girl is yet
                mature enough. Let them have a year or two for happiness and
                getting acquainted with each other, and working and studying
                together,” she continued. Early marriages do away with illicit
                relations and immorality among the youth of today.</p>
            <p>“Do not be afraid of the word sterilization,” she said. “It will
                figure largely in the future and is a thing that is needed for
                many types. </p>
            <p>“Birth control in 20 years will build a new and constructive
                civilization. It does not decrease the population, but provides
                the country with intelligent, cultured, educated persons.”</p>
            <p><q who="EPT"> Mrs. Sanger said it is inevitable that within the
                    coming five to 10 years, because of overcrowded population
                    in <place>Germany</place>, <place>Italy</place> and
                        <place>Japan</place>, the face of the world will be
                    changed. When too many people inhabit a section of the
                    world, war cannot be avoided.</q>
            </p>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger will lecture and show a special film at a meeting
                for all El Paso doctors Thursday at 8 p.m. in the West Room of
                Hotel Paso del Norte. </p>
            <p> The <org reg=" El Paso Birth Control Clinic Committee">Birth
                    Control Clinic Committee </org>will meet Thursday at 10 a.m.
                at Hotel Paso del Norte.</p>
        </div>

    </docBody>
</doc>
