<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011-07-27 NC</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1946-07-30">30 July 1946</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Birth Control -- Ten Eventful Years</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp216662</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>MSM</title>S72:0501</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="STEER">Stebbins, Ernest L.</name>
            <name id="RCC">Roman Catholic Church</name>
            <name id="COP">Committee on Public Health</name>
            <name id="USCC">United States Circuit Court</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
            <name id="MDSS">Medical Division of Selective Service</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>No published version found; for another version, see <title>MSM</title>
            S72:0517.</p><index level1="birth control" level2="international"/><index
            level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="history of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="American opinion on"/>
        <index level1="African-Americans" level2="birth control and"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Birth Control -- Ten Eventful Years</head>
        <p>Ten years ago, a colorful chapter in the saga of birth control had reached its climax and
            another was beginning. In 1936, in a far-reaching decision, the Federal courts lifted a
            Victorian ban which for sixty-three years had prevented physicians from freely
            exchanging information and materials for the control of human fertility. The decade
            following this decision was to mark attainment of maturity for the birth control
            movement, following its early history of perennial court battles, office raids and
            public controversy.</p>
        <p>In the professions and among the public, fertility control won majority acceptance as a
            normal part of health education and preventive medicine. The term “planned parenthood”
            came into being as the description of a program which includes not only birth control
            but also includes aid to childless couples and education for marriage. The use of birth
            control for healthful spacing of births won inclusion in maternal care programs of seven
            states. And at the close of the decade control of human fertility was receiving
            approbation and support as a world need in the manner which <person
                reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>, founder of the birth control
            movement in the <place>United States</place> had first seen it a quarter of a century
            before in relation to ill health, mortality, poverty, population pressures and cause of
            war.</p>
        <p>Following clarification of the legal status of birth control in 1936, the inclusion of
            fertility control in public health programs throughout the country became a major
            objective of the birth control movement. For the better accomplishment of this purpose
            two organizations, the <org>American Birth Control League</org> and the <org>Birth
                Control Clinical Research Bureau</org>, were merged into one organization in 1938.
            One result of this merger was to eliminate duplication of effort and to permit
            presentation to the public of a comprehensive and practical program of education and
            action under the leadership of one strong national organization--the <org>Birth Control
                Federation of America</org>. A few years after the merger, in order to emphasize the
            positive character of the organization, the name of the national organization was
            changed to the <org>Planned Parenthood Federation of America, Inc.</org></p>
        <p>The Planned Parenthood Federation today is the national agency and clearing house for
            thirty-five state leagues and more than three hundred local committees affiliated with
            the national organization. The local committees carry the burden of operating privately
            supported clinics for parents unable to afford the services of private physicians. Since
            1938, the time of the merger, the number of planned parenthood centers (including
            private, public health and hospital clinics) has grown from 489 to nearly 600.</p>
        <p>The number of clinical services, however, do not indicate the phenomenal growth of public
            acceptance and use of birth control. For while the clinics perform a necessary and still
            expanding service, many millions of parents now find it possible to obtain advice and
            help in planning their families through the services of physicians in private practice
            or through commercially distributed contraceptives. Increasingly, too, other
            professional workers serving the family--nurses, clergymen, social workers,
            educators--have demonstrated acceptance by advising and counseling parents in the
            non-medical aspects of planned parenthood as an integral part of their services. Largely
            through this means the ignorance and prejudice once surrounding control of human
            reproduction have been vastly dissipated within the last decade.</p>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"><emph rend="underline">PUBLIC OPINION.</emph></head>
            <p> There are still an estimated 6,000,000 married couples in the nation unreached by
                even the most elementary knowledge of fertility control. At the same time, public
                opinion polls during the last decade have repeatedly demonstrated the development in
                public acceptance of birth control as a health and social measure. These polls have
                been weather vanes indicating the prevailing winds of thought in relation to the
                control of human fertility.</p>
            <p>In 1938 the <title>Ladies Home Journal</title>, reaching homes in every state, found
                in a survey that seventy-nine per cent of American women favored birth control. A
                    <title>Fortune Magazine</title> poll in 1938 estimated that sales of
                contraceptives then totaled close to $250,000,000--a figure which undoubtedly
                increased appreciably in subsequent years. A nation-wide <title>Gallup</title> poll
                in 1940 among both men and women revealed that seventy-seven percent of those
                questioned favored furnishing birth control information through government health
                centers. In 1943, 84.9 per cent of women, answering a second <title>Fortune</title>
                poll, declared themselves in favor of making knowledge of birth control available to
                all married women. </p>
            <p>Even in <place>Massachusetts</place> and <place>Connecticut</place>, the only two
                states still forbidding physicians from giving birth control information for any
                cause whatever opinion polls show the views of the public in sharp contradiction to
                the repressive legal barriers in those states.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"><emph rend="underline">MEDICAL and PUBLIC HEALTH
                ACCEPTANCE.</emph></head>
            <p>Striking evidence of the progress of the planned parenthood movement is found in the
                sanction it has received from the medical profession in the last decade. From the
                few doughty and far-seeing physicians who thirty years ago were willing to support
                contraception control as a necessary health and social measure, the picture has been
                almost completely revised so that only a small majority of physicians still refuse
                to make it part of their practice.</p>
            <p>The most significant milestone in medical progress was passed in 1937. The
                    <org>American Medical Association</org> adopted a report of its “<org
                    reg="American Medical Association, Committee to Study Contraceptive Practice and Allied Problems"
                    >Committee to Study Contraceptive Practices and Allied Problems</org>”, thus
                accepting birth control as an integral part of medical practice. From then on,
                advance along the road to medical recognition came quickly. The following year, 332
                physicians of the <org reg="National Medical Council on Birth Control">National
                    Medical Council</org>, including the <person reg="Holden, Frederick"
                    >president</person>, presented a signed document at a conference held by the
                    <org reg="United States Children's Bureau">Children’s Bureau</org> in <place
                    reg="Washington D.C">Washington</place>, asking that contraceptive information
                be included in all obstetrical, maternal and post-natal clinics as a means of
                reducing infant and maternal mortality.</p>
            <p>Shortly thereafter, the <title>Journal of the American Medical Association</title>
                for the first time published a series of articles giving approved standards of
                contraceptive techniques and a list of reliable products. This medical triumph was
                immediately succeeded by another when the first scientific treatment of the subject
                of conception and birth control appeared in the <title>Cyclopedia of Medicine and
                    Surgery</title>. Over a decade discussion of various phases of conception
                control have appeared in medical journals with increasing frequency. Most recently a
                study made by the <org
                    reg="Planned Parenthood Federation of America, Medical Committee">Medical
                    Committee of the Planned Parenthood Federation</org> showed that of the 3,381
                physicians, obstetricians and gynecologists answering a questionnaire, 96 per cent
                declared their approval of conception control when medically indicated; that 88 per
                cent approved of it for spacing births; and 77 percent believed it should be
                furnished to any married woman on request.</p>
            <p>Perhaps the most straight forward recognition of birth control by the medical
                profession was given at a dinner during the Federation’s Annual Meeting in 1943 when
                a committee of forty-five outstanding <place reg="New York, NY">New York</place>
                doctors, headed by Dr. <person reg="Herrick, William W.">William W.
                Herrick</person>, President of the <org>New York Academy of Medicine</org>,
                sponsored by a Physicians Dinner to discuss the subject, “<title>Responsibility for
                    the Health of Tomorrow’s Family.</title>” Nationally known leaders in the fields
                of obstetrics, gynecology, psychology, psychiatry and public health took part in the
                discussion.</p>
            <p> With the rapid growth of medical acceptance of birth control as a health measure,
                and the growing interest of the public in family planning, effective steps have been
                taken to provide educational facilities for Doctors in the techniques of conception
                control. To medical meetings have gone exhibits, films and technical manuals.
                Textbooks and pamphlets have had nation-wide circulation among physicians and
                medical students. Increasing interest by nurses, health officers and social workers
                in planned parenthood resulted in the circulation of voluminous amounts of technical
                literature. “<title>The Technique of Conception Control</title>”, published in 1933,
                has gone through a half-dozen editions and has become a text book in senior medical
                classes. Requests for copies come from <org reg="United States Navy">Navy</org>,
                    <org reg="United States Army">Army</org> and <org
                    reg="United States Marine Corps">Marine</org> Hospitals and translations have
                been made into Spanish and Hebrew. In 1942, more than half of the Grade A medical
                schools were reported giving students some teaching in contraceptive technique.</p>
            <p>Expert testimony as to the advantage of spacing children was the study of 7,000,000
                births and stillbirths made by Dr. <person reg="Yerushalmy, Jacob">Jacob
                    Yerushalmy</person>. This study indicated that mothers could lower the chance of
                still birth in their babies were born neither too close nor too far apart. His
                findings supported the long-standing contention of medical authorities that
                child-spacing is a maternal health measure.</p>
            <p> In the annual report of the New York Academy of Medicine for 1945, the <org
                    reg="New York Academy of Medicine, Committee on Public Health">Committee on
                    Public Health</org> restated an opinion it had first expressed in 1931: that “<q
                    who="COP">the public is entitled to expect counsel and information concerning
                    contraception, given by competent physicians.</q>” Finding from a survey of 89
                hospitals in Greater New York, that only five had special contraceptive service in
                their gynecologic departments, the Committee recommended strongly that “<q who="COP"
                    >Child spacing should be recognized as a medical indication and that
                    contraceptive advice should be given by well-trained physicians, both in their
                    offices and in hospitals clinics.</q>”</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"><emph rend="underline">LEGAL ACCEPTANCE.</emph></head>
            <p>Legal obstructions which for more than a half century hampered the democratization of
                birth control knowledge in the United States have all but been swept away in the
                past ten years. Epochal was the decision in the <org>United States Circuit
                    Court</org> in 1936 (<title>U.S. versus one Package</title>) that contraceptives
                imported for legal purposes did not come within the restrictions of the Federal
                Statutes as these were articles employed by conscientious and competent physicians
                    “<q who="USCC">for the purpose of saving life or promoting the well-being of
                    their patients.</q>” Similar decisions were thereafter won in the Canadian
                courts, the judge ruling that birth control information was “for the public good.”
                And in Puerto Rico, the <person reg="unidentified">United States District
                    Judge</person> ruled in favor of a defendant, declaring that “<q who="UNK"
                    >contraceptive articles may have a lawful use</q>.” </p>
            <p>The <org>United States Treasury</org>, recognizing the humane character of the birth
                control movement, declared the American Birth Control <supplied>League</supplied> a
                philanthropy and therefore tax free; that gifts and bequests were deductible from
                tax returns. Furthermore, cooperation with the <org
                    reg="United States Federal Trade Commission">Federal Trade Commission</org>
                resulted in halting advertisements of fraudulent and dangerous drugs.</p>
            <p>Significant of the trend of modern legal opinion are recent decisions on the question
                of the right of birth control literature to the use of the mails. By a decision of
                the <org>United States Court of Appeals</org>, the <org>Consumers’ Union</org> won
                the right to recommend approved contraceptives to married women. A similar decision
                was won after the pamphlet, “<title>Preparing for Marriage</title>” by <person
                    reg="Popenoe, Paul">Paul Popenoe</person>, a recognized authority, had been
                barred from the mails. Neither case, said the court, came under the Comstock
                obscenity law as charged by the <org reg="United States Post Office">Post
                    Office</org> authorities. </p>
            <p>Implicit in all the Federal decisions that have been won in these ten eventful years,
                is the recognition of birth control as a health service, having medical and social
                sanctions.</p>
            <p>Two adverse decisions in state courts prove temporary setbacks. Temporary because
                they do not reflect public sentiment and because they are anachronisms in a
                democracy. In <place>Massachusetts</place> the <org
                    reg="Massachusetts Supreme Court">Supreme Court</org> ruled that the State’s
                proscriptive law on birth control was constitutional and with no exceptions for
                physicians. Immediately a <org>Committee for Defense of Medical Right</org> was
                formed, among whom were leaders in medicine, public health, religion, education,
                business. In 1944, a referendum to repeal the law lost by a close vote, although
                public opinion polls a few weeks before the election had indicated a majority of
                voters in favor.</p>
            <p>In <place>Connecticut</place>, the <org reg="Connecticut Supreme Court">State Supreme
                    Court of Errors</org> likewise upheld an antiquated statute retained through
                religious and political pressure, making it illegal for physicians to prescribe
                contraceptives or for individuals to use them. This ruling was appealed to the
                    <org>United States Supreme Court </org>which, on the basis of a technicality,
                declined to review the decision of the lower courts.</p>
            <p>Efforts are continuing among citizens’ groups to turn the clock forward in
                Massachusetts and Connecticut in line with the liberalization of legal restrictions
                on birth control everywhere else in the nation.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"><emph rend="underline">RELIGIOUS ATTITUDES.</emph></head>
            <p>Marked has been the increased interest and growing support of Planned Parenthood on
                the part of the Protestant and Jewish clergy. During the late 30's many of the
                leading Protestant and Jewish denominations took positive positions favorable to
                birth control. More recently, concerned with juvenile delinquency which begins with
                unwanted and rejected children, with an all-time high divorce rate, with the number
                of illegal abortions which are estimated as high as one to every three births, with
                the vast number of army rejections for mental or physical ill-health, clergymen of
                the country have come to recognize that planned parenthood fosters both responsible
                parenthood and the birth healthy, wanted children--a quality population. In
                increasing numbers clergymen have extended their ministry to include marriage
                counseling, providing instruction for modern young men and women as to the spiritual
                significance of marriage, of the importance of good sexual relationship and
                harmonious family life.</p>
            <p>Responsive to this awakening, a <org
                    reg="Planned Parenthood Federation of America, National Clergyman's Advisory Council"
                    >National Clergymen’s Advisory Council</org> of more than one thousand leaders
                was organized in 1944, and planned parenthood leagues in fifteen states formed state
                advisory councils to cooperate with the National organization. The National Council
                was responsible for distributing thousands of copies of the manual, “<title>Marriage
                    Counsel in Relation to Planned Parenthood,</title>” among clergy and lay
                counselors of many denominations.</p>
            <p>The most consistent opposition to the birth control methods prescribed by most
                doctors has come from the <org>Roman Catholic Church</org>. However, in 1937 that
                church gave its “<q who="RCC">ecclastical approbation</q>” to “<title>The
                    Rhythm</title>”, a now widely distributed book by Dr. <person reg="Latz, Leo J."
                    >Leo J. Latz</person>, offering a “natural” method of birth control. To many the
                difference between Catholic and non-Catholic opinion on birth control now appears to
                center on method rather than on principle.</p>
            <p> Youth itself, during the past dynamic years when the salvation of the world from
                tyranny rested on young shoulders, demanded scientific information upon the facts of
                sex. Many High Schools and Universities, Y.M. and <org
                    reg="Young Womens Chrisian Association">Y.W.C.A.</org>s, Public Hygiene service
                in Army and Navy have responded to this challenge. The decade has witnessed the
                subject of sex, marriage and birth control emerge from whispers to serious,
                scientific, open discussion among America’s future parents.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"><emph rend="underline">MINORITY GROUPS.</emph></head>
            <p>During this past decade the greatest need for birth control information has been most
                apparent among the less privileged minority groups. This has been particularly true
                of the negro population in as much as twice as many negro mothers die in childbirth
                as do white mothers; twice as many babies die at birth as do white babies. Parallel
                to other efforts to better the economic, health and social lot of the negro, in 1939
                a duel program of birth control service and education was initiated; demonstration
                areas in the south were established and a <org
                    reg="Planned Parenthood Federation of America, National Negro Advisory Council"
                    >National Negro Advisory Council</org> organized. From that date on educational
                and clinical services have met increasing cooperation. Effort has been made to reach
                even the most limited in opportunity.</p>
            <p>In 1944 a bi-racial committee on work with Negroes was apppointed, a full-time Negro
                worker added to the National Planned Parenthood staff and later a full-time field
                consultant. Conferences, meetings, institutes have part of an extensive and
                successful educational program. Over a period of a few years strong support has come
                from the <org>National Medical Association</org>, the <org>National Council of Negro
                    Women</org>, <org>The Negro Newspaper Association</org>, Jeannes teachers,
                public health educators, the <org reg="Young Mens Christian Association">Y.M.</org>
                and Y.W.C.A. staffs, the <org>National Urban League</org> and the <org> </org>. In
                twenty-four Negro colleges and professional schools, interpretative programs have
                been given, clinics in congested Negro districts opened and Negro doctors added to
                the list of Planned Parenthood referral physicians. </p>
            <p>The condition of the migrant labor, particularly in the years before World War II and
                during the depression, brought poignantly to the attention of the American people
                the plight of the migrant workers. With thousands of families uprooted, homeless,
                camping on roadsides, the future uncertain, insecure, the immediate need for birth
                control knowledge and service was obvious. Children were being born in wayside
                camps, mothers unattended. Death rates among both mothers and babies were
                phenomenally high. With the cooperation of official agencies and camp public nurses,
                birth control service was brought to many migrant camps and remote rural
                communities. In one year, 1938, more than 20,000 women had been reached through this
                special effort.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"><emph rend="underline">THE WAR YEARS.</emph></head>
            <p>Out of 22,000,000 young men in the <org reg="Selective Service System">Selective Service</org>, 8,000,000 were found
                unfit to fight. Commenting thereon, the <org reg="Selective Service System, Medical Division">Medical Division of Selective
                    Service</org> said, “<q who="MDSS">many of the defects which have resulted in
                    the rejection stem from the fact that they are the children of parents who were
                    unfit for reproduction.</q>” Leaders concerned with maternal health, aware of
                war marriages hastily contracted, of long separations, of the mass recruiting of
                women into industry, of congestion in industrial centers, stressed the importance of
                planned parenthood to the well-being of children born in this period.</p>
            <p>With millions of new women workers taking jobs on factory production lines, old
                patterns were broken as women left their homes and migrated to industrial centers.
                Under abnormal war-time conditions illegal abortion became commonplace in factory
                centers. To meet this menace to the health of their workers, certain industrialists
                introduced maternal care programs which included planned parenthood information and
                service. In so doing they were supported by the <org>Industrial Hygiene
                    Division</org> of the <org reg="United States Public Health Service">United States Health Service</org> which recommended
                child spacing for married women in industry as part of maternal health program.</p>
            <p>As the war came to a close, planned parenthood organizations launched efforts to
                provide marital guidance to the returning soldier, who was confronted with the
                problem of finding a home for himself and young wife, of procuring a job and of
                adjusting himself psychologically to peacetime living. The Planned Parenthood
                Federation brought out two pamphlets to guide young husbands and wives. “<title>The
                    Solider Takes a Wife</title>” had a circulation of tens of thousands among
                service men and women and was translated into brailled by the <org>Library of
                    Congress</org> for the use of the Navy blind. And “<title>Planning to Have a
                    Baby</title>”, a pamphlet addressed to young wives, had instant acceptance and
                is widely used in college marriage courses and in Y.W.C.A.s.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"><emph rend="underline">INFERTILITY PROGRAMS.</emph></head>
            <p>In the last few years planned parenthood organizations have accepted aid to childless
                couples as a basic element of their program. In as much as one married couple out of
                ten is involuntarily sterile, the demand for medical fertility specialists in this
                field has increased yearly. Scores of letters ask for the names of such specialists.
                More than 23,000 copies of the Planned Parenthood Federation’s pamphlet, “<title>To
                    Those Denied a Child</title>” were circulated in the first year following
                publication.</p>
            <p>Unfortunately, extension of both infertility research and services was severely
                hampered during the war years. At the present time there are only forty-seven
                established clinics where childless couples can obtain treatment. The number of
                private specialists is also limited, although fresh emphasis on teaching in medical
                schools on this subject can be effective. Most of the existing infertility services
                are now located in medical schools and hospitals, and a few in regular planned
                parenthood centers. Indicative of planned parenthood interest, was a grant of $2500
                by the <org reg="Planned Parenthood League of Connecticut">Connecticut League</org> in 1946 for infertility research at <org>Yale
                    University</org>.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"><emph rend="underline">CLINIC SERVICES.</emph></head>
            <p>One ultimate goal of the planned parenthood movement was reached during the past
                decade in seven states. In 1937 <place>North Carolina</place> became the first State
                to make child-spacing an integral part of its program for maternal care.
                    <place>South Carolina</place> followed in 1938. Five other states have since
                included planned parenthood in their state health programs: <place>Alabama</place>,
                    <place>Florida</place>, <place>Texas</place>, <place>Mississippi</place> and
                    <place>Virginia</place>. Meantime medical interpretation of birth control as a
                health measure has been vigorously carried on in a number of other states to
                encourage acceptance of child-spacing in their public health services. </p>
            <p>In 1941, the transition from the private clinic to state or county <org>Departments
                    of Health</org> was facilitated by the action of the United States Public Health
                Service when it declared that should a State Department of Health decide on its own
                initiative to undertake a child spacing program, the Federal Public Health
                    Service would give the proposal the same consideration given to any other
                state health measure. Still another important ruling was issued by the
                    <person reg="Stebbins, Ernest L.">Commissioner of Health</person> of <place reg="New York, NY">New York
                    City</place> in 1944 whereby “<q who="STEER">upon request directional information may be given
                to any person asking for the location of a child-spacing service</q>.”</p>
            <p>Throughout the decade which has included a great depression and a great war, 568
                Planned Parenthood clinics have continued to serve thousands of patients, in
                hospitals, in public health centers and in their extra mural services. Hundreds of
                thousands of letters from parents have been answered, directing burdened mothers,
                hopeful brides or troubled fathers to physicians when no clinic was near. </p>
            <p>The war interfered severely with clinical service, owing to shortages of professional
                personnel and the difficulty in getting medical equipment, yet the clinics, country
                over, carried on as the need for their services became ever greater.</p>
            <p>The referral service of the Planned Parenthood Federation lists approximately 3,000
                physicians to whom inquiries can be directed. In addition to these inquires are
                other thousands of inquiries from physicians, social workers, nurses, educators,
                ministers, professional workers desiring technical or specialized information.</p>
            <p>An enormous amount of Planned Parenthood literature has been necessitated to meet the
                constantly growing demand for information on the planning of families. An ever
                broadening stream of technical material has poured steadily to State and Local
                groups, furnishing the tools for furthering local programs and procedures. In the
                later years of the decade, the literature has been directed mainly toward
                specialized groups rather than to the public on the profession at large. General
                acceptance of planned parenthood has called for constant interpretation, for more
                and more medical literature, for special studies of delinquency, of the emotional
                aspects of parenthood, of venereal disease as these social disorders relate to the
                need for birth control and early sex instruction.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"><emph rend="underline">PUBLIC INFORMATION.</emph></head>
            <p>By 1937, the taboo had already been lifted from the subject of birth control in a
                number of popular magazines. Each year their number has increased, reflecting the
                demand of the part of their readers for frank discussion of sex and health problems.
                From various angles magazines, their combined circulations reaching tens of
                millions, have discussed planned parenthood. From 1937 when <title>Current
                    History</title> published “<title>Birth Control’s Big Year</title>” until 1945
                when <person reg="Roosevelt, Eleanor">Mrs. Franklin D. Roosevelt</person> twice in
                the <title>Ladies’ Home Journal</title> advocated the spacing of children in the
                interest of family well-being, magazines have given evidence of the ever growing
                interest in this subject.</p>
            <p>Use of radio has also increased as a medium for public education. In 1942 the
                    <org>National Association of Broadcasters</org> informed radio stations that
                there was nothing in its code which would bar a discussion of birth control from the
                air. The announcement was followed by a larger number of radio broadcasts of
                National conferences, forums and programs initiated by local groups.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"><emph rend="underline">INTERNATIONAL ASPECTS OF BIRTH CONTROL.</emph></head>
            <p>The problem of the control of fertility is not confined to our country alone but is a
                subject of global proportions; its solution of profound consequence to the human
                race. Moreover, demographers see in uncontrolled reproduction of human life as it
                exists in many countries a constant threat to the well-being and peace of the world. </p>
            <p>To study this larger aspect of the birth control movement, Margaret Sanger, in 1922,
                made a trip around the world, noting that wherever there were over crowded
                populations, there was also abject poverty, vast hunger, disease, and high maternal
                and infant death rates. The discontent and hopelessness among teeming populations
                has frequently exploded into wars for the conquest of neighboring land or ampler
                resources when exploited by unscrupulous leadership.</p>
            <p>This direct relationship of population pressures to war has been strikingly apparent
                in the immediate history of <place>Germany</place>, <place>Italy</place> and
                    <place>Japan</place> whose leaders, in planning for world conquest, suppressed
                all birth control information and encouraged unlimited reproduction.</p>
            <p>In our “one world”, the problem of feeding famine stricken areas confronts the world.
                In countries like <place>India</place>, <place>China</place>, and nearer home,
                    <place>Puerto Rico</place> hunger is constant and well-nigh universal. With
                resources utterly inadequate to feed vast and multiplying populations, the people
                live at or below subsistence level. Death rates for mothers and babies are high, the
                span of life is short. India presents a classic and appalling example of
                uncontrolled fertility. Where over a quarter of her children do not reach their
                second birthday and although 3,000,000 died in 1943 of starvation, her relentless
                birth-rate more than offset this repeating catastrophe.</p>
            <p>With these situations in mind, birth control and its relation of world health and
                security became a subject for thoughtful consideration by the <org>United
                    Nations</org>.</p>
            <p>At the <org reg="United Nations, International Health Conference">International Health Conference of the United Nations</org>, presided
                over by Dr. <person reg="Parran, Thomas">Thomas Parran</person> of the United States
                Public Health Service, the subject was introduced by Dr. <person
                    reg="Tutunja, Djamil Pasha">Djamil Pasha Tutunja</person>, health director of
                    <place>Transjordania</place>. Dr. Tutunja declared
                that birth control is as important as control of the atom bomb. He warned the
                conference that the population at the present rate of growth will be too large
                within 100 years unless something is done about it. He urged the conference to
                support birth control as the first means of stopping wars.</p>
            <p>And thus the subject of birth control, thirty years ago but a whisper, is beginning
                to be heard, like the world democracy, around the world. </p>
        </div>


    </docBody>
</doc>
