<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011-08-05 NC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-26 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1953-09-00"><supplied resp="MSPP">Sept 1953</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Clinton Chance</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp220433</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S72:0859</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="CHACL">Chance, Clinton</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>For a draft version see <title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title>
            S72:0855.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head rend="underline">From <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Mrs. Sanger</person></head>
        <p>In the death of <person reg="Chance, Clinton">Clinton Chance</person> I have lost not
            only a close friend but an invaluable adviser and co-worker in the cause of <org
                reg="Planned Parenthood Federation of America">Planned Parenthood</org></p>
        <p>Back in 1920, on one of my annual visits to <place reg="London, England">London</place>,
            Clinton was taking a psychological view of the future possibilities of planned
            parenthood movement. He was a keen observer of character and believed in giving support
            not only to ideals but to action. In our final summing-up of activities and dreams of
            conquests he said “<q who="CHACL">Let me know when there is an important joh to do and
                money needed for it</q>”. </p>
        <p>A few months later the decision of the <org reg="New York State Court of Appeals"
                >Appellate Court of <place>New York</place></org> was given that doctors could give
            contraceptive advice to patients. I cabled Clinton that I could get a woman doctor to
            open a Birth Control Clinic but that five thousand dollars was needed for her salary and
            the clinic set-up for the first year -- was he interested? The cable in reply said “<q
                who="CHACL">Go ahead. Cheque follows</q>”. That was the first legal clinic under
            medical supervision to be opened in the U.S.A. and from it sprang some 600 clinics. </p>
        <p>Clinton was too modest to take credit for the important part he had played in the planned
            parenthood movement. His left hand did not know what his right hand gave out. </p>
        <p>It is good to have indelible memories of a man like Clinton Chance, of his honest
            forthright opinions, of his vision and loyalty and truth, of his wit and laughter in the
            midst of turmoil. He was a man, a friend, I am proud to have known. </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
