<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2013/11/13 JK</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/04/13 EK clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1932-02-00">Feb. 1932</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Birth Control</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp223063</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Birth Control</title></bibl>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Church and Society</title>, Feb. 1932, Vol 5, No. 4, pp.
                1-2</bibl>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers Microfilm Edition, Smith College Collections</bibl>
            <bibl><title>MSM</title> S71:400, L128:414, C16:327, L45:378</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="CaS">Church and Society</name>
            <name id="TAUFR">Taussig, Frederick J.</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>Earlier drafts can be found in MSM S28:410 and S71:390.</p>
        <index level1="United States Children's Bureau"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="overpopulation in"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="public health programs"/><index level1="parenthood"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues" level3="in US"/>
        <index level1="abortion" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="child spacing"/>
        <index level1="birth order"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <div>
            <head>Voluntary Parenthood</head>
            <head type="sub">Birth Control</head>
            <dateline>February, 1932</dateline>
            <p> It is the conscious control of the birth rate by means that prevent conception.
                Emphasis is placed n the word prevent. In preventing conception, one does not
                destroy life; no life has been conceived to destroy. The ovum, when it is not
                fertilized, passes out of the body regularly, as it does when one remains unmarried
                or lives a continent or celibate life. Emphasis is also placed on the world control.
                In controlling the birth rate or the size of the family, it does not mean one must
                limit births to any given number. We control our motors; we control the heat from
                the furnace; we control our time, our appetites, our resources, our lives. Birth
                Control applied to the family does not mean to limit the number of children to a one
                or two-child family system. It means to have the number of children consistent with
                and in consideration of (1) The mother’s health (2) The child’s possible heritage
                (3) The father’s earning capacity (4) Standards of living desirable to maintain</p>
            <p>The conscious control of the powers of fertility would awaken men and women to the
                responsibility of Parenthood. That consciousness is a growing and awakening force
                now developing in the human race is generally conceded. When consciousness is
                applied to the process of generation there will be fewer children born as the result
                of a reckless abandon to the hour; fewer children brought into the world unwanted
                and unloved; more children planned for and conceived in love; more born of the
                mother’s conscious desire; and more given the heritage of healthy bodies and sound
                minds. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Why do we need Birth Control?</head>
            <p>Because the practice is both a health and an economic necessity. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">1. Health </head>
            <p>Women suffering from tuberculosis, heart disease, kidney disease and other ailments
                are known to die as the results of pregnancy. There were over 20,000 mothers who
                died last year besides the large number of mothers who are “always ailing, never
                failing.” Many of these mothers died needlessly from diseases such as those
                mentioned, and from abortions, and would have been alive today had contraceptive
                instruction been given them in time. The number of deaths due to abortions each year
                are a blot on our civilization and a disgrace to any country. I refer you to <person
                    reg="Taussig, Fred J.">Dr. F. J. Taussig’s</person> illuminating treatise on
                this subject, <title type="article">“Abortion in Relation to Fetal and Maternal
                    Welfare.”</title> This article was prepared by the <org>Committee on Prenatal
                    and Maternal Care for the White House Conference.</org> Dr.Taussig makes the
                following statements in his summary: <q who="TAUFR">“The increase in the number of
                    abortions is noticed primarily among married women who have three or more
                    children.</q>” and “<q who="TAUFR">The maternal death loss from abortion in the
                        <place>United States</place>has been estimated as 15,000 annually. Deaths
                    from puerperal sepsis following abortions are relatively seven times as frequent
                    as those from puerperal sepsis after childbirth.</q>" While the practice of
                birth control is a humane expedient for maternal health, it is even more urgent as a
                means of curtailing the infant death rate . We know that this question of infant
                mortality has three very vital factors: the first factor is the father’s wage. As it
                goes up, a larger number in the family survive, and if it goes down, a larger number
                of the children die. Second is the spacing of the number of children in a family. If
                children are born with three or four years between each birth, their chances are
                better because the mother has had an opportunity to recuperate and rebuild her
                health. The family income has been stretched out over the intervening period of
                years to meet the coming infant’s needs. Statistics from our <org
                    reg="United States Children's Bureau">Children’s Bureau</org> clearly show that
                the second child has a better chance to live than the 5th and the 5th a better
                chance than the 12th certainly. Sixty per cent of all the 12th children born in this
                world are doomed to die before they reach their first birthday. Thus, about 6 out of
                every 10 children who are 12th in the family are doomed to death before they breathe
                their first breath. How much better to have a declining birth rate with a greater
                decline in the death rate-- fewer children born but more children to live to grow up
                decently and develop their <name type="deity">God</name>-given powers. What a waste
                of mother power and child life now goes on which might be put into the constructive
                forces of this world. A government which allows men and women to become parents
                whose records show insanity, feeble-mindedness, epilepsy, syphilis, pauperism,
                idiocy and various other transmissible defects, cannot be said to consider the
                welfare or happiness of the country or of the next generation. Billions are now
                spent on charities, both public and private, in the <place reg="United States"
                    >U.S.A.</place> The normal and intelligent citizens are being taxed and drained
                and bled to keep alive an increasing horde of human beings who never should have
                been born into a civilized society. Birth Control should be practiced in early
                marriages, especially when the young people are in the adolescent period. Parenthood
                should be deferred until the girl is at least 23 and the boy at least 25 and they
                have had a chance to gain their own development. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">2. Economic </head>
            <p>Necessity The father’s economic responsibilities should be given full consideration
                in planning a family and birth control comes as a blessing to help young fathers get
                on their feet financially, and keep their earning power ahead of the needs of a
                growing family. Birth Control should be practiced for a year or two years after
                marriage as a means of adjustment. Greater stress should be placed on the importance
                of giving marriage a chance to develop and grow into the ideal relation many of us
                believe possible. The young romantic bride who returns from her honeymoon in a
                pregnant condition never has a chance to develop the woman in her, and both are
                deprived of the opportunity to cement the love bond, to play, grow and expand
                together in mutual affection and love. Premature parenthood has made them skip over
                a period of development at a time and in circumstances when adjustment is essential.
                Two years to play, grow, develop together, will make for more permanent marriages,
                happier homes and larger families. There are other questions -- WHO? WHERE? and HOW? --
                which could be answered, and are given in full in the literature available on the
                subject . Birth control is not a panacea for all the social and economic ills in the
                world but t least it is the most important immediate help which can be applied as a
                solution to the present problems of millions of men and women here and now. Those
                who are practicing birth control because they are fully conscious of the moral
                responsibility of bringing a child into the world are units in the building and
                reconstruction of the new world. They are laying the foundation for the unfolding of
                a vast experiment in race building never before known in the history of mankind.
            </p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
