<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2012-06-18 AW Initial Tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-17 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1955-10-00">Oct 1955</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Foreword to Proceedings of 5th International Conference
                    on Planned Parenthood</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp223799</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Fifth International Conference on Planned Parenthood, Report of the
                    Proceedings</title> (Tokyo: October, 1955)</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Papers Microfilm, Smith College Collections</title>
                S72:0964</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="birth control" level2="international conferences on"/>
        <index level1="conferences" level2="International Conference on Planned Parenthood"
            level3="1955 (5th)"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>FOREWORD</head>
        <p>The <org reg="International Conference on Planned Parenthood, 5th">Fifth International
                Conference on Planned Parenthood</org> was not only the biggest and most significant
            conference the <org>International Planned Parenthood Federation</org> has held: it was
            the best organized. To this end, the several principal voluntary associations concerned
            with family planning in <place>Japan</place> had federated in 1953 to form a national
            organization known as the <org>Family Planning Federation of Japan</org>. Following the
            acceptance in 1954 of the Japanese invitation to hold the conference in <place
                reg="Tokyo, Japan">Tokyo</place>, a conference planning committee was immediately
            formed under the chairmanship of Senator Mrs. <person reg="Kato, Shidzue Ishimoto"
                >Shidzue Kato</person>, with Professor <person reg="Kitaoka, Juitsu">Juitsu
                Kitaoka</person> as Secretary-General, and in the intervening twelve months this
            small committee devoted itself to ensuring the success of the conference.</p>
        <p>We were fortunate in having at our disposal the spacious meeting halls of the
                <org>Masonic Building</org> in Tokyo, which comfortably accommodated the large
            audiences at each plenary session and study group. More than 500 delegates and observers
            from all over Japan and from 20 other countries registered for the conference. The
            opening session on Monday, October 24th, 1955, was addressed by <org
                reg="Japan Government">Japanese Government</org> and planned parenthood leaders and
            by distinguished international guests. In the unavoidable absence in <place>New
                Zealand</place> of the Japanese Minister of Welfare, the Hon. Mr. <person
                reg="Kawasaki, Hideji">Hideji Kawasaki</person>, who had consented to be Honorary
            President of the conference, the Minister of Transport, the Hon. Mr. <person
                reg="Miki, Takeo">Takeo Miki</person>, deputised. A message of welcome was read from
            the Governor of Tokyo, the Hon. Mr. <person reg="Yasui, Seiichiro">Seiichiro
                Yasui</person>, and greetings were given by the leaders of the three major political
            parties in Japan. From the Government of the Colony of <place>Singapore</place>, the
            Hon. Mr. <person reg="Braga, A.J.">A.J. Braga</person>, the Minister for Health, brought
            greetings, and there were many other messages of goodwill from all over the world.</p>
        <p>The widespread support in Japan for family planning was evidenced by the closeness with
            which the conference proceedings were followed in the press, on the radio and on
            television, and by the many invitations extended to international delegates by
            prefectural and city officials and by prominent social welfare and economic
            organizations. The final proof, if any were needed, of our welcome presence in Japan was
            the scroll which the Minister of Welfare, Mr. Hideji Kawasaki, presented to me on his
            return from New Zealand on behalf of the Japanese people, and in the honor done to me by
            their Royal Highness, the <person reg="Hirohito (Japan)">Emperor</person> and the
                <person reg="Akihito (Japan)">Crown Prince</person> of Japan.</p>
        <p>The papers to be presented to the conference had been mimeographed in advance in both
            Japanese and English, and a small band of indefatigable interpreters, several of them
            Japanese doctors who had volunteered their services, made possible the conduct of the
            conference proceedings in both languages. I cannot praise too highly the technical
            arrangements for the conference. No detail was overlooked from the paper- posters,
            announcing in English and Japanese the speaker and subject, which were prominently
            displayed as each speaker came to the rostrum, to the beautiful Japanese flower
            arrangements which graced every room. The proceedings ended on October 29th with a
            get-together dinner, arranged by <person reg="Amano, Kageyasu">Dr. and <person
                    reg="Amano, Fumiko Y.">Mrs. Amano</person></person>, which will be long
            remembered for the many and lovely gifts which were distributed to all guests. The
            smooth-running of the arrangements for visits the following week to the beauty spots of
            Japan, such as <place reg="Nikko, Japan">Nikko</place>, <place reg="Kyoto, Japan"
                >Kyoto</place> and <place reg="Nara, Japan">Nara</place>, and to places of interest
            in Tokyo itself, were due also to the hard and unremitting work of these two Japanese
            doctors. </p>
        <p>The importance of the conference to Japan was the Government’s desire to replace the
            existing abortion program by a program of conception control. When I was asked by the
            Minister of Welfare in 1954 to address the <org reg="Japan Diet">Japanese Diet</org> on
            Birth Control, I told him and other Hon. Members that I considered Japan already had the
            key to this problem in the training in contraceptive technique of 20,000 midwives who
            could take this knowledge into the very homes of the people who most need it.</p>
        <p>The importance of the conference to us all was the bringing together for the first time
            anatomists, biologists, biochemists and other research workers for the discovery of a
            biological method of conception control, the miracle tablet maybe. Some ten top-level
            scientists from <place>Great Britain</place>, <place>India</place>,
                <place>Israel</place>, Japan, <place>Sweden</place> and the <place>United
                States</place> made available to the conference their findings. To Dr. <org
                reg="Koya, Yoshio">Yoshio Koya</org>, Chairman of the Organizing Committee, go
            special thanks for having sifted through the names of scientists and other specialists
            to bring together the finest group of men and women we have ever had at a conference.
        </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
