<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "file:/S:/TRANSCRIPTIONS/XML%20Drafts/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2009/07/15 LL</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2009/07/20 CH Proof tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2009/07/21 LL correct tags</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1931-02-00">Feb 1931</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Comments on the Pope's Encyclical</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp223805</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
                <title>The Birth Control Review</title>, Feb. 1931, 40-41. </bibl>
            <bibl><title>MSM</title> S71:0218</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="Bible">The Bible</name>
            <name id="Augustine">St. Augustine</name>
            <name id="Pope">The Pope</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="birth control"
            level2="response to the Pope's statements on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="religion and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Comments on the Pope's Encyclical</head>
        <byline>MARGARET SANGER <lb/><emph rend="italics"> Chairman,
                    <org>National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth
                    Control</org></emph></byline>
        <p> Evidently the <person reg="Pope Piux XI">Pope</person> believes in
            birth control, although he countenances only one method, namely,
            continence. Physicians agree, however, that it is unwise to attempt
            the general application of any single method. Fortunately the Pope
            does not anywhere command us to have large families. It is true that
            he quotes the Biblical injunction, “<q who="Bible">Increase and
                multiply and fill the earth,</q>” but as these orders have now
            been carried out, the earth is reasonably full. By crowding together
            we may still have a few patches left for growing potatoes, but it is
            widely recognized that humanity suffers from over-population.</p>
        <p>I agree with the Pope’s statements that “<q who="Pope">the
                cultivating of mutual love, and the quieting of
                concupiscence</q>,” as well as procreation, are purposes of
            marriage, and I applaud his quotation from <person>St.
                Augustine</person> saying that “<q who="Augustine">children
                should be begotten of love</q>,” but I question the traditional
            theory that procreation is the primary purpose of sexual union.
            Reproduction may, indeed, be the most tangible result, but who shall
            say, and how can he prove his contention, that this is the primary
            purpose? Consider the fact that nature demands sexual union during
            certain periods of life and under certain circumstances when there
            is no possibility of child bearing. What is the logic of that, if
            the primary purpose is procreation?</p>
        <p>The Pope maintains that any performance of the sexual act in a way
            which frustrates procreation is a "<soCalled>sin against
                nature</soCalled>." Yet he allows “<soCalled>virtuous
                continence</soCalled>," which must be somewhat of a sin against
            nature since it frustrates the “<soCalled>quieting of
                concupiscence</soCalled>,” which, he admits, is on purpose of
            marriage. However, I think that to say “<soCalled>sin against
                nature</soCalled>” is only a manner of speaking. All of us, the
            Pope included, are habitually defeating the ways of nature; the
            advance of civilization has been achieved largely by triumphing over
            nature.</p>


    </docBody>
</doc>
