<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/06/29 NC</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1937-11-00">Nov. 1937</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Notes from a Recent Trip to the Orient</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp223985</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>The Journal of Contraception</title>Nov. 1937,
                pp.201-03</bibl>
            <bibl><title>MSM</title>S71:0961</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="THOWA">Thompson, Warren</name>
            <name id="CMA">Chinese Medical Association</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><index level1="birth control" level2="international"
            /><index level1="birth control"
            level2="international conferences on"/><index level1="Japan"
            level2="birth control clinics and leagues"/><index level1="Japan"
            level2="birth control in"/><index level1="Japan"
            level2="political situation"/><index level1="Japan Chronicle"
        /></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Notes from a Recent Trip to the Orient</head>
        <byline>By Margaret Sanger</byline>
        <p/>

        <p>On August 7th, 1937, a group of us* sailed from <place
                reg="Honolulu, HI">Honolulu</place> on a contemplated trip to
                <place>China</place>. The resolution adopted by the <org>Chinese
                Medical Association</org> “<q who="CMA">that contraception is a
                part of the activities of public health, especially in the field
                of maternity and child welfare</q>,” the intensive educational
            campaigns carried on by the <org>New Life Movement</org>, the
                <org>Mass Education Movement</org>, and other organizations, and
            the cordial invitations from a number of Chinese public health
            officials to assist in the development of a practical birth control
            program, led me to make plans to return to China for the Fall months
            of this year.</p>
        <p>Despite peaceful seas, there was not "smooth sailing" in our minds,
            owing to the rumors of war and the possibility of a major conflict
            involving the whole of <place>Asia</place>, and perhaps the world.
            But, opposed to these fears was the faith, based on experience in
            the past, that the difficulty would be likely to blow over, and the
            Chinese “incident,” so-called by the Japanese, be of short duration.
            It was the general opinion that by the time of our arrival in China,
            peace negotiations would be under way. On August 1st, I had written
            and wired the <person reg="Cummings, Homer Stile">Secretary of
                State</person> for advice, and was informed that the <org>United
                States Government</org> was not advising American citizens
            against going to China.</p>
        <p>Daily radio reports, however, from <place reg="Shanghai, China"
                >Shanghai</place> revealed that the “incident” was growing more
            and more serious. By August 14th communications with Shanghai were
            entirely cut off, and by the time we arrived at <place
                reg="Kobe, Japan">Kobe</place>, no one knew what the actual
            conditions there might be. There we were met by <person
                reg="Rose, Florence">Florence Rose</person>, staff secretary,
            who had preceded us to China and who had managed to return to Kobe
            after the Shanghai bombardment. Her account of the terror and horror
            that accompanied successive bombings of sections of Shanghai crowded
            with helpless refugees, including the heart of the International
            Settlement where she had gone for greater safety, made it evident
            that all plans for China at this time must be abandoned.</p>
        <p>We were met at Kobe also by <person reg="Kato, Shidzue Ishimoto"
                >Baroness Shidzue Ishimoto</person>, who has bravely and
            gallantly led the birth control movement in <place>Japan</place>.
            Several reporters were also present, and in spite of the fact that
            war news was dominating the front pages of the Japanese and English
            papers published in Japan, the subject of birth control took its
            place as one of the outstanding topics of interest. The day after
            our arrival at Kobe, the <title>Japan Chronicle</title> devoted two
            columns in its leading editorial to my return to Japan and the
            significance of birth control to the future welfare of the country.
            In fact, throughout our stay there were daily interviews with the
            press, and every activity had some mention in both the foreign and
            Japanese press.</p>
        <p>There is a vast difference in the Japan of 1937 and the Japan of
            1922, at which time I made my first visit. In 1922 the population of
            Japan was 64 millions. Since then it has been increasing by from
            800,000 to one million annually. Japan has annexed
                <place>Manchukuo</place>, and has thus added vastly to her
            territory. In spite of this increased territory, and its supplies of
            coal, ore, and petroleum, Japan’s ambitions have not been fulfilled.
            She is keenly disappointed over the natural resources of Manchukuo,
            and she is still land-hungry. Japan seeks more natural resources to
            build up her industries to feed her ever-increasing population.
            Owing to her mountainous, untillable acreage, Japan, like
                <place>Italy</place>, is one of the most densely populated
            countries in the world. As far back as 1925, Professor <person
                reg="Thompson, Warren">Warren Thompson</person>, in his
            brilliant analysis of the population problem, named Italy and Japan
            and <place>Germany</place> as “<q who="THOWA">danger spots</q>” of
            the world. Japan is fulfilling that prophecy, and not only are these
            countries the danger spots of the world, but they are the destroyers
            of our civilization through their ruthless method of waging arrogant
            warfare against innocent, peaceful peoples.</p>
        <p>Throughout Japan, especially in the cities, one notes the rapid
            Westernization. Not only in the broad, paved streets, the
            automobiles, the Western costumes of the men and the children; but
            also in the restaurants, in the use of knives and forks and spoons,
            high tables, iced tea, and even air-cooled systems, is the change
            noted. The rickshaw is fast disappearing. While many of the women
            still wear their kimonos and clogs and keep their old coiffure, the
            more educated women, particularly those who have traveled abroad,
            have already adopted the “bob” and prefer western chic costumes of
            French or American design. Baroness Ishimoto laughingly states that
            the only time she wears a kimono is when she visits <place
                reg="United States">America</place>!</p>
        <p>I was disappointed, however, to find that the progress of the women
            of Japan has been retarded. They have not been able to maintain the
            advances they had made as far back as 1922. Then they were making
            rapid strides on the wings of enlightenment in education, but soon
            after the earthquake the reactionary forces of government set up a
            strong, bureaucratic, militaristic government, and women since have
            not been allowed the natural freedom of evolutionary progress. While
            there is a certain equality of education in the lower grades, women
            are not granted degrees in their colleges and universities, and of
            all the women who have been allowed to attend medical universities,
            only a bare sixteen have been granted medical degrees, through
            “special dispensation.”</p>
        <p>Due to the courteous hospitality of the <person reg="Ichita, Kobashi"
                >Mayor of <place reg="Tokyo, Japan">Tokyo</place></person>, we
            were officially received at his request by the <person
                reg="Unidentified">Commissioner of Health of Tokyo</person> and
            his staff in the beautiful and picturesque Kiyosumi Garden, reserved
            for such occasions. The <person reg="Unidentified">Director of the
                Tokyo Division of Hygiene</person>, a <org
                reg="Rockefeller Foundation">Rockefeller</org> fellowship
            physician of vision, assisted in the arrangements for this
            reception, and a staff <person reg="Unidentified">member</person> of
                <org>St. Luke’s International Hospital</org> graciously acted as
            interpreter. Among those present were directors and representatives
            of many public health institutions in Tokyo.</p>
        <p>Contrary to American custom, in his “official capacity” the
            Commissioner welcomed us, agreeing that the cause of birth control
            was noble and good, but “unofficially” he expressed himself as being
            uncertain where he stood because of the difference between “<q
                who="UNK">perpendicular versus horizontal morality</q>” of the
            two civilizations. In Japan, the Commissioner claimed, morals came
            down “<q who="UNK">perpendicular</q>” from the <person
                reg="Hirohito">Emperor</person> to the head of the family, on
            downwards, to the husband and then down to the wife, whereas, in the
            Western countries there is a “horizontal” morality or equality of
            men and women, husband and wife. In other words, behind the
            objections to birth control lies the fact that it is going to give
            woman more power, greater freedom, and a greater chance to develop
            her personality; and from this growth her economic dependence on
            man, and on the male members of her family clan, will be
            lessened.</p>
        <p>On the evening of the same day a meeting was held at the St. Luke’s
            International Hospital. This meeting was arranged and presided over
            by the <person reg="Unidentified">President</person> of the
                <org>Japanese Gynecological Society</org>. Over 300 professional
            people assembled, and the Chairman informed me later that every
            outstanding medical authority who was in Tokyo at the time was
            present at the meeting. Also attending were 25 public health nurses,
            now receiving training at St. Luke’s International Hospital, as well
            as the officials of leading organizations of midwives, who hold a
            respected position in Japan. They represent an important link in the
            public health system, as many communities are solely dependent upon
            midwives for any medical service whatever. Prominent social workers,
            and individuals active in community projects were also present at
            this meeting, which was not open to the public. Altogether it was an
            influential group which, if once authorized to act, could exert a
            far-reaching influence in the curtailment and elimination of many
            social and health problems that now confront civil and health
            authorities.</p>
        <p>A national campaign of public health is just raising its head in
            Japan, and through the establishment of the new <org
                reg="Japan Public Health Institute">Public Health
                Institute</org>, a gift of the <org>Rockefeller
            Foundation</org>, which will open next year, there will be a
            thousand or more professional positions open to the professions in
            the rural districts. This should be an excellent opportunity for the
            mothers in outlying districts to receive medical aid. If birth
            control could go hand in hand with public health instruction, it
            would not only be a blessing in the reduction of maternal and infant
            mortality, but also an indirect means of bringing peace on earth and
            good will to the mothers and fathers of Nippon.</p>
        <p>Most encouraging was the gathering held to celebrate the opening of
            the first modern birth control clinic in Japan. While Baroness
            Ishimoto has, in the past, single-handed practically, carried on
            birth control service and educational work under great difficulties,
            this new clinic is the first clinic comparable to those in Western
            countries. The clinic will be open every day including Sundays, with
            a medical woman in charge, regular schedules will be kept, medical
            examinations given, scientific, accurate records maintained, and in
            general the new clinic will conform to the standards of the
                <org>Birth Control Clinic Research Bureau</org>, with which it
            is affiliated.</p>
        <p>We congratulate Baroness Ishimoto and her co-workers; and feel that
            now in Japan the work has started on its way to the goal of eventual
            adoption by medical and public health authorities.</p>
        <p>Although it was not my intention to do more than make a few social
            visits in Japan, it happened that a great deal has been started in
            many directions.</p>
        <p>One of the <person reg="Unidentified">foremost gynecologists</person>
            has agreed to institute and to carry on a piece of research on Foam
            Powder under his direction in his <org reg="Unidentified">Gynecology
                and Obstetrics Department at a leading hospital</org>. It had
            also been my hope to visit <place>Korea</place> en route to <place
                reg="Beijing, China">Peiping</place>, but this proved
            impossible. Arrangements however were made for a medical social
            worker from <place reg="Seoul, Korea">Seoul</place>, who has been
            cooperating with <person reg="Kaufman, Alvin R. ">Mr. A.
                Kaufman</person> of <place>Canada</place> in doing birth control
            work in Korea, to also set up a Foam Powder project among the
            Koreans, and to keep suitable records.</p>
        <p>In many directions excellent contracts were made, and renewed impetus
            given to our courageous co-worker, Baroness Ishimoto, in her
            ceaseless struggle to carry birth control to the mothers of her
            country. One can never foresee what may happen in a militaristic
            country, and so the future is still dark and overclouded, but with
            the cooperation offered by many of the outstanding medical men and
            the approaching inauguration of a public health program, I dare hope
            that the seeds planted may eventually bear flourishing fruit.</p>
        <p>* The group consisted of <person reg="Brush, Dorothy Hamilton">Mrs.
                Alexander C. Dick</person>, <person reg="Parker, Joanne">Mrs.
                Joanne Parker</person>, Mrs. <person reg="Holt, Rackham">Rackham
                Holt</person> and <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret
                Sanger</person>.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
