<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2003/10/13 NS</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-04-10 CH clean regs</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-20 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1925-02-00">Feb 1925</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart> Radiant </titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp224227</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title>, Feb. 1925, pp. 35-36</bibl>
			<bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Smith College Collections</title> S71:17</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="ELLHA">Ellis, Havelock</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<index level1="Ellis, Havelock"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>RADIANT</head>
		<p>Each February it becomes our privilege and honor to offer to <person
				reg="Ellis, Havelock">Havelock Ellis</person> this humble tribute. Each year it
			becomes increasingly difficult to express in words the depth of our gratitude. For as
			time passes we realize that our debt to this serene and solitary spirit becomes heavier
			and heavier. The truth is that the spirit of Havelock Ellis is a radiant one–-radiant I
			mean in the true sense of that overused word: Havelock Ellis radiates light and warmth
			so that everywhere in the world individuals are the recipients of his miraculous,
			life-giving influence. How then is it possible to repay, to repay in the inadequate
			coinage of mere words, this ever increasing debt?</p>
		<p>All that we can do is to acknowledge the receipt of that spiritual, creative power. To
			receive it, however, is to gain a new conception of living, to awake to fresher and more
			intense values in life, to be liberated and to be endowed with a greater capacity for
			what this great man names "<q who="ELLHA">free and exalted living</q>." In a world, in a
			period like today, where as the man we honor expresses it "<q who="ELLHA">the essential
				things are hidden from sight by people who either fail to see them or take pains to
				ignore them or else openly profess that they are not there</q>," no one can feel his
			influence without beneficing deeply by it. For this reason we acclaim Havelock Ellis as
			one of the greatest life-giving forces of our times. Aloof, impassive, removed as he
			seems to be from the everyday struggles and tragedies of ordinary men and women, he yet
			possesses the secret power of reaching, with his intangible yet healing power, into the
			very souls of people scattered here and there over the earth.</p>
		<p>Time does not respect the work of men who fail to make it a component part of their
			creative effort, it has been truly said. Time has gone into the creation of Havelock
			Ellis's work. There is nothing undigested, nothing chance, nothing ill-considered in the
			words he utters. Yet on the other hand there is no suspicion of the pontifical, not the
			slightest suggestion of arrogance. For this reason the world is beating a path to his
			door, and more and more men and women are reshaping their lives according to the
			creative values he has asserted. No triumph in days such as these, when all of us have
			been led astray by listening to false prophets, could be greater than this of Havelock
			Ellis. They are turning from false standards and seeking the renovation of their lives
			by a fresh appreciation–-which he has awakened-–in the simple, profound and essential
			joys that lie hidden in everyday life.</p>
		<p>We acclaim Havelock Ellis in these pages not merely as a prophet of Birth Control. He is
			above this particular battle. We acclaim him because no one more truly, no one more
			eloquently, no one more patiently, no one more courageously, during so long a period,
			has asserted the finer values in life. No one has possessed so sure, so unwavering a
			vision of the Future. No man has possessed so illuminating, so keen, so penetrating a
			vision of the hidden nature and as yet the unrevealed beauty latent in womanhood. In our
			struggles and battles against injustices, in the sordid tragedies of oppressed womanhood
			that demand our immediate attention, in the hot discussions of theories and economic
			fact, most of us are prone to lose sight of the more profound beauties of life, to
			become blind to the goal toward which we are, consciously or unconsciously, striving. At
			such hopeless moments we must turn for refreshment, for rejuvenation of our energies, to
			those cool serene pages in which we find the expression of this great spirit.</p>
		<p>We turn again to Havelock Ellis as a parched traveler turns to a spring. This spring is
			life-giving. We cannot plumb its depths. We lesser mortals cannot surmise the source of
			its strange power. But we know that in spite of the apparent passivity, the seeming
			remoteness of the man from the squabbles and hot controversies of the moment, his
			beneficent, life-giving power is exerting itself day and night.</p>
		<p>And so again, this month, we lay our humble tribute at the feet of Havelock Ellis. We
			wish only that we were more gifted, that we possessed greater resources, a wider scope
			of influence, so that our debt of gratitude might be more nobly repaid. Volumes are
			published in homage to lesser men. Sophisticated folk run after each new literary idol,
			elevating to temporary immortality the newest comet on the literary horizon, decorating
			with awards and prizes men who are "great" with a manufactured greatness. They fail to
			realize that greatness is not a matter of mere size or bulk. True greatness in a man is
			to be measured by depth, by a man's power to get beyond the superficial and provincial
			aspects of human nature, by the strength and power of his roots, by his ability to
			recreate human nature, and to re-direct it along the path of his own vision. Herein lies
			the true greatness of Havelock Ellis. We wonder how long it will take the professional
			critics to discover this secret of yours and mine.</p>
		<byline>MARGARET SANGER.</byline>
	</docBody>
</doc>
