<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2001-08-21 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2001-09-05 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2002-08-15 KH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2002-08-19 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2003/08/14 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2003/09/07 CH add page cites</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/08/09 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/03/11 CH Entered corrections suggested by Andy Carloff.</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/03/12 EK clean regs</prepDate>

        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1937-07-06">6 Jul 1937</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>At Long Last</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp224215</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>New Masses</title>, July 6, 1937, 19-20</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S71:948</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="LATLE">Latz Leo</name>
            <name id="CRAFR">Crane, Frederick </name>
            <name id="AMAOGAS">American Medical Association, Obstetrical, Gynecology and Abdominal
                Surgery Section</name>
            <name id="AMA">American Medical Association</name>
            <name id="EASMA">Eastman, Max</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
        <index level1="Catholic church"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="maternal"/>
        <index level1="physicians" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="public health" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="class-based"/>
        <index level1="American Medical Association"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>At Long Last</head>
        <head type="sub"><emph rend="weight(bold)italics">A veteran crusader for birth control
                reflects on the campaign in terms of the medical association's action</emph>
        </head>
        <byline>By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></byline>
        <p>The action of the <org>American Medical Association</org> in adopting the report of its
            committee to study contraceptive practices opens the door to a new epoch in preventive
            medicine. It marks the close of a twenty-year struggle for medical recognition of birth
            control as a legitimate practice.</p>
        <p>On the one hand I am filled with joy and gratitude that the policy underlying a program
            which I saw so clearly after my return from <place reg="the Netherlands">Holland</place>
            in 1916 has been justified. Birth control, or "neo-malthusianism" as it was cumbersomely
            called, was more a philosophical concept, a theoretical idea, than a practical matter.
            It was primarily an issue of free speech and free press. I saw, however, soon after I
            became convinced of the fundamental importance of the movement, that it must be
            considered as a medical and technical problem if it was to serve as an instrument for
            woman's freedom. This conviction was due in large part to my education as a trained
            nurse, in part to what I learned in the clinics of Holland, and from such men as <person
                reg="Ellis, Havelock">Havelock Ellis</person>.</p>
        <p>From the day I opened America's first birth control clinic in <place reg="Brooklyn, NY"
                >Brownsville</place> (<place reg="New York, NY">New York City</place>) in 1916 to
            the present time I have stood for medically directed clinics, for the principle of birth
            control as a necessary part of medical practice, and for recognition of this by the
            medical profession as a whole.</p>
        <p>The student of public opinion will find much to intrigue him in a study of the gradual
            build-up which led this year to the court decision firmly establishing the legality of
            birth control, and in its medical recognition by the American Medical Association.</p>
        <p>Fears and taboos, inertia and bigotry, ignorance and dogma blocked the path. One by one
            these barriers have been cleared away. Support from individual physicians with vision
            and courage came first. Support from leading religious denominations soon followed. Even
            the <org>Catholic Church</org>, previously the outstanding enemy of birth control, was
            forced to recognize the need for family limitation when it sponsored the rhythm, or
            so-called safe period, method. Dr. <person reg="Latz, Leo">Leo Latz</person>'s book,
                <title type="book">The Rhythm</title>, which carries on its fly-leaf the phrase "<q
                who="LATLE">Published With Ecclesiastical Approbation,</q>" gives reasons for family
            limitation which agree point for point with those advocated in birth-control literature.
            The Catholic Church has wriggled out of its absurd and inconsistent position by
            conceding the truth of the <emph rend="italics">principles</emph> of birth control, but
            it differs on <emph rend="italics">methods</emph>.</p>
        <p>Gradually more and more medical schools included instruction on contraceptives in their
            curricula, and articles on the subject both in medical and lay magazines increased in
            number and improved in quality year by year. The demonstration clinic in Brownsville was
            closed as a "public nuisance," but the gesture served its purpose; in the test case
            arising from that step the courts ruled that physicians were permitted to give
            birth-control instructions "<q who="CRAFR">for the cure and prevention of
            disease.</q>"</p>
        <p>Thus a group of judges admitted twenty years ago that birth control was a medical
            problem, which affected health and was part of preventive medicine. A broad
            interpretation of the word "disease" opened the way for giving birth-control instruction
            for economic as well as health reasons.</p>
        <p>The history of birth control clinical service, which stemmed from this decision, is
            another story. But all progress and activity in this field has had a bearing on the
            victories of today. On the strength of the interpretation of the <place>New York</place>
            state law rendered by the courts, I founded the <org>Birth Control Clinical Research
                Bureau</org> in 1923. It has been serving the women of New York and vicinity ever
            since. It has, to date, advised more than 58,000 patients. From this one clinic the
            movement has grown to 350 clinics scattered all over the country, all medically
            directed, all keeping scientific records, and functioning under medical advisory boards
            composed of leading physicians in their respective communities.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile evidence as to the medical necessity for birth control was piling up. Studies
            carried out by the <org reg="United States Children's Bureau">U.S. Children's
                Bureau</org> proved the necessity of planning and spacing families. The inquiry into
            the causes of infant and maternal mortality stressed the inescapable relationship
            between infant deaths and children born too close together. It showed the correlation
            between the age of the mother and maternal deaths, and the effect of financial ability
            to provide proper maternal and infant care upon the chance of survival for both mother
            and child.</p>
        <p>Medical evidence as to conditions when pregnancies should be avoided or postponed was
            finding its way into medical journals. The obvious truth that birth control--the
            prevention of conception--is far preferable to abortion--that is, termination of
            pregnancy after conception has taken place--was increasingly emphasized.</p>
        <p>This demand of medical recognition grew. Outstanding among physicians who courageously
            advocated birth control as a medical necessity was Dr. <person
                reg="Dickinson, Robert Latou">Robert L. Dickinson</person> of the <org>National
                Committee on Maternal Health</org>. Ever a fearless crusader, he fought against the
            taboos and inhibitions which made the medical profession ignore the whole field of sex.
            Dr. <person reg="Willson, Prentiss">Prentiss Willson</person> of <place
                reg="Washington, DC">Washington, D.C.</place>, was moved to action by the testimony
            presented at our Congressional hearings on a birth control bill to amend the obsolete
            Comstock statutes. Feeling that physicians were letting the lay public fight the battles
            they themselves should wage, he organized the <org>National Medical Committee on State
                and Federal Birth Control Legislation</org>. The support of individual doctors
            developed into support, formally taken through resolutions, or organized groups, of
            local, county, and state medical societies, and of national medical organizations.</p>
        <p>The wonder, in retrospect, is that the American Medical Association's action was so long
            delayed. For while the doctors were delaying, while questions of expediency and politics
            delayed their action, women and babies were dying needlessly. One-fourth of all maternal
            deaths in this country are caused by abortions. And abortions occur, for the most part,
            among married women with several children, who take this tragic and desperate means of
            preventing the birth of another child they cannot provide for. Birth control would have
            saved their lives. It would also have saved the lives of countless infants who died
            because their mothers were too depleted in health to give them a fair start in life.</p>
        <p>In 1924 Dr. <person reg="Pusey,William Allen">William Allen Pusey</person> advocated
            birth control in his presidential address before the annual convention of the American
            Medical Association. The following year the section on obstetrics, gynecology, and
            abdominal surgery of the Association passed a resolution favoring "<q who="AMAOGS">the
                alteration of existing laws, wherever necessary, so that physicians may legally give
                contraceptive information to their patients in the regular course of practice.</q>"
            But there, as far as the Association was concerned, the matter rested for eight
            years.</p>
        <p>It took three years, from 1932 to 1935, for the Association to appoint a committee to
            study the subject. Its first report a year ago was marked by timidity, confusion of
            thought, and an unwillingness to consider the problem in the only way physicians should
            consider it, as a medical issue.</p>
        <p>Its second report, adopted in <place reg="Atlantic City, NJ">Atlantic City</place> on
            June 8, 1937, brings the story, finally, to a "happy ending." Birth control was
            recognized, at long last, by the medical profession as a whole. The report recommends:
            (1) that the American Medical Association take such action as may be necessary to make
            clear to physicians their legal rights in relation to the use of contraceptives; (2)
            that the Association undertake the investigation of materials, devices and methods; (3)
            that through instruction with respect to the various factors pertaining to fertility and
            sterility, be promoted in medical schools.</p>
        <p>Thus the Association has sanctioned the legality of birth control, medical control of
            methods and materials, and medical education.</p>
        <p>The full report and further findings on the subject are to be printed in the <title
                type="journal">Journal</title> of the <org reg="American Medical Association"
                >Association</org>, thus making them accessible to all physicians, and, indeed, to
            any interested member of the general public.</p>
        <p>"<q who="AMA">Information concerning contraception,</q>" says the report, "<q who="AMA"
                >is admittedly available to persons in favorable economic circumstances.</q>" This
            has been my contention for years. Women who have the fee to pay private physicians can
            and do secure contraceptive advice. But the thousands upon thousands of women whose only
            contact with physicians is through free clinics have been denied it. The 350 clinics of
            which I spoke are doing yeoman's service, but they cannot begin to take care of all who
            should have their help.</p>
        <p>But the future is bright. Nothing now prevents public-health organizations from giving
            birth-control advice to those who need it. Poor parents, as well as rich, can now secure
            instruction on how to plan their families and space their children. They need no longer
            be forced through ignorance to have children they cannot afford to rear adequately. And
            women need no longer be at the mercy of blind chance, helpless victims forced to
            undertake motherhood when they are physically unfit.</p>
        <p>I place all these much to be desired conditions in the present, but my enthusiasm outruns
            the facts, I fear. This rosy picture still lies in the future. But it can and should
            exist, and we, the public, can make it come to pass. For birth control is today a part
            of human knowledge, which must not be denied to all who want it and need it.</p>
        <p>The <title type="journal">NEW MASSES</title>--and the "old"--can proudly celebrate the
            1937 birth-control victories, for through the long years they have given fearless
            support to the movement. In 1914, when I launched the first birth-control magazine in
            America, The <title type="journal">Woman Rebel></title>, the <title rend="italics"
                >Masses</title> said: "<q who="EASMA">We must thank Margaret Sanger for speaking out
                clearly and quietly for popular education in the means of preventing conception. And
                if she goes to court in this fight,</q>"-- and I <emph rend="italics">did</emph> go
            to court--"<q who="EASMA">we must go too and stand behind her and make her martyrdom, if
                martyrdom it must be, the means of that very publicity she is fighting to win. There
                is no more important stand, and no stand that requires more bravery and purity of
                heart, than this one she is making.</q>"</p>
        <p>The old <title type="journal">Masses</title> and the <title type="journal">NEW
                MASSES</title> have always seen clearly that legal obstruction and medical
            obscurantism is class injustice, that it denies to the poor what is the privilege of the
            rich.</p>
        <p>The way is open today for justice in this field. For all parents knowledge which is their
            right and due, so that they may bring into the world only wanted children, with the
            heritage of sound bodies and sound minds.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
