<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "file:/S:/TRANSCRIPTIONS/XML%20Drafts/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2003/06/25 SB</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2003/07/01 CH </prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/26 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/08/09 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007/06/27 CH Oxygen Update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/03/11 CH Entered corrections suggested by Andy Carloff.</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1918-10-00">Oct 1918</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>All Together--Now!</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp225142</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>The Birth Control Review</title> Oct. 1918, 7</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S70:801</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="Birth Control Review, The" rend="italics"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="MS on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="goals and strategies"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="propaganda and publicity"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>ALL TOGETHER–-NOW!</head>
        <p rend="italics">Dear Co-Workers:--</p>
        <p>Birth Control is breaking through. The barriers against which we have been dashing
            ourselves are beginning to fall. No one who has read the last few issues of <title
                rend="italics">The Birth Control Review</title> can doubt that we have made even
            greater progress than we had realized toward the emancipation of woman.</p>
        <p>This number is the record of a significant success and of a strong counter attack. You
            will find in it the stories of the unprecedented indorsement of our movement by staid
            old medical journals and by hitherto silent or antagonistic officialdom. You will find
            also an account of the arrest of <person rend="italics">Kitty Marion</person>.</p>
        <p>We are in a battle–-every foot of ground we win moves the reactionaries to a fresh effort
            to wipe out all we have done.</p>
        <p>Recently when an issue of this publication was held up by the postal authorities, we met
            that interference with the declaration that instead of receding we would issue a bigger,
            better and more fearless magazine. With your help, we are making good. </p>
        <p>In this issue we are saying to that odorous organization left behind him by <person
                rend="italics" reg="Comstock, Anthony">Anthony Comstock</person> that for every
            woman jailed, we will raise up ten women to devote their lives to this fight for free
            womanhood. With your help we can keep this promise too. </p>
        <p>We need more women – more women actively and consciously at work for this cause. Two out
            of five wives in the <place reg="United States of America" rend="italics">United
            States</place> now practise and privately approve of Birth Control. We want these women
            to come into the open and stand courageously for the liberation of their less fortunate
            sisters. </p>
        <p>The quickest way, the best available way to enlist new champions of this movement is to
            place in the hands of your neighbors <title rend="italics">The Birth Control
            Review</title>. First, see that your copy does a maximum of service–-pass it on to your
            friends and tell them to pass it on to theirs. </p>
        <p>Next, see that at least three of your acquaintances subscribe for <title rend="italics"
                >The Review</title>. Explain to them that this publication is not conducted for
            profit, that neither the editors nor stockholders get a cent out of it–-that it exists
            only for the betterment of the condition of women. </p>
        <p>Every new subscriber means several new readers. Every new reader means the possibility of
            another woman consecrating herself to this work.</p>
        <p>Women alone can win this fight for women. You are both soldier and recruiting agent in
            the army battling for Birth Control. The times are full of hope and full of danger. Do
            your part now!</p>
        <byline>Margaret Sanger</byline>
    </docBody>
</doc>
