<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2003/07/22 SR</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-09 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1923-07-00">Jul 1923</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>The Vision of George Drysdale</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp225187</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title>, July 1923, 177-179.</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S70:1008</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="DRYGE">Drysdale, George</name>
            <name id="FRE">French</name>
            <name id="GER">German</name>
            <name id="ITA">Italian</name>
            <name id="ROBPA">Robin, Paul</name>
            <name id="EXAMIN">Examiner</name>
            <name id="MONPA">Montegazza, Paolo</name>
            <name id="ZEIKO">Königsberger Hartungsche Zeitung</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>This article is the first of a four-part series of the same title. For
            following article see <title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title>
            <xref from="219520">Aug. 1923</xref>, <xref from="239148">Sep. 1923</xref>, and <xref
                from="2111447">Oct. 1923.</xref></p>
        <index level1="xxxx"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>The Vision of George Drysdale</head>
        <byline>By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></byline>
        <p><person reg="Drysdale, George R.">George Drysdale</person> is perhaps the greatest
            pioneer of our modern conception of Birth Control, because he was the first to approach
            this great problem from the point of view of individual and social psychology. He saw,
            more clearly than any of his predecessors, the great necessity of a new science and
            psychology of sex. He revitalized the theory of <person reg="Malthus, Thomas Robert"
                >Malthus</person> by lifting it out of the sphere of political economy, and
            vindicating Birth Control from the point of view of human and individual need. He
            discarded the old metaphysical preconceptions of political and theological dogma, and
            insisted upon the necessity of scientific and biological study of human instincts and
            needs. In studying this great and forgotten achievement, we must remember that it was
            wrought by a young man still in his twenties. Also, that "<title type="book">The
                Elements of Social Science</title>" was first published in 1854, long before the
            crystallization of modern evolutionary science, in the very darkest days of the
            Victorian era. This explains why many of the most illuminating points in the vision of
            George Drysdale fell on stony ground. He was so much in advance of his day that by the
            time European thought had caught up to him, his great book had been discarded or
            forgotten. I hope to show, for instance, in the course of the present study, how closely
            Drysdale predicted the technique and aims of the Freudian school of psycho-analysis.
            Nevertheless, in spite of the neglect that Drysdale has suffered, we must not minimize
            the tremendous influence exerted by "<title type="book">The Elements of Social
                Science</title>" throughout the civilized world during the latter half of the
            nineteenth century.</p>
        <p><person reg="Nietzsche, Friedrich">Nietzsche</person> remarks that every philosophy is,
            in a certain sense, a confession or an autobiography. If this is true, the "<title
                type="book">Elements of Social Science</title>" reveals an unusually attractive,
            vigorous personality, uninhibited by the restraints and repression of the harsh and
            Puritanical environment in which he was born and brought up. Born in <place
                reg="Edinburgh, Scotland">Edinburgh</place> in 1825, the son of the Treasurer of the
            City of Edinburgh, Drysdale revealed from childhood all those exceptional qualities that
            we are accustomed to associate with the term "genius." He evinced such great power of
            intellect that his teacher, <person reg="Musgrave, Mr.">Mr. Musgrave</person>, in the
                <org>Circus Place School</org>, named him, for his rapid progress in elementary
            studies, "King." He passed seven years at the <org>Edinburgh Royal Academy</org>,
            obtaining the highest prizes in all his classes. At the time of his death, November 19,
            1904, his brother, Dr. <person reg="Drysdale, Charles R.">Charles R. Drysdale</person>,
            declared that the medals and books given to his brother for merit formed a collection
            and a library in themselves. After seven years at the Edinburgh Royal Academy, George
            Drysdale studied at the <org>University of Glasgow</org>, and obtained honors equally
            from all the professors there. Shortly after the death of his <person
                reg="Drysdale, William">father</person>, George, with Charles Drysdale and their
                <person reg="Lane, Edward Wickstead">brother-in-law</person>, made a tour through
                <place>France</place> and <place>Switzerland</place>. The younger brother speaks of
            George's pre-eminence in all physical and outdoor sports, just as he was pre-eminent in
            his studies. This splendid love of physical perfection and activity, combined with
            intellectual pursuits, is expressed throughout his book.</p>
        <p>Like all of the young thinkers of the early half of the nineteenth century, the Drysdales
            became interested in the study of political economy, which had become the center of most
            of the intellectual activity of that time. George Drysdale took copious notes of the
            works of <person reg="Smith, Adam">Adam Smith</person>, <person reg="Ricardo, David"
                >Ricardo</person>, Malthus, <person reg="Chalmers, Thomas">Chalmers</person>,
                <person reg="Whately, Richard">Whately</person> and the two <person
                reg="Mill, John Stuart"><person reg="Mill, James">Mills</person></person>. Returning
            from the continent he resumed his residence in Edinburgh, where he graduated in
            medicine.</p>
        <p>"<title type="book">The Elements of Social Science</title>," written at the age of
            twenty-seven, is the living monument of his exceptional youth and joyous vitality. It
            has been criticized as being, from our modern point of view, unscientific. Yet in spirit
            it is truly not lacking in this quality. We must not forget that scientific details and
            discoveries keep changing our point of view; and we must at least credit Drysdale with
            an illuminating foresight into the discoveries and scientific interests of our own
            century.</p>
        <p>The young man hurried down to <place reg="London, England">London</place> in the hope of
            immediately finding a publisher. It was not so much personality and egotistical pride in
            his own book that made him do this; he did it in a truly visionary spirit. He felt he
            had expressed the truths of which humanity was in dire need. Perhaps he did not realize
            the extent of his own iconoclasm. He felt that he was truly following in the footsteps
            of the great Malthus and the two Mills. A good deal of the "<title type="book">Elements
                of Social Science</title>," it is true, is a restatement of the principles and
            convictions of those early pioneers in social reform. But imbedded in the closely
            printed pages of this astonishing book there is ample evidence of George Drysdale's
            realization of the great fundamental and central truths of human nature.</p>
        <p>Needless to say, he found great difficulty in finding a publisher for his book. In 1853
                <place>Great Britain</place> was laying the foundations of Victorian prudery; and it
            is not surprising that such a book as the "<title type="book">Elements of Social
                Science</title>" was refused by all reputable publishers. But at length, by a lucky
            chance, Drysdale discovered <person reg="Truelove, Edward">Edward Truelove</person>, a
            free-thought bookseller, living at that time near Temple Bar. Mr. Truelove undertook the
            printing of the work. Edward Truelove, we may note in passing, possessed scarcely less
            courage and bravery in his own particular field than the Drysdales themselves. He was
            vitally interested in the neo-Malthusian movement. He suffered imprisonment for
            publishing, not the "<title type="book">Elements of Social Science</title>," but other
            works of the same character. The dauntless courage of the early English Malthusians
            opens a fascinating chapter in the history of human thought.</p>
        <p>The "<title type="book">Elements of Social Science</title>" was published anonymously,
            not merely in its first edition, but in all the editions printed during George
            Drysdale's lifetime. An edition appeared in 1905 with George Drysdale's name in
            parenthesis under the pen-name of the author--"<q who="DRYGE">A Doctor of Medicine.</q>"
            In his preface to the first edition, Drysdale confessed that "<q who="DRYGE">Had it not
                been from fear of causing pain to a relation, I should have felt it my duty to put
                my name to this work; in order that any censure passed upon it should fall upon
                myself alone.</q>" The "<q who="DRYGE">relation,</q>" as we may guess, was his
                <person reg="Drysdale, Elizabeth Copeland Pew">mother</person>. Charles R. Drysdale,
            who inserted a brief memoir of his brother in the posthumous edition, tells us that
            George wrote anonymously, at first on account of his dislike to give pain to his mother
            by his avowal of heretical opinions in theology and traditional morality, and finally
            because, his health becoming weaker, he disliked those wordy disputes which interfered
            with "<q who="DRYGE">that philosophic tranquility so necessary for thinking out the
                different problems of social life.</q>"</p>
        <p>George Drysdale devoted all the remaining years of his life (he died at the age of
            seventy-eight, November 19, 1904) to the translation of his book and its publication in
            the other European countries. To do so, he made himself familiar with most of the
            Continental tongues, even with Russian, a feat which was rendered possible only by his
            deep studies in language and science. He was thus enabled to criticize the style and
            expression made use of by his translators, French, German, Italian, Spanish, Portuguese,
            Swedish and Danish. In later years, with the appearance of each successive edition, he
            added much material to the book, but the great fundamental truths remained unchanged.
            With his characteristic, challenging boldness, Drysdale confessed that he did not make
            the slightest pretention to have offered any comprehensive or adequate exposition of
            social science. He aimed instead to be suggestive and stimulating. He acknowledged his
            indebtedness to Mill's "<title type="book">Logic</title>" and to <person
                reg="Comte, August">Comte</person>'s "<title type="book">Positive
            Philosophy</title>." He dissented from Comte on most of the vital points of moral and
            social doctrine, but he expressed the profoundest admiration for the manner in which the
            French Positivist carried out the leading ideas of his great work. He agreed that the
            first need was to emancipate the human mind from supernaturalism, to prepare the way for
            a great intellectual regeneration, when human life might be governed by sincere and
            openly expressed convictions.</p>
        <p>In the years following its first appearance, this anonymously published book gained a
            wide European reputation; but due perhaps to its anonymous publication, this reputation
            became mostly an underground one. We find little reference to it in the revolutionary
            literature in which the great spiritual heretics of the latter half of the nineteenth
            century found expression. Drysdale, nevertheless, was a true precursor of the dynamic
            Dionysianism of Nietzsche, and of all our modern multiform striving for intellectual and
            psychological freedom.</p>
        <p>By 1880, six German editions had appeared; by 1881 four Italian editions; while in France
            the book was published both in its entirety and in parts. <person reg="Robin, Paul">Paul
                Robin</person> spoke of it as one of the "<q who="ROBPA">bibles of humanity</q>,"
            while M. Robin's son-in-law, <person reg="Giroud, Gabriel">G. Hardy</person>, himself
            made a translation of that section entitled, "<title type="article">Poverty, Its Only
                Cause and Its Only Cure</title>." In Great Britain, the British colonies and <place
                reg="United States">America</place>, more than 19,000 copies were sold. The great
            virtue of the book, according to <person reg="Ellis, Havelock">Havelock Ellis</person>,
            is that it brought to the attention of many, who had no means of intelligent
            information, the importance of sexual science.</p>
        <p><person reg="Bradlaugh, Charles">Charles Bradlaugh</person> recommended it to the members
            of the <org>International Workingmen's Association</org> (the first <foreign lang="FRE"
                >Internationale</foreign>). The <title rend="italics" type="journal"
                >Examiner</title> spoke of it as "<q who="EXAMIN">the only book that has fully,
                honestly and in a scientific spirit recognized all the elements in the problem--How
                are mankind to triumph over poverty, with its train of attendant evils?--and
                fearlessly endeavored to find a practical solution.</q>" The <title rend="italics"
                type="journal">British Journal of Homeopathy</title> in 1860 spoke of Drysdale's
            book as the most remarkable one in many respects the writer had ever read. This
            conservative editor thought that some of Drysdale's remedies tended rather to a
            dissolution than a reconstruction of society; but nevertheless admitted the benevolence
            and philanthropy of its motives.</p>
        <p>One of the great admirers of the book who was undoubtedly influenced and stimulated by
            its ideas was the distinguished <person reg="Montegazza, Paolo">Paolo
                Montegazza</person> of <place reg="Florence, Italy">Florence</place>. Montegazza
            wrote of Drysdale in the <foreign lang="ITA"><title rend="italics">Medico Di
                    Casa</title></foreign>, 1874: "<q who="MONPA">Afoe to all hypocrisy and
                prejudice, the author of the '<title type="book">Elements of Social Science</title>'
                calls things by their real names, and shrinks only from the excessive sufferings and
                privations to which the poor children of <person>Adam</person> are condemned. He is
                firmly convinced that to measure human fecundity in accordance with the economical
                production of families and nations is the most certain means of destroying pauperism
                and all forms of want; and in this perhaps he is in error, for the evils of modern
                society have many sources, and with the drying up of one (perhaps even the most
                fruitful), another and another would present themselves, which only the combined and
                constant labours of future generations will, perhaps, be able to overcome. However
                this may be, the courage with which the author faces one of the most formidable
                problems of human society is most praiseworthy. Human morality is gradually changing
                its centre of gravity to rest upon a more solid and durable basis. In this new
                morality, the doctrines of Malthus and those of the author of the '<title
                    type="book">Elements of Social Science</title>' must also have a large share. In
                the place of the alms-giving which humiliates, in the place of that charity which
                caresses an evil that it does not know how to cure, there will be substituted
                preventive philanthropy, which by studying want and suffering in their most hidden
                and deep-seated springs, will be able radically to remove them. Jurisprudence,
                medicine and morality follow the same movement, are aiming at the same end--to
                prevent rather than to cure.</q>"</p>
        <p>In <place>Germany</place> and <place reg="Netherlands">Holland</place> likewise, the book
            aroused much discussion, praise as well as adverse comment. Though little spoken of in
            public, it was, nevertheless, to produce a quiet, lasting effect. The <foreign
                lang="GER"><title rend="italics" type="journal">Königsberger Hartungsche
                    Zeitung</title></foreign> (December 4, 1871) confessed that "<q who="ZEIKO"
                >whatever may be said against this fearless laying bare of the most intimate
                relations of social life, and against his whole theory--purely and undisguisedly
                materialistic as it is--even the opponent of Dr. Drysdale will be unable to deny him
                the merit of scientific closeness of reasoning; and what is quite as important, of
                warm and zealous philanthropy. He will rather honor the moral courage and mental
                energy with which the author must have had to work his way out of the bewildering
                maze of hitherto unsolved problems and conflicts to a conviction so logically
                consistent, so luminous and yet so opposed to established institutions and to the
                moral sentiments in which men have been brought up</q>."</p>
        <p>In probing into the deepest causes of human misery and unhappiness, in pointing the way
            to a new emancipation, a truly spiritual and physical freedom, Drysdale is never
            irritated, never fault-finding, never seeking to blame individuals or classes. This is a
            point well worth remembering, when we compare his work with that of other leaders who
            use the weapons of invective and angry attack against their enemies.</p>
        <p>Further evidence that this remarkable mind was truly "future piercing" is to be found in
            his essay on war, published in 1881. George Drysdale was fully conscious that the great
            principle of restrictive fecundity might give, if put to practice, new orientation to
            individual and social activity. The intensive culture of the human race, as opposed to
            nationalistic and racial imperialism, eliminating the need and controlling the cry of
            national expansion and territorial aggression, might do much to wipe out war as a
            fearful remnant of barbarism. He saw that international relations were then in an
            essentially chaotic state, and that war was the natural and inevitable result of
            competitive armament and of international relations based on secret agreements. He
            discussed the question of the general reduction of armaments, of a league of nations or
            confederation of states and of the place of international armies. He saw that
            disarmament could be only a palliative, and not a cure, for present evils, which today,
            as we know, are even more aggravated than in the days when he was writing.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
