<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2003/07/30 SR</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-04-17 EK clean regs</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-09 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1924-04-00">Apr 1924</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart type="article">The Meaning of Radio Birth Control</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp225299</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title>, Apr. 1924, pp. 110-11</bibl>
			<bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Smith College Collection</title>,
				S70:1041.</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name/>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>Sanger gave this speech on Feb. 29, 1924 at the <org>New York State Birth Control
				Conference</org> in <place reg="Syracuse, NY">Syracuse, New York</place>. That
			version has not been found. It was broadcast over local Syracuse radio station
				<org>WFAB</org>.</p>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="eugenic justifications"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="morality of"/>
		<index level1="poverty" level2="family size and"/>
		<index level1="child spacing"/>
		<index level1="conferences" level2="New York State Birth Control Conference" level3="1924"/>
		<index level1="progress"/>
		<index level1="women" level2="enslavement of"/>
		<index level1="mortality rates" level2="infant"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>The Meaning of Radio Birth Control</head>
		<byline>By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></byline>
		<p>Every step forward in our history, from those remote days when our prehistoric ancestors
			first discovered fire, tilled the soil, and domesticated the animals, has been gained
			through control over some force of NATURE. One by one these great wild powers, each one
			of them destructive and overpowering, have been harnessed, directed and mastered by
			human intelligence and made to serve some constructive purpose. The power of the wind,
			the power of steam, the power of electricity, all and with increasing rapidity have thus
			been subjugated.</p>
		<p>By each of these successive steps, men have made use of these tremendous forces to free
			themselves from the slavery of toil. At every step in this long journey they have met
			the opposition of the prejudiced majority. These opposing groups, which have taken no
			part in progress, laughed at <person reg="Columbus, Christopher">Columbus</person> when
			he told them the world was round. They burnt great scientists at the stake. They said
			that automobiles would be impracticable and dangerous. They scoffed at the very idea of
			aviation. But in spite of all this opposition, a few have been brave enough, strong
			enough, courageous enough, to bear aloft and to carry onward the torch of
			civilization.</p>
		<p>In Man's onward march towards civilization, one after another, he has conquered and
			controlled the forces of Nature. Thereby he has diminished disease, pestilence, and
			famine. Hygiene, surgery and sanitation have been the outcome of his triumph. In gaining
			control over these powers of Nature, step by step, mankind has made progress.</p>
		<div>
			<head type="sub">Hunger and Love</head>
			<p>If you stop to think for yourself, you will agree with me that there are two dominant
				forces of human nature that drive every one of us onward, day in and day out, to
				work, to struggle, to achieve; to make homes, to establish families. These are the
				instincts of Hunger and Love. To satisfy our hunger, men compete in business with
				their fellow men, they labor to attain a little security in life. And similarly to
				satisfy our undying need for love, we marry, we make homes, we bring children into
				the world.</p>
			<p>You all know as well as I do that morality means the control of these two instinctive
				impulses. If we aim to satisfy our hunger by eating too much, by refusing to share
				our bread with our fellow-man, we become immoral and sink to the level of beasts. We
				are no less immoral if irresponsibly we bring children into this world without first
				considering our ability to cherish and protect them; without giving thought to the
				health and strength of the mother, upon whom the great burden falls. Unless he can
				assure them health, adequate nourishment, sunlight and care, no man is justified in
				calling an unlimited number of children into being.</p>
			<p>Now, just as Man has freed himself from Nature's bondage through invention and
				machinery, so must Woman free herself from the crushing slavery of undesired
				maternity through the instrument of knowledge and science. She must learn to space
				the years between the births of her children. In this matter, let mothers consider
				the example of the gardener.</p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<head type="sub">A Garden of Children</head>
			<p>Just think for a moment of the meaning of the word kindergarten--a garden of
				children! To me, that is just what the world ought to be--a garden of children. In
				this matter we should not do less than follow the example of the professional
				gardener. Every expert gardener knows that the individual plant must be properly
				spaced, rooted in a rich nourishing soil, and provided with sufficient air and
				sunlight. He knows that no plant would have a fair chance of life if it were
				overcrowded or choked by weeds. To grow into maturity, to bud, to blossom, to
				produce beautiful sturdy flowers in its own season, each plant must have constant
				attention, incessant care and tender devotion.</p>
			<p>If plants, and live stock as well, require space and air, sunlight and love, children
				need them even more. The only real wealth of our country lies in the men and women
				of the next generation. A farmer would rather produce a thousand thoroughbreds than
				a million runts.</p>
			<p>How are we to breed a race of human thoroughbreds unless we follow the same plan? We
				must make this country into a garden for children instead of a disorderly back lot
				overrun with human weeds.</p>
			<p>In a home where there are too many children in proportion to the living space, the
				air and sunlight, the children are usually overcrowded and underfed. They are a
				constant burden on their mother's overtaxed strength and the father's earning
				capacity. Such homes cannot be gardens in any sense of the word. As each new baby
				comes, a poor little victim brought unwanted into an already overcrowded home, he
				has less and less chance to survive in his bitter struggle for life. Statistics
				prove this fact. In families where there are too many children, there is a high rate
				of infant deaths. Then the schools are overcrowded. Little tots are driven to work
				at an age when they should be in fields and playgrounds.</p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<head type="sub">A Miracle of Science</head>
			<p>The control of this great overpowering human energy, the instinct of reproduction--is
				what we mean by Birth Control. We, who are carrying on the battle for the great
				human right of Birth Control, are fighting for better, healthier children, for a
				race of strong men and beautiful women here in <place reg="United States"
					>America</place> We place quality above quantity. We want each child to have
				proper food, warmth, sunlight and fresh air, devotion and love.</p>
			<p>Birth Control does not mean childlessness. On the contrary, it does mean fewer,
				finer, stronger babies, happier, healthier mothers, fathers freed from worry, making
				their way to success and achievement, because they are inspired and strengthened by
				harmony and love.</p>
			<p>You who are listening in tonight, who are taking part in this miracle of science, in
				this human control over one of the greatest energies of Nature, in this triumph of
				intelligence over prejudice and ignorance, remember that just listening in is not
				enough. Let your intelligence likewise be radioactive. Investigate our claims for
				yourself. Think for yourself. If you do, I am sure every one of you will join in our
				great movement to broadcast health and the heritage of health to every mother and
				child in this land.</p>
		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
