<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2009/07/16 LL</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2009/07/20 CH proof tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2009/07/21 LL correct tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-10 CH Cleaned regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1931-10-00">Oct 1931</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>A Public Nuisance</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp225696</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
                <title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title>, Oct. 1931, 277-280.</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Smith College Collections</title>
                S71:0232.</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="FREJO">Freschi, John J.</name>
            <name id="MOOJO">Mooney, John</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>The article contains brief header summarizing its contents. Includes and illustration of
            the flyer announcing America's first birth control clinic, written in English, Yiddish,
            and Italian.</p>
        <index level1="New York City" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="birth control clinics" level2="Amboy street clinic"/>
        <index level1="law-breaking and direct action"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="arrests and trial of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>A Public Nuisance</head>
        <byline>By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">MARGARET SANGER</person></byline>
        <div type="Section">
            <p>The selection of a place for the first birth control clinic was of the greatest
                importance. No one could actually tell how it would be received in any neighborhood.
                I thought of all the possible difficulties: the indifference of women’s
                organizations, the ignorance of the workers themselves, the resentment of social
                agencies, the opposition of the medical profession. Then there was the law--the law
                of <place reg="NY">New York</place> State.</p>
            <p><name type="law" reg="New York Penal Code, Section 1142">Section 1142</name> was
                definite. It stated that no one could give information to prevent conception to
                anyone for any reason. There was, however, <name type="law"
                    reg="New York Penal Code, Section 1145">Section 1145</name>, which distinctly
                stated that physicians (only) could give advice to prevent conception for the cure
                or prevention of disease. I inquired about the section, and was told by two
                attorneys and several physicians that this clause was an exception to 1142 referring
                only to venereal disease. But anyway, as I was not a physician, it could not protect
                me. Dared I risk it?</p>
            <p>I began to think of the doctors I knew. Several who had previously promised now
                refused. I wrote, telephoned, asked friends to ask other friends to help me find a
                woman doctor to help me demonstrate the need of a birth control clinic in New York.
                None could be found. Not one wanted to go to jail. No one cared to test out the law.
                Perhaps it would have to be done without a doctor. But it had to be done; that I
                knew.</p>
            <p>Finally at 46 Amboy Street, in the Brownsville section of <place reg="Brooklyn, NY"
                    >Brooklyn</place>, we found a friendly <person reg="Rabinowitz, Joseph"
                    >landlord</person> with a good place vacant a fifty dollars a month rental; and
                Brownsville was settled on. It was one of the most thickly populated sections. It
                had a large population of working class Jews, always interested in health measures,
                always tolerant of new ideas, willing to listen and to accept advice whenever the
                health of mother and children was involved. I knew that here there would at least be
                no breaking of windows, no hurling of insults into our teeth; but I was scarcely
                prepared for the popular support, the sympathy and friendly help given us in that
                neighborhood from that day to this.</p>
            <p>We determined to open a birth control clinic at 46 Amboy Street to disseminate
                information where it was poignantly required by human beings. Our inspiration was
                the mothers of the poor; our object, to help them.</p>
            <p>With a small bundle of handbills and a large amount of zeal we fared forth each
                morning in a house-to-house canvas of the district in which the clinic was located.
                Every family in that great district received a “dodger” printed in English, Yiddish
                and Italian.</p>
            <p>Would the people come? Did they come? Nothing, not even the ghost of <person
                    reg="Comstock, Anthony">Anthony Comstock</person>, could have stopped them from
                coming! All day long and far into the evening, in ever-increasing numbers they came.
                A hundred women and a score of men sought our help on that opening day . . .</p>
            <p>It was on October 16, 1916, that the three of us-- <person reg="Mindell, Fania">Fania
                    Mindell</person>, <person reg="Byrne, Ethel Higgins">Ethel Byrne</person> and
                myself-- opened the doors of the first birth control clinic in <place
                    reg="United States">America</place>. I believed then and do today, that the
                opening of those doors to the mothers of Brownsville was an event of social
                significance in the lives of American womanhood.</p>
            <p>News of our work spread like wildfire. Within a few days there was not a darkened
                tenement, hovel or flat but was brightened by the knowledge that motherhood could be
                voluntary; that children need not be born into the world unless they are wanted and
                have a place provided for them. For the first time, women talked openly of this
                terror of unwanted pregnancy which had haunted their lives since time immemorial.
                The newspapers, in glaring headlines, used the words “birth control” and carried the
                message that somewhere in Brooklyn there was a place where contraceptive information
                could be obtained by all overburdened mothers who wanted it.</p>
            <p>Ethel Byrne, who is my sister and a trained nurse, assisted me in advising,
                explaining, and demonstrating to the women how to prevent conception. As all of our
                488 records were confiscated by the detectives who later arrested us for violation
                of the New York State law, it is difficult to tell exactly how many more women came
                in those few days to seek advice; but we estimated that it was far more than five
                hundred. As in any new enterprise, false reports were maliciously spread about the
                clinic; weird stories without the slightest foundation of truth. We talked plain
                talk and gave plain facts to the women who came there. We kept a record of every
                applicant. All were mothers; most of them had large families.</p>
            <p>It was whispered about that the police were to raid the place for abortions. We had
                no fear of that accusation. We were trying to spare mothers the necessity of that
                ordeal by giving them proper contraceptive information. It was well that so many of
                the women in the neighborhood knew the truth of our doings. Hundreds of them who had
                witnessed the facts came to the court room afterwards, eager to testify in our
                behalf.</p>
            <p>One day a woman by the name of <person reg="Whitehurst, Margaret">Margaret
                    Whitehurst</person> came to us. She said that she was the mother of two children
                and that she had not money to support more. Her story was a pitiful one-- all lies,
                of course, but the government acts that way. She asked for our literature and
                preventives, and received both. Then she triumphantly went to the <person
                    reg="Cooper, Edward W.">District Attorney</person>’s office and secured a
                warrant for the arrest of my sister, Mrs. Ethel Byrne, our interpreter, Miss Fania
                Mindell, and myself.</p>
            <p>The crusade was actually under way! It is no exaggeration to call this period in the
                birth control movement the most stirring period up to that time, perhaps the most
                stirring of all times, for it was the only period during which we had experienced
                jail terms, hunger strikes, and intervention of the <person
                    reg="Whitman, Charles S.">Chief Executive of the state</person>. It was the
                first time that there was any number of widespread, popular demonstrations in our
                behalf.</p>
            <p>I refused to close down the clinic, hoping that a court decision would allow us to
                continue such necessary work. I was to be disappointed. Pressure was brought upon
                the landlord, and we were dispossessed by the law as a “public nuisance.” In <place
                    reg="the Netherlands">Holland</place> the clinics were calledthe “public
                utilities.”</p>
            <p>When the policewoman entered the clinic with her squad of plain clothes men and
                announced the arrest of Miss Mindell and myself (Mrs. Byrne was not present at the
                time and her arrest followed later), the room was crowded to suffocation with women
                waiting in the outer room. The police began bullying these mothers, asking them
                questions, writing down their names in order to subpoena them to testify against us
                at the trial. These women, always afraid of trouble which the very presence of a
                policeman signifies, screamed and cried aloud. The children on their laps screamed
                too. It was like a panic for a few minutes until I walked into the room where they
                were stampeding and begged them to be quiet and not to get excited. I assured them
                that nothing could happen to them, that I was under arrest but they would be allowed
                to return home in a few minutes. That quieted them. The men were blocking the door
                to prevent anyone from leaving, but I finally persuaded them to allow these women to
                return to their homes, unmolested, though terribly frightened by it all.</p>
            <p>Crowds began to gather outside. A long line of women with baby carriages and children
                had been waiting to get into the clinic. Now the streets were filled, and police had
                to see that traffic was not blocked. The patrol wagon came rattling through the
                streets to our door, and at length Miss Mindell and I took our seats within and were
                taken to the police station.</p>
            <p>As I sat in the rear of the car and looked out on that seething mob of humans, I
                wondered, and asked myself what had gone out of the race. Something had gone from
                them which silenced them, made them impotent to defend their rights. I thought of
                the suffragists in <place>England</place>, and pictured the results of a similar
                arrest there. But as I sat in this mood, the car started to go. I looked out at the
                mass and heard a scream. It came from a woman wheeling a baby carriage, who had just
                come around the corner preparing to visit the clinic. She saw the patrol wagon,
                realized what had happened, left the baby carriage on the walk, rushed through the
                crowd to the wagon and cried to me: “<q who="UNK">Come back! Come back and save
                    me!</q>” The woman looked wild. She ran after the car for a dozen yards or so,
                when some friends caught her weeping form in their arms and led her back to the
                sidewalk. That was the last thing I saw as the Black Maria dashed off to the
                station...</p>
        </div>
        <div type="Section">
            <head type="sub">THE TRIAL</head>
            <p>Arrested at the same time as my sister, and like her charged with the dissemination
                of birth control information, I continued my activity as soon as I was released on
                bail. My first act had been to reopen the clinic in Brownsville. I was promptly
                rearrested and then charged with “maintaining a public nuisance.” By the time my
                case came up for trial, I was becoming more and more familiar with legal procedure
                and courtroom conventions. I must say that I was also more and more puzzled by the
                stilted language, the circumlocutions, the respect for precedent. I saw the
                realities, the suffering. All of these statues were being defended while over the
                whole country women were suffering and sacrificing their lives. I must confess that
                these legal battles, fought in a curiously unreal world, intensified my defiance to
                the breaking point. I longed for a battle in the open, in simple, honest terms,
                without hypocrisy, above board and on real merits.</p>
            <p>My trial was as different from my sister’s as day is from night. Although little more
                than three weeks had elapsed between them, public opinion had changed in a very
                short time.</p>
            <p>The courtroom was packed. Smartly dressed women were present as well as the poor
                women of Brownsville. Reporters turned out in large numbers. Hundreds of photographs
                were taken. I went to the courtroom accompanied by a group of prominent women who
                had entertained me at breakfast. Officially, I had the backing of several
                organizations: <org>The International Child Welfare League</org>, <org>the Women’s
                    City Club</org>, <org>the Committee of One Hundred</org>, the various State
                Leagues for Birth Control.</p>
            <p>The <org reg="Brooklyn Court of Special Sessions">Court of Special Sessions</org> was
                seething with a crowded assortment of humanity. About fifty of the poor mothers of
                the Brownsville section crowded into the courtroom with their children, their
                nursing babies, their fruit, their bread, their pacifiers and their extra diapers.
                No less than thirty of these mothers had been subpoenaed by the District Attorney.
                Their testimony was to be offered in evidence against me; but they, dear things,
                smiled reassuringly at me, certain that they were going to help free me. Most of
                them had been in the Amboy Street clinic the day the raid had taken place...</p>
            <p>I admitted the charge of giving birth control advice to the poor mothers of
                Brownsville. The prosecutor had little to prove. I knew I had violated the letter of
                the law. I was fighting that law. I thought there would be no argument at all. But
                once again an untrue charge was made. Police Sergeant <person reg="Mooney, John"
                    >John Mooney</person> said I had told him that our whole clinic was “<q
                    who="MOOJO">a bluff</q>,” run to see if we could “<q who="MOOJO">get away with
                    something, to do away with the Jewish people</q>.” As that accusation fell flat,
                he then tried to make it appear that the clinic was a money-making affair. Our
                ten-cent fee for the registration of patients did not begin to cover the regular
                expenses, of course; this was merely one of the stories our opponents had concocted
                to discredit us, if possible. We were faced with vindictive lies on every hand.</p>
            <p>Justices <person reg="Freschi, John J.">Freschi</person>, <person reg="Herman, Moses"
                    >Herman</person>, and <person reg="O'Keefe, George J.">O’Keefe</person> sat as a
                tribunal. My brilliant young <person reg="Goldstein, Jonah J.">attorney</person>
                strongly advised me to accept a suspended sentence, if it were proffered. Owing to
                my ill health, he wanted me to avoid the prison term. The case was a big one, and to
                his legal mind, freedom alone meant victory.</p>
            <p>I sat listening impatiently to what seemed an interminable discussion between my
                lawyer, Mr. Goldstein (now Magistrate) and Judge Freschi on the bench... Finally,
                the decisive question was put to me:</p>
            <p>“<q who="FREJO">All we are concerned about is this statute, and as long as it remains
                    the law will this woman promise here and now unqualifiedly to respect it and
                    obey it? Now, is it yes or no? What is your answer, Mrs. Sanger?</q>”</p>
            <p>“I cannot respect that law as it stands today,” I answered. Then I was sentenced:</p>
            <p>“<q who="FREJO"><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>, with the
                    additional evidence submitted by the learned District Attorney after your case
                    reopened last Friday to meet the claim that the proof was insufficient, there is
                    now additional evidence that makes out a strong case that you established and
                    maintained a birth control clinic where you exhibited to various women articles
                    which purported to be for the prevention of conception, and that there you made
                    a determined effort to disseminate birth control information and advice.</q></p>
            <p>“<q who="FREJO">We are not here to applaud nor to condemn your beliefs; but your
                    declarations and public utterances reflect an absolute disregard for law and
                    order. You have challenged the constitutionality of the law under consideration
                    and the jurisdiction of this Court. When this is done in an orderly way, no one
                    can find fault. It is your right as a citizen. Refusal to obey the law becomes
                    an open defiance of the rule of the majority as expressed in this statue. I can
                    see no good reason for all this excitement by some people. They have a perfect
                    right to argue freely about amending the law, but not to advise how to prevent
                    conception</q>.</p>
            <p>“<q who="FREJO">While the law is in its present form, defiance provokes anything but
                    reasonable consideration. It is wholesome that we have discussion by citizens on
                    matters that affect the welfare of the citizens</q>.</p>
            <p>“<q who="FREJO">People have the right to free speech, but they should not allow it to
                    degenerate into license and defiance of the law. The judgment of the Court is
                    that you be confined to the workhouse for the period of thirty days.</q>”</p>
            <p>After the sentence had been pronounced by the presiding judge, there was a moment’s
                silence, and then a murmur of protest and resentment spread throughout the crowded
                room.</p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
