<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
<mepHeader>
<prepDate>2003/06/25 SB</prepDate>
<prepDate>2004/07/27 CH</prepDate>
<prepDate>2004/08/09 CH</prepDate>
<prepDate>2014-03-07 CH clean regs</prepDate>
<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
<docDate value="1920-03-00">Mar 1920</docDate>
<docTitle>
<titlePart>Put Your House in Order</titlePart>
</docTitle>
<idno>msp225692</idno>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl><title type="journal">The Birth Control Review</title>, Mar. 1920, 3-4</bibl>
<bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Smith College Collections</title> S70:835</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
<respStmt>
<resp/>
<name id="VANFR">Frank A. Vanderlip</name>
</respStmt>
</mepHeader>
<headNote resp="MSPP">
<index level1="Martens, R. C."/>
<index level1="men" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
<index level1="population" level2="birth control and"/>
<index level1="population" level2="excess"/>
<index level1="population" level2="food supply and"/>
<index level1="population control" level2="morality of"/>
<index level1="Vanderlip, Frank A."/>
<index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
</headNote>
<docBody>
<head>Put Your House in Order</head>
<byline rend="italics">By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></byline>
<p>The woman who reads the interview with Mr. <person reg="Martens, R. C.">R. C. Martens</person> in
this number and who ponders carefully its significance can hardly be in doubt as to her duty to the
race and to the nation during the next five years.</p>
<p><place>Europe</place> is already beginning to starve, and panic is imminent in the <place reg="United States"
>United States</place>. Unless Mr. Martens and others almost equally well informed are in error, our
people will at some time within the next two or three years feel the pinch of hunger as they have
never felt it before.</p>
<p>The only way to meet this crisis is to cease to bring forth more mouths to be fed. Women must put
the national house in order. They must stop bearing children until there is more assurance of peace
within and without the country--until there is a better prospect that their children will not suffer
for the necessities of life. Any other course is sheer folly.</p>
<p>Some of the women of America, at least, have awakened to the wisdom of this course. For the most
part, these women have been such as have been closely in touch with the inner workings of our
industrial and financial systems. These have recognized at once the necessity of making ready to
meet the disaster which the world is facing. Men, too, have come forward to approve the suggestion
that no more children be borne until the world is in a more settled condition. And almost without
exception these have been men who are better informed than the average--men who know the courses of
the basic currents of our national life.</p>
<p>That the world's present condition of shipwreck is due largely to surplus population is plainly
indicated not only by what Mr. Martens has to say, but even more plainly by the observations of
others, notably <person reg="Vanderlip, Frank A.">Frank A. Vanderlip</person>, one of the foremost
of American financiers. In a copyrighted interview with the <title>United Press</title>, February 6,
Mr. Vanderlip said: "<q who="VANFR">Just now the people of <place>Austria</place> and other Central
European countries are exhausted and dying of starvation.</q>" In other words, the great crash is
here, so far as <place>Central Europe</place> is concerned.</p>
<p>And again: "The present situation was evident a year ago. But the people who made the peace
treaty paid no attention to economic data. They had not taken into consideration the fact that the
populations of Europe, under the influence of an industrial age, had grown to far larger numbers
than Europe's fields can feed."</p>
<p>Not only Europe, but the world as a whole, has more people than it can feed under the present
system of production and distribution. In the face of this fact, so amply and terribly
substantiated, it is not only a mistake but a crime to bring another child into being until
conditions improve.</p>
<p>Masculine statesmanship, commercial policy, and industrial management have wholly failed to cope
with the problem. The all but hopeless case must be taken in hand by the women if we are to avoid
the supreme catastrophe. The one sensible, humane and wise thing to do in the face of increasing
disorganization of the world's productive and distributive machinery is to curtail the number of
those who are to suffer and to starve.</p>
</docBody>
</doc>
