<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011-07-20 NC</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1944-07-00"><supplied resp="MSPP">July
            1944</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Lasting Peace for the War Marriage</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp226160</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Records of PPFA, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>MSM</title>S72:0411</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Margaret Sanger handwrote two alternate titles,
            "When Johnny Comes Back Home" and "Will that War Romance End in
            Divorce?"</p><index level1="divorce" level2="in U.S."/><index
            level1="war" level2="marriage and"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>LASTING PEACE FOR THE WAR MARRIAGE</head>
        <byline>by Margaret Sanger</byline>
        <p>Several people have said in horrified tones to me lately. “<q
                who="UNK">Have you heard how many of these hasty war marriages
                are cracking up? They say hundreds and thousands of applications
                for divorces have been filed, that the only reason they haven't
                gone through yet is that one can't divorce a man in the armed
                forces!</q>”</p>
        <p>I have heard ominous overtones of discontent, of what will happen
            when the soldier gone these many months and years comes home to his
            waiting wife, with whom he's had only a V-mail relation for so long.
            I know that the last war was followed by a tragically high number of
            divorces and that all of us sincerely hope it won't be as bad this
            time.</p>
        <p>On the side of the dire predictors of high divorce rates we have the
            fact that many more young people married in haste during this war
            and that because it is a much longer war, the mental, emotional and
            physical strains have far surpassed those of the last.</p>
        <p>On the brighter side we may hope for more scientific treatment and
            solution of marital problems. Although sex enlightenment has been
            slow and persistently blocked by a few of the more conservative
            religious factions, some steps forward have been taken since the
            last war period. Sex education has advanced along with marriage
            counseling, both privately and in the schools, child spacing
            knowledge has been more widely accepted.</p>
        <p>The easiest way to face a problem is through the human beings
            involved, and all of us have been involved in this war either
            through our own personal problems or those of ones near and dear to
            us.</p>
        <p>I would like to estimate the chances for future happiness of several
            young couples whom I know well, and who are faced with the same
            problems as other young people who have married in war times.</p>
        <p>Bill had to leave Sadie with two babies, quite close together because
            Sadie wanted it that way and Bill knew that he could leave her in
            the care of his relatives. They were carefully planned babies, hence
            their chances for health and happiness even during this period of
            world tragedy were good, for Sadie understood her obligation to be
            both mother and father to them during Bill's absence.</p>
        <p>Sadie knew more than that. She sensed from Bill's letters that war,
            besides being the horror that it is, was a great adventure for Bill,
            that he was meeting new and interesting people, having experiences
            that would never have come to him in the living of an ordinary life.
            She read between the lines Bill's growth, and knew that he wouldn't
            want to return to find her merely the girl he's left behind whose
            outlook was no broader than the space between the constant string of
            diapers on the line and the living room radio.</p>
        <p>So in spite of the fact that it took effort, and time and she was
            often much too tired to have her heart in it, she began taking music
            lessons again. Bill had often said he wished she hadn't neglected
            her music, that it was a shame the way the babies had spoiled it for
            her. She has kept at it persistently since Bill went away and he is
            going to have a pleasant surprise when he comes home. Another thing,
            she's diligently studying Spanish because she knows Bill isn't going
            to be happy at his old auto salesman's job when he returns even if
            autos are being sold again by that time. He's talked of openings in
                <place>South America</place>, of exploring new country, beating
            new tracks; he won't be the old Bill when she returns and she won't
            try to fit him back into the old mold. She will take pride in his
            new ambitions and skills and try to progress with him. I think that
            marriage is headed for permanent success, even though a new Bill
            will come home to meet a new Sadie.</p>
        <p>With the Martins it is different. <person reg="Martin, James">James
                Martin</person> has already been demobilized, one of the 70
            thousand being demobilized daily. For him the war is over, yet it
            isn't really over and this makes things difficult for James. For two
            years in the mud and foxholes of the <place>South Pacific</place>
            he's dreamed of this homecoming to his wife <person
                reg="Martin, Helen">Helen</person>. He didn't dream he'd return
            before the war's end or that constant fighting would shatter his
            nerves almost to the point of exhaustion. The doctors and
            psychiatrists have dismissed James as cured. That he is cured of
            being a soldier. It was a difficult job turning the hundreds of
            thousands of Jameses into soldiers in the first place. They'd been
            taught from infancy, love, and kindness, not to hurt others
            needlessly. The army had to teach them that sometimes it is
            necessary to be ruthless killers, they had to be reconditioned for
            war, taught group thinking, group emotions. Then came the end of the
            war for James Martin. Again he had to be re-educated back to
            peace-time emotions. It isn't easy for him. Fortunately Helen
            realizes this. She's had a difficult time too. She and James chose
            to defer having a baby until the war would be over and the child
            could have both a mother and father. She waited and worked and led a
            very dull life during James' absence. His return would be glorious,
            the end of loneliness and frustration. But it wasn't.</p>
        <p>James found to his horror that the happiness he needed and had
            yearned for most with his wife was denied him partly by his
            eagerness for it. He was impotent. At first this made him impatient
            with his wife, angry with her as well as with himself. How many
            young wives could have remained calm as Helen did, explaining that
            this condition would be temporary, telling James that the horrors
            he'd gone through couldn't be erased immediately. Helen had the
            sense to seek expert advice of a good marriage counsellor; she has
            been willing to wait patiently until James returns fully to the
            cycle of his normal living, from civilian, to solider, back to
            civilian. It involves much more, Helen has learned, as so many
            others will, than just putting on and then taking off the
            uniform.</p>
        <p>These are only two examples; I could cite hundreds and each couple
            will have their own problems of personal adjustment. Some of the
            problems may seem insurmountable; many will give up and rush to the
            divorce courts, or back home to mother. Some husbands will find in
            their haste that they have truly married the wrong girl, and some
            girls will discover to their horror that the dream man in the
            uniform is quite another thing back in civilian life. There will
            inevitably be many divorces. We must expect them. It is the needless
            ones, the ones that can be avoided with a little mutual
            understanding and patience that we want to obviate.</p>
        <p>I wish there could be cut and dried rules for how to be a good
            husband and how to be a good wife. There aren't but there are a few
            precepts that should be followed.</p>
        <p>First of all, remember that marriage is both a concession and a
            demand; a living thing, never static, even during absence. There
            must be constant growth, constant consideration for the other
            partner. Don't be shocked by change but go along with it, encourage
            it, build with your husband or your wife. A recent survey shows that
            among the soldiers already demobilized only about one third want to
            return to their old jobs. The wives must be ready to understand this
            and help the husbands to find new work better suited to new
            talents.</p>
        <p>Second, if your problems of adjustment seem too much for you, seek
            expert advice. The <org>Red Cross</org> will help you, so will the
                <org reg="United Service Organization">USO</org>-<org
                reg="Young Men's Christian Association">YMCA</org> and <org
                reg="Young Women's Christian Association">YWCA</org>. The <org
                reg="Planned Parenthood Federation of America">Planned
                Parenthood Federation</org> in <place reg="New York, NY">New
                York City</place> will give you sources of information on the
            sound planning of your family. That is if your problem is fear of
            having a child or another child before you are quite ready and have
            learned to know each other again and made proper adjustments, go to
            a child spacing clinic. If you want a child and feel that you can't
            have one, this Federation will refer you to a doctor or service to
            help discover and correct this difficulty. Remember there is a
            solution for all your problems and nine times out of ten it need not
            be the divorce courts. Take advantage of the many services existing
            to aid you in your present crises.</p>
        <p>Finally, a little advice to husbands. So far I have laid the emphasis
            on understanding wives. You husbands have a duty too and it is just
            as important for you to be patient and understanding in the
            difficult situation of becoming reacquainted with your wife and
            family. Remember, she has romanticized you, idealized you; don't be
            too great a shock to her. Don't forget her side of this union by
            your urgency, your too sudden demands on her. In some cases you may
            need the counsel of a wise person to help you appreciate your wife's
            viewpoint. Don't be afraid to seek help. She has spent months,
            perhaps years of loneliness and worry. She has remained faithful to
            you having often a pretty dull time doing this. Perhaps she's been
            tied down by your babies. Now she expects romance and consideration.
            She wants appreciation for her waiting part in the war. Perhaps
            she's found the task of being both father and mother to your
            children almost more than her strength or courage could bear. She
            expects not just a husband to return to her but a lover.</p>
        <p>The husband's responsibility in marriage hasn't been stressed much
            until recently. Now it is quite obvious that it is as much to his
            advantage as to his wife's that he help in planning the family. The
            increasing recognition of the father's active part in the home can
            be seen in the new maternity center classes for fathers. I believe a
            School for Husbands should be started to give young husbands
            valuable lessons in how to make their wives happy. Let the husband
            look to himself when his wife seems shrewish and nags. Maybe she is
            frustrated. Maybe he is taking romance for granted or feeling that
            their relationship should be beyond that stage. Maybe he's
            minimizing the pent-up emotions of his wife, the loneliness of his
            long absence. Husbands should realize now that problems of the home,
            including that most important one of spacing the children belong to
            him, provide for his comfort and happiness just as much as for his
            wife's.</p>
        <p>Marriage is a two-way contract. When both parties realize its
            seriousness and try to see the marriage from the viewpoint of one
            another rather than just as an individual problem, there is a chance
            to stop some of those menacing “post-war divorces”. Otherwise we'll
            have too many of the sudden war marriages ending in sudden divorce,
            and too many of our fine large crop of war babies growing up in the
            tragedy of split homes.</p>


    </docBody>
</doc>
