<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
<mepHeader>
<prepDate>2003/06/25 SB</prepDate>
<prepDate>2004/07/27 CH</prepDate>
<prepDate>2004/08/09 CH</prepDate>
<prepDate>2014-03-7 CH clean regs</prepDate>
<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
<docDate value="1920-02-00"> Feb 1920</docDate>
<docTitle>
<titlePart>The Call to Women</titlePart>
</docTitle>
<idno>msp226678</idno>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl><title type="journal">The Birth Control Review</title>, Feb. 1920, 3-4</bibl>
<bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S70:833</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
<respStmt>
<resp/>
<name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
</respStmt>
</mepHeader>
<headNote resp="MSPP"><index level1="birth control" level2="class-based"/><index
level1="Martens, R. C."/><index level1="population" level2="food supply and"/><index
level1="population" level2="excess"/><index level1="women"
level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/></headNote>
<docBody>
<head>The Call to Women</head>
<byline rend="italics">By Margaret Sanger</byline>
<p>No woman who has the welfare of her children and of society at heart should bear a child within
the next five years. Last month we called upon women to adopt this plan in order that the world may
have time to catch up with the task of caring for those people already here. Again we urge this
step--and urge it with all the emphasis at our command.</p>
<p>We directed attention last month to the first of a series of interviews with Mr. <person reg="Martens, R.C.">R. C.
Martens</person>, an authority upon the world food situation. Mr. Martens informed us that Europe's
food supply is on the verge of exhaustion and that there is a world food shortage. That shortage, he
declared, will bring about a crash in world affairs that will result in the starvation of millions
in Europe. It will also have a dire effect upon <place reg="United States"
>America</place>, which effect Mr. Martens is not as yet willing to discuss in detail.</p>
<p>In the interview published in this number, Mr. Martens points out an industrial situation which
strikingly emphasizes what he said last month. It also makes exceedingly plain the need of a
cessation of births as a reconstruction measure.</p>
<p>The gist of the warning by this authority is just this: the world food supply is short. Millions
will starve. Among those who survive, millions will suffer because of the demoralization of industry
as it is now conducted. The great crash is inevitable.</p>
<p>Mr. Martens does not stand alone in predictions of this nature. Business men know that trouble is
here and that more is coming. Financiers have again and again pointed out similar facts. Students of
economics have joined their voices with conservatives and with radical propagandists, crying out
that something must be done.</p>
<p>The world has too many people to care for under existing circumstances. Its machinery of
production is demoralized. It cannot even produce enough food and distribute it. All things are in a
stage of transition, and it will be years before the present state of disorganization
disappears.</p>
<p>Moreover, the human wrecks of the Great War are to be cared for. Again, millions of children were
born in Europe during the war. Most of them have been undernourished; many of them are otherwise
defective, perhaps. Both the cripples of the war and these children are, to a greater or less
degree, public burdens for the rest of their lives. There will be added to these the helpless
individuals produced by the demoralization of our productive machinery.</p>
<p>In the face of these facts the nations should grapple at once with the population problem. They
are not doing so. Instead, some of those madmen whose motto is "<q who="UNK">After us, the
Deluge</q>," are crying for higher birth rates. So the problem of the birth rate comes for solution
to those who have always had to solve it--the women, the bearers of children. And what woman, who
has thought upon the situation, is willing to bring a child into a disordered world, where lack and
misery is likely to be its portion? What woman, through bringing a child to birth, is willing to
make the situation worse?</p>
<p>It was suggested by some of our friends that last month's editorial should have called only for a
cessation of births among the poor. In these days of upheaval, what condition is stable? The rich of
today may be poor tomorrow. The child born in luxury today may, a few years hence, be in no better
condition than the one born in poverty now.</p>
<p>The call goes to all women. Men have refused to apply fundamental remedies to the ills of the
world. It is for women to right the situation by decreasing the pressure of populations. It is for
women to exercise the sacred right of motherhood in refusing to bring a helpless child into a world
that has nothing to offer it but the prospect of misery.</p>
</docBody>
</doc>
