<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Speech">
<mepHeader>
<prepDate>2003/07/15 SR</prepDate>
<prepDate>2003/07/23 SR</prepDate>
<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
<docDate value="1922-03-14"> 14 Mar 1922</docDate>
<docTitle>
<titlePart>War and Population</titlePart>
</docTitle>
<idno>msp226793</idno>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl><title>Birth Control Review</title>, June 1922, 106-7.</bibl>
<bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Smith College Collections</title>, S70:931.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
<respStmt>
<resp/>
<name id="POSBE"> Berliner Post</name>
</respStmt>
</mepHeader>
<headNote resp="MSPP"><p>This is a published version of a speech given by <person
reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person> to the <org reg="Young Men's Christian Association"
>Y.M.C.A.</org> in <place>Toyko, Japan</place>.</p>
<index level1="censorship" level2="in Japan"/>
<index level1="Asia" level2="overpopulation and"/>
<index level1="Europe" level2="overpopulation and"/>
</headNote>
<docBody>
<head>War and Population</head>
<byline>By Margaret Sanger</byline>
<p>I regret exceedingly that I am not allowed to speak to you this afternoon upon the subject of
Birth Control. Why this privilege has been denied me I do not know, for I have addressed audiences
on the subject of Birth Control in nearly every country in <place>Europe</place> and every large
city in the <place>United States</place>. However, I am grateful for small
favors and am pleased that I have been able to gain the permission to address you on the subject of
War and Population.</p>
<p>In 100 years Europe had about doubled her population while the increase of her food supply was
less than 5 per cent. She had been piling up huge debts for future generations to pay. She had piled
up such conditions as slums, unemployment, child-labor, inertness, inefficiency, dependency, and
finally war. The World War which started in Europe in 1914 was the natural result of the manifold
conditions which made such a volcanic eruption inevitable.</p>
<p>During the past 50 years, there was a tendency in every country in Europe to increase its numbers
overwhelmingly in one group and to increase slowly in another. The latter group consists of
individuals who do not let nature control their destinies. Here the forces of fecundity have been
mastered. In this group with slow increase in numbers, conditions are progressive and advanced. The
other group who are at the mercy if the urge of generation are those who have not only increased
their numbers but have increased their problems beyond the development of the social conscience or
the intelligence of the nation. Out of this group in every country in Europe arose the great
problems, both social and economic, with which the world was confronted in 1914.</p>
<p>In some countries, as in <place>England</place>, it was possible through colonization to
alleviate the conditions in this group somewhat by sending the surplus population to
<place>Canada</place>, <place>Australia</place> and other parts of the globe. <place>France</place>,
on the other hand, had kept her numbers more or less stationary and had aimed to develop quality in
her people. It was to France that we turned for culture, for science, for advancement in almost
every line of scientific thought.</p>
<p><place>Germany</place>, however, was the central country in Europe, which, though in some
departments far more advanced than other countries, was blocked in her progress, and her conditions
at home made complex and chaotic. Germany had been the first country in Europe to bring into her
country the largest resources of alleviation for her population. During the dark and middle ages,
Germany had relied upon infant mortality, disease and pestilence to keep her population within
bounds. It was quite a natural event for a family during that period to have from 10 to 20 members,
but for only one or two, or at the most four to survive to full maturity. This was the course which
Nature had taken to lessen the possibility of war and to keep nations somewhat at peace with each
other.</p>
<p>With the advance of humanitarian thought and scientific and preventative medicine, Germany began
to check her death rate, but to increase her problems. The urge for expansion on the part of the
increasing population in any country when brought up against geographical barriers acts blindly in
the direction of conflict--whether in colonial rivalry or territorial swarming. The opportunities
for Germany's expansion were strictly limited by other powers and the prosperity due to the opening
of new countries had long passed its maximum. The possibilities for expansion that were open a
century ago were fairly well exhausted and Germany found herself with serious problems on her hands
which meant national expansion or ultimate stagnation. We find then the situation in Germany to be a
rapidly increasing population brought largely to full maturity at a great expense to the government
through social service, old age pensions, maternity benefits, ect., while the necessaries for
feeding this population were out of her reach, making her dependent upon other countries for the
subsistence of her people. There was a tendency too, toward a surplus of highly trained professional
and technical men. The elaborate educational system of Germany was producing more engineers,
surveyors, electrical engineers, industrial chemists, and experts along various lines than the
nation's industries could utilize or absorb. The result was that such men had to be content with a
smaller wage than unskilled workingmen could procure, or emigrate into foreign lands where skill and
inventiveness became the assets of other countries at Germany's cost.</p>
<p>While Germany's birth rate was on the decline--in 1900 it was 36.5, in 1909, 32. and in 1913,
29.5--the number of deaths diminished also by such proportion that her rate of survival became
higher, and her population increased in a faster proportion than it had done with the higher birth
rate. There was an increase of from 700,000 to 800,000 souls a year, which amounted to nearly four
millions of new individuals every five years. It was upon such conditions briefly and fragmentarily
related here, that Germany based her claim to a place in the sun and the right of livelihood of her
surplus population. The <title type="journal">Berliner Post</title> in 1913 said: "<q who="POSBE">
Can a great and rapidly growing nation like Germany always renounce all claims to further
development or to the expansion of its political power? The final settlement with France and
England, the expansion of our colonial possessions in order to create new German homes for the
overflow of our population...these are the problems which must be faced in the near future</q>."</p>
<p>If one studies the comments of the press during the five years preceding the great war, one will
find that the argument of the right of any country to prepare for war was based upon her increasing
and growing population. Germany in 1910 had a population of 70,000,000. At the rate she was
increasing she was bound to have in a short time double that number. It was the argument of her
militarists and others who were making greater demands for Germany that she must find an outlet for
her people, that Germany was hungry for trade, that she needed colonies, that she could not confine
her growing population within her narrow geographical boundaries. </p>
<p>In one magazine, the <person reg="Wilhelm II (Germany)"> Kaiser</person> was quoted as having said
that in 1950 Germany would possess a population of two hundred millions or something near to it. It
might have been supposed that counsels, such as those emanating from the best of thinking Germans,
might have been critical of this condition of things, but, extraordinary as it may seem, the Marxian
philosophy has taken a strong hold upon the people of Germany and particularly of the working people
during the preceding 25 years, and had inculcated the doctrine that the greater the numbers of the
proletariat the higher would be their wages, the stronger their demands in the labor market and the
larger the numbers in the ranks of the revolutionists. Hence up to 1914 there was every tendency on
the part of the thinkers of Germany, both economic, social and political, to approve the increase in
their numbers and to trust to the gods the results, believing that <emph rend="italics">might makes
right!!</emph></p>
<p>This, briefly, is one of the chief causes of the war in Europe in 1914. We all know the results
and the consequences, but none of us can foretell the terrific decadent consequences which Germany
is <emph rend="italics"> yet</emph> to feel. Her most fit manhood was slaughtered in the war, her
mothers and children left at home in a condition of physical starvation which must affect the
generations of the future. When I was in Germany in 1920 and saw for myself more than 10,000 little
starving infants, the results of the blockade and the war, I felt that it would be far kinder for
Germany's future and for the future peace of the world to humanely allow these little victims to
pass away rather then to keep them alive to perpetuate disease and misery. More then 45 per cent. of
the women of Germany were made permanently sterile owing to the lack of food and the improper
nourishment for child-bearing. The present conditions in Germany include extremely heavy taxes, low
value of money, deficiency of labor in many establishments, scarcity of food and cost of living so
dear that the average wage-earner lives upon a ration which means partial starvation.</p>
<p>The conclusion to be drawn from Germany are that a nation will not find the solution of its
problems in war: that war is no longer the way to settle international disputes. Nevertheless we
cannot hope for world peace until all nations recognize that there are fundamental dynamic forces at
work which must be controlled. These forces are hunger and propagation, and we cannot solve one
without including the other. Until these forces are recognized and acted upon wisely, the idea of
international peace will remain a dream and a myth.</p>
<p><place>Japan</place> has problems today which are becoming as great as those of Germany in 1914.
She has a right to have those problems solved in a rational, humanitarian way, but until our
diplomats and statesmen recognize the causes of war and make a study of the population question in
all its manifold departments, all our <org reg="League of Nations">Leagues of Nations</org>,
international conferences, agreements and international treaties will become the proverbial "scraps
of paper." Men and women of Japan, I appeal to you to look into this subject thoroughly. The women
and mothers in your country are just as desirous of wiping out poverty, misery, suffering and war as
the women of the other nations of the world. I appeal to you to set your motherhood free! To make
your women something more than breeding machines, such as the women of every nation have been during
some period of that nation's development. The time has come for international brotherhood and
international emancipation, based upon free, conscious maternity.</p>
<p>The advancement of hygiene and sanitation and welfare work in any country only increase its
population problem. Population must then find its outlet through emigration or armed invasion of
some other country. Each nation must control its population to the point where it will not be
necessary to make aggression upon its neighbors. </p>
<p>The study of the population will reveal to you the initial cause of the suffering of mankind, it
will reveal the cause for its struggles and its divisions into factions and parties. It will point
out the remedy for these differences and the way to establish a new order of civilization. To the
working man, it will show that his state of oppression under tyranny can exist only as a result of
his ignorance; that the struggle between classes, between capital and labor, and the wars between
nations are the inevitable consequences of that ignorance. The working man has himself been the
producer of these conditions through his unlimited procreative powers--unchecked and uncontrolled;
while he and his brother are the initial sufferers from the flagrant inequalities found in all
nations today. </p>
<p>Let us then, friends, depart from the old methods of quantity production, and turn our attention
to producing quality in our peoples. It will then be possible for everyone to have independence and
personal dignity; motherhood will be glorified, and the nation may expect to promote for its
population peace, justice, happiness, and the International Brotherhood of the World.</p>
</docBody>
</doc>
