<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Review">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2003/07/30 SR</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-04-09 CH clean regs</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-09 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1924-03-00">Mar 1924</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>A Review by Margaret Sanger Introducing Hugh de Selincourt</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp226799</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title>, Mar. 1924, pp. 87-88.</bibl>
			<bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Smith College Collections</title>
				S70:1045</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="BLAWI">Blake, William</name>
			<name id="SELHU">de Selincourt, Hugh</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<index level1="DeSelincourt, Hugh" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="men" level2="sexuality of"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>A Review by <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person> Introducing Hugh
			de Selincourt</head>
		<p>Appropriately <person reg="de Selincourt, Hugh">Hugh de Selincourt</person> dedicates
			this book to <person reg="Ellis, Havelock">Havelock Ellis</person>. In his ability to
			face facts of life that are as a rule sedulously avoided even by the most desperate of
			realists, by the very calmness and serenity of his courage to spiritualize phases of
			life that are dismissed by the all-too-prurient as "ugly" or "unpleasant," and to reveal
			the organic relationship of these facts to the very root and heart of life, Hugh de
			Selincourt must be acclaimed as the legitimate disciple of the most inspiring humanist
			of our times.</p>
		<p>I do not mean to suggest that "<title type="book">One Little Boy</title>" is any mere
			"case history" of sexual aberration. On the contrary: Hugh de Selincourt has achieved
			something which might baffle even more expert craftsmen of fiction. He wastes no time on
			non-essentials. He brings the young mother of his story face-to-face with the sexual
			awakening of her young son, a lad of eleven. He makes this attractive young
			Englishwoman, who has been left a widow with two children, awaken to the realization of
			her own inability to cope with these primal mysteries. <person
				reg="Hullerston, Mrs. (fictional)">Mrs. Hullertson</person> found that a child's
			pursuit of truth is relentless. "<q who="SELHU">To him there is no danger in knowledge:
				you travel light at the age of eleven, speeded by natural modesty and unweighted by
				false shame.</q>"</p>
		<p>"<q who="SELHU">Mrs. Hullerston felt that <person reg="Hullerston, Graham (fictional)"
					>Graham</person> was somehow a challenge to the foundations of which the fabric
				of her life was built. Her wish to be his friend was too genuine to allow her to be
				satisfied in fobbing him off or damping him down with the commonplaces that slipped
				from her tongue. It was no good dismissing his questions as naughtiness: they were
				patently genuine: yet she was unable to answer them...</q>" How Mrs. Hullertson
			appeals to the schoolmaster for help; the absolute failure of that worthy to meet a
			universal human problem, though one hundred and fifty growing boys had been entrusted to
			his guardianship; how Graham must perforce turn to other sources for answers and
			guidance; and the final solution, all make a significant and vivid tale. "<title
				type="book">One Little Boy</title>" is a book for every parent, a book especially
			for every mother. Nothing published in recent years possesses to such a degree the power
			to awaken parents to the problems they must face in directing the deep-rooted impulses
			of their children into normal healthy channels.</p>
		<p>"<title type="book">One Little Boy</title>" is interwoven with irony and satire. But
			there is no stridency, no anger, in the pen of Hugh de Selincourt. Like his master
			Havelock Ellis, there is only gentleness, tenderness, understanding. This curious blend
			of qualities makes possible an even greater daring in frankness of expression than the
			ordinary, since the author unites unusual power of expression with a fine delicacy of
			perception. He is never offensive nor shocking. When we finish reading "<title
				type="book">One Little Boy</title>" we realize as never before that the sins of the
			fathers which are visited upon the children are too often psychic sins--the sins of
			pruriency, hypocrisy, suppression and inhibition, diseases which may be more devastating
			to the younger generation than actual physical aliments. Unless we are honest,
			straightforward and frank ourselves, we cannot expect our children to be healthy.</p>
		<p>Because Hugh de Selincourt has himself become a master of the difficult art of life,
			because he possesses calm courage and luminous vision, this theme becomes beautiful
			instead of bitter. One shudders to think what it might have become in the hands of a man
			who understood life less, even though he might be a greater craftsman in fiction than
			Mr. de Selincourt.</p>
		<p>This book is infused with the life-giving beauty of a great spirit. Not without
			significance is the fact that he lives in a sixteenth-century house in <place
				reg="Sussex, England">Sussex</place> once occupied by <person
				reg="Shelley, Percy Bysshe">Shelley</person>. Hugh de Selincourt possesses something
			of the flame-like purity of Shelley. And in another sense he is a descendant of <person
				reg="Blake, William">Blake</person>, proclaiming with the poet:</p>
		<p rend="blockquote">"<q who="BLAWI">Thou art a man. <name type="deity">God</name> is no
				more. Thy own Humanity lean to adore.</q>"</p>
		<p>There is moreover, something Greek in his outlook on life. But this classical aspect is
			never akin to the orchidaceous aestheticism of <person reg="Pater, Walter"
				>Pater</person>. For devout as he is in his worship of beauty, Hugh de Selincourt
			has reached the profounder conviction that there can be no true beauty in humanity
			without health. Perhaps it is this realization that has led him to desert the hectic
			bustle of <place reg="London, England">London</place> life, to flee far from the
			literary market place, to cultivate his garden in the "<q who="SELHU">green and
				pleasant</q>" land of Sussex, or to play cricket on the village green of <place
				reg="Pulborough, England">Pulborough</place>. Unlike Mr. <person
				reg="Shaw, George Bernard">Shaw</person>, he has not beaten the drum before his own
			show booth. And so, even in <place>England</place>, where some ten or twelve of his
			books have already been published, Hugh de Selincourt remains comparatively unknown.
			But, as in the case of <person reg="Hudson, William Henry">W. H. Hudson</person>, his
			reputation is bound to attract more and more attention among those who are interested in
			the everpresent and profoundly simple truths of human life.</p>
		<p>I can think of no more praiseworthy inauguration of a young and ambitious publishing
			house in this country than the introduction to American readers of the best novel yet
			written by so fine a spirit as Hugh de Selincourt. For he is so much more than merely a
			novelist engaged in telling an entertaining story. He should become one of the guiding
			spirit of our young century. No one more penetratingly or more eloquently has expressed
			for us the eternal beautiful unity of body and spirit; no one has more reverently, and
			yet without the faintest trace of sentimentality, depicted the sacred relationship that
			exists between mother and child. For this reason, for exhibiting the courage and daring
			to present this book "<title type="book">One Little Boy</title>" to American readers, I
			must express my unqualified gratitude to Messrs. <person reg="Boni, Albert"
				>Albert</person> and <person reg="Boni, Charles">Charles Boni</person>.</p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
