<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Draft Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011-07-20 NC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-24 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1944-06-00"><supplied resp="MSPP">June, 1944</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Editorial on Venereal Disease for Writer's War Board</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp226893</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Records of PPFA, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S72:0400</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Handwritten additions were made by Margaret Sanger. For draft versions
            see S72:0397 and 0402.</p><index level1="venereal disease"/><index
            level1="venereal disease" level2="prevention of"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Editorial on Venereal Disease for <org>Writers' War Board</org></head>
        <byline>by <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></byline>
        <p>The mere words VENEREAL DISEASE so terrified the <del>American public</del>
            <add>Federal officials</add> thirty years ago that the <org
                reg="United States Post Office">Post Office</org> department twice suppressed the
                <title type="journal">New York Sunday Call</title>
            <add>a paper circulated mainly among workers,</add> for printing two articles of mine
            under the title, “<title type="book">What Every Girl Should know</title>,” one
                <del>about</del>
            <add>dealing with</add> syphilis, the other about gonorrhea. These diseases were then
            considered to be of <del>no possible interest to the</del>
            <add>such offensive nature (or subject) that the</add> average person, <add>could not
                openly be seen reading such matter</add> even though the average man or woman quite
            often became the one-in-ten to contract syphilis <add>or that they could not be publicly
                discussed.</add></p>
        <p>Today the <org>United States Government</org> has a <org
                reg="United States Public Health Service">Public Health Department</org> whose
                <person reg="Parran, Thomas, Jr.">official head</person> is valiantly trying to bring
            knowledge and enlightenment to the people of this nation of that same subject of
            venereal disease. Sound sex knowledge is increasingly recognized as one of the surest
            safeguards for young and old alike. The problem has to a great extent shed its chrysalis
            of false modesty and is recognized for what it is--a serious national health issue.
                <add>&amp; hopefully one of both prevention &amp; of cure.</add></p>
        <p>More and more it is realized that the problem is one that affects all <del>parents</del>
            <add>adults</add>. It is no longer solely the concern of the prostitute and the
            philandering male, but of the mother who may give birth to stillborn or blind syphilitic
            babies, and most tragically of all, of our own youth, our boys and girls in their teens.
                <add>who may innocently contact others in work or <gap reason="illegible"
                    extent="one word"/></add></p>
        <p>The <org>New York Health Department</org> recently reported there is the great increase
            in cases of syphilis for the first ten months of 1943. Among girls of 15 to 19 years the
            increase over the same period of the preceding year was 83% and for both sexes of this
            age the increase was 108.3%. Multiply this by figures throughout the country, in
            boomtown areas where conditions are very bad. Add to this the many young boys afflicted,
            the men being treated in the array and you have a growing picture, a tidal wave that
            must be stopped, that demands the full cooperation of all of us. We are fighting the
                <del>terrible</del>
            <add>ghastly</add> world war with stern realism; we must fight our domestic battle on
            the health front with the same realism.</p>
        <p>Penicillin and sulfa drugs are making many cures possible in brief periods of time, but
            until the last shred of false modesty is torn from the study of venereal disease, until
            we give diseased women the knowledge of how to defer births of offspring until they have
            fully recovered from gonorrhea and syphilis, we will continue to increase our tragic
            toll of blind infants, of stillbirths, of human beings crippled physically and mentally,
            burdens to themselves and to the state.</p>
        <p>In addition to all the government is now doing, an educational plan should be advanced
            preparing men and women not only to report any symptoms immediately but to realize the
            importance of being isolated as the Board of Health isolates diptharia,
            measles or scarlet fever. This may seem to be a harsh part of the cure, but ignorance or
            carelessness has and is causing suffering to innocent persons and should no longer be
            tolerated or appeased by government squeamishness.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
