<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2003/06/26 JA</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/02 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/08/09 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007/08/28 CH Oxygen update</prepDate><prepDate>2014-03-07 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1919-10-00">Oct 1919</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Meeting the Need Today</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp226864</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title>, Oct. 1919, 14-15</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S70:826</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Comstock act"/>
        <index level1="midwives" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="nurses" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="physicians" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="sex education" level2="need for"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Meeting the Need Today</head>
        <byline>
            <emph rend="italics">By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></emph>
        </byline>
        <p>It is indeed a strange task for me to seek for the medical profession a right which has
            neglected to claim for itself. None knows better than I, perhaps, the indifference,
            neglect and evasion which has so generally characterized the attitude of physicians
            toward Birth Control. Be its sins of omission and commission what they may, however, the
            fact that we are compelled to make use of the skill and the knowledge of the medical
            profession in order to meet a definite situation should not deter us from meeting that
            situation. I believe that our present problem of bringing relief <emph rend="italics"
                >now</emph> to hundreds of thousands of suffering women can be most effectively
            solved (so far as legislation can solve it) by the enactment of the so-called
                "doctors and nurses' bill." </p>
        <p>What is the situation that we must meet <emph rend="italics">today</emph>? Let us take
            stock of the human elements that we have to work with. First, we have the mass of men
            and women who are ignorant of their own bodies and especially of the physiology of their
            sex organs. We have also three closely related classes of people who do possess
            knowledge of the human body and of he physiology of sex -- the only classes of persons
            who have made a special study of the subject. They are the doctors, nurses and midwives.
            This constitutes our first big fact.</p>
        <p>The second fact to be faced is that there exists in this state a law forbidding anyone,
            even doctors, nurses and midwives to give information concerning contraceptives to
            anyone. This law is now in existence, it is in operation at this hour and at this hour
            women are suffering and dying because of its tyrannous enforcement.</p>
        <p>The third fact is that the only classes of persons who can bring effective help to the
            sufferers are restrained from doing so by the operation of the law, though the masses,
            who are ignorant of the physiology of sex, very generally disregard it. The only
            practical effect -- the real tragedy of the present law -- is that it deprives us of
            knowledge and skill of the only persons who are capable of instructing the masses. So
            far as free speech is concerned it is impossible to deprive the individual woman of that
            right in regard to Birth Control. The state cannot put a policeman in every home. So,
            law or no law, women are giving to each other the scanty Birth Control information
            available under present conditions. But the trained persons, who are best qualified to
            impart scientific information, are silent. They will remain silent while the law is
            unchanged. If every woman's organs were exactly alike and if one method would meet the
            needs of every woman, the existence or change of the present law would make little
            difference. But every woman's organs are likely to be in a different condition according
            to the number of children she has borne, the kind of work she is doing, and the kind of
            care and medical skill she has had the benefit of. These conditions complicate and make
            necessary individual advice in Birth Control methods if the woman is to be assured
            protection against pregnancy.</p>
        <p>WHERE SHALL WOMEN get this individual attention? Certainly they cannot get it from any
            other agency than a doctor, a nurse or a midwife. The majority of those who need Birth
            Control most, usually come into contact with a doctor or a nurse who is connected with
            some dispensary or other public agency. And while doctors in private practice may run
            the risk of violating the law, the doctor or nurse in public practice is not likely to
            invite attack of the prejudiced clericals who permeate all public and semi-public
            institutions.</p>
        <p>We know of cases in which women suffering from tuberculosis, syphilis and other diseases
            in which pregnancy is a direct danger to her life are being refused contraceptive
            information at the dispensaries and hospitals at which they are under treatment. This is
            the real tragedy of the present law. The chief practical benefit to be derived from a
            change of the law is the opening of these institutions and others like them yet to be
            established, to the women who need Birth Control. The doctors and nurses bill will best
            accomplish that result.</p>
        <p>This so-called "obscenity law" has never held the respect of many
            Birth Control advocates. The very genesis of the movement was the conscious, deliberate
            and public violation of this statute. The most important thing in the movement is not to
            change the law, but to relieve the suffering of overburdened women, law or no law.
            Meanwhile, however, it becomes desirable incidentally, to seek to change the statute, in
            order that the millions of women who depend upon dispensaries and similar institutions,
            may receive relief at capable hands. These, at least, can be helped now. They, at least,
            can regain health, obtain time for self-improvement, and be of use in the larger
            struggle from human freedom. This is our present task. The "doctors and
                nurses' bill" goes most effectively to this point.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
