<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011-07-29 NC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011-09-15 EK upload + index terms</prepDate><prepDate>2014-03-30 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1950-02-13">13 Feb 1950</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Response to MacArthur</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp227963</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S72:0052</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
            <name id="MACDO">MacArthur, Douglas</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>The following was a press release issued by the <org>Planned Parenthood
                Federation of America</org>.</p>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="population policies of"/>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="government of"/>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="U.S. occupation of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="in Japan"/>
        <index level1="MacArthur, Douglas"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>STATMENT BY <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">MARGARET SANGER</person></head>
        <dateline><date value="1951-02-13">RELEASED FEBRUARY 13, 1950</date></dateline>
        <p>I must refuse to accept as final the reported decision of <person
                reg="MacArthur, Douglas">Gen. MacArthur</person> that I may not come to
                <place>Japan</place> at the invitation of the Japanese. That an American can be
            barred from a perfectly proper mission by the bigotry or whim of other Americans is
            intolerable.</p>
        <p>This is not the first time I was told I could not visit Japan. In 1921 I was refused
            permission by the Imperial <org>Japanese government</org>. It is tragic to see that our
            Occupation authorities, while mouthing democratic principles, are emulating the old
            Japanese military regime. However, in 1921 the angry protests of the people forced the
            lifting of the ban. I am confident that something of the same sort will occur in
            1950.</p>
        <p>When I asked to have Gen. MacArthur reconsider the refusal to admit me, I believed he
            meant what he was quoted as saying last July--<q who="MACDO">that birth control was a
                matter for the Japanese peple and the Occupation had a policy of hands off.</q> I
            hope that this attitude will be resumed. Anything else is a denial of the right of the
            Japanese to decent and healthy family life. Anything else is a denial of the basic
            democracy which we are trying to help this people achieve.</p>
        <p>My invitation came from the press, health officials and private groups. They wanted me to
            advise them on carrying out their new laws which legalize birth control, because they
            know that it is the only way to halt the disastrous rise in population.</p>
        <p>If I can help them in applying their new laws on birth control, I mean to do so. I shall
            continue to work for a reversal of any ruling that seeks to stop me.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
