<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/05/24 CE</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/06/21 CE Corrections</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1942-11-00">Nov 1942</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied>Shall the War Bride have a Baby
                Now?</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp228416</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith
                College.</bibl>
            <bibl><title>MSM</title> S72:0366.</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="birth control" level2="war and"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="population growth and"/>
        <index level1="family planning"/>
        <index level1="feeble-minded persons"
            level2="fertility and birth rate of"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="infant"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="maternal"/>
        <index level1="population" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="population" level2="war and"/>
        <index level1="race suicide"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="population of"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
        <index level1="World War II" level2="population and"/>
        <index level1="World War II" level2="women and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head><emph rend="underline">Message from <person reg="Sanger, Margaret"
                    >Margaret Sanger</person></emph></head>
        <p>I have been honored with the invitation to send a message to women
            over your station and I feel the most timely message at this time
            would be to those millions of women who are deeply involved in this
            war. You are being asked to take the place of men in industry, even
            to join the <org reg="United States Army">army</org>, <org
                reg="United States Navy">navy</org>, and <org
                reg="United States Air Force">air corps</org>. You will be, in
            increasing numbers, doing a man's work in this war. Yet you are also
            expected to bear and raise the nation's children, her future
            citizens. Throughout the country the question has been a burning
            issue, “Shall the war bride have a baby now, or shall she wait
            until the more settled conditions of peace time after the war?”</p>
        <p>Present rising birth rates show that many of you are making the
            decision of having babies now, of perpetuating the man you love. For
            those of you who are physically, emotionally and economically able
            to undertake this added a burden under present conditions, I say go
            ahead, more power to you. But consider wisely these facts, ask
            yourself these serious questions.</p>
        <p>Will I be able to support this child in the event my husband does not
            return? Or if her should return a helpless invalid or cripple?</p>
        <p>Will my child suffer in the event of a prolonged war and the severe
            rationing of food, as a children in <place>Europe</place> are
            suffering?</p>
        <p>Will my anxiety for the return of my husband affect the child after
            he is born -- even before he is born?</p>
        <p>Is my own health, my emotional stability, equal to the strain of
            making it possible for me to bear a healthy normal child under
            present conditions?</p>
        <p>Most of all, is it fair to deprive my child of his father during his
            early years, perhaps for all his life?</p>
        <p>It is difficult to give these matters reasoned consideration during
            troubled emotional times such as these, when the instinct of a woman
            is to perpetuate the one she loves and may lose, but it is unfair to
            the child, to herself, to society, if she lets her emotions
            over-rule her reasoned considerations.</p>
        <p>There is no danger of race-suicide in <place>America</place>; our
            birth-rate is the highest in our history and rising steadily. Our
            national concern now should be for quality, for healthier babies and
            mothers, fewer infant and maternal mortalities, fewer social misfits
            who should never have been born and are a rising burden on
            society.</p>
        <p>Stories come from all over the nation of incredibly crowded
            conditions in maternity hospitals, babies being delivered in
            doctors' offices, in trailers, mothers sent home from hospitals with
            their infants immediately after delivery. Conditions such as these
            are bound to affect the mortality statistics of mothers and new born
            babies. Consider these things; consider the fact that many more
            millions of you will be needed in industry before this war is won,
            before you rashly and emotionally succumb to an instinct to bear a
            war baby. You chances for happiness may be much greater in many
            cases if both you and your husband wait until the grim business of
            war is over, and times are more nearly normal again.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
