<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2002-01-07 CH</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2002-08-15 KH</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2004/08/09 CH</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-03-10 CH clean regs</prepDate><prepDate>2014-12-15 CH correct and enter tags</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1921-11-11">11 Nov 1921</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>The Use of The Pessary</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp229952</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</bibl>
			<bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Smith College Collections</title> S67:754-757</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="DEVLY">DeVilbiss, Lydia </name>
			<name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote>
		<p><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger</person> gave this talk at a doctors-only session
			in contraceptives at the <org reg="American Birth Control Conference, 1st">First American Birth Control Conference</org> in <place
				reg="New York, NY">New York City</place>. This session was not included in the
			published proceedings.</p>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="methods and devices" level3="pessaries (diaphragm)"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<p>Madam <person reg="DeVilbiss, Lydia Allen">chairman</person>, and friends. In <place
				reg="Netherlands">Holland</place> the particular method that is recommended there is
			the <supplied resp="MSPP">occlusive</supplied> pessary. More than thirty five years ago at the
			medical congress of <place reg="Amsterdam, Netherlands">Amsterdam</place>, the
			physicians decided that this subject of birth control was one that must be
				<unclear>taught</unclear> to their people if they would remain within their borders.
			At once the medical profession began to test out the use of a pessary. They have from
			that time on used and recommended what is called the <supplied resp="MSPP"><person
					reg="Mensigna, Wilhelm">Mensinga</person></supplied> pessary, which has, I
			believe, seven sizes. It is a little different from the one used in
				<place>England</place> and also the one used in the <place>United States</place>.
			This is made of different material and different sizes. Altogether I have seen as many
			as fourteen different pessaries devised and effected in Holland. Now, the physicians
			soon came to recognize that it was quite necessary to take their time, to find a way to
			teach the woman who was normal the use of a pessary, and so <person
				reg="Rutgers, Johannes">Dr. Rutgers</person>, who was most interested in this
			subject at that time, has instructed the nurses how to fit the pessary upon a normal
			woman who is not suffering from disease. It is most interesting to see these women come
			to these clinics and to be there and to witness the instruction. They are first taught
			to douche. A small syringe is used, and they are taught the use of this syringe. Next
			this pessary is inserted with soapsuds and is fitted. The nurse does this until she gets
			the correct size. When this round one does not fit, there is another kind which does fit
			almost always. You see what that does? It covers the whole wall. It is not like the
			small American pessary which I will show you later. That is the kind of pessary that is
			used in <place>Germany</place>, and in <place>Austria</place>, and in Holland.</p>
		<p>This small pessary is the one that is used in <place>France</place> and now has been
			taken on in England.</p>
		<p>My personal experience from women whose records I have is that this is the kind of
			pessary that accidents happen from. This can be pushed aside. It does not seem to have
			the same skin, and it does not seem to fit so well over the cervix as that other kind
			which is called here the <supplied>'mizpah'</supplied>. The top comes off and seems to
			be a more practical kind.</p>
		<p>This kind, the little one, the French pessary, has been used in France for many years,
			and of course there have been no records kept so you cannot tell how many times this has
			failed.</p>
		<p>In England today this is the method being used there in the so-called mother clinics. In
			America we have the records of the 1250 families who have used methods successfully for
			at least one year; the pessary, 335 families have used the pessary followed by a douche,
			of which 265 have used the douche following the use of the pessary; the condom--355
			people have used the condom successfully, and 171 of these people have followed the use
			of it by a douche; next on record is the suppository, 181 families have used
			suppositories, and 108 have followed it by a douche. The other methods that are here, an
			antiseptic douche, only 264 people. Most of us know that an antiseptic douche is not a
			preventative, but is a hygienic measure. Coitus <supplied resp="MSPP">interruptus</supplied>, 175
			families have used that method, 61 have followed by a douche.</p>
		<p>This is recent information we have had of people in the United States who have used those
			methods and have been willing to give us the information.</p>
		<p>As far as pessaries are concerned, I think that the kind used in Holland is the best. The
			records there for five years show that there were only 1% failure, and five years
			previously 3% were failure. But they claim that if a woman is normal, if her organs are
			normal, and if she is taught and knows how to insert a pessary, that this practice
			cannot fail.</p>
		<p>Now, they do not advise the woman to leave this in the body only over night. The next day
			when the husband is gone and the children are out at school, the woman is advised to
			take a cleansing douche and to wash the pessary and put it away. The reason they like it
			best is because it is not expensive; the only cost is its first outlay. And before the
			war they had the right kind of rubber and it was supposed to last from three to five
			years, and the charges were something like a gilder or a gilder and a half, which meant
			about sixty cents. Altogether the pessary is considered in Holland and in France the
			most successful method of birth control. (applause)</p>
		<p>THE CHAIRMAN: <q who="DEVLY">I have asked Mrs. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret"
					>Sanger</person> if this type of pessary was available in America. And she told
				me not this kind. In as much as this is the kind we are able to get in America, I
				would like to ask her if they use an ointment or something like it in connection
				with this.</q></p>
		<p>MRS. SANGER: The idea is this. A little powder, any antiseptic dry powder in the cup
			before it is put on doubly secures against pregnancy, particularly if it is well fitted.
			That is always one reason why I have stood so definitely for the principle of birth
			control being disseminated by the medical profession. As a nurse myself, I know that all
			women are not alike, that they are different. That it means individual examination or
			individual instruction. And with powder placed in the cup before it is inserted, and
			with the woman taught how to insert it, we have had a great deal of success, and very
			few failures with the right kind of pessary.</p>
		<p>QUESTION. <q who="UNK">Will you kindly state what kind of powder?</q></p>
		<p>MRS. SANGER: Boric powder, and even bicarbonate of soda.</p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
