<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2003/07/01 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/01 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/11/28 CH correct typos</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-01 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1921-11-11">11 Nov 1921</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Opening Address to the First American Birth Control Conference</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp229953</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S67:800</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>This speech was given at the opening session of the <org reg="American Birth Control
            Conference, 1st">First American Birth Control
                Conference</org>, held at the <org>Hotel McAlpin</org> in <place reg="New York, NY">New York
                City</place>. For an incomplete draft version see Library of Congress Microfilm 129:698.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="international"/>
        <index level1="eugenics" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="eugenics" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="First American Birth Control Conference (1921)"/>
        <index level1="&quot;unfit&quot; to reproduce" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="&quot;unfit&quot; to reproduce" level2="social burdens, as "/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="socioeconomic conditions"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <p>Madam chairman, and ladies and gentlemen: I am glad to join with Mrs. <person
                reg="Hooker, Edith Houghton">Hooker</person> in her welcome of you here today. I
            cannot tell you what this conference means to me. I cannot tell you with what enthusiasm
            we have all be inspired by the results of the letters and the answers that we have had
            while we have been getting up this conference. I cannot tell you how much I appreciate
            the assistance and help of all those of you who are here, and the thousands of others
            who have written us and encouraged us to go ahead with this great work at this
            particular time.</p>
        <p>The idea in calling together this conference was to bring together not our old friends
            and advocates who have been putting the idea of birth control forward for the last few
            years, but the idea has been rather to bring to us new people, new ideas, of those who
            have been working in social agencies, those who have been working in other groups for
            the same result, namely a better nation, a better people in our nation.</p>
        <p>And so we rejoice to have you here who are representing other social activities, health
            agencies, and we have thought and we hope that you will give us new ideas, as we hope
            that you will listen attentively to what is being read here, and that you will also be
            inspired by some thing to help you further your own work and your own cause.</p>
        <p>We are today confronted in the <place reg="United States">United
                States</place> with various problems. One of the serious problems is that the fit
            and healthy members of our community are carrying the burden of the unfit members of the
            community. Everywhere we look we see that poverty and large families go hand in hand.
            Everywhere we look we see that we for the past quarter of a century have been putting
            the energy and the efforts of our healthy and fit elements into bricks and mortar. We
            have been building up environment while we have paid very little attention to the
            quality of human life. We have erected palatial residences for the unfit, for the
            insane, for the feeble-minded, and for those who should not have been born, to say
            nothing of being able to carry on the next generation. We are confronted with this
            problem and everywhere we see that the sentiment of our people has developed far beyond
            human intelligence.</p>
        <p>We are in a condition of society today, not only here but practically in every country in
            the world, where the masses of the unfit have propagated to such an extent that our
            intelligence is not able to grasp the conditions or to cope with the conditions which
            this has created. Now the time has come when we must all join together in stopping at
            its course, misery, ignorance, delinquency and crime.</p>
        <p>And that is the program of the birth control platform. That is what the birth control
            movement intends to do, to stop at its source these qualities which are making for a
            weakened and a deteriorated race.</p>
        <p>There have been two instincts which have ever guided mankind in its destiny. Those two
            instincts are hunger and sex. The instinct of hunger has received consideration in
            practically every civilized country and man has adapted his institutions to meet these
            needs. But the instinct of sex has been ignored. Now I claim, and most of us who make a
            study of this subject know, that this instinct is just as deep, is just as fundamental a
            thing as the instinct of hunger. It cannot be crushed. It cannot be ignored. It cannot
            be denied, not can it be thwarted by denying it. But we must understand it. We must
            recognize it, and we must in recognizing and studying it, we will then utilize it as we
            utilize music and prayer for our higher powers and for a higher illumination.
            (applause)</p>
        <p>The question that confronts us is, is it desirable that man shall control this instinct.
            Is it desirable that this instinct may be satisfied without increasing the population of
            the world? Is mankind to be benefitted by obtaining control over this instinct? And is
            it desirable that in satisfying it we shall say whether offspring shall be the result of
            this or not. The question we will try to answer today is, is it desirable to obtain
            control over this instinct? Is it desirable that the unhealthy, the unfit, the feeble
            members of the community shall propagate their kind and fill the world with their
            offspring? Is it right for these to populate the world, as has been done, or shall some
            stringent war measure be taken to stop this if we are to survive. After discussing the
            desirability of these questions, the next question to be discussed will be the
            possibility of bringing this about.</p>
        <p>We all know that knowledge is power. Man has a right to all knowledge. Ignorance is not a
            virtue, nor is it a safeguard against immorality. If there is knowledge which enables
            man to control birth, or to control conception, then it is only right on principle that
            he should have all knowledge, and he should be able to obtain that result.</p>
        <p>The proceedings of this conference will be to discuss these two subjects. We must first
            establish the principle of the right of birth control. We must encourage this principle
            to be accepted by other agencies and to have this placed into the programs of other
            agencies for peace, for social betterment, and for a better world.</p>
        <p>The idea of birth control is not new. It has been advocated almost from the very earliest
            history of man. We know that <person>Plato</person> and <person>Aristotle</person>
            advocated it. It has been advocated by practically all the greatest philosophers and
            thinkers of all times. But the idea in the past of limiting their numbers was a little
            different from that of today. The method which was employed to limit numbers in the past
            has been infanticide, abortion, mainly, while today it is preventing conception. This
            new idea is now making headway in practically every country in the world. The birth
            control movement as it stands in the United States has been the greatest instrument for
            circulating this idea, this modern scientific idea in every country in the world. So far
            we have groups in <place>China</place>, in <place>India</place>, in
            <place>Japan</place>, in <place>Mexico</place>, in <place>South America</place>, to say
            nothing of groups in <place>Germany</place>, <place>England</place>, <place>Scandinavian
                countries</place>, <place>Italy</place>, <place reg="Soviet Union">Russia</place> and
                <place>Hungary</place>. This new idea is taking its place in the social body, in the
            constructive platform of all of these countries, and I think for that we can say that
            America has been the leading country in this new idea of birth control. (applause)</p>
        <p>This is the first birth control conference ever held in this country, and we have a very
            elaborate platform, and our aims, as we understand them, are based upon scientific
            principles. We intend to organize the thinking populations of this country. We intend to
            have our groups, active groups, in every city in this country. We know, most of us, that
            where people have privately believed in birth control and have agreed with us on the
            side, yet they have not had the courage to come out and speak in public or to work for
            this principle, and the time has come when this must be changed. The time has come when
            we must make the intelligent members of our community come forth and work with us and
            join with us in making this a national program. We want to have the restrictive laws,
            both federal and state, repealed, and we stand very definitely--our group--that doctors
            should give this information. We stand very definitely on that principle, that this
            question of giving information is not a question of free speech, but it is a question of
            scientific, technical knowledge. (applause) We want the medical profession to give to
            women the most scientific data obtainable. It was only a few years ago, you know, that
            obstetrics was considered good enough for any woman to take care of. A woman who had to
            have a child was allowed to have her neighbor come in to deliver her. The medical
            profession did not consider that that was dignified enough for them to look after. And
            now the same thing has been considered of contraception, and we are going to make this
            function of the control of birth a scientific one. We are going to put it into the
            dignified role of science and that is where it belongs.</p>
        <p>Our aim is definitely to repeal these laws so that the medical profession may give to
            women as their request knowledge to prevent conception. We believe that with intelligent
            guidance and with the assistance of the intelligent members of our community we can
            bring this about in a very short time, but we need your help. We need your courage. We
            need you to come out and stand with us on our platform. We also want your guidance, and
            your assistance, and your suggestions. There is not any of us that think we know it all.
            We know that you in your special lines have experience by which we can benefit and we
            want your cooperation. In other words, we want to join together to make this country the
            greatest country in the world. We want to make this a country where its inhabitants and
            every member of the community is an independent, self-reliant, courageous individual who
            will take its place among the forward national of the civilized world. (applause)</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
