<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2003/10/10 NS</prepDate>
		<prepDate>05/09/2011 AW</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-04-10 CH clean regs</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-20 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1925-01-00">Jan 1925</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>An Urgent Appeal in the Tresca Case</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp230111</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title>, Jan. 1925, p. 4</bibl>
			<bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Smith College Collections</title> S71:14</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="ACLU">American Civil Liberties Union</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP"><p>The author of the petition that Sanger circulated in this article was
			the <org>American Civil Liberties Union</org>.</p>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="propaganda and publicity"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="suppression of"/>
		<index level1="censorship"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>An Urgent Appeal in the Tresca Case</head>
		<p>On November 23, 1923, <person reg="Tresca, Carlo">Carlo Tresca</person>, editor of <title
				type="journal">Il Martello,</title> an Italian anti-Fascisti weekly, was convicted
			of the crime of publishing in his paper a two-line advertisement of a book on Birth
			Control. On November 10, 1924, the <org><place>United States</place> Circuit Court of
				Appeals</org> affirmed his sentence of a year and a day in <org
				reg="United States Penitentiary, Atlanta">Atlanta Penitentiary</org>. The
			miscarriage of justice in this sentence is indicated in the endorsement by a number of
			prominent people to Mr. Tresca's application to President <person reg="Coolidge, Calvin"
				>Coolidge</person> for a commutation of sentence. The formal endorsement reads, in
			part, as follows:</p>
		<p>"<q who="ACLU">The petitioner was convicted upon one count only in an indictment
				containing eight counts under <name type="law"
					reg="United States Criminal Code, Section 211">Section 211 of the U.S. Criminal
					Code</name>, for offense of causing to be mailed an advertisement giving
				information as to how and by what means conception may be prevented. The
				advertisement was of a book, the Italian title of which literally translated, means
				the art of how not to create children. The other seven counts of the indictment
				charged the mailing of this book and other books. On these seven counts the
				petitioner was not convicted, but the owner of the bookstore at which the books were
				mailed, testified that he himself had mailed the books, and furthermore that he had
				inserted the advertisement in the paper while petitioner was absent on his vacation.
				This <person reg="Nieri, Umberto">bookstore owner</person>, subsequently indicted
				for the same offenses, pleaded guilty and has served four months</q>. </p>
		<p>"<q who="ACLU">The petitioner's conviction on the eighth count has been sustained by the
				Circuit Court of Appeals and is undoubtedly sound, though it must be pointed out
				that not only was there no evidence that he had any actual knowledge of the
				advertisement but that there was undisputed evidence (a) that he denied actual
				knowledge of it (b) that he was away on vacation at the time; and (c) that the other
				man, who subsequently pleaded guilty and served his sentence, was the man who had
				knowledge of any who inserted the advertisement. It should further be pointed out
				that the actual issue of the paper containing the advertisement never reached the
				eye of a single member of the reading public. It was stopped and returned by the
				post office authorities and only remailed when the offending advertisement had been
				physically deleted</q>.</p>
		<p>"<q who="ACLU">Under the circumstances outlined above, it is urged that to cause this man
				to serve a penitentiary sentence of a year and a day is not in accordance with the
				real ends of justice. The principal offender in the case received and served four
				months</q>.</p>
		<p>"<q who="ACLU">In other similar federal cases, so far as available records show, only
				small fines have been imposed; and in similar cases under state laws the average
				sentence was 30 days, and the longest six months</q>."</p>
		<p>We earnestly appeal to all our readers to join in this protest to President Coolidge
			against the punishment of an innocent man.</p>
		<byline>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">MARGARET SANGER</person>
		</byline>
	</docBody>
</doc>
