<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2003/07/01 SB</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/27 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/08/09 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007/08/28 CH Oxygen Update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/03/11 CH Entered corrections suggested by Andy Carloff.</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-12 CH cleaning errors/regs</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/05/16 CH added link to news version.</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1919-12-00">Dec 1919</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Breaking into the South--A Contrast</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp233034</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title>, Dec. 1919, 7-8</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title>, S70:829</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>For a news report of the Elizabeth City speech see "<xref
                from="422004.xml">Speech at the Alkrama Hotel</xref>," Nov. 2, 1919.</p>
        <index level1="African-Americans" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues" level3="establishment of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="opposition to"/>
        <index level1="League for Women Voters" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="New York" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="North Carolina" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="physicians" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="physicians" level2="women"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="speaking tours" level3="1919 (U.S.)"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="southern region"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Breaking Into the South--A Contrast</head>
        <byline rend="italics">By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></byline>
        <p>The first public lecture on birth control in the South developed into a series of
            addresses within twenty-four hours, and was in every way a gratifying surprise to me. I
            had the feeling that it would be hard to break the ice for the birth control movement in
            a city in which not even a suffragist had delivered a public lecture. To my delight,
            however, I found that people, both white and black, in <place reg="Elizabeth City, NC"
                >Elizabeth City, N.C.</place>, were so eager to know about birth control that every
            possible moment of my time was given to speaking.</p>
        <p>The first lecture, which was the only one I expected to deliver in Elizabeth City, was
            arranged by Mr. <person reg="Saunders, W. O.">W. O. Saunders</person>, editor of <title
                type="journal">The Independent</title>. It was delivered in a theatre Sunday
            afternoon, November 2nd. Women in the audience requested an address for women only, and
            this was given immediately following the general lecture. These meetings were attended
            by white women of all classes and conditions, some of them being farmer's wives --
            mothers of five, six or more children -- some of whom drove fifteen or sixteen miles to
            hear about birth control.</p>
        <p>After the lecture, a number of elderly women lingered to ask further questions and to
            express their appreciation of the movement. They were singularly unanimous in their
            expressions. "<q who="UNK">The message comes too late for me</q>," was the tenor of
            their words, "<q who="UNK">but thank God it comes in time to save my daughters from what
                I have undergone</q>."</p>
        <p>A committee of negro women urged a public address for negroes in a negro church for the
            same evening. This was delivered and was followed the next day by a short talk on
            "Education" at the negro normal school, and in the afternoon a lecture for negro women
            only on methods of birth control.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, women who came from near and far were gathering at the hotel where I stopped.
            Among these were a number of social workers and public-spirited citizens, who asked help
            in establishing a clinic for the mill workers. A temporary committee was formed, and is
            going ahead with the work of bringing fundamental, practical help to those women who
            work in the mills.</p>
        <p>All this happened between noon on Sunday and three o'clock Monday afternoon.</p>
        <p>Never have I met with more sympathy, more serious attention, more complete understanding
            than in my addresses to the white and black people of this Southern mill town. Each
            element in the audience seemed to look at the question from its own standpoint. All in
            all, these audiences were a striking demonstration of birth control's universal message
            of freedom and betterment.</p>
        <p>Among the white people, the argument which appealed most strongly was that of family
            betterment and increased happiness in the home, where the size of the family can be kept
            down to a point in which the father's earnings and the mother's attention are adequate
            for the care of children. That birth control results in longer life among women and
            decreases the mortality among infants and children of tender years appealed to
            representatives of insurance companies, who made it plain that they had got the point.
            Even a mill-owner, who is perhaps the most powerful citizen of Elizabeth City, was
            open-minded enough to recognize that birth control, in bettering the condition of the
            workers in his mills, would tend to increased efficiency.</p>
        <p>That the wives of farmers and of other workers recognized the liberty, the mental,
            physical and spiritual advantages that come with birth control was made plain by their
            attention, by their questions, and by their expressions of appreciation. They need it
            most, and doubtless it was they who best understood.</p>
        <p>If Elizabeth City is an index of the South, it is ready, waiting, crying for the message
            of birth control.</p>
        <p>It is with somewhat similar pleasure I look back upon a lecture given October 28th before
            members of the <org>League for Women Voters</org> in <place reg="New York, NY">New York
                City</place>. It was an interesting audience. These were workers -- active business
            women, some in clerical positions, some of them professional women, some of them
            housewives. They were mostly women who have grappled with practical problems and who
            have been tasting the first fruits of an expanding freedom. Their attitude was one of
            intelligent reasoning -- they wanted the message; they wished to weigh it and decide for
            themselves whether to apply it. There was in this audience but one objector -- a mother
            of four children, who said she wished she had four more. The rest of the audience joined
            in the hope that since she desired them, she might have them.</p>
        <p>In unhappy contrast to these meetings was the <org>Conference of Social Hygiene</org>, a
            division of The League for Women Voters, at which I was one of the speakers. This was
            held at the Park Avenue Hotel, New York, October 20th. At once one could feel hostility
            in this audience, composed almost entirely of women physicians. One wondered whence such
            antagonism could come, but when the lecture was over and questions and discussion began,
            one was not left long in the dark. The antagonism was among the women physicians
            themselves -- the people whom one would least expect to have that attitude. Yet there it
            was.</p>
        <p>One physician rejected birth control because she believed I claimed too much for it. She
            did not believe that it can accomplish as much for women as I believe it can --
            therefore she dismissed the whole subject!</p>
        <p>Another objected to birth control, saying that when a woman's children are arriving so
            rapidly as to make her lot unendurable, she should leave her husband. Asked what a woman
            living in the slums, and having four or five children barely supported by her own
            earnings and those of her husband should do with the children, this physician blandly
            dismissed the whole matter by saying she <emph rend="italics">should take them with
                her.</emph> This from a woman physician whose practice is, presumably, largely among
            the poor!</p>
        <p>A third woman physician objected to any discussion of the subject, saying that it was
                "<q>nasty</q>." It is hardly to be supposed, however, that this physician refuses
            either to give her services or accept fees in maternity cases. Dr. <person
                reg="Halton, Mary">Mary Halton</person> quickly settled this point by her positive
            assertion of the beauty and cleanliness of all that relates to the sex life. Her defense
            of birth control was clear, strong, and illuminating.</p>
        <p>But let us not deceive ourselves as to the general attitude of either women or men who
            are attached strongly to institutions -- whether these institutions be professional
            organizations or something else similar in spirit. Usually their egos have become
            attached to these institutions -- they have built up the old organizations -- upon those
            organizations they depend largely for their standing and personal success.
            Subconsciously these well-meaning people know that their institutions are going to
            tumble into disuse before the vigorous, fundamental remedies which we propose to apply.
            The women physicians who follow the old manner of thinking subconsciously know and fear
            the effect of birth control, which will largely dispense with their services as they are
            now rendered. These will never take the initiative in freeing the world from its chains.
            They love their institutions, their prejudices, their own chains, better than they love
            humanity and the truth. </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
