<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011-08-04 NC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2012-03-28 CH proofed tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-08 CH clean regs</prepDate>
           <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1954-04-19"><supplied resp="MSPP">19 Apr 1954</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Birth Control Interest in Japan</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp233122</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S72:0899</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>Sanger made this speech at one of the many events she attended during her 1954 trip to
            Japan, possibly at a meeting of the <org>Family Planning Federation of Japan</org>.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="in Japan"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="pill"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <dateline><place>Tokyo, Japan</place></dateline>
        <p>It is good to be in <place>Japan</place> again even though the cherry blossoms did not
            wait for my arrival. It has been wet and cloudy some days, but when the sun does come
            out, the air is fresh and clean. All nature seems to smile as children do after a bath. </p>
        <p>The purpose of my visit at this time is to learn the results of the three village
            experiments where the <org reg="Institute of Public Health of Japan">Institute of Public
                Health</org> has sent nurses and midwives to the homes to teach the parents methods
            of Birth Control. The results while not conclusive are encouraging. The <org
                reg="Institute of Public Health of Japan, Health Department"><org
                    reg="Institute of Public Health of Japan, Welfare Department">Health and Welfare
                    Departments</org></org> should be encouraged to expand their guidance to many
            more villages and help mothers to avoid the necessity of abortion. </p>
        <p>The most encouraging impression I have had is the overwhelming desire on the part of
            women, men, newspaper men, and nurses and doctors to learn and obtain the so-called
            Birth Control pill or medicine. So much has been talked about as a future possibility.
            My telephone rings, callers come, people at meetings, all plead to be given the “pill”.
            It is my greatest regret that this so-called “pill” is not ready for general
            distribution yet. There are several tests being made in the <place reg="United States"
                >United States of America</place>. There will, I trust, be a selected group of
            medical officers and scientists in Japan to join with the American scientists to test
            out this special ingredient before it is given a wide national distribution. </p>
        <p>Other demand comes from many countries and it will not be too many months before there
            will be the possibility of this cheap, simple, safe contraceptive. This demanding
            interest on the part of the Japanese people is a healthy attitude toward the population
            problem. Japan needs to cut down the birth rate to equal the death rate : to hold a
            stationary population for years, give the living children a chance. With 87 million
            people crowded into such a small island, there is no need of increasing this number for
            years to come. The people here especially the children look healthy and well-fed. People
            do not look over-fed, but they look vital, active, energetic. and always the charming
            courtesies and beautiful manners of all people so typical of Japanese culture which
            exists no where else on this earth. </p>
        <p>I am happy to have so many friends in this country and it will be a great honor for all
            of us from <place>Europe</place> and America to assemble here in Tokyo for our <org
                reg="International Conference on Planned Parenthood, 5th">International Planned
                Parenthood Conference</org> in October-November of 1955. </p>
        <p>So it is Hail and Farewell, Farewell and Hail until that time.</p>
        <byline>Mrs. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person><lb/> President<lb/>
            <org>International Planned Parenthood Federation</org><lb/>
            <date value="1954-04-19">April 19, 1954</date><lb/> Tokyo, Japan</byline>



    </docBody>
</doc>
