<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011-08-05 NC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-26 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1954-04-09">9 Apr 1954</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Greetings to my Friends in Japan</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp233124</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S72:0894</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>Sanger gave this address at the beginning of her 1954 tour of Japan.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="in Japan"/>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="population policies"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>GREETINGS TO MY FRIENDS IN JAPAN</head>
        <opener>
            <dateline>
                <date value="1954-04-09">April 9, 1954</date>
            </dateline>
            <byline>Mrs. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>, President,
                    <org>International Planned Parenthood Federation</org></byline>
        </opener>
        <p>It is good to come back like the spring to your beautiful country. It is going to be a
            renewed experience for me to be here in April, for it was that month in 1922 that I
            first came to <place>Japan</place>, and now I am here again with a very charming friend,
            half of your country, and half of mine, <person reg="Hata, Chieko">Mrs. Chieko
                Hata</person>, who was born in the <place>United States</place> of Japanese parents. </p>
        <p> The purpose of my trip is to get first hand information about the progress that has been
            made by the Japanese Minister of Welfare, Dr. <person reg="Hashimoto, Ryugo">Koseisho</person>,
            and Dr. <person reg="Koya, Yoshio">Y. Koya</person>, Director of the Institute of Public
            Health. They are both in their various fields combining to the contribution of the
            welfare of the people of Japan in the program of mothers health by establishing first
            ranking positions in the world through family planning. Their method of imparting
            information to the mothers personally and privately is the first method of this kind
            anywhere to be given, and I am very anxious to consult with them both as to results. </p>
        <p> Also the <org>Family Planning Federation of Japan</org> has been organized, and its
            first National meeting is to be held April 18th. I am happy to be there in person to
            congratulate them and to see for myself and to hear from the field workers of family
            planning as to their successful results. </p>
        <p> It is my pleasure to be in <place>Japan</place> in April, and I trust that the cherry
            trees will still be in bloom. My first visit to Japan was in April, 1922, an experience
            that I have never forgotten. </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
