<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2002-08-08 KH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2002-08-15 KH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2003/08/08 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/08/09 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2001/03/11 CH Entered corrections suggested by Andy Carloff.</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-18 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1929-02-26">
            <supplied resp="MSPP">26 Feb 1929</supplied>
        </docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>
                <supplied resp="MSPP">Opening Address for Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau
                    Dinner</supplied>
            </titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp234094</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title>, S71:153</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="CRAFR">Crane, Frederick Ewen</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>Margaret Sanger gave this speech at a dinner promoting the Birth Control Clinical
            Research Bureau at <place reg="New York, NY">New York's</place>
            <org>Plaza Hotel</org>. Other speakers were: <person reg="Lovejoy, Owen">Owen
                Lovejoy</person>, <person reg="Fairchild, Henry Pratt">Henry Pratt
                Fairchild</person>, <person reg="Hankins, Frank">Frank Hankins</person> and <person
                reg="Stone, Hannah Mayer">Hannah Stone</person>. For Sanger's introductions for
                <xref from="128197.xml">Hankins</xref>, <xref from="128190.xml">Lovejoy</xref> and
                <xref from="128197.xml">Fairchild</xref>. Additions were made by hand by <person
                reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>. For an early draft see LCM
            130:479.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="propaganda and publicity"/>
        <index level1="Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau"/>
        <index level1="physicians" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues"/>
        <index level1="Brownsville Clinic"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>
            <add>Opening Address by Margaret Sanger</add>
        </head>
        <p>We are here tonight to celebrate a birthday. The <org>Birth Control Clinical Research
                Bureau</org> has just entered the seventh year of its existence. In the six years of
            its existence the Research Bureau commonly called the Birth Control Clinic--has
            demonstrated the success of a new way of solving old problems.</p>
        <p>Just about one hundred years ago, when the possibilities of the control of population
            first seized the minds and the imagination of the Anglo-Saxon world, pioneers like
                <person reg="Place, Francis">Francis Place</person> and <person
                reg="Mill, John Stuar">John Stuart Mill</person>, thought that all that was
            necessary was to scatter millions of leaflets to the masses telling them why and how
            they could prevent large families. A century ago men put great faith in the printed
            word. They scattered leaflets from the roofs of tenements and defied arrest for
            scattering broadcast "diabolical handbills." </p>
        <p>Fifteen years ago, when the idea of Birth Control captured my imagination I went through
            the same experience and wrote, printed and disseminated leaflets and booklets. I was
            stopped by the Post Office Authorities and indicted for breaking a federal statute
            enacted under the reign of St. <person reg="Comstock, Anthony">Anthony
            Comstock</person>.</p>
        <p>But experience is a bitter teacher. The more you go through, the less you believe in the
            miracle of printed words to effect the salvation of the lives of women and children. </p>
        <p>In 1915 I visited <place reg="Netherlands">Holland</place>, and spent three months
            studying the actual technique of contraception. I became convinced that that
            overburdened women could be educated in Birth Control only by scientific instruction
            received from competent physicians and nurses in clinics established for that purpose
            and that purpose alone.</p>
        <p>When I returned to this country, that idea was the central one in my mind. I did not
            realize the gigantic obstacles to overcome before that idea could be converted in
            reality. I plunged into activity, established a clinic in the Brownsville section of
                <place reg="Brooklyn, NY">Brooklyn</place>. We operated for ten days and no less
            than four hundred and eighty eight mothers crowded into our limited quarters. Then the
            police descended upon us and called us a "public nuisance."</p>
        <p>I carried this fight to the Supreme Court. In a decision handed down by the <org
                reg="New York State Court of Appeals">New York Court of Appeals</org> permitted
            lawfully practising physicians to give contraceptive advice "<q who="CRAFR">for the cure
                of prevention of disease.</q>" This technical victory was won in 1918. With the aid
            of a <person reg="Bocker, Dorothy">woman physician</person> I ventured on my own
            responsibility to establish a research bureau as a preliminary toward a clinic. In the
            meantime a small group of pioneers was working incessantly toward converting
            unintelligent public opinion to the legitimacy of the idea of Birth Control.</p>
        <p>It was not until 1923--just six years ago--that I succeeded in finding anyone with
            sufficient faith and courage to support the research bureau with financial backing. Now
            Ill tell you an interesting little secret. It was not an American, but a <person
                reg="Chance, Clinton E.">gentleman in <place>England</place></person> who advanced
            the first five thousand dollars to pay the doctor's salary. That was all I needed. I
            found a competent physician. The research bureau was opened.</p>
        <p>From that small beginning, the bureau has grown slowly, steadily and surely. Today we
            have seven women physicians on our medical staff, five trained nurses and two social
            workers.</p>
        <p>We have investigated thirteen thousand cases. From that vast number we have the full
            records of ten thousand women who came to the bureau for advice and instruction as
            permitted under the law, "<q who="CRAFR">for the cure of prevention of disease.</q>"
            Hundreds of overburdened mothers who appeal to us are turned away because despite their
            misery and poverty do not come under this classification.</p>
        <p>Since my first clinic was destroyed by the <org reg="New York City Police Department">New
                York police</org>, the idea has gown and matured not only in this country but in
                <place>Great Britain</place> as well. There are not twenty-six similar
            establishments in this country and about twenty in England. Our aim here is to develop
            the Clinical Research Bureau as a model of all other similar agencies in the
                <place>United States</place>. In this aim we are succeeding. Physicians from all
            civilized countries of the world come to us to learn the techniques of scientific
            contraception. We are aiming to perfect the bureau so that its methods and its
            administrations shall be above criticism.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
