<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/07/08 NC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>200/07/13 NC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/07/13 CH final edit</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1940-09-28">28 Sep 1940</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">New Bedford Massachusetts Radio
                    Speech</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236032</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>MSM</title>S72:0173</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="SCMAS">Supreme Court of Massachusetts</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Margaret Sanger gave a radio speech in <place>New
                Bedford, Massachusetts</place> from 6:00 - 6:15 p.m. The
            following press release preceded the talk.</p><p>Interlineations and
            corrections made by Margaret Sanger. For draft versions see MSM
            S72:0155, 0161, 0167, and LCM 130:0103.</p><index level1="women"
            level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/><index
            level1="United States" level2="government"
            level3="birth control and"/><index level1="population"
            level2="birth control and"/><index level1="men"
            level2="birth control and"/><index level1="family planning"/>
        <index level1="family size"/><index level1="birth control"
            level2="laws and legislation" level3="Massachusetts"/><index
            level1="birth control" level2="American opinion on"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <p>A few years ago the people of the world, for the first time in the
            history of man, were <emph rend="underline">confident</emph> that
                <add>at last</add> an enduring peace could be achieved. But
            today the world is swept by the most brutal war that man has <emph
                rend="underline">ever</emph> known. Even during those years when
            nations were planning for peace, there were forces
                <add>already</add> at work that made this <add>Second
                World</add> war inevitable.</p>
        <p>This war is really, but one phase of a struggle which has been in
            progress throughout <del>all of</del>
            <add>the</add> history <add>of mankind</add>. Actually those same
            forces of <emph rend="underline">destruction</emph> which are now
            sweeping <place>Europe</place> like a fire<add>,</add>
            <emph rend="underline">yearly</emph> take the lives of millions
            throughout the world--of thousands even in our <add>own</add>
            <emph rend="underline">country</emph>. <add>For</add> As long as
            people are born into the world by <emph rend="underline"
                >chance</emph> rather than by the intelligent choice of parents,
            they will die by the thousands, some even before they have begun to
            live <add>at all</add>, others before they have lived out <del>a
                normal life</del>
            <add>their First 5 years</add>.</p>
        <p>We are horrified because in the present world war so much suffering
            has fallen on innocent women and children. In the desperate struggle
            for survival which continues even in years of peace, it is the <emph
                rend="underline">children</emph>, and the <emph rend="underline"
                >women</emph> who bear <del>them</del>
            <add>the children</add>, that suffer the heaviest toll.</p>
        <p rend="blockquote">Fourteen thousand mothers lost in childbirth!</p>
        <p rend="blockquote">Seventy-five thousand babies born dead!</p>
        <p rend="blockquote">Seventy thousand babies lost in the first month of
            life!</p>
        <p rend="blockquote"><emph rend="underline">These</emph> are the
            casualties in our <emph rend="underline">own</emph> country during
                <emph rend="underline">one year of peace</emph>. Or <emph
                rend="underline">is</emph> this peace? The war in Europe has
                <emph rend="underline">not</emph> killed more innocents than
            these. <emph rend="underline">But these are only the dead.</emph>
            What of those who survive? <add>What of the living?</add> Let us
            consider <del>the</del>
            <add>our own American</add> children.</p>
        <p rend="blockquote">Six million are improperly nourished.</p>
        <p rend="blockquote">A million have weak or damaged hearts</p>
        <p rend="blockquote">Three millions have impaired hearing</p>
        <p rend="blockquote">A million have defective speech</p>
        <p rend="blockquote">850,000 definitely <add>are</add> feeble-minded</p>
        <p rend="blockquote">300,000, crippled</p>
        <p rend="blockquote">400,000, Tubercular</p>
        <p rend="blockquote">50,000, partially blind</p>
        <p>And the cause of this?</p>
        <p>Mothers dying needlessly, in giving birth to children who might
            better not have been born; <del>fighters</del>
            <add>men</add> fighting a hopeless fight to provide for their
            families the necessities of decent living; young men and young women
            forced by need or neglect into lawlessness, nations vying with one
            another for land with which to support their surplus
            population--these all spring from the same cause, the heedless,
            unplanned <emph rend="underline">reproduction</emph> of
                <add>the</add> human <del>beings</del>
            <add>race</add>.</p>
        <p>But <emph rend="underline">these</emph> are the conditions of the
            jungle. We take it for granted that in the jungle thousands will die
            by violent death or by starvation for every <emph rend="underline"
                >one</emph> that survives. But among human being<add>s</add>
            this is the very abdication of reason.</p>
        <p>It is said that the ability to <emph rend="underline">laugh</emph>
            distinguishes <del>men</del>
            <add>man</add> from the lower animals. Another characteristics of
            man alone is the ability to <emph rend="underline">plan</emph> the
            birth of his young. This is the foundation upon which he can build a
            way of life which offers to every individual the full promise of his
            in-born potentialities. Planned parenthood, Children born <emph
                rend="underline">because</emph> they are wanted, because their
            parents can provide for them the environment of a wholesome life;
            the family-basic unit of any civilized society--strong in its
            loyalties, cheerful in its outlook, self-sustaining and
            self-respecting.</p>
        <p>Science has given us the means of planned parenthood. Contraception,
            or the evidence of unintended conception, is possible to every
            couple. The methods are simple, reliable--made so by years of
            patient research. This knowledge is, or should be, a part of the
            working equipment of every practising physician.</p>
        <p>Why, then, are children still born unwanted, to live in neglect, and
            to become charges of society?</p>
        <p>It is not because of the indifference of women. This is certain. It
            is not because of the callousness of men. Men as well as women
            benefit by planned parenthood, and they too are seeking the means to
            achieve it.</p>
        <p>It is not because of the inability or the unwillingness of doctors to
            advise their patients. A few valiant leaders of the medical
            profession have fought <emph rend="underline">for years</emph> to
            make planned parenthood a reality.</p>
        <p>Planned parenthood is <emph rend="underline">not now</emph> a reality
                <emph rend="underline">because</emph> of the shame with which
            so-called reformers of an older generation invested any matter
            related to the love of men and women, <add>idea</add>
            <del>and because one religious body has tried to impose upon <emph
                    rend="underline">all</emph> the people its won conception of
                the proper marriage relationship</del>. <del>These two</del>
            <add>This</add> attitude, by tactics unworthy of a democracy,
                <del>were</del>
            <add>was</add> written into laws which restricted the information
            which the medical profession could give to a patient, even though
            life itself were at stake. A more enlightened age has restored to
            the medical profession its <emph rend="underline">inalienable</emph>
            right to use the full resources of science for the health and
            welfare of patients. <place>Massachusetts</place>, however, remains
            as a dark area.</p>
        <p>Massachusetts well may be proud of its record of caring for its
            mothers and children, of the schools it has built, of its health
            services and of its care of the old and the dependent. But of what
            avail are these in meeting the greatest need of any family if the
            law in Massachusetts <emph rend="underline">so curbs</emph> the
            rights of the medical profession<add>,</add> that a <emph
                rend="underline">doctor cannot tell</emph> a patient how she can
                <del>avoid a pregnancy?</del>
            <del>[illegible]</del>
            <add>plan a family.</add></p>
        <p>In five years, from 1934 to 1938, in this rich state, 6,702 infants
            under one year of age <emph rend="underline">died</emph> in six of
            its largest cities, 14,207 died throughout the state. There were
            9,092 still births. One thousand, five hundred and twenty-nine
            mothers died in child birth. Most of these were needless deaths. The
            waste and the human suffering they caused could so easily have been
            avoided. There was the knowledge and there was the eagerness to
            learn. But <emph rend="underline">ignorance</emph>, with a brutality
            as great as war’s, brought death at the point of life’s beginning,
            or its highest achievement.</p>
        <p>What does the law in Massachusetts say? It says that <emph
                rend="underline">anyone</emph> giving information regarding
                <emph rend="underline">any means</emph> whatever of
                <del>preventing pregnancy</del>
            <add>contraception</add> is guilty of a crime<add>,</add> and shall
            be punished by imprisonment in a state prison or be fined. In 1938,
            the highest court of this state held that the law is “<q who="SCMAS"
                >sweeping, <emph rend="underline">absolute</emph>, and devoid of
                    <emph rend="underline">ambiguity</emph></q>” and “<q
                who="SCMAS">contains no <emph rend="underline"
                >exceptions</emph></q>”.!!</p>
        <p>Well, this law is not going to stay on the statute books. It is in
            conflict with the rights of the medical profession, and with the
            interests of the people. It runs counter to the basic liberties
            guaranteed to us in the bill of rights. It has no place among the
            laws of any democracy.</p>
        <p>Throughout the nations the great movement for planned parenthood is
            gaining momentum. Leaders in every walk of life are represented in
            the national sponsoring committee. In two states information about
            child spacing is regularly given through the public health services.
            Local public health units in hundreds of communities in other states
            are doing the same. Educators, scientists, clergymen, see planned
            parenthood as a way to strengthen our human resources in a time of
            great national need. Most important of all, in the heart of every
            woman, is the conviction that women should have the right to decide
            when they shall bring children into the world.</p>
        <p>Only in Massachusetts and her sister-state <place>Connecticut</place>
            does the law stand as an obstacle to this movement. Only here has
            ignorance gained a victory over science, shame over the dignity of
            human life. This is <emph rend="underline">not of the choosing
            </emph>of the people of this state today.</p>
        <p>The people of Massachusetts want this law changed. In a recent poll
            by an impartial agency, 82 per cent of the people of this state
                <emph rend="underline">declared</emph> that they would vote for
            legislation which would free doctors to prescribe
                contraception<add>,</add>
            <emph>for their patients</emph>. The medical profession itself is
            taking leadership in a campaign at <del>thi</del> this time to see
            that the wishes of the people, thus expressed, result in a change in
            this outmoded law.</p>
        <p>You will want to help in this campaign, and in saying that I know
            that I am speaking to the great majority of those who are
            listening.</p>
        <p>All that you need do is to register your will. Write to the <org>
                Massachusetts Mother’s Health Council</org>, 143 Newbury Street,
                <place reg="Boston, MA">Boston</place>, or in care of this
            station, and say that you want to sign the petition to the
            legislature for restoration of medical rights in Massachusetts. You
            will be sent a blank. Your signature on that blank will be a blow to
            the bigotry and ignorance which now keeps motherhood in bondage in
            Massachusetts.</p>


    </docBody>
</doc>
