<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011-08-05 NC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2012-04-04 CH Proofed Tags</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1954-04-09">9 April 1954</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Japan</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236043</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S72:0895</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>Margaret Sanger likely gave these remarks at one of the meetings she
            attended in Tokyo to help organize the Japan Planned Parenthood
            Federation and the Fifth International Conference on Planned
            Parenthood, held there in 1955.</p>
        <p>For draft version see <title>MSM</title> S72:0881.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="in Japan"/>
        <index level1="abortion" level2="MS on"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>JAPAN</head>
        <opener><dateline><date value="1954-04-09">April 9,
                1954</date></dateline>
            <byline>Mrs. <person>Margaret Sanger</person>, President,
                International Planned Parenthood Federation</byline></opener>
        <p>I have come back (like the spring) to <place>Japan</place>. It is
            going to be a renewed experience for me to be here in April, for
            that was the month in 1922 that I first came to your beautiful
            country, through an invitation of a most distinguished group of
            intellectuals. </p>
        <p>I bring today cordial greetings from the <org>International Planned
                Parenthood Federation</org>, who have honored me in <place
                reg="Stockholm, Sweden">Stockholm</place> last August by
            electing me their President. This Federation now consists of
                <del>8</del>
            <add>9</add> national organizations: <place>United Kingdom</place> -
                <place>England</place>, <place>Scotland</place> &amp;
                <place>Wales</place>- <place>Sweden</place>, <place
                reg="Netherlands, the">Holland</place>, <place
                reg="West Germany">Western Germany</place>,
            <place>India</place>, <place>Hong Kong</place>,
                <place>Singapore</place>, Japan. Several other national groups
            are organizing their forces to make application as affiliates. </p>
        <p>It is also my pleasure to personally accept the invitation the
                <org>Japanese Family Planning Federation</org> had extended to
            the International Planned Parenthood Federation to hold the next
            conference in this country in 1955! We are grateful for this
            invitation, and I am here in person, as President, to accept it with
            our gratitude and respectful thanks. </p>
        <p>Your own Committee <add>J F P. assn</add> is expanding its interest
            through fields and areas and villages with results of much concern
            to our Federation, for as your original projects succeed in lowering
            the birth rate in a safe and healthful method, so shall other
            nations follow your example and apply these methods to their
            population problems. </p>
        <p>The Americas, through spending huge sums on educational work on birth
            control, have not thus far reached the submerged population to any
            extent. While we have hundreds of birth control clinics
                <add>(500)</add> throughout every state in the union, these are
            not available to thousands of mothers who live on farms, on ranches,
            and in slums of large cities. Clinics, though well organized as
            teaching centers, are usually too far away for poor parents to reach
            and availe themselves of proper scientific instruction given by
            medical experts in this field. Your project which helps the same
            group of parents in overcrowded areas by sending into the homes
            nurses or midwives trained to advise and instruct mothers and
            fathers personally in the technique of contraception is a far better
            way to reach those most desperately needing it. </p>
        <p>When a mother must resort to abortion in order to keep alive the
            children already born, it is a proof that she is in a desperate
            state of mind. She needs help. She needs understanding advice. She
            should have the best information your medical and welfare
            departments of your government has available. This should be her
            right! The decision should be a joint agreement between the father
            and mother, or husband and wife. There should be nothing put in
            their way to thwart that decision. Parents want children. They want
            healthy strong, vital children. Why has such knowledge been kept
            from the poorest parents, while the well to do, the educated have
            for generations practiced spacing their children and limiting the
            numbers the parents could educate and bring up to become adults,
            helpful to the nation and to our civilization. </p>
        <p>Now at last the parents of the lower income brackets have become
            articulate. They speak for themselves. Their voices are heard around
            the world. They do not want to be forced to the indignity and
            necessity of abortion. They call out to the health and welfare
            ministries for scientific knowledge and information. These
            departments in your country have bravely answered them and are
            giving the help in family planning to all. I congratulate you. </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
