<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed draft speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2010/04/28 AC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2010/04/29 CH proof</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-11 CH clean up errors</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1938-02-08">08 Feb 1938</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Tucson Mothers' Health Center Address</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236022</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger MicrofilmM</title>, S71:974</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>The complete text of <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger</person>'s
            speech has not been located. This was likely prepared by her secretarial staff. </p>
        <index level1="unfit to reproduce" level2="descriptions of"/>
        <index level1="poverty" level2="family size and"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="maternal"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="infant"/>
        <index level1="mentally disabled and diseased"/>
        <index level1="United States Children's Bureau"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Summary of Address by Margaret Sanger? Speaking in Behalf of the <org
                reg="Tucson Mothers Health Center">Mothers' Health Center</org> Carroll Street,
                <place reg="Tucson, AZ">Tucson, Arizona</place>. At the <org>Pioneer Hotel</org>,
            Tuesday, Feb. 8, 1938</head>
        <p>There are some basic truths which should form the corner stone of any national security.
            These are:</p>
        <p>First, that the physically unfit usually beget the unfit.</p>
        <p>Second, that the mentally unfit nine times out of ten produce the mentally unfit.</p>
        <p>Third, that mental defectives, morons, idiots, imbeciles, are begotten by parents or
            progenitors whose blood stream carries the taint which affected them.</p>
        <p>Fourth, that the birth of every defective child adds to the burden which lowers the
            standard of living as well as lowers the general intelligence throughout the nation.</p>
        <p>Eighty five percent of our population have an I.Q. below that of a fifteen year old
            juvenile. Yet in a democracy the majority rules, and rules according to its
            intelligence. The burden of the hordes who inhabit our land and fill our institutions
            bids fair to destroy our civilization. Already they are sapping the energy and resources
            of this generation, and debts are piling high upon the backs of generations yet
            unborn.</p>
        <p>According to a recent conference (Jan 17-18, 1938) of the <org
                reg="United States Children's Bureau">Children’s Bureau of the Department of
                Labor</org>, held in <place>Washington, D.C.</place>, it was reported that at least
            35,000 infants are left motherless each year; 14,000 women die from causes connected
            with childbirth; 75,000 infants are still born; 69,000 infants die during the first
            month of life.</p>
        <p>The report also states that the maternal deaths have not been reduced during the past
            twenty-two years, while the death rate from other causes has been greatly reduced.</p>
        <p>The Birth Control Movement has been calling out for the past twenty-two years against
            this evil and has advocated definite means to eradicate abortion and to space the births
            of children so that the mothers’ health shall be restored after one birth before she is
            confronted with the complications of another pregnancy.</p>
        <p>The report further states that nearly one million of the two million births occur
            annually in families on relief or which have a total income of less than $750 a year. It
            also states that the highest birth rates generally prevail in areas where economic
            conditions are least favorable. Of course the Children’s Bureau recommended better
            professional care for the mothers before or after the birth of the infant, but the fact
            remains that until mothers have adequate knowledge to space, limit, or control their
            offspring, the Children’s Bureau will continue to find the death rate of mothers
            unchanged.</p>
        <p>Science has given us the means of knowledge which, when applied our problems, could
            reduce maternal deaths, lessen poverty, wipe out unemployment, and create a race of
            human thoroughbreds. Birth Control is a pivotal force in the lives of all married
            people. It is not only a health and economic expedient; it is a great social factor
            through which the health of mothers and children is conserved, and the earning capacity
            of the father is balanced with the number of children he can support.</p>
        <p>“Every child a wanted child,” is our slogan. We shall never stop our activities until
            this ideal becomes a reality. </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
