<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>    
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed draft speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2003/07/16, 2003/07/28 SR</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-09 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2012-05-03 AW</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-05-06 CH corrected title and others</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1923-02-11">11 Feb 1923</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>The Meaning of Birth Control</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236021</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S70:958</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>This speech was given in <place reg="Hartford, CT">Hartford, Connecticut</place> at a
            mass meeting organized by the <org>Connecticut Birth Control League</org>, at the
                <org>Parsons' Theatre</org>. For a draft version without Sanger's handwritten
            corrections, see Library of Congress Microfilm 130:436. The speech was also published as
                "<title type="article">The Need for Birth Control In America</title>" in <person
                reg="Meyer, Adolf">Adolf Meyer</person>, <title type="book">Birth Control Facts and
                Responsibilities</title>, (Baltimore, 1925), 11-49.</p>
        <index level1="abortion"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="class-based"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits and risks"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="history of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="continence"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="safe period"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="morality of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="opposition to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="prostitution and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="socio-economic benefits of"/>
        <index level1="birth rate"/>
        <index level1="child spacing"/>
        <index level1="children" level2="rights of"/>
        <index level1="client letters"/>
        <index level1="England" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="eugenics" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="family size"/>
        <index level1="&quot;feeble-minded&quot; persons" level2="allowed to reproduce"/>
        <index level1="fertility rates"/>
        <index level1="heredity" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="immigration" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="infanticide"/>
        <index level1="Jukes family"/>
        <index level1="Kallikak family"/>
        <index level1="Keynes, John Maynard"/>
        <index level1="marriage"/>
        <index level1="men" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
        <index level1="men" level2="sexual fulfillment of"/>
        <index level1="mentally disabled and diseased" level2="fertility of"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="infant"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="maternal"/>
        <index level1="Netherlands" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="parenthood"/>
        <index level1="population growth"/>
        <index level1="pregnancy" level2="fears of"/>
        <index level1="prostitution" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="race suicide"/>
        <index level1="Scotland" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="sexuality"/>
        <index level1="sterilization" level2="methods of"/>
        <index level1="&quot;unfit&quot; to reproduce"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="enslavement of"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="freedom and rights of"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>The Need of Birth Control in <place reg="United States">America</place></head>
        <byline>Margaret Sanger President, <org>American Birth Control League</org>, Inc.</byline>
        <p><person reg="Porritt, Annie Goodrich">Madam Chairman</person> and Ladies and
            Gentlemen:</p>
        <p>Birth Control is the keynote of a new social awakening. It is not only a health and
            economic expedient; it is a great social principle, a principle that is interlocked with
            the spiritual progress of the race and its future. The idea of Birth Control is not new;
                <del>it is</del> only the methods that are being advocated and pressed today
                <del>that</del> are comparatively new; but the idea of Birth Control or the
            limitation of the family is as old as nature itself. In fact, nature is the most
            ruthless, the most cruel advocate of Birth Control; her methods are disease, famine,
            pestilence, flood and wars. Through these methods nature has controlled her population;
            through these methods nature has eliminated the unfit, those who are unable to compete
            for their survival, and in this way and through theses methods, she has perpetuated and
            improved her types.<add>Man also</add>in practically all stages of his evolution has
            attempted to limit the size of his family, has attempted to keep the population down by
            other methods of Birth Control. Those methods are infanticide or killing of babies; the
            abandonment of children, and foeticide--these have been the methods through the stages
            of savagery <add>&amp; barbarism</add> and even during the early stages of civilization
                <add>by which man has tried to control population.</add></p>
        <p><person>Plato</person> advocated the exposure to the elements of all infants, to see if
            they were worthy <del>of</del> the keep of the State <del>or by the state</del>.
                <person>Aristotle</person> advocated that the State should fix the number of
            children born to a family; and even <person>Seneca</person> advised that all children
            that were born of immoral or diseased parents should not be allowed to survive. Even
                <place reg="Rome, Italy">Rome</place> who built up her power by the conquest of
            weaker nations also condemned healthy children to an early death. These methods were
            used to such an alarming extent that from the Middle Ages practically down to the end of
            the 18th century, infanticide was <del>a</del>
            <add>the</add> most common, the most prevalent crime of western Europe, <del>during that
                time</del>. No matter what was done to put down this crime of infanticide, it
            continued to increase. The practice spread itself continually. We read in our histories
            of most atrocious tortures that were applied to the mothers who abandoned or who killed
            their children. In one sovereign's reign <add>in <place>Germany</place></add> which took
            about eighteen years there were more than 20,000 mothers tortured <add>to death</add>for
            the crime of infanticide. These mothers--and most of them were married women--were put
            to death by being put into a bag with a cat and a dog and a viper, and <del>they</del>
            were thrown into a <del>ditch</del>
            <add>body</add> of water, if there was one near<add>by.</add></p>
        <p>If, after a certain period of time, the victim had not ceased to move and to struggle,
            she was removed from the bag and was then put to death with <add>glowing</add>
            <unclear resp="MSPP">tongs</unclear>. <del>And</del> yet this did not put an end to
            infanticide. All the tortures, all the threats of hell-punishments, did not put an end
            to infanticide; and it was not until the practice of abortions became generally known
            and the practice became generally prevalent that infanticide went out of fashion.</p>
        <p>We today, believe in beginning at the other end. We believe not in the methods of nature
            and not in the methods of savages or <del>early</del> barbarians, but we believe in
            control of the birth rate by scientific means to <add>that</add>prevent contraception.
            That is the definition of Birth Control. <del>Now</del> we believe that Birth Control is
            the key to the greatest of human problems,--that of reconciling humanitarianism with
            race improvement. We know that <add>the</add> develop<add>ment</add>
            <add>of</add> the mind, <del>to develop</del>
            <add>and</add>the intellect <del>of man</del> has been a process of evolution. It is a
            very slow growth, which while the reproductive process or capability of man is almost
            unlimited, yet unless we put some check, some control over the powers of reproduction,
            we are bound inevitably or eventually to be in such a state of society, to have so large
            a proportion of individuals in a community, that the mind, the intellect of that same
            group at that same state, is unable to keep up with the conditions created out of the
            numerous people who have multiplied and reproduced.</p>
        <p>Now if we let this condition alone, as it has been let alone in the past, nature would
            take care of that; nature would simply thrust to the wall the old and the diseased and
            the sickly, and the feeble--and she would adjust her types, <del>and</del> she would
            adjust her population until they evolved gradually to make conditions and a system of
            society convenient for them all. But we today, with the <del>development</del>
            <add>advance</add> of Christianity, with the development of humanitarianism and
            democracy and the <del>whole</del> development of our sympathetic nervous system, we
            will not let that process take place; we will not let nature do this work. And so we
            through our sympathies, through the finer development of man, we reach out our hands and
            we take care of your sickly and the diseased, the mentally deficient, and we take them
            to our hearts; we erect great institutions for their upkeep; and we <del>practice</del>
            force <del>upon the process of</del>
            <add>them to</add> reproduce their types. <del>This is what has happened, and the
                consequence is that we have</del> as we look out upon the world
                today,--<del>you</del>
            <add>we</add> find two very definite groups in society, as affected by the knowledge and
            the lack of knowledge in Birth Control. In all the western countries you find <del>two
                groups</del> the small family group and the large family group. In the small family
            group you find people who have limited the size of their families; for instance, you
            take some statistics by Dr. <person reg="Bertillon, Jacques">Bertillon</person> of
                <place reg="Paris, France">Paris</place>; he found that of a thousand women between
            the ages of 14 and 50, in the poor district of Paris that out of a thousand women of
            that district there were 166 births; for the same number of women between the same ages
            in the wealthy district, he found 32 births. And in <place reg="Berlin, Germany"
                >Berlin</place> for that same number of women between the same ages, he found 57
            births among the well-to-do and 147 among the poor; in <place reg="Vienna, Austria"
                >Vienna</place> it <del>went practically at</del>
            <add>was</add> the same proportion--67 to 197. And in <place reg="London, England"
                >London</place>, practically the same; and this is what we find in almost every
            large city in the world. </p>
        <p>But now let us look a little closer at that, because in my estimation that stationary
            problem among the well-to-do is not an immediate problem. You look at this group and we
            see that they may have perhaps two, three or four children; and the great majority of
            those children, the greatest percentage of those children are brought up to full
            maturity. It is in this group that we find a great percentage of health, of wealth, of
            comfort, of highest standards of living, the best standards of education; we find there
            the opportunity for development; not only for the father and mother, but the children
            themselves; we find there that although there are a few children, that those children
            are given the best advantages of education; they are the ones who fill our universities
            and our colleges. It is from this group that we <del>take and</del> fill the best
            offices of state and society.</p>
        <p>On the other hand we find that large family group and what do we discover there? You see
            there almost every problem that we are trying to solve today. You find large families
            have been perpetuated for generations, and you find <del>where</del>
            <add>there that</add> large families and poverty go hand in hand; you find the problems
            in that group have also been perpetuated; you find there poverty, misery, ignorance,
            infant mortality, maternal mortality, slums, over-crowding; you find there child labor,
            unemployment; you find every problem, practically every problem that we are trying to
            solve; and you find the one group on the one hand, the great percentage of them, are
            taxed, are over-burdened with charities, with the support of members of the other group. </p>
        <p>Now it seems to me that this one group, in perpetuating themselves, are also perpetuating
            for generations to come the evils that are here before us. <del>Now</del> most of us do
            not like these conditions and the most of us, in fact,--are trying to do all we can to
            alleviate the conditions in this large family group. But how do we go about it to remove
            them? There has been practically no attempt to really, <del>fundamentally</del> wipe out
            the evil conditions of society today. Rather do we attempt to alleviate, we attempt to
            legislate, we run off to our capitols and try to legislate out of existence child labor,
            infant morality, maternal mortality and all the other conditions that are here, and that
            we do abhor. But are we able to legislate them out of existence? Let us see today, for
            instance. Take infant mortality; that is a problem that affects us all. We have in this
            great country more that 250,000 infants who die each year before they reach one year of
            age. Ninety percent of those children die from causes due to poverty and neglect. Yet we
            allow <add>the</add>
            <del>to remain in ignorance</del> 500,000 parents of these children to remain in
            ignorance of how to prevent the coming of 250,00 more children the next year, ninety
            percent of whom will die of causes due to poverty and neglect.</p>
        <p>We don't get underneath the cause of infant mortality. In my work as a trained nurse in
                <place reg="New York, NY">New York City</place> for more than fourteen years I found
            there were causes that most of us close our eyes to today. For instance, one cause was
            two frequent pregnancies. pregnancies that did not always terminate in the birth of a
            child. Again I found children coming too close together, too close together for the
            mothers health. Take a mother who had to go out and toil, working sometimes the whole
            day, sometimes at night, <del>and she would come home when she worked at night</del>,
            she <del>would</del> come home through the day and carry on the duties of the mother and
            of the wife in the home. That mother was exhausted and was using up the capital of that
            child before it was born. How can you expect <del>that</del> those children born under
            such circumstances and conditions to have the vitality, the endurance to withstand the
            diseases of early infancy?</p>
        <p><del>And</del> again I found that women were rebelling against having too many children.
            I found women would rather die than have another child, and <del>they</del> were glad
            enough to face death in order to avoid it. Women who have five and six and seven
            children, whose husbands were toiling for a mere pittance,--every instinct in that
                woman<del>'s</del>
            <del>life and heart</del> told her that another child should not be born; <del>and</del>
            she had but one of two things to do: to resign herself to unlimited numbers of children,
            to unlimited pregnancies, or to perform illegal operations. And the rebellion of these
            women today is not resigning themselves to unlimited children, but they are resorting to
            illegal operations. This is the condition which we find when we are close to the
            mothers, close to the women who belong to the large family group.</p>
        <p>We also find that our maternal mortality problem is one that could be helped if we could
            get down to fundamentals. It is said that we have 22,000 mothers who pass out of life
            each year from causes incidental to pregnancy, <del>22,000</del>. Do you know what that
            means? That means that two mothers every hour of the night and that day pass out of
            life, pass into the great beyond from causes that might be prevented. You find among
            these mothers <del>that there will be</del> some <del>of them</del> who die from
            tuberculosis, and not so much tuberculosis as pregnancies during the development of the
            stages of tuberculosis. Out of every seven women who have tuberculosis four of them die,
            not from tuberculosis, but from pregnancy. Those women should never be allowed to become
            pregnant; and yet we know that the medical profession is allowed legally to relieve them
            of their pregnancy in order to save their lives; but they are sent back to their homes,
            back to the same environment and the same conditions without assistance, without advice,
            of how to prevent their getting into that condition again. We are like the ostrich--we
            have our heads in the sand; and we will not face the dangers.</p>
        <p>We have also women who suffer from kidney disease, from heart disease, and it is only
            fair and honest and right that these women at least should be helped and protected from
            further pregnancies because every time they become pregnant it means that that disease
            is enhanced, and there is one of two things for the physician to do: to let her develop
            her pregnancy and die, or to relieve her pregnancy.</p>
        <p>We find the same is true with our feeble minded. Dr. <person reg="Goddard, Henry H."
                >Goddard</person> has said that there are 400,000 feeble minded in the United
                States–-<del>and</del> I think this was in 1910--and only 34,000 of these 400,000
            are in institutions. The others are living amongst us; they are our neighbors; they--in
            fact--are forming a very great problem for future generations to solve. There we find
            among the feeble minded, that the feeble minded mother is three times as prolific as the
            normal woman, and we also find that a great percentage, over 65 percent, of the women
            living in prostitution are found to be feeble minded; and yet we close our eyes and let
            the feeble minded continue in reproduction. We have today an appalling problem with the
            insane and the feeble minded; <del>and when you think that the insane in practically
                every insane asylum are not sterilized,</del>
            <del>but </del><add>there are few institutions where the insane are sterilized</add>
            <add>yet </add>a certain proportion of <del>them</del>
            <add>the inmates</add> are allowed to go home <add>at intervals</add> and almost
            inevitably leave behind them progeny, <del>and then are</del>
            <add>while the parent is</add> returned to the asylum! We have many cases, and you have
            them here also, where men have <add>become temporarily sane &amp;</add> been allowed to
            go home <del>temporarily sane</del>, <del>and yet would only be home perhaps</del>
            <add>while within</add> a few weeks, sometimes a few days, <del>and</del> have returned
            raving maniacs, leaving behind them a pregnant wife. We have in most of our states --
                <del>and I suppose the <person reg="Kallikak family">Kalecks</person></del>
            <add>increasing problems from these conditions</add> and <person reg="Jukes family"
                >Jukes</person> family is familiar to all of you -- but it never hurts to bring to
            mind what is going on in practically every community of the United States today, as long
            as we allow the Feeble minded to reproduce. Here for instance, is the story of <person
                reg="Kallikak, Martin">Martin Kalack</person>, a feeble minded man who married
                <person reg="Kallikak, Rhoda">Rhoda</person>. This was in 1808. Four hundred and
            seventy known descendants; and of the progeny, there 143 feeble minded, 36 illegitimate
            children, 33 sexually immoral persons, mostly prostitutes,--24 confirmed alcoholics, 3
            epileptics, 82 who died in infancy, 3 proprietors of houses of ill-fame, and 3
            criminals.</p>
        <p>Again there were 12,00 descendants of the Jukes family in 75 years. Of these, 130 were
            professional paupers who, in all, spent 2,300 years in poor-houses; 50 prostitutes, 7
            murderers, 60 habitual thieves, and 130 common criminals. The expense of maintaining of
            this one family, including cost of prostitutes, and care of others in institutions
            amounted to $1,300,000. in this 75 years. That would be nothing compared to what they
            would cost today.</p>
        <p><del>Now</del> we know that in every state we have the <add><person reg="Kallikak family"
                    >Kalliack</person></add> family and the Jukes family, but we are reluctant to
            face fundamentals and to get at the bottom, <add>of</add>
            <del>in fact, I <unclear resp="MSPP">always say</unclear> that</del>. <del>And</del> I
            found in my own nursing work that we were very much today--and all social workers and
            nurses and doctors and those who are attempting to solve our social problems--that that
            we are all like the old fashioned quack--, the old fashioned quack who used to attempt
            to cure cancer by burning off the top. On the outside everything looked all right; but
            underneath the deadly disease continued to develop until the whole vitality of the
            individual was eaten up. We will take many of our societies today--and I think one that
            I would like to illustrate is the <org
                reg="New York Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Children">Society of
                Prevention of Cruelty to Children</org>, a most worthy society. My only objection to
            it is that it doesn't go back far enough. Why doesn't it attempt to prevent cruelty to
            children born of diseased parents? Why doesn't it prevent the cruelty of children being
            born in misery, in ignorance, in immorality? Why doesn't it herald the rights of the
            unborn child from the housetops?</p>
        <p>I often think that if children had something to say about their parents, I think we would
            have a little more responsibility in our parenthood. I would like to see parenthood a
            privilege, instead of an accident, as it is today. And I often wonder, if parents had to
            apply in some unknown and unusual way, if they had to apply as they have to apply today
            perhaps for maids or for chauffeurs, if they had to apply to some kind of state or
            social registry where the unborn child would have something to say, I can almost hear
            some of the questions the average child would ask, and I think the first question would
            be, "<q who="UNK">Mr. Father, have you a health certificate with you?</q>" I think the
            second question might be, "<q>How do you live? Where do you live? How many rooms have
                you got, and how is Mother's health; is she a happy comfortable, jolly mother, or is
                she a nervous, worn-out drudge, a wreck?</q>" And furthermore, it might say, "<q
                who="UNK">Well my dear parents-to-be, the talents, the potentialities of a genius
                are within me. Do you understand those elements in a child? Would you prepare for me
                the environment for the development of my talents?</q>"</p>
        <p>Is society <del>even</del> ready for that? And again it might say, "<q who="UNK">How do
                you plan to bring me up? Have you any plans for my life and my development? Am I to
                be a chimney sweep thrust out to earn my own living, or am I to have possibilities
                of perhaps being a president?</q>" And again I think it would say, "<q who="UNK"
                >What is your wage? What kind of table do you set? How many children have you got
                already?</q>" And when the answer would "<q who="UNK">Eight</q>", I think the
            average intelligent child would say, "<q> No thank you.</q>" (Laughter.)</p>
        <p>Now we all know that we have very stringent and rigid immigration laws in this country,
            by which we keep out of this <del>country</del> people, persons that,--well, that we
            just don't want here; we keep out those individuals who will become a burden upon the
            state; who won't let into the country an insane person or a diseased person; we won't
            let in a pauper; there has to be a certain amount of money that you must have in order
            to come into this country; you have to have somebody more or less responsible for you;
            and I think--if I am not mistaken--that we don't let people in if we don't like their
            ideas.</p>
        <p>But what about the enemy from within? Anyone in this country can become a father or
            mother. It makes no difference if you are diseased, if you are a pauper, if you are
            insane, no responsibility--no possibility of bringing up a child, or feeding it, no
            development of character for understanding the child. You can be cruel, you can be
            anything <add>in</add> any stage of <add>mental</add> development, <del>and</del>
            <add>yet</add> you are allowed to be a parent; and I think it is time that if we
            recognize that it is not right to bring individuals into this country in order to
            protect ourselves from them, then I think it is also necessary for us to protect
            ourselves from within. (Applause).</p>
        <p>Now many people ask us, in talking about this subject, they say "<q who="UNK">Do the
                people really want Birth Control?</q>"--People who have perhaps lived and enjoyed
            the existence of only their own kind of people do not recognize how desperate the women
            who are having children too often, how desperate they have become, and how they reach
            out to see information. Within the last week we have received within our organization
            1200 letters from mothers, and the letters are about like these,--I have just brought
            two of them to show you the nature of the letters, 1,200 of which we receive practically
            every week. That means more than 50,000 of these letters every year. The first one
            is:</p>
        <p rend="blockquote">"<q who="UNK">I was married when I was a girl of only 17. There were 13
                children of us. My father always drank and we had to go to work very young, myself
                when I was 11 years old, caring for the boarders in a large boarding house.</q></p>
        <p rend="blockquote">
            <q who="UNK">I have been married eight years. My first child was only a six months baby.
                She only lived three days. She was born in July and about January the first a
                miscarriage. The next January a little girl was born; in about four months another
                miscarriage; and then the next January 27 another girl; 21 months and a boy, who is
                now two years old; and I have had two miscarriages since then.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="blockquote">
            <q who="UNK">I have never had a chance to regain my real strength. When my second child
                was born I suffered a week from paralysis and I said then if I was ever that way
                again I would commit suicide.</q>
        </p>
        <p>(Second letter)</p>
        <p>These are just illustrations of the thousands and thousands of mothers who reach out
            their hands and they say "<q who="UNK">Please help me.</q>" What do they ask? They only
            ask a chance to bring up their children, those they have already got. They ask just for
            a little rest for themselves. Many of them say "<q who="UNK">I am already the mother of
                ten children.</q>" Sometimes they say they have had 20 pregnancies. Again they say
            they have had 15 births and they have six children living. And the story is "<q
                who="UNK">I just want a chance to rest. I want one night's sleep before I die.</q>"
            And they tell how night after night they get up to get a drink of water. And they never
            have one night's rest from the time they become a mother until they pass out of life.
            This is all they ask,--a chance to know their husbands, a chance to be a real mother to
            their children. And it seems to me as I look out on the world that every agency of
            church and state of society should be at the <del>fight</del>
            <add>feet</add> of these women, should be glad to help <del>them</del>, to assist them,
            to just get a little out of life, to be the real mothers that we want them to be. It
            seems very little to ask, <del>because</del> can any mother serve society when she
                <del>nearly</del>
            <add>would rather</add> die<del>d</del>
            <del>by having one child</del>
            <add>than have another child</add>? Can she serve society by having other children? I
            don't think so. I think that is the least we can do for these mothers.</p>
        <p><del>Now</del> many of us in working out these problems and in planning for a better
            civilization and a better society and meeting these problems fairly and squarely we have
            thought out some general rules that really should apply to make for a better
            civilization.</p>
        <p>I believe there are eight definite reasons when women should not have children: the first
            is, I think that no parents should have children when they themselves have diseases,
            transmissible diseases or when there is insanity, feeble-mindedness or epilepsy in their
            family. That seems a very matter of fact and east thing to ask and to demand; second, I
            believe that mothers or women should not be allowed to become pregnant while the mother
            is suffering from tuberculosis and any <del>kidney</del> disease, heart disease or
            pelvic deformities; she should not become pregnant until these diseases are cured;
            third, a woman or couple should not have children when the children they have already
            are not normal, even though they themselves are normal, but the children they have are
            subnormal. We know that these diseases go far back, and it is a call, a symptom and a
            sign that they should not have more when these that they already have are not up to
            standards; again, I believe that there should be at least two, if not three years apart
            from the births of children. A woman should have at least a year to recuperate from the
            strain and ordeal of the birth of one child; she should have a year to rest and try to
            prepare for the coming of the next child. Again, I think that today we want more than
            just the physical operation of bringing children into the world; we want children to
            have some of the development, some of the benefits of our intellectual development; so
            that, I believe that young girls should not have children. A women should be at least 22
            if not 23 years old. Not that a woman could not give birth to perfectly healthy children
            younger. She can. We have seen them even at 14 and 15 giving birth to perfectly healthy
            children; but after all, the adolescent period has not passed until the 22d or 23d year
            and it seems to me that it is no longer necessary nor good for women to become mothers
            until they have passed through the adolescent period, until the physical, the mental and
            we might say the psychic side of her nature have developed and <del>have been</del>
            <add>all</add> interlocked.</p>
        <p>And again we say that parents should not become parents until their economic condition is
            such that they can give to children the best possible advantages of the day. I also
            believe that a woman should not have children until she is well rested, not while she is
            fatigues from early labors, for instance, many children who come to work early, young
            girls who go to work at 10, 12 and 13 years, marry and become mothers almost
            immediately. I believe that every woman should rest from such toil for at least two, if
            not three years, before she becomes a mother.</p>
        <p>I found in <place>Scotland</place> in one district that was practically built up during
            the war that out of 5,000 mothers or parents who were there, all having small families
            because they were all quite young, the teacher said that 85% of the first children born
            of these parents would fall to sleep some time during the day at school; and in her
            calculations and mine we found that these mothers, almost all of them, had been to work
            in the <place reg="Lancashire, England">Lancashire</place> cotton districts and had gone
            to work when they were 9 and 10 years old. The mothers were always tired. They had never
            had a chance to rest and they were married and became mothers almost immediately after
            marriage.</p>
        <p>And again,--and perhaps many of you will not agree with this, but I believe that no young
            couple should have parenthood thrust upon them; and that, furthermore, they should not
            have children for at least two years after they are married. Now I believe in early
            marriages, but I <del>always</del>
            <add>also</add> believe in building up the marriage relation; I believe in building up
            the home <del>as a</del>
            <add>in</add> preparation, as a nest for the coming of the children that are wanted.</p>
        <p><del>Now,</del> I have seen and I believe that if two young people entering into the
            marriage state had a year or two years to know each other, to play together, to read
            together, to develop their love lives, I believe that there would be a finer, and a
            stronger bond between them; I believe also that the waiting and the building up of this
            bond of love and harmony between them would intensify the desire for maternity. I have
            seen it through the war when many young women wanting to be married and dreading the
            fact that the man they loved would be called away, did not want to have children under
            those conditions and we have seen many cases where that same woman said: "<q who="UNK">I
                am not never to be a mother; I don't believe I would understand children and I have
                no particular maternal instinct in myself.</q>" We have definitely seen that most of
            those women have come back and said "<q who="UNK">This thing has awakened in me. I want
                to have children.</q>"</p>
        <p><del>And so</del> we believe in waiting for a year or two <add>fix up</add> after
            marriage before parenthood comes <add>upon them</add>
            <del>them</del>.</p>
        <p><del>Now, often all</del>, when you look out and when you see what we do today,--we pick
            out our young girls and our boys and we bring up our daughters <del>with an instinct of
                rebellion about</del>
            <add>to regard with resentment</add> everything concerning the <add>sex</add> relations,
                <del>of men and women;</del> and then, miraculously, we put a marriage certificate
            in that girl's hands, and <del>we</del> think that everything is going to be beautiful.
            It doesn't work that way. Love is like a plant; it has to be nurtured; it has to be
            developed; it has to be cared for. It is not a thing that just happens accidentally. And
            we believe in building up <del>that</del>
            <add>a</add> love relationship before a child is called into being. These are
                <del>practically</del>
            <add>some of </add>the <add>simple</add> rules <add>of life</add> we say that people
            should <del>have</del>
            <del>applied</del>
            <add>apply</add> to themselves if they desire to make for happier homes and also to take
            part in being part of a hardier and healthier race.</p>
        <p><del>Now</del> most of us believe that Birth Control might be a good thing in some cases,
            but we all more or less have some objections, and I am not going to take up the time for
            all these objections, but I am just going to dwell upon one or two of them: the first
            objection that is raised almost universally--I found the same objection in
                <place>Japan</place> and in <place>China</place>; you find it everywhere--the
            objection is that if women have information to prevent conception,--in other words, if
            they know how to avoid having children,--that the race will die out, <del>that we wont
                have children</del>
            <add>that there will be race suicide.</add></p>
        <p><del>Now</del> I believe that that is absolutely false. I think that in the first place
            the knowledge of Birth Control does not interfere in any way with anyone who desires a
            big family. We only hope to bring it to those who don't want to have a big family; and
            we say as we see it is a sound principle, that we believe that those who don't want to
            have a big family should have the same privilege as those who do want to have a big
            family. That is all.</p>
        <p><del>Now</del> The instinct of maternity is not a thing that can be wiped out or killed
            by such a simple thing as knowledge. The instinct is too old; and if any of you have
            seen the cases that I have seen in my gynecological work,--women who thought they could
            not become mothers, if you could see and know the agony and pain that they have endured
            in going though operations when there has only been one chance in a hundred that that
            operation would result in giving that women the power of maternity! And yet hundreds and
            hundreds of these women take that one chance. The maternal instinct is very deep and one
            of the reasons today <del>that</del>
            <add>why</add> (I believe) we have small families, sometimes only one child in a family,
            is because that child has come too quickly into that woman's life. She has never had a
            chance to develop herself; she has been first a girl, then a mother. This wife in her,
            the woman in her had never had a chance to evolve; <del>and also any</del>
            <add>the fact that motherhood was accidental or enforced make that</add> condition
                <del>thrust upon us becomes</del> abhorrent to <del>us</del>
            <add>her</add>. If she had waited for a time after her marriage, if there had been a
            chance to develop that maternal instinct in her, motherhood would have been a joy to her
            and not a dread and a fear. And I believe that this knowledge <add>of BC will increase
                the desire for motherhood</add>
            <del>the instinct will be developed</del>. </p>
        <p>Also we found in the high birth-rate and low birth-rate countries this fact,--that in the
            high birth-rate countries, like China, where there has been no <add>conscious</add>
            Birth Control <del>applied</del> where women have brought to birth children as often as
            nature has allowed it, the population has remained practically stationary for some
            hundred years. On the other hand, the low birth-rate countries, with the exception of
                <place>France</place>, which I will take up later, the low birth-rate countries,
            like <place>England</place> and <place>Germany</place>, <place reg="the Netherlands"
                >Holland</place>, <place>New Zealand</place>, and <place>Australia</place>, these
            countries, while the birth-rate has been lower and has continued to be lower, the infant
            mortality and the general death-rate have also been lower; consequently the population
            has increased.</p>
        <p>And certainly we have three very good examples of what Birth-Control, when nationally
            applied and controlled, can do to disprove the argument of race suicide in such
            countries as Holland and New Zealand and Australia. for, in Holland, for instance, in 35
            years her birth-rate has decreased; her infant mortality in <place
                reg="Amsterdam, Netherlands">Amsterdam</place>, <place reg="Rotterdam, Netherlands"
                >Rotterdam</place> and the <place reg="the Hague, Netherlands">Hague</place> is
            lowest of any <del>states</del>
            <add>cities</add> in the world, and this <add>is</add> particularly so since Birth
            Control has been established there <del>in cities</del>. Holland has the fastest
            increasing population of any country in Europe. <del>She also has a very queer thing
                that has developed there that we cannot find in any other country and that is taken
                from the army statistics in 1915:--she not only had the highest military standing
                but she had the highest male stature in these 40 years. So</del> that Birth Control
            goes for race improvement as well as increasing the population.</p>
        <p>The race suicide theory simply does not stand. And besides, I often say to people who say
            that they are standing for bigger populations, they want more people to justify our
            existence, they will not be consistent, because if they were consistent they might stand
            for polygamy. There is no quicker way in the world of getting big families than through
            polygamy; but it doesn't stand; and they don't really stand for big families or
            increased population.</p>
        <p>Another objection is that it is going to lead to immorality. That is a very serious
            objection and one that we cannot pass over lightly. It is <del>a</del>
            <add>this aspect of the </add>subject which took me to <place>Europe</place> before
            Birth Control was <del>taken up</del>
            <add>launched</add> in the United States. I found, for instance, in Japan, that my son
            and I had to revise our ideas of morality. I found that the things we found immoral here
            were found very moral in Japan. Morality today has been immorality a hundred years ago
            and immorality today is likely to be morality a hundred years from now. I think it is an
            insult to suggest that our women will become promiscuous if they have knowledge or if
            they have not the fear of the result to keep them moral. In other words, you <del>have
                got to</del> be <add>the inference is that a woman must</add> be kept ignorant to
                <del>be kept living</del>
            <add>live</add> a clean life. I don't believe that is true.</p>
        <p>Again, we might say that everything can be mis-used. All knowledge can be mis-used; we
            know that. Everything today has some mis-use of it. But we don't stop the progress of
            humanity because of the few who mis-use things. Automobiles can be mis-used; certainly
            razors can be mis-used, and as a matter of fact, when razors were first put on the
            market there was just the same objection. In the old days <add>a</add> man <add>could
                not shave himself</add>
            <add>only</add> a doctor had <del>to shave a man secretly</del>
            <add>that privilege</add>; <del>then</del>
            <add>later</add> they had a public barber; and gradually men began to buy razors and
            shave themselves. And they said, "<q who="UNK">Why, if you let any man have a razor
                    <del>and</del>
                <add>to</add> shave <del>a man</del> he will cut the throat of the man he <del>is
                    mad with</del>
                <add>quarrels with</add>.</q>" <del>We know the whole </del>
            <add>The</add> secret of life is to teach people the proper use of knowledge. And that
            is what we have got to do with knowledge of Birth Control. We have got to teach
                <add>young people</add> the proper use <add>of knowledge</add>.</p>
        <p>Again, we found in Holland, instead of increasing immorality it <del>made</del> increased
                <del>in</del>
            <add>the</add> marriage <add>rate</add>. Young people were not afraid to get married and
                <del>they</del> were not afraid of a big family <del>that</del> they could not
            support. In 1914 I went to the <org reg="Netherlands Central Bureau for Genealogy"
                >Central Bureau</org> of the Hague and I was challenged to find a native woman alive
            in Holland at that time who was a prostitute. The first thing the parents do when they
            see the boy and girl interested in each other, if they are both of the families that
            they like, they encourage an early marriage and then they get their information from the
            Birth Control Clinics, of which there are 55 in that little country today. And they are
            impressed with the responsibility of having children; they are told that to have a child
            is the greatest responsibility in the world and you have no moral right to have children
            that you cannot take care of; you have no right to have more children than you can
            support; you should not just have children and have your neighbor bring them up. And so
            the responsibility of parenthood is impressed upon the young couple very early.</p>
        <p>They look upon it, and have even used the argument to me, "<q who="UNK">Why should we
                have children any more than we should have an automobile? It isn't only the having
                it here but it is the keeping it up.</q>" And this is the way the Dutch mind looks
            upon having children. It has not increased immorality; it has increased morality.
            Marriages are popular; there has been an increase of total marriages. Immorality and
            prostitution have decreased. By this I don't want anyone to think there is no
            prostitution in Holland. There was prostitution in Holland even then; but they told me
            it was professionals that came in from France and Germany to catch the trade.</p>
        <p>Whether those same facts and statistics stand together today I don't know. It may be that
            the war has changed the conditions; but up to 1914 that was the condition in Holland.
            After all, we know that early marriages will do just that.</p>
        <p>Again, we find that 77% of the men who frequent houses of prostitution are married men.
            Now, let us see why that is. In my own nursing experience I found a very extraordinary
            thing developing in this country, and that is, the wrong concept of the relations of
            marriage, the wrong concept of the whole process of creation. Women have developed
            almost a cloak of frigidity and they have an ideal in that frigidity; they believe that
            is the natural and right and spiritual way to be. I contradict that and I don't believe
            that that is the condition to create in themselves or that it is going to make for
            happiness in the home. And I also found that a woman would say to me, "<q who="UNK"
                >Well, my husband is a perfectly fine man; he is one of the best in the world; but
                if only, well, if only this relationship of marriage did not exist I would be
                perfectly happy.</q>" Now that man, on the other hand, is a creature of evolution of
            nature and of expression. And we find there is one of the causes for this great
            percentage of men who visit prostitutes. So that we say that Birth Control knowledge
            back of that is going to help that woman to remove from her the fear of pregnancy
            because back of that frigidity is often the fear of pregnancy. She has standards to live
            up to; she has her life which she is developing and she does not want a big family; and
            the consequence is that she usually drives her husband away from her. They do not
            develop together fully; and immorality, or rather, lack of Birth Control is the cause of
            immorality in the home as well as out of the home. We believe that Birth Control is
            going to build up the home; it is going to stand for early marriages and for finer
            companionship in the home after marriage.</p>
        <p>There is only one other objection that I am going to take up and that is that people say,
                "<q who="UNK">Wouldn't you do much better for the world if you were talking about
                self control rather than birth control?</q>" Perhaps I would; I don't know; but let
            us look at what one means by control. After all, we all have to be controlled; I believe
            in self control; I believe in it most decidedly, most emphatically; but I believe in it
            as part of our development of character; I believe in it as part of our development in
            social evolution. We have to be controlled. I also believe in it as part of the beauty
            of marriage and of our comradeship in marriage: but I don't believe in it is a good nor
            right method of Birth Control. I don't believe it is the best method of Birth
            Control.</p>
        <p>Now, what do they mean, to be very frank. Let us look at these things frankly. It may
            mean when they say control, they may mean that the relation of marriage or the union of
            marriage should take place only for pro-creation. Well, that means that the average
            normal people who can only afford to have two or three children, to bring them up
            properly, that this relationship, which is allied to the divine, shall take place in
            your lives but two or three times. I think that is unduly harsh and unnecessary and is
            also a condition that cannot be lived up to by the average normal people.</p>
        <p>Secondly, we must remember that even the most controlled people--and I have many cases in
            mind where people are controlled to the fullest of their ability--and yet with only one
            union a year there have been big families because that is all it takes to have one
            child,--a year and a half,--and you can have 15 or 16 children in a life-time.</p>
        <p>Again, they say they believe that there is a certain period in a woman's development when
            she is partly or wholly sterile; and this is untrue; it is absolutely untrue as applied
            to every woman. If it were true and if that is what is meant by control there might be
            some possibility of its being enacted; but when it is absolutely denied by the medical
            profession that this state exists in the average woman ,--in fact, they say it is only
            one percent of women who are at this time partly sterile,--so we say that control
            instead of birth control is not practicable.</p>
        <p>Here is a case that came to me, a <add>social</add> worker has a very severe cardiac
            case; the woman was suffering from heart trouble and was pregnant. This social worker
            was rather annoyed at this condition, so she took it upon herself to call upon
                <del>this</del> husband <add>of the woman</add> on Sunday when he was at home. He
            was a young man about 32, a very fine, decent man and he loved his wife and loved his
            children; he was what his wife called a <del>home body</del>
            <add>"good man."</add> He was a truck driver. This little nurse went to him and
                <del>she</del> told him he was taking his wife's life in his hands if she had
            another child. The man was amazed. What could he do? And this nurse, after calling him a
            few uncomplimentary names, said he should control himself. He said he would; it was the
            last thing he wanted to do to bring his wife to the grave. So the nurse went on; they
            had just a few <del>farms</del>
            <add>rooms</add> there. But in a short time, less than three months, this little wife
            came back to the social worker and she said to her "<q who="UNK">You have ruined my
                husband; I had a good husband, a good man who never struck me, who never struck the
                children, but was always home; who gave me his money and we were happy together. Now
                I have a man who has turned into a brute; he <del>corrected</del>
                <add>beat</add> one of the children and when I tried to plead with him he struck me.
                He is never home; he is always out on the corner with <del>one</del>
                <add>some</add> of the loafers.</q>" And she said "<q who="UNK"> It is your fault;
                something that you said to him; and he has not been the same with me. I would rather
                have <add>a</add> child every year and have the love of my husband, than the kind of
                man you have made.</q>" This social worker was very much disturbed; she went to one
            of the physicians in charge and asked him about this case, and he said, "<q who="UNK"
                >That is perfectly right; that is just exactly what would happen.</q>" This man
                <del>who</del> was a primitive sort of man was <del>simply</del> thrust out of one
            state of his evolution and put into another. It was suppression, <del>which was
                something in</del>
            <add>from without self control is</add> a condition that we have to live up to, that we
            have to evolve to. This is what self-control is; it is not a thing that can be thrust
            upon one from without; it must be worked up from within. Control is a beautiful thing
            which we should evolve to and develop within ourselves; but it is not either a practical
            for all people nor is it the best or the most harmless method of Birth Control.</p>
        <p><del>Now</del> there are many,--in fact, I want to say there are three kinds of Birth
            Control; and I do hope if anyone who has come here this afternoon has expected me to
            discuss the methods of Birth control--so many people have thought the methods of Birth
            Control would be discussed from the platform--it has never been our method or custom to
            discuss them here. We want to establish clinics in all thickly populated communities. We
            want them as they have them in Holland; they also have them in England, and also in
            China; and we in the United States still have none. We want these to be the places with
            doctors and trained nurses in charge so that women or men may come there and receive
            individual instruction suitable to fit <add>the</add> individual <del>women</del>
            <add>womans case</add>. We want to raise this subject of Birth Control from the gutter
            where it has been placed by our laws. We want to raise it to the same plane with other
            scientific measures. There are three methods: <add>continue: sterilization and means
                that prevent contraception</add> one method is continence or celibacy, perhaps
                <del>the</del>
            <add>this</add>
            <del>best</del>
            <add>safest</add> we have ever <del>heard of</del>
            <add>known</add>. <del>Do you know that in your state that is a crime -- to live a
                celibate today? Because your law says that you cannot use methods of Birth Control,
                and yet there is not a better method of Birth Control known in all the world today
                than to remain single. So all you single people who are over the age of maturity
                should be imprisoned. But, as Mrs. Porritt said, that is unique. You have that very
                unique law.</del>
            <del>Yet, </del>continence is a method; sterilization is a method--and there are two
            kinds, surgical and that <del>as</del>
            <add>which is</add> induced by the X-ray. There is no doubt that the X-ray is going to
                <del>take</del>
            <add>play</add> a very important part in the whole process of Birth Control in the
            future. It is said they are now developing the X-ray to such an extent that they will in
            time be able to control the dosage; that is, that a woman suffering from tuberculosis
            should not become a mother until she is cured, that she can be made sterile by the X-ray
            for a period of three to five years and when she is cured then the power of motherhood
            would return to her. If this is perfected it will be one perhaps of the best methods of
            Birth Control.</p>
        <p>Then from continence and sterilization we come to the medicinal and mechanical methods of
            Birth Control which would be common in public clinics which we want the physicians to
            give as applied to each individual, because every individual woman is different. A woman
            who has had nine or ten children and who has not perhaps had the best surgical care
            after the birth of her children must have different advice and different instruction
            from the woman who has had only one or two children. So we want to make this instruction
            individual, have it scientific, have it so the poorest woman can have the best
            information to her needs, physical, economical and often spiritual, because we want to
            direct this woman for the best interests of the race.</p>
        <p>Now friends, after eight months' trip around the world I have found this,--that the
            people of all the world believe in and want to practice Birth Control. It is evidently
            all a process of responsibility. We want to be responsible for our acts. The people of
            China, of Japan, of <place>India</place>, of all the European countries, look to this as
            to a tolerance, while the governments of the same countries are blind to its
            improvement; they are blind to its improvement in reducing taxation, in reducing the
            burdens of charities.</p>
        <p>Again we find churches are very timid in coming out and taking a stand for it, but we
            have had a few illuminating examples, such as <add>Lord <person
                    reg="Dawson, Bertram Edward">Dawson</person></add> physician who came to the
                <org reg="Lambeth Conference">conference at <place reg="Lambeth, England"
                    >Lambeth</place></org> last year, and took his stand firmly for Birth Control
            and told the people that unless they listened to them, they might just as well close
            their doors. Then there is Dean <add><person reg="Inge, William Ralph"
                >Inge</person></add> of St. Paul's Cathedral. You have men like <person
                reg="Wells, H. G.">H. G. Wells</person>, <person reg="Murray, Gilbert">Gilbert
                Murray</person> of Oxford, <person reg="Russell, Betrand">Bertrand Russell</person>,
                <person reg="Cox, Harold">Harold Cox</person>. You have some of the finest thinking
            men in England; and <person reg="Keynes, John Maynard">John Maynard</person> is also
            standing for Birth Control. He told me in <place reg="London, England">London </place>
            that this subject of Birth Control was a most important subject on the political horizon
            and he said unless we are going to recognize the population question, we may as well
            throw all our peace treaties and our agreements between nations in the waste paper
            basket; they can never come to anything until the population question is recognized.
            This is not only an individual problem, it is not only a national problem, it is a race,
            it is a world problem. I agree with H. G. Wells, who says in his last book that the
            whole world is crammed with meaningless lives, hordes of people who are born, who live,
            who die, and have done nothing to move the race forward one iota. There have been
            repetitions, all that has been said has been said before; all that they have done better
            before. They come and use up the energies and the resources of the earth.</p>
        <p>Now on the other hand, what we are trying to do is to make for a better world, and we
            maintain that the greatness of a country cannot be measured by the size of its
            population. You have got to ask yourself, "<q who="UNK">Is your country breeding great
                men and women? Is it creating immortal records of poetry, art and science, and are
                these being used for the development of mankind?</q>" We want to make the world a
            saner, better, cleaner place. We are fighting for the women and the children of this
            generation; we are fighting for the women and children and the men of the next
            generation; and we want to safeguard everything that affects the dignity of motherhood.
            We also want to raise motherhood from the degradation and servility and sex slavery to a
            glorified privilege. We want to free woman from incessant child bearing; we want to free
            her from undesired pregnancy. We want children conceived in love and to be born only
            when they are wanted. Then we want to make these bodies of ours holy temples; we want to
            make them fit and perfect symbols that will be ready when examined to take its part in
            the mystery of material being. </p>
        <p>(Applause)</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
