<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed draft article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2009/07/30 LL</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/11/30 PS Transcribed newly discovered draft of what we had been publishing as
            235041</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/12/05 PS Finished transcription and indexing</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-02 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1932-03-22">22 Mar. 1932</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>World Population Increase and War</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp235041</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sopia Smith Collection, Smith College.</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title>, S71:404.</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>For other versions see Library of Congress Microfilm 48:256B, <title>Margaret Sanger
                Microfilm</title> S71:370, 374, and 384.</p>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="population growth and"/>
        <index level1="Italy" level2="overpopulation and"/>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="overpopulation and"/>
        <index level1="overpopulation" level2="colonialism and"/>
        <index level1="overpopulation" level2="effects of"/>
        <index level1="overpopulation" level2="emigration and"/>
        <index level1="overpopulation" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="population growth" level2="natural resources and"/>
        <index level1="war"/>
        <index level1="war" level2="causes of"/>
        <index level1="war" level2="overpopulation and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <p>In the past there have been many and diverse causes of War, but the economic factors and
            the pressure of population on the resources of <del>the</del>
            <add>a</add> country are pre-eminently at the root of our modern wars.</p>
        <p><del>Just as</del><add>It is an acknowledged fact that</add> the big battalions of babies
                <del>make</del><add>have made</add> the working man's life a constant battle to keep
            his productive or labor powers up to <add>the need of</add> his reproductive
                powers<del>, so has</del>. <add>We also know that</add> the revolution in modern
            industry <add>has</add> made the necessity for man power of less value than the ox or
            the dray horse.</p>
        <p>The tragic difference is that the reproduction of the ox or dray horse is controlled and
            its numbers predicated on potential needs. While the man with only his labor power to
            sell, proceeds to multiply and increase his numbers regardless of his own ability to
            provide for his offspring or regardless of the social or economic needs of <del>men
                power</del>
            <add>the labor that he has to sell.</add></p>
        <p>There are two or three essential and fundamental factors to recognize at the beginning of
            any plan for National or International Peace.</p>
        <p>1. Normal marriage leads to offspring.</p>
        <p>2. The normal couple can produce during the child-bearing years from ten to twelve
            children.</p>
        <p>3. Unless death through disease, famines or other misfortune, takes off a large number of
            these children yearly, no social order known today can provide and maintain <add>the
                multiplication &amp; increase of</add>such vast numbers in so short a period.</p>
        <p><del>Just as an</del>
            <add>An</add> acre of land is limited to the number of plants it can occupy<del>, <gap
                    extent="two words"/> a man's labor power limited to the number of children he
                can decently provide for.</del></p>
        <p>5. <del>That the</del> The social factors, or returns to the State from slums and
            over-crowded territories <del>dwindle</del> decrease rather than increase our racial
            wealth.</p>
        <p><add>Populations have been kept down in the past by keeping the death rate almost equal
                to the birth rate. The survival rate was very low but it allowed for a healthy, fit
                population and enabled it to compete in the struggle for existence. Today we have
                changed all this. We can not allow disease, floods, pestilences and famines to
                spread over a civilized land. The consequence is that we have greatly lowered our
                death rate while we have at the same time increased the longevity of adult men and
                women.</add></p>
        <p><add>Both of these good factors have been obtained mainly through the lowering of our
                birth rate. Those Nations who fight against this civilized means of applying science
                to the control of population, become the danger spots in World Peace.</add></p>
        <p>With these facts in mind, we know that the quality of a population making up a State is
            an <add>equally</add> important factor in its progress. A population on any given
            territory must produce its own food or get food from other areas. Not only food but the
            necessary means of maintenance which today means oil, iron, fuel and natural resources.
            If a Nation can not maintain its population, <del>it leads</del>
            <add>the first effort</add> to the only way out <del>-</del>
            <add>is through emigration.</add></p>
        <p><add>But</add> when other countries close their gates against migrants, they are then
            forced to remain at home. <del>They then have one of three problems <add>to
                face</add>.</del><add>There are then but three remaining solutions to their
                problem.</add></p>
        <p>1. Reduce the birth rate.</p>
        <p>2. Lower the standards of living.</p>
        <p>Expand into other territory by force of Arms and declare War.</p>
        <p><place>Japan</place> has recently given us an excellent example of
                <del>this</del><add>the</add> fact <add>of overpopulation</add>. She has a
            population of approximately 60,000,000 according to the census of 1928. She has
                <add>about</add> 150,000 square miles of territory. Only one-sixth of this area is
            cultivable which brings her density of population up to 993 persons a square mile - the
            highest in the world. She has an enormously high birth rate of 34.8 and a death rate of
            19.2 - the second highest natural increase <del>than</del>
            <add>of</add> any country <add>today</add>
            <del>in the world</del>. <del>From</del>
            <add>Besides this she has an increase of</add> 800,000 to 900,000 infants a year.</p>
        <p>Japan has not the resources to feed <del>her</del>
            <add>this growing</add> population. <del>Japan</del>
            <add>She</add> has not been allowed free access to other lands as <add>other</add>
            European <add><unclear resp="MSPP">aliens</unclear></add>. The world has closed its
            doors against her surplus population. Japan has not the natural resources of iron and
            coal to become a manufacturing or industrial nation which could be exchanged for food.
            Her silk industry can not provide sufficiently for her needs. Her standards of living
            were fairly high. <del>Her population is</del>
            <add>Japan's population is highly intelligent &amp; largely literate, which like Germany
                in 1914 must have an outlet as well as a return on her [ILLEGIBILE] for educational
                facilities.</add></p>
        <p>She had three ways to settle the problem.</p>
        <p>1. To lower her standards of living and increase her death rate.</p>
        <p>2. Decrease the birth rate to a very low figure as quickly as possible to check the
            increase of numbers.</p>
        <p>3. To acquire new territories where she <del>could</del>
            <add>can</add> have ready access to fuel and mineral resources in order to create
            industries and provide for the needs of her present and future population.</p>
        <p>We know now which of the above Japan chose to do. She had little or no choice <del>in the
                way out in 1932</del>
            <add>after she allowed conditions to drift until 1932</add>. A far seeing Government
            would have <del>at least</del> attempted to prevent the now inevitable catastrophy by
            encouraging a check on the birth rate back in 1910 when the <name type="law"
                reg="Chinese Exclusion Act">U.S.A. Exclusion Act</name> spread to
                <place>Australia</place> and other countries.</p>
        <p><add>Italy is preparing herself to go the way of Japan. Already she has a population
                which <del>her</del> she cannot feed from her own soil.</add></p>
        <p>The population in 1927 was 40,548,683, her birth rate 26.4, which had decreased as other
            countries in <place>Europe</place> had since 1914.</p>
        <p>Her death rate of 15.5 had also decreased giving her a natural increase of 10.9 per
            thousand, far too high for the peace of Europe. She has not over 120,000 square miles of
            of territory, less than that of Japan proper.</p>
        <p>As Italian emigrants are now practically barred from <place reg="United States"
                >U.S.A.</place> it means that she must provide for the surplus of 90,000(?) Italians
            who came each year to this country &amp; settled here more or less permanently before
            the ban.</p>
        <p><place>Italy</place>'s problem then is to absorb the 25% natural increase or an
            additional 500,000 persons into her national economy each year. Her density of
            population is about 325 per square mile, which is the danger point for any nation in
            this day of modern industry with the craze for foreign markets. Italy, like Japan, has a
            choice of ways to meet the situation but unlike Japan she has deliberately set her <gap
                extent="one word" reason="illegible"/> by the authority of Church &amp; State &amp;
            refuses to control her birth rate.</p>
        <p>To this course of action, <gap extent="one word" reason="illegible"/> her policy of
            reckless breeding, will bring about an International situation the detriment of which
            can scarcely now be gauged.</p>
        <p><del>Then may </del></p>
        <p>Their need be no excuses today for any nation overflowing its boundaries. Population
            increase must &amp; should be controlled, not only as to its births, but as to its
            distribution.</p>
        <p>The death rate is already partially controlled through the Administration of Public
            Health Agencies. The birth rate must likewise be regarded as fully imporant
            consideration &amp; responsibility. If we would lay the foundation for World Peace</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
