<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/06/13 CE</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/06/20 CE</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011-11-28 CH correct typo</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-01 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1937-06-27">27 June 1937</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Why Birth Control is Needed</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236023</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Smith College</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S71:0936</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="IHBCD" type="song">I Heard the Bells on Christmas Day</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger</person> used this speech as a short radio address, to be used in <place>Tampa,
            FL</place> and elsewhere. The suggested introduction reads, "Mrs. Margaret Sanger, who coined
            the term <emph rend="underline">birth control</emph> and put this vital health movement
            on the map of the world will speak to you and tell why <emph rend="underline">Birth
                Control is Needed</emph>.</p>
        <index level1="abortion" level2="birth control vs."/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues" level3="in US"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="definitions of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="economic benefits and risks of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits and risks"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="in marriages"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"
            level3="negative consequences of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Federal"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="legalization of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods"/>
        <index level1="child spacing"/>
        <index level1="family planning"/>
        <index level1="men" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
        <index level1="New York City" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="pregnancy" level2="fears of"/>
        <index level1="&quot;unfit&quot; to reproduce" level2="descriptions of"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="government" level3="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Radio address for phonograph transcription.</head>
        <p>Before telling you why I fervently believe birth control is needed not only in <place
                reg="United States">America</place> but throughout the world, I want to make clear
            what the term really means. For this is a movement which has aroused both loyal support
            and unfortunate opposition. The latter comes, I feel, from a misunderstanding of what
            birth control can do to help mothers and children, and to make a better race.</p>
        <p>Birth control is the <emph rend="underline">conscious</emph> control of the birth rate by
            methods which temporarily prevent conception. Please note the words. <emph
                rend="underline">Control</emph>: which has a positive as well as a negative meaning.
            Note the words: <emph rend="underline">to prevent conception</emph>. a very different
            thing from destruction of life after it has begun. Birth Control must not be confused
            with abortion, for they are poles apart. And one of the major benefits of adequate birth
            control information and its practise is that it will save women from taking such
            dangerous and desparate a step.</p>
        <p>When physicians and scientists discovered safe, reliable and easily learned ways of
            enabling parents to plan their families and space their children, a new day of hope
            dawned for women and for mankind. Up to that time mothers everywhere had been at the
            mercy of blind chance, they were forced through ignorance to go on bearing children
            whether they were physically and mentally fit or not. Unwanted children, overburdened
            parents, such is the toll of ignorance.</p>
        <p>The story of man’s attempt to control population goes far back into ancient times, but
            modern scientific birth control as we know it today, is a discovery of the twentieth
            century.</p>
        <p>Birth control is needed by every married couple in order that they may plan their
            families according to several basic conditions. <emph rend="underline">First</emph> and
            foremost, the health of the mother, for no woman should bear a child while she is ill.
            In so doing she is unfair to herself and to her child. <emph rend="underline"
                >Second</emph>, no child should be born if either mother or father carry hereditary
            taint which can be transmitted to the next generation. And <emph rend="underline"
                >third</emph>, a family should be planned with due regard to the father’s earnings,
            so that all the children can be given a fair start in life and an adequate
            education.</p>
        <p>These three conditions sound like simple common sense. Yet, despite the discoveries of
            science, thousands, no millions, of women in America today are still in ignorance and
            darkness. I wish you could read the records of any birth control clinic, or the letters
            which I receive from women pleading for help. Women broken in body and spirit by endless
            childbearing; women trying to bring up their families when the father is out of work,
            driven to distraction by fear of the coming of another baby; women with tuberculosis,
            heart trouble, other conditions which make pregnancy dangerous. And young, ambitious
            couples starting out in life who want to plan their families, space their children, and
            enter the career of parenthood voluntarily, masters--not victims--of their fate.</p>
        <p>If you know of such mothers, such families, if you who are listening to me feel that you
            can be a better mother by learning about birth control, talk the matter over with your
            own family doctor. If that is not possible, and you cannot afford to go to some
            physician for advice, find out if there is a birth control clinic in your community. For
            in more than 350 cities and towns, clinics, often called motehrs health centers, have
            been started so that no mother need be deprived of this modern help because of the
            smallness of her income.</p>
        <p>Here in America we have fought a winning fight against taboos and bigotry, against
            inertia and misunderstanding. Our laws have been stupid and muddled, so that no one knew
            what was legal and what was forbidden. All that is now happily changed. For in a test
            case, the <org>United States Circuit Court of Appeals</org> recently gave out a decision
            clarifying and interpreting the old Federal laws which had been so great a stumbling
            block to progress. The intention of these laws, so ruled the wise judges, was not to
            prevent the conscientious physician from giving contraceptive advice for the health or
            well being of his patients. Thus the law of the land now recognizes birth control,
            legally, as a necessary part of medical practice.</p>
        <p>Further and significant progress was made when the <org>American Medical
                Association</org>, which represents organized medicine in this country, unanimously
            adopted the report of its <org
                reg="American Medical Association Committee to Study Contraceptive Practices"
                >Committee to Study Contraceptive Practices</org>. This report recommended that
            birth control be taught in medical schools and that methods and materials be studied and
            reported on.</p>
        <p>Thus the organized medical profession has taken a step to check harmful, unreliable
            “over-the-counter” methods, and to make clear that birth control, to be reliable, safe,
            and harmless, must be prescribed <emph>for</emph> the individual woman <emph
                rend="underline">by a physician</emph>.</p>
        <p>With medical and legal recognition, every hospital in the country, every health and
            welfare agency can include this life saving and truly humane service in its program.</p>
        <p>Birth control will bring health and happiness to countless families. It will save the
            lives of thousands of mothers. In saving the lives of mothers it saves lives of infants
            as well. It will, through controlling overpopulation, bring about--if anything can--and
            promote, “<q who="IHBCD">Peace on earth, good will to men</q>” over the entire face of
            the globe.</p>
        <p>Closing announcement: You have been listening to <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret
                Sanger</person>, birth control leader, who has just told you what she feels this
            movement can do to bring happiness to women and children. If there is a clinic in your
            community, use it and support it; if not, help to start one. To do this is to take part
            in a work which is truly constructive. If you wish further information on how to do
            this, write to The <org reg="Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau">Clinical Research
                Bureau</org>, 17 West 16th Street, <place reg="New York, NY">New York
                City</place>. Remember the number, 17 West 16th Street, New York City.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
