<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed draft speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2010/03/24 AC</prepDate>
		<prepDate>5/10/2012 AW Corrected Tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-04-10 CH clean regs</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-22 CH proof tags and etner</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1927-11-29">29 Nov 1927</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>Social and Individual Need of Birth Control</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp236134</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
			<bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Smith College Collections</title> S71:124</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person> most likely gave this speech in
				<place>Berlin, Germany</place>. No published version has been found.</p>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues" level3="in US"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits and risks"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="continence"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="sterilization"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="definitions of"/>
		<index level1="England" level2="birth control in"/>
		<index level1="Europe" level2="birth control in"/>
		<index level1="mortality rates" level2="maternal"/>
		<index level1="New York City" level2="birth control in"/>
		<index level1="population growth" level2="regulation of"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>
			<add>The Social and Individual Need of Birth Control</add>
		</head>
		<byline>
			<del>Editor of Proceedings </del> - <del>Mrs.</del> Margaret Sanger</byline>
		<p> There is probably no other subject of equal importance which cuts so deeply into the
			foundations of social evolution as birth control. There is no other subject of equal
			importance that has been kept so long in equal obscurity, not only by the scientists but
			by <add>the</add> medical profession as well, yet none <add>which</add> has leapt so
			suddenly upon the horizon <add>of</add> international <add>thought</add> as this subject
			has done within the past ten years. <person reg="Shaw, George Bernard">George Bernard
				Shaw</person> says that it is by far the most revolutionary discovery of the 19th
			Century.</p>
		<p> The prominence of this subject has been brought forward not only by the economic and
			social pressure of the age, but because it signifies a new moral standard, a new social
			and moral responsibility. It signifies a new responsibility of parents toward their
			children, of men and women toward the race. Birth control may be defined as the
			conscious control of the birth rate by scientific mean that prevent the conception of
			human life.</p>
		<p> Why, you may ask, is it necessary to control human life? Because the population of the
			world must from now on be controlled consciously and intelligently. It has previously
			been controlled by the forces of nature, such as by disease, pestilence, floods, famines
			and wars. These have been called “Nature’s checks”, and according to the Darwinian
			theory it is against these means that man has struggled, thereby strengthening and
			perfecting the human type.</p>
		<p> With the development of science man consciously began to control the population by such
			means as infanticide and abortion. It is interesting to recall the fact that infanticide
			was the prevailing custom in Middle <place>Europe</place> in the <del>greater</del>
			<add>latter</add> part of the 18th Century, while all the punishments and tortures that
			were inflicted upon women for this crime did not avail, and it was not until knowledge
			and the technique of abortion became generally known that infanticide generally
				<add>gradually</add> went out of practice.</p>
		<p> The same forces that underlie the practice of infanticide underlie the growing practice
			of abortion, not only in <place>Central Europe</place>, but throughout the civilized
			world today. And it is my belief that these practices will continue to increase unless
			knowledge to prevent conception is made accessible and available to all adult men and
			women.</p>
		<p> Modern civilization is confronted with two problems: 1) that of the pressure of
			population upon the food supply of the world and, 2) that of reconciling humanitarian
			and democratic practices with race improvement. Modern and progressive scientists say
			that birth control is the solution of both. Lord <person reg="Dawson, Bertrand E."
				>Dawson</person>, that distinguished English surgeon, who had the courage to take
			this question into the <org reg="Birmingham Church Congress">Church Congress of
				Bishops</org> a few years ago, said that birth control was here and was here to
			stay, that the churches and other opponents might just as well try to sweep the ocean
			back with a broom as to forestall its development.</p>
		<p> Let us look at this question more closely: if you look with an unprejudiced eye, you
			will realize that there are two <del>groups of pe</del> groups of people in every
			country, <del>who</del>
			<add>one group</add> have practiced and continue to practice birth control. They have
			limited the number of children in the family according to the health of the mother, the
			income and earning capacity of the father, as well as the accepted social standards of
			life. We see in this group that perhaps only two or three children are born into the
			family over a long period of years. But we see also that the number of children born are
			usually, in the majority of cases, brought up to full maturity. It is from this group
			that there is the lowest infant mortality and the lowest maternal mortality. It is from
			this group that the children not only attend the best schools, but also enter the
			colleges and universities, and later fill some of the most lucrative positions in
			society.</p>
		<p> On the other hand there is another group where birth control has not been
			practiced,--not because the parents do not desire the knowledge; not because the parents
			are less disciplined in their sexual habits than those in the other group; not because
			their desire to have innumerable children is any stronger than that of the parents in
			the first group, but simply because knowledge to prevent conception is in most cases
			denied them and is generally made inaccessible and difficult for their practice. It is
			in this group that mothers are over-burdened, not only with living children, but with
			the ordeal of pregnancies too frequent for their health and for human endurance. It is
			here that we find the highest percentage of infant and maternal mortality. It is here
			that we find more than 50% of the children born that are doomed to die before they reach
			their first year of age. It is in this group that we find over-crowding, slums,
			unemployment, lack of educational opportunities, child labour, disease and most all of
			the social problems that confront our civilization <del>today</del>. It is in this group
			that the mothers are broken in health, spiritless, and their young lives turned to
			drudgery and toil before they arrive at full maturity. It is here that motherhood does
			not know its greatest joys nor ever comes into full flowering.</p>
		<p>It may be comforting to some of us to feel that some assistance is given to this group
			through legislative measures and philanthropic activities. But there is perhaps no
			country in the world where there has been greater philanthropic expenditure than that
			lavished on pallative measures in the <place>United States</place>. In 1923, $8 billion
			were expended on disease, defect, delinquency, and dependency. In 1924 this sum had
			increased to $9 billions, and in 1925 the sum had gone <add>far</add> beyond $ 9
			billions the <add>budget</add>, and we have every reason to believe that within the next
			ten years this <add>amount</add> will be trebled and not just doubled, because such
			philanthropy makes it possible for individuals with transmissible disease, such as
			insanity and feeble-mindedness, not only to live themselves, but to perpetuate and to
			multiply their types and their ailments tenfold. These philanthropic activities can not
			be reconciled with racial improvement. They are dysgenic and anti-social in the long
			run. The feeble-minded and the insane are increasing far out of proportion to the normal
			increase and it is known that the feeble-minded mothers give birth to three times more
			children than the normal women in the same class.</p>
		<p> If we take as an instance the problem of maternal mortality, and analyze it closely, we
			will see how important a part birth control (that is, prevention of conception), should
			take in this reprehensible condition. There are in the United States--I cannot speak for
				<place>Germany</place>--25,000 women who die each year from causes due to pregnancy.
			That means that every hour the clock strikes in the day or the night, two mothers pass
			out of life into the great beyond. These lives have been unnecessarily sacrificed, and
			deaths could have been avoided in seven cases out of ten by the prevention of
			conception.</p>
		<p> We know further that the danger of the <del>idea</del> disease of tuberculosis is
			increased by pregnancy. We know that women suffering from heart and kidney disease
			should not be allowed to become pregnant. We know that four women out of seven who have
			tuberculosis die, not from tuberculosis, but from pregnancy. This is criminal in the
			deepest sense of the word, for every mother who has any of these diseases and who
			consults a physician is always told that she must not become pregnant again. And under
			our laws in the United States, as well as of the laws of <place>England</place>, a
			physician has the right to interrupt the pregnancy in such cases where the woman’s life
			is in danger. But after that she is sent back to her home, to her husband, to the same
			conditions, without accurate instruction of how to prevent pregnancy,--but, with a death
			sentence hanging over her head.<add>!!</add> No woman can endure the continued strain of
			curatage, no matter how surgically performed. We also know that a woman <del>in
				more</del> is more receptive to pregnancy immediately after curtage, consequently it
			is most imperative that she should be protected.</p>
		<p> Infant mortality is even more deplorable. While we have reduced the infant death rate in
			the United States within the past ten years, it could have been reduced far quicker and
			with less cost in suffering and energy had instruction been given to the parents of the
			children who die. We have 250,000 infants who die each year before they reach one year
			of age. It is said that 90% of these die from causes due to poverty and neglect. We
			know, and the most optimistic of us would not contend that either poverty or neglect
			will be eradicated from the world next year; and yet we allow the same 250,000 mothers
			and 250,000 fathers of these children to bring into the world the next year another
			250,000 children to die of poverty and neglect. It is true that we are lavish with free
			milk stations, free food, free medical supplies, free dental attention, free everything
			in the material sense of the word, but not in the one essential thing that would enable
			these parents to help themselves and to stand on their own two feet and better their
			condition and to <del>make</del>
			<add>face independently</add> their future.</p>
		<p> Birth control information (that is, methods of the prevention of conception), could help
				<add>many of</add> these parents to solve the problems of infant mortality
			themselves. Children who die under one year do so from various causes, but it is
			generally recognized by specialists that three underlying causes are important factors
			in the infant death rate: 1) too frequent pregnancies <del>that</del>
			<add>of</add> the mother whose children are born in full term but so close together that
			the mother does not have an opportunity to give adequate care to a child with feeble
			inheritance. 2) too frequent pregnancies which in many cases are interrupted, leaving
			the mother in a feeble state of health, also lowering her resistance and vitality
				<add>when</add> she eventually carries a child to full term. 3) the condition of
			women desiring to interrupt the pregnancy through drugs, and often deadly injurious
			abortifacents, becoming discouraged by the failure of the drug and then carrying the
			pregnancy to full term. Research now in progress is demonstrating the fact that many of
			these children were endangered in the womb of the mother through these harmful attempts
			at abortion and consequently came into the world with lessened vitality and, in many
			cases, with weakened organs.</p>
		<p> One could go on analyzing in this way every social problem existing today, but these
			cases are sufficient to illustrate the necessity for fundamental application of
			knowledge rather than pallative measures.</p>
		<p> I wish there were time to dwell upon the subject of child labour, for there is nothing
			that so wrings my heart and makes me feel the importance of fighting on until the end of
			time, for this cause, when I see little children forced into fields and factories and
			workshops to spend their childhood days. I sometimes wish that the venerable societies
			for the prevention of cruelty to children could prevent the cruelty of children being
			born in conditions that make cruelty inevitable. If we could prevent the cruelty of
			children being born in disease and misery, immorality and poverty, we would, within a
			generation, re-make the world.</p>
		<p> In advocating the practice of birth control, that is, the prevention of conception, I do
			not say that all parents should be compelled to limit their families, but I do maintain
			that there are certain conditions when, for the benefit of children that might be born
			as well as in consideration of furture generations, that no children should be born at
			all. There are some cases where sterilization should be applied as the solution of this
			problem, but in the great majority of needy cases contraception could very well be
			practiced. I maintain that birth control must be practiced,-- <list>
				<item>1) wherever there is a transmissible disease in either the father or the
					mother;</item>
				<item>2) wherever the woman is suffering from any of the temporary diseases, such as
					tuberculosis, heart or kidney diseases;</item>
				<item>3) wherever the children that are already born are sub-normal;</item>
				<item>4) in order that there may be two to three years between the births of
					children, that the mother may have rest from her labour, a rest and a period to
					enjoy her new baby, and a period to prepare for the coming of the next
					child;</item>
				<item>5) if marriage takes place during the adolescent period, or before the 23rd
					year, <del>and</del> the woman should wait until that age before she becomes a
					mother;</item>
				<item>6) until parents are economically able to provide for them decently and to
					give them the opportunities to develop their potentialities;</item>
				<item>7) at least one year, and if possible, two years <add>should transpire</add>
					after marriage so as to cement and strengthen the relationship of love between
					the man and the woman before a child comes into being.</item>
			</list>
		</p>
		<p> The <del>form</del>
			<add>method</add> of control must depend upon the individual case. We who have studied
			this subject in its entirety for the past ten years recognize that there are three
			groups of practices: 1) abstinence, or continence, where coitus does not take place at
			all; 2) sterilization, which does not mean castration, but is applied to the man or
			woman through surgery or irridation--this of course renders a permanent condition of
			sterility which <del>may not always be</del>
			<add>in normal cases is seldom</add> advisable; 3) the temporary application of chemical
			or mechanical means to prevent conception.</p>
		<p> There is a good deal of research work going on in America and in England in regard to
			these three methods. I myself have been director of a <org
				reg="Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau">Birth Control Clinic</org> in <place
				reg="New York, NY">New York City</place> for the past five years where we have had
			about 6,000 cases to whom we have given either chemical or mechanical appliances and
			instruction as to their use. We have three physicians in charge, as well as three nurses
			and a social worker who goes into the homes to follow up the cases to see if perfect
			satisfaction is given and, if not, to report back to the Clinic what is the cause. I am
			pleased to say that while by no means perfect, nevertheless in our last report we can
			say that we have had not more than 2% of failures when the instruction given has been
			followed.</p>
		<p> In New York City, while we have only one clinic and we are studying the science of
			methods, in <place reg="Chicago, IL">Chicago</place> there are five clinics under the
			direction of <person reg="Yarros, Rachelle">Dr. Yarrows</person>, and in
				<place>California</place> there are two clinics, one in conjunction with the
				<org>Stanford University Hospital</org>. In England there are 22 clinics run under
			private auspices, and the women of England are now waging a fight on the <org
				reg="United Kingdom Government">Government</org> to allow contraceptive advice and
			instruction to be given at the maternal and infant welfare centers. The <org
				reg="United Kingdom House of Lords">House of Lords</org> has already passed a
			resolution that this should be done, and now the women plan to bring a motion before the
				<org reg="United Kingdom House of Commons">House of Commons</org> and have this
			instruction available in every Health Center as woman’s normal and natural right. I am
			strongly in favour of this information being given by the medical profession, in their
			public and private practice, but I especially recommend that until such time as the
			methods are perfected that special Clinics be established where this information is
			given, not only as a corrolary of diseases, but for economic and social reasons as a
			special means of ascertaining facts and data whereby the methods may be eventually more
			perfected.</p>
		<p> Briefly, this is the case for Birth Control in its individual and social aspect. It is
			my belief that women must free themselves <add>herself</add> from the forces which have
			made them <add>her</add> child-bearing machies throughout the ages. She must choose the
			time to be a mother or not to be a mother, as she sees fit. Women, through knowledge of
			Birth control, will not only free themselves, but will also free the children from
			social conditions which otherwise will remain inevitable. As they free themselves and
			their children, then can they come <add>go</add> forward with men <add>,</add> toward
			that greatest of all goals--the emancipation of the human race. </p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
