<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed draft article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2012-04-11 AW Initial Tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2012-04-13 CH Proofed tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2012-04-16 AW Corrected Tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2012-05-15 CH 2nd Proof</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-10 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="0000-00-00">N.d.</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Sex Impulse (fragment)</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236152</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S73:0214</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>No additional information was found on fragment.</p>
        <index level1="sexuality" level2="men's"/>
        <index level1="sexuality" level2="women's"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <p>Religion and tradition taught women to repress as disgusting and sinful all
            manifestations of the sexual impulse, with the result that in women more than in men the
            sexual impulse tends to be driven below the surface and to seek an outlet in remote and
            often unconscious paths, this being the great fact on which <person reg="Freud, Sigmund"
                >Freud</person> seized.</p>
        <p> We cannot regulate the sex life of man without considering that of woman, and it has
            become increasingly evident from recent investigations and studies that there is not and
            never has been a special sexual psychology of woman. It was an idea originating in
            monasteries and convents, and is now rapidly falling into discredit.</p>
        <p>It is the modern viewpoint of such scientist as <person reg="Briffault, Richard"
                >Briffault</person> that mammals as a whole show <del>less the sex impulse</del> the
            sex urge takes two forms--sex impulse and mating impulse, the latter being that desire
            or tendency to prolonged association of the sexes, as in courtship, marriage, and
            parental care and affection. This latter impulse, however, does not exist in the great
            majority of animals, while the sex impulse is almost universal and is the basic force
            behind or underlying the motives of the mating instinct in the primates.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
