<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2010/02/24 AC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/03/10 EK clean regs</prepDate>

        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1933-10-00"><supplied resp="MSPP">October 1933</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Margaret Sanger Advocates the ABC--American Babies' Code</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236126</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</bibl>
            <bibl><title>MSM</title>S71:0529</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="WILIR">Wile, Dr. Ira S.</name>
            <name id="LITCC">Little, Dr. C. C.</name>
            <name id="HOOHE">Hoover, Herbert</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="birth control" level2="economic benefits and risks of"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="population growth and"/>
        <index level1="poverty"/>
        <index level1="New Deal" level2="legislation"/>
        <index level1="National committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>MARGARET SANGER ADVOCATES THE ABC--American Babies' Code</head>
        <byline>Foremost Advocate of Birth Control Declare's the "Blue Stork" must come to the aid
            of the Blue Eagle</byline>
        <p> In his fantastic play "<title type="play">The Blue Bird</title>" <person
                reg="Maeterlinck, Maurice">Maurice Maeterlinck</person> placed one famous scene in
            the Azure Palace, where children still to be born waited to come into the world of the
            living. This Palace was named the Kingdom of the Future. Each morning at dawn, Time
            opened its great portals and the Unborn crowded down into the realm of the Living.</p>
        <p>In his strange novel “<title type="novel">Erewhon</title>” the eccentric English
            satirist, <person rend="Butler, Samuel">Samuel Butler</person>, also described the World
            of the Unborn and the fantastic theory of Preexistence which was a part of the creed of
            his imaginary Erewhonians.</p>
        <p> It is a strange phenomenon of Progress that ideas that once seem preposterous and
            incredible often enter the sphere of the probably and finally crash the gate of
            reality.</p>
        <p> The Rights of the Unborn seems to be one of these ideas. For we are coming gradually to
            recognize that all our efforts at improving the environment must come to naught unless
            we make sure that sound health and racial strength must be assured to every baby which
            is brought into the world. Scientists today insist that there must be a Blue Stork to
            supplement the work of the Blue Eagle.</p>
        <p> Speaking recently before a fashionable gathering of civic leaders in the Biltmore Hotel
            in <place reg="Providence, RI">Providence, R. I.</place>, Dr. <person reg="Wile, Ira S."
                >Ira S. Wile</person>, celebrated physician of <place reg="New York, NY">New York
                City</place>, declared:</p>
        <p> “<q who="WILIR"> who=""It is obvious that while the <name type="law">National Recovery
                    Act</name> may utilize the Blue Eagle with thunderbolts and wheel in its talons,
                there is an equal necessity for a Blue Stork to fly by its side in the interest of
                the nation. And pendant from its beak should be the scales of Justice, its pans
                balanced with economic security and parental affection. If the eagle represents
                possible business readjustment through the acceptance by capital, labor and the
                public of generic and specific codes based upon reasoned compromises in the interest
                of the financial well-being of the nation, the stork would equally symbolize the
                more intelligent control of propagation in the interest of stabilizing national
                welfare.</q></p>
        <p> "<q who="WILIR">The more intelligent development of our population is paramount in the
                interest of insuring our social and economic recovery. In the last analysis, the
                National Recovery Act is designed to promote social recovery in its broadest
                sense.</q></p>
        <p>"<q who="WILIR">The overproduction of goods in a non-buying market may induce severe
                economic difficulties, but the unthinking overproduction of actual and potential
                non-earning consumers is social insanity. The overproduction of children, beyond the
                capacity of their parents to take care of them, increases our social difficulties by
                affording the dysgenic problems of mental deficiency, juvenile delinquency and
                crime, unemployment, dependency and the despairing trails of miserable old
            age.</q></p>
        <p>"<q who="WILIR">The National Industrial Recovery Act stresses business and its expansion,
                its possibilities of wages and profit and its promotion of financial stability. The
                origin of that act, however, lies in the needs of human beings. Business may have
                been bad, and banking may have been worse, but the people of this country were in
                dire straits. Not want of business but want of food was making its restless plea for
                relief. The demands of families for reasonable opportunities to earn their
                sustenance, as becomes a free people, were fundamentally responsible for the
                numerous courageous recommendations that were an outgrowth of President <person
                    reg="Roosevelt, Franklin ">Roosevelt</person>’s assumption of leadership only a
                little more than seven months ago.</q>"</p>
        <p>With this point of view I am in thorough agreement. For twenty years I have been battling
            for the rights of the unborn. And why now, in these days of reconstruction, when all
            traditional ideas have been turned topsy-turvy in <place reg="Washington, D.C."
                >Washington</place>, I am urging, as an indispensible supplement to the <org
                reg="National Recovery Administration">NRA</org>
            <add>and</add> the PWA (<org>Public Works Administration</org>), <del>the</del>
            <add>an</add> ABC-- <del>the</del>
            <add>an</add> American Babies’ Code:</p>
        <p> As chairman of the <org>National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth
                Control</org>, I have been asked to outline just what this Code for American Babies
            should provide. In attempting to draw up a fair and equitable code for the children of
            tomorrow, I have been compelled to go back and put myself in the position of those
            unborn children who have not been yet called into the realm of earthly reality. In other
            words, we are compelled to knock at the opalescent portals of Maeterlinck’s Azure Palace
            and to make our applications to the Unborn.</p>
        <p>If, in imagination, we do this, we may easily set down the sort of questions these
            Children-to-be might put to us. Such questions as these might be put:</p>
        <p> “Do you want us to come into your world only as the result of the chance convergence of
            two blood streams--one of the other of them polluted?” <del>Do you think</del></p>
        <p> “Do you think children should be called into existence as the result of chance
            parentage?”</p>
        <p>“Shall we come as the undesired, unwanted progeny into a country where already millions
            of children are wandering the highways and roads looking for food and work?- Into a
            world where you are spending millions on building roads and tunnels so that you can get
            nowhere much more rapidly-- but where you give little thought to building parks and
            playgrounds and nurseries for the troop of newcomers who are brought into your world by
            chance and folly? While it may be true that you give certain care to some children in
            day nurseries-- while their mothers are working or looking for work-- you have no
            systematic, definite program for our well-being. We want more than free milk, dolls,
            factories and unemployment to look forward to. What provision are you making for our
            well-being, and our future?”</p>
        <p>“Your former President, <person reg="Hoover, Herbert">Herbert Hoover</person>, admitted
            that of forty-five million children more than ten million were definitely handicapped.
            He admitted that six million of the babies you sentimental Americans had called out of
            the nowhere into the here were improperly nourished; a million at least were handicapped
            by bad heredity, with weak of damaged hearts; nearly four hundred thousand tubercular;
            while the number born totally deaf, crippled, partially blind or totally blind from
            birth was disgracefully high.</p>
        <p>Of these ten million children born deficient, President Hoover admitted, more than eighty
            per cent failed to receive proper attention, “<q who="HOOHE">though,</q>” added our
            ex-president, “<q who="HOOHE">our knowledge and experience show that these deficiencies
                can be prevented and remedied to a high degree.</q>” And conditions have become much
            worse since the palmy pre-depression days of Hoover.</p>
        <p>Were we to confer upon the Unborn Children of our great country equal rights with the
            living in a court of justice, it would indeed be difficult to defend our social
            practices from the indictment they might bring against us.</p>
        <p>“Your machines,” they might declare, “have taken regular employment from our father and
            mothers, our brothers and sisters, and we are not really wanted to add to the confusion,
            the misery and the starvation in your land. Come back when you are better prepared to
            welcome children and to provide strong and healthy bodies and free souls for them.”</p>
        <p>Dr. <person reg="Little, Clarence Cook">C. C. Little</person>, past president of the
                <org>University of Maine</org>, the <org>University of Michigan</org>, and the
                <org>American Eugenics Society</org>, is another distinguished scientist to point
            out that the major economic problem of the world today-- overproduction-- applies with
            equal force to human beings; Dr. Little, in a recent article, asserted:</p>
        <p>“<q who="LITCC">...A population growing at a very rapid rate may be an excellent thing
                for a young country with a huge reserve of natural resources, and a very poor thing
                for a stable country in which the balance between resources and their consumption is
                at a more precarious stage. From the point of view of labor, overproduction of
                workers in the United States has been recognized for some years as being a menace to
                our standards of living and social stability. Immigration of adults from other
                countries was the first and most obvious point at which a blow was struck following
                the recent economic pinch. Immigration of children from the unrealized stage to the
                condition of being economic liabilities, is the second level at which the economic
                conditions have forced a revision of our profligate, unthinking, and uncontrolled
                attitude.</q></p>
        <p> “<q who="LITCC">....An overabundance of domestic tragedies, an enormous increase in the
                needs of charities and a growth in expenses for the care of defectives, have
                gradually impressed upon American citizens the need for care and intelligence in the
                sphere of human reproduction as well as in the realm of economic
            commodities.</q></p>
        <p>“<q who="LITCC">....Unwanted and uncared for children spreading misery and disease have
                produced a flood of criminals and have disturbed the progressive development of a
                sane social structure. Defectives, insane, feeble-minded, habitual criminals,
                paupers, and others, have threatened the development of public educational programs
                by the extent to which they constitute a financial burden on the taxpayer and
                state.</q></p>
        <p>“<q who="LITCC">....Communities and states supported by taxation of an enlightened
                citizenry will refuse to hold themselves financially responsible for the increasing
                item of care of dependents and defectives produced blindly and heedlessly by any
                group which dogmatically says “Breed-- breed.” Concomitant with this will come a
                division of the burden, so that those who insist upon a disproportionate share in
                producing the crisis will be held responsible for meeting it from their own
                resources. When this happens democracy will be more nearly realized. It is only a
                pseudo-democracy that fails to use the best available scientific methods in
                analyzing and solving its existing problems. There are distinct signs that our
                civilization is passing through the crisis of rebirth. Such speed of change and
                progress is imminent that, not many years hence, the issue will be raised and
                settled.”</q></p>
        <p>In advocating the Code for Babies, I carry <add>on</add> our fight for the removal of
            legislative obstacles to conscious, intelligent procreation, by becoming the voice of
            the children-to-be and those unfortunates who are bearing the heaviest burden of our
            present confused state of civilization. In pleading for a Code, these children, were
            they articulate, might say to President Roosevelt and General <person
                reg="Johnson, Hugh">Hugh Johnson</person> and Secretary <person reg="Ickes, Harold"
                >Ickes</person> and the rest of the distinguished gentlemen in Washington:</p>
        <p>“There are ten millions of us in this great country whom your Child Welfare experts
            characterize as handicapped from birth. Some of us are blind, lame, tubercular,
            speechless, deaf-- and through no fault of our own. We are the victims of an
            irresponsible parenthood. Few of us have any hope of living full and useful lives. We
            are a care on our parents, relatives, and many a burden upon the taxpayers of the
            nation. We did not ask to be born, and had we anything to say to the summons which
            called us from the realm of the unborn, we would<gap extent="pages" reason="missing"
            /></p>
        <p/>


    </docBody>
</doc>
