<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed draft article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2012-05-31 AW Initial Tag</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-04-10 CH clean regs</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-20 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1925-03-15">
			<supplied resp="MSPP">15 Mar 1925</supplied>
		</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>Church and Birth Control</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp236196</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</bibl>
			<bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Smith College Collections</title>
				S73:0036</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<name id="BIB">Bible</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>No final version has been found. For an earlier draft version see MSM S71:19.</p>
		<index level1="Catholic Church" level2="birth control and"/>
		<index level1="Catholic Church" level2="MS on"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>CHURCH AND BIRTH CONTROL.</head>
		<p>To those who claim that the concern of the church is not for those on earth so much as
			filling heaven with souls.--</p>
		<p>That it is man’s duty to create souls for heaven that they may have the possibility of
			everlasting life.</p>
		<p>They state boldly and openly that abortion is better than contraception. That a monstrous
			birth is better than no birth; that they are not concerned with the quality of lives or
			souls--but only with numbers--quantity.</p>
		<p>The same church which advocates this barbarous, uncivilized, revolting theory, is most
			careful that its own select men and women--(priests and nuns) take no part in performing
			this task. What inconsistency! What cruelty to impose upon weaker, more ignorant and
			gullible minds; duties and obligations that the officials and stronger members of the
			organization will not do.</p>
		<p>“<q who="BIB">Be fruitful and multiply</q>” calls for populations--large and
			overpowering, indiscriminate populations, with all their concomitant results.
				(<place>China</place> and <place>India</place> examples)</p>
		<p>Those who advocate this procedure should be consistent and logical. In order to obey this
			injunction, then one should advance means and methods whereby the injunction is
			fulfilled.</p>
		<p>Polygamy, illegitimacy, promiscuity--</p>
		<p>Do they dare stand for these methods of multiplication?</p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
