<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011-09-12 KG</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-01 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1933-00-00">
            <supplied resp="MSPP">1933</supplied>
        </docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>
                <supplied resp="MSPP">Notes on Sexuality and Feminism</supplied>
            </titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236168</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Papers</title> S71:0590</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
            <name id="NOMAL">Nomad, Ali</name>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>A portion of this draft appears in "<xref from="236121.xml"><title type="article">Woman
                    of the Future</title></xref>," but no published version was found. Some
            paragraphs were typed on separate sheets of paper.</p>
        <index level1="feminism and feminists" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="sexuality" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="spirituality" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="freedom and rights of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <p> It is strange though true that the woman’s movement for emancipation has kept itself
            apart from any cause which advocated sex reform, sex hygiene, or even birth control. For
            it is just that difference of sex--the fact that the biological burden of childbearing
                <add>rests on her--that</add> is mainly the cause of less efficiency in woman and
            consequently her unequal position in society.</p>
        <p>We have to recognize that there are two sexes, man and woman. Both lead a separate and
            different sexual life. But the importance of the functions that fall to each are
            basically different, and woman’s inequality is based solely on the biological task of
            childbearing. Consequently, until that function is under her complete control she can
            never hope to accomplish equal rights with man. The woman who is constantly in the
            condition of pregnancy, or who is submerged in fears of pregnancy can never be equal in
            economic or social efficiency to man. Even with great exceptions of wealth and care, she
            can not keep step with him under these conditions. Therefore, the foundation of the
            Feminist or Woman’s Movement should be how to augment the efficiency of woman, how to
            release her sexual bondage of child-bearing and place it on the plane of a voluntary and
            conscious undertaking in order to be approximately equal to man. Upon this foundation
            only she can strive for equal rights. Are there any women anywhere in political life
            with large families? No! Nor in industrial or commercial or professional leadership. It
            is only because they have had child-bearing in complete control that they have been able
            to rise to any heights in modern life.</p>
        <p>The leading women in the Feminist Movement, while accepting the practice of birth control
            for themselves, have been adept in cloistering the views which their ecclesiastical
            fathers handed down to them, thus <gap reason="missing" extent="one or two words"/> that
            virginity or motherhood were the only two states of respectable womanhood. Sex as such
            was akin to sin, shame, and only the bearing of a child sanctioned its expression. With
            such ideas the Feminists should have parted at the beginning, and it has been left to
            such men as <person reg="Ellis, Havelock">Havelock Ellis</person>, <person
                reg="Carpenter, Edward">Edward Carpenter</person>, <person reg="Forel, Auguste"
                >August Forel</person>, <person reg="Krafft-Ebing, Richard von"
                >Krafft-Ebing</person> and others, including the newer school of
                psychoanalysts--<person reg="Freud, Sigmund">Freud</person>, <person
                reg="Jung, Carl">Jung</person> and <person reg="Adler, Alfred">Adler</person> (all
            men)--to awaken and arouse the public interest in the beauty and power and magnitude of
            sex, and to dissociate it from indecency, obscenity and pornography. All through the
            ages, in Religion, Politics, Education and Social Institutions, it was woman’s place and
            honor (her destiny) to serve and to suffer. The same hindrance to full intellectual
            development was her sexual inequality.</p>
        <p>The whole field of Sex Psychology is forging ahead hand in hand with other advanced
            ideas. A newly awakened interest was ushered in about the time of the radio, the
            airplane, discovery of the atom and radium. It links itself up with a higher phase of
            consciousness, and will, in the opinion of many advanced students of occult phenomena,
            be the ladder by which the human race will advance and evolve.</p>
        <p>There are many links to the chain, many spokes to the wheel, but I think it reasonable
            and sound to insist that proper instruction in methods of birth control be of the first
            consideration in any plan or program; enlightened opinion on sex instinct; an
            understanding attitude in regard to sex self-discipline; the ennoblement of love based
            on sexual attraction and communion; the rightness to apply scientific knowledge and
            contraceptive methods to life’s experience in her long march to Perfection.</p>
        <p>The question of abstinence is one on which opinions differ, and I consider it important
            to review this aspect of the question as briefly as time will allow:</p>
        <p> First, the day has passed to consider that the sexual urge has procreation as its
            primary <emph rend="underline">purpose</emph>. Rather is this the result and not the
            purpose of the urge. It is difficult to find any man or woman who thinks of desire for
            offspring or race preservation at the time sex desire is at work. The whole moving force
            of the sex urge is consciously for Oneness-- for union, for satisfaction, and for
            nothing else. This frank and scientific attitude must be faced and accepted before we
            can go forward in any attempt to evaluate sex behavior.</p>
        <p>The sexual instinct is universal in animals and man. It is one of the basic requirements
            of man’s nature. In the lower stages of man’s development it surges alone, while in his
            higher evolution it motivates the mating instinct or urge. With his tendency toward
            courtship, marriage, parental care and affection, it moves into still higher realms of
            love. Love, according to Ellis, is a new phase of sexual development.</p>
        <p>I do not regard child-bearing and rearing as the end and aim of woman’s existence. Nor do
            I consider the first duty of the married couple to be the perpetuation of the species.
            In fact, in many cases I regard it as man’s patriotic duty to refrain from such a crime
            against posterity.</p>
        <p><person>Plato</person> is said to have observed that “<q who="UNK">the second coming of
                    <person reg="Jesus Christ">Christ</person> is rightly symbolized by a
            Cross</q>”--the eternal bi-une sex principle in action. The <org>Christian Church</org>
            has taught that sex is a physical function only, thereby keeping the race from seeking
            the higher areas of spiritual consciousness. Lack of physical vitality has erroneously
            been estimated as spirituality, ignorance as innocence, restraint as chastity, until the
            very word “spiritual” makes a normal, healthy person reject (shudder).</p>
        <p>People have been and are as ignorant and confused about the subject of Sex as they are of
                <name type="deity">God</name>. We must clarify the former in order to understand the
            latter. Civilization cannot rise to its highest possibilities while the mental attitude
            toward the basic function of life is one of shame or sin.</p>
        <p>The history of marriage reveals a long drawn out life of tragedy, of misunderstanding of
            the spiritual function of sex. Many persons today are advancing the physiological and
            hygienic side of the sex subject. This is a good foundation. It is for those who know
            the value of Sex as a Creative Principle to help carry on, to help the world realize the
            importance of sex as the basis of regeneration upon which the kingdom of love shall be
            founded.</p>
        <p>Our civilization is founded on the suppression and sublimation of the sex instinct. This
            foundation is basically wrong, and often results in mental disease. The building up of a
            new civilization on radically different principles, would lead us to real mental
            health.</p>
        <p>“<q who="NOMAL">Every form of religious worship from prehistoric time down to and
                inclusive of the present century, among all races, savage and civilized, has been
                founded upon Sex--the inevitable, the unviolable, the unescapable and the
                unfathomable mystery of Creation.</q>” (by <person reg="Nomad, Ali">Ali
                Nomad</person>)</p>
        <p> Age after age has shown woman taken from her lofty heights, where she was referred to as
            a Creative Deity--Giver of Life--Divine Mother--and placed on the level of the
            nurse-maid, permitted to care for man’s offspring--allowed to compete with his animals
            as pack-horse.</p>
        <p/>
    </docBody>
</doc>
