<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Autograph draft article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2012-05-02 AW Initial Tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-08 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="0000-00-00">N.d.</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Facts of Sex</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236393</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S73:0077</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="sex education"/>
        <index level1="sexuality" level2="MS on"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <p>Experience is the sculptor which chisels away the surplus desires of the material man
            enfolding his nakedness in all its pristine beauty.</p>
        <p>The fact now reveals itself that this very silence &amp; has defeated its purpose for
            instead of safeguarding the purest minded it has kept from our youth the plain facts of
            nature which they should possess in order to live clean high lives--</p>
        <p>The real fact of the matter was that no one knew <emph rend="underline">how</emph> to
            tell or present the facts of Sex for the best way to clean the mind of the prurient is
            to remove the pruriency by light of knowledge. The majority of people have in the past
            considered that woman had no sex desires--and that only “bad” women exhibited any such
            feelings. This has been so prevalent &amp; wide spread a vein in Christianity &amp; held
            for so long--that women of the past generations would rather die than admit that they do
            at times have a yearning a desire for sex expression--Only during the past few years
            have women come boldly forward &amp; acknowledge to physician &amp; those who make a
            study of these intimate subjects that their desires are intense at times &amp; that they
            are seldom satisfied.</p>
        <p>There is no doubt that Economic conditions &amp; the single standard of morale have had
            much to do with woman’s inhibited sex impulse--</p>
        <p>She has been ashamed of desire--&amp; flattened out curves--</p>
        <p>Wives submit yourselves to your husbands has been the cursed edict to all womankind.</p>
        <p><del>Man</del> When a woman is <unclear resp="MSPP">claimed</unclear> at times when she
            has no natural desire for the union--the act is injurious as it reduces her
            vitality--&amp; tends to lessen her power to enjoy it when her natural desire
            returns--</p>
        <p>Period of desire in women--explain period--</p>
        <p>It means that a greater happiness &amp; enjoyment is to be derived for love lives if the
            woman is never falsely stimulated into passion unless she desires the union.</p>
        <p><person reg="Carlyle, Thomas">Carlyle</person> when he says the marks of a noble &amp;
            original temperament are wild strong emotions that must be controlled by a discipline as
            hard as steel.</p>
        <p>People strive to root out passions instead of helping to get them under control.</p>
        <p>Great pain as well as great happiness is part of the great fullness of the great
            Love.</p>
        <p>There are the noble young men &amp; women who desire to know the responsibilities of
            life--of marriage &amp; love--and how to best conduct their lives to meet these
            responsibilities.</p>
        <p>Few of them leave more than the vaguest ideas on the subject. Nor do they know where to
            turn to seek the help they desire.</p>
        <p>There is need of frank honest discussion and I am glad that the Sex Education Movement is
            at last taking its place in the world of Science.</p>
        <p>In <place>Germany</place> there is now a <org reg="Institut für Sexualwissenschaft"
                >college for the Study of Sexual Science</org>--</p>
        <p>In <place>England</place> there is a <org
                reg="British Society for the Study of Sex Psychology">Society for the Study of Sex
                Psychology</org>. A frank treatment of the sex subject is &amp; has been regarded as
            dangerous because many sincere &amp; earnest people feel that the effect on prurient
            minds will be to give them food for their morbid fancies.</p>
        <p>This together with the attitude of the <org reg="Roman Catholic Church">Church</org> (which I
            claim has always feared losing its hold over people when they shall know the power of
            the sex principle &amp; understand its higher uses) has been largely the cause of the
            fear &amp; ignorance mapped around the subject of <emph rend="underline"
            >mating</emph>.</p>
        <p>Power of Church &amp; State shall fall away when individuals shall cultivate their own
            inner natures &amp; control their destinies. </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
