<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Autograph Draft Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/07/15 RT Initial Tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/07/29 RT Correct Tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/08/17 CH Correct </prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011-11-28 CH correct typo</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/11/30 CH Correct typo</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-01 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1939-02-00"><supplied resp="MSPP">Feb 1939</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Cost of Public Relief</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236370</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Smith College</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S72:61</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp ><name id="ICCHWATC">Interdepartmental Committee to Coordinate Health and Welfare
                    Activity Technical Committee</name></resp>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>No final version was found.</p>
        <index level1="physically disabled and diseased" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="&quot;unfit&quot; to reproduce"/>
        <index level1="poverty" level2="family size and"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="infant"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="maternal"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>

        <p>Just one year ago Feb. 1938, a committee on Medical Care made a report to the
                <org>Interdepartmental Committee to coordinate Health &amp; Welfare
            Activities</org>. This Committee was appointed by <person
                reg="Roosevelt, Franklin D.">Pres. Roosevelt</person> in Aug. 1938 &amp; the
                <org
                reg="Interdepartmental Committee to Coordinate Health and Welfare Activity, Technical Committee"
                >Technical Committee</org> made certain recommendations for Public Health and
            Welfare.</p>
        <p>The plan was to cover a period of ten years at a cost of $850,000,000. The greatest part
            of these costs were for the medical care of “<q who="ICCHWATC">that one third of our
                population in the lower income levels &amp; receives inadequate medical
                services.</q>”</p>
        <p>Huge sums are to be spent but nowhere was there a suggestion of preventive means of
            sterilization or any other means to decrease the numbers of “<q who="ICCHWATC"
                >habitually Criminal</q>” or “<q who="ICCHWATC">seriously psychotic.</q>”</p>
        <p>The figures over maternal &amp; infant deaths were presented &amp; they were told again
            that almost 15,000 women die from causes connected with pregnancy. </p>
        <p>75,000 infants are still born.</p>
        <p>70,000 infants die in the first month.</p>
        <p>4/5 of this number from causes associated with prenatal life a process of birth.</p>
        <p>35,000 children are left motherless each year.</p>
        <p>1,100,000 births occur each year in families on relief or with a total income (including
            homes produce on farms of less than 1000.)</p>
        <p>13 million of our 35 million children are in families on relief or with incomes of less
            than $750 a year. there are about 40 million of our population in need of medical
            care.</p>
        <p>1,000,000 babies come into the world with no nursing care of the mother &amp; another no
            medical care at all.</p>
        <p>To break down source of these figures we find fathers in certain estimates making $186 a
            year -- $15 a month, 25 a day -- children are born from parents undernourished &amp;
            diseased. Share croppers &amp; migratory workers many of them our purest stock could
            become self supporting if their births were spaced.</p>
        <p>We are already overloaded with debts &amp; burdens -- no relief in sight.</p>
        <p>We shall carry ten million on relief for many years to come -- unemployment -- Relief --
            Pensions, go with each of initiative shiftlessness, dependency -- those who offer B
            control must answer for this condition -- were it not for opposition State &amp; Federal
            Governments would long ago place in the world again --?</p>
        <p>The working of the human mind during the past Century has been crab like in action,
            circumventing &amp; ameloriative in results -- while forces of nature have been dynamic
            &amp; direct.</p>
        <p>We spend millions on Charity &amp; philanthropy billions on Crime &amp; disease. Millions
            to equip and maintain institutions for diseased, insane, feebleminded &amp; Epileptic
            &amp; <del>morons</del> while millions of normal parents never see a Doctor or
            nurse.</p>
        <p>During the past 20 years those agencies directly responsible for the <add>today’s</add>
            muddle of uncontrolled breeding have come to realize our call. </p>

    </docBody>
</doc>
