<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Draft Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/07/08 NC</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1940-09-02">2 Sep 1940</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Massachusetts and the Birth Control
                Movement</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236357</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>MSM</title>S72:0147</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="FAIHE"> Fairchild, Henry Pratt</name>
            <name id="PARTH">Parran, Thomas</name>
            <name id="ROOFR">Roosevelt, Franklin Delano</name>
            <name id="HOLJO">Holmes, John Haynes</name>
            <name id="ZINHA">Zinsser, Hans</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>The following outline was likely used by Sanger on her Massachusetts
            speaking tour from October 13 to 18, 1940.</p><p>Handwritten notes made by unknown
            secretary.</p><index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/><index
            level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about" level3="morality of"
            /><index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Massachusetts"
            /><index level1="birth control" level2="morality of"/><index level1="birth control"
            level2="religion and"/><index level1="birth control" level2="war and"/><index
            level1="Catholic Church"/><index level1="children" level2="unwanted"/><index
            level1="population" level2="war and"/><index level1="United States" level2="government"
            level3="birth control and"/><index level1="working classes" level2="birth control and"
        /></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>OUTLINE OF SPEECH MATERIAL FOR MRS. SANGER</head>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">INTRODUCTORY MATERIAL</head>
            <p>One hundred and eight years ago a little book was published in <place
                    reg="Boston, MA">Boston</place> that was destined to become an historic document
                in the fight for birth control -- Dr. <person reg="Knowlton, Charles">Charles
                    Knowlton</person>’s “<title>The Fruits of Philosophy</title>.” For more than
                forty years that little book circulated throughout the world quietly, steadily. It
                was translated into several languages; reprinted many time<add>s</add>. Finally
                through its circulation in <place>England</place>, Mrs. <person reg="Besant, Annie"
                    >Annie Besant</person> and <person reg="Bradlaugh, Charles">Charles
                    Bradlaugh</person> were brought to trial, an <del>historic</del> event in the
                history of the birth control movement out of which grew the first
                    <org>Neo-Malthusian League</org> in England. So Boston, as it
                        <unclear><del>was</del></unclear> can for many movements for human welfare,
                can lay claim to be one of the birth-places of the whole movement for planned
                parenthood.</p>
            <p>In that period of more than a hundred years the <place reg="Massachusetts"
                    >Commonwealth of Massachusetts</place> developed, progressed, contributed
                mightily to the progress of the nation. Her great institutions of learning turned
                forth scholars who have left their impress upon the life of the <place
                    reg="United States">Nation</place>; promoted the cause of learning; developed
                research which has resulted in inestimable benefits to humanity.</p>
            <p>There is one thing in which this city of Boston pioneered that I will always remember
                -- a movement which is linked closely to the <add>movement</add> for which I am
                speaking now. Here at the <org>Massachusetts General Hospital</org> in 1905 was
                established the first attempt to link medicine with the social problems of the
                    <add>patient</add> founded on the belief that adequate medical care <del><gap
                        extent="one or two words"/>attention</del> must consider the social needs of
                the patient. Out of that <add>attempt -- now called medical social work --</add> has
                developed a greater feeling of social responsibility on the part of physicians in
                many sections of the country; <add>has brought medicine into its own as a <emph
                        rend="underline">great social force</emph>.</add></p>
            <p>With that background of progressive development, with that record of achievement in
                human welfare, it seems well-nigh incredible that this Commonwealth should be one of
                the only two in the <place reg="United States">United States</place> which forbids
                physicians to prescribe scientific means of contraception where the imperative
                health and welfare needs of their patients demand it. That, to me, seems a challenge
                to the citizens of this State; a challenge for them to demand that minority pressure
                groups of personal prejudice will not stand in the way of right of a physician to
                utilize the full force of scientific discovery and technique for the health and
                welfare of his patients; nor stand in the way of the right of every mother to
                determine for herself when and how often she shall undertake the heavy and
                far-reaching responsibility of motherhood.</p>
            <p>But before I talk further about your problem here in Massachusetts, I want to discuss
                the real, intrinsic meaning of birth control; what it means to individuals and to
                the nation; and in its broadest aspects, the whole problem of planned
                parenthood.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">I. PLANNED PARENTHOOD.</head>
            <p> Great misunderstanding exists as to the true nature of birth control and planned
                parenthood. Opponents of the movement, with characteristic disregard for facts, link
                it to race suicide or to abortion. These are ugly words to apply to a movement that
                Dr. <person reg="Fairchild, Henry Pratt">Henry Pratt Fairchild</person> has
                described as “<q who="FAIHE">one of those achievements of science and rational
                    public sentiment upon which the human race laboriously builds its progress
                    toward a more satisfactory individual life and a more orderly and stable social
                    organization.</q>”</p>
            <p>Simply birth control is the scientific means, administered by the medical profession,
                by which parents undertake the responsibility of parenthood consciously and with due
                regard for the health of the mother, the economic circumstance of the family and the
                right of <del>the</del>
                <add>a</add> child to be wanted and to be cared for properly.</p>
            <p>It is a means by which parenthood is no longer treated as a punishment for
                shiftlessness or carlessness; by which parenthood is taken out of the sphere of
                accident. Thus, for the individual parent, parenthood becomes a matter of conscious
                knowledge; of deeper satisfaction; of ready and eager acceptance of
                responsibility.</p>
            <p>Far beyond the implications of birth control for individual parents, in its meaning
                to this democratic nation. Now, in this time of crisis, we are arming; preparing
                with the full vigor of the nation to defend the rights and freedoms so deeply
                imbeded in our way of living.</p>
            <p>With all its emphasis on the materials of defense, this great national effort is
                proceeding, and must proceed, on the belief that a nation is no stronger than its
                people. Only a few months ago, Surgeon General <person reg="Parran, Thomas">Thomas
                    Parran</person> of the United States, spoke these significant words. He said:
                    “<q who="PARTH">The people of this nation must be physically tough, mentally
                    sound and moreally strong. If they are not, we can leave our planes on paper,
                    our battleships unbuild. We shall not be able to use them.</q>”</p>
            <p>What does all this mean to planned parenthood? Simply this. The words “<q who="ROOFR"
                    >one third of a nation, ill-fed, ill-clothed, ill-housed</q>” are real, tragic
                words today in America. Yet more tragic is the inescapable fact that this
                under-priveleged part of our American people is forced to bear the majority of the
                children born each year. More than one million children are born each year into
                families with annual incomes of less than $1,000. These families are American
                families, sturdy, independent, capable of bearing the kind of children we need to
                maintain a strong, vital people. Yet they are forced, through ignorance, to bear
                more children than they can care for properly; forced to lower their already low
                living standards; forced to perpetuate their condition of poverty because they
                cannot plan their families.</p>
            <p>Is it any wonder so many children in <place reg="United States">America</place> today
                are undernourished; so many mothers die in child-birth; so many babies are born
                dead!</p>
            <p>I say in all seriousness that this nation cannot afford to permit such a condition to
                exist for long, if it has any regard for its national strength.</p>
            <p>Fifteen years ago, following the <org>Sixth International Neo-Malthusian and Birth
                    Control Conference</org> in <place reg="New York,NY">New York</place>, I urged
                that President <add><person reg="Coolidge, Calvin">Coolidge</person> and later Pres
                        <person reg="Hoover, Herbert">Hoover</person></add> appoint a Population
                Commission to consider such population problems as this and to initiate a program to
                remedy them. Apparently <del>the time then was not ripe for such a move.</del>
                <add>such proposals were ignored but</add>
                <del>It is more than ripe today.</del> If the present Administration in <place
                    reg="Washington D.C.">Washington</place> wishes to make truly effective its
                drive for national defense, it will take immediate steps to begin a coordinated
                program to <emph rend="underline">strengthen our human resources</emph>. It will
                integrate efforts already made for the welfare of our people; it will provide the
                scientific means of family planning for all mothers who wish it; it will seek means
                of making the economic burden of bearing children less heavy. And when it does these
                things, it will truly be seeking to strengthen the nation for defense of its
                freedom.</p>
            <p>I’ve attempted to discuss the meaning of planned parenthood for individuals and for
                the nation. Now to discuss with you your problem here in Massachusetts.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">II. THE MORAL PROBLEM.</head>
            <p>In the name of morality in Massachusetts, an old law was resurected and seven clinics
                were closed. Since this was done in the name of morality, it seems appropriate to
                discuss that aspect first. How better can I tell you of the true, deep morality of
                planned parenthood than by reciting to you the words of the leader of this great
                Church, the Reverend Dr. <person reg="Holmes, John Haynes">John Haynes
                    Holmes</person>. <add>Only</add> a few years ago he said: “<q who="HOLJO">If
                    imparting knowledge of how to space births -- how to safeguard mothers -- and to
                    help married people produce normal, vigorous children; if that be encouraging
                    morality -- then I’m immoral. In true fact, birth control education is an
                    expression of the highest form of morality -- morality dedicated to the great
                    end of preventing human suffering -- saving the lives of mothers and children --
                    fostering community health and welfare. this is what I mean by morality; <emph
                        rend="underline">the service of mankind.</emph></q>”</p>
            <p>What better way can I demonstrate the essential morality of birth control than by
                reciting to you the names of those who believe in it and sponsor it -- <person
                    reg="Fosdick, Harry Emerson">Harry Emerson Fosdick</person>; Dean <person
                    reg="Kinsolving, Arthur B.">Arthur B. Kinsolving</person>; <person
                    reg="Compton, Karl">Karl Compton</person>; Reverend <person
                    rend="Elliot, Frederick M.">Frederick M. Elliot</person>; Dr. <person
                    reg="Rock,John">John Rock</person>; Bishop <person reg="Abott, H.P. Almon">H.P.
                    Almon Abbott</person> of <place>Kentucky</place> -- and hundreds of other men
                and women whose daily lives are testimony to that true morality: <emph
                    rend="underline">the service of mankind</emph>.</p>
            <p>Morality isn’t static; it deepens with the growth of knowledge. Once in human
                history, quinine was refused to malaria sufferers in the name of morality.
                Vaccination against smallpox, immunization, the germ theory of disease, the use of
                anesthesia, the cell theory of lifee -- all these were opposed once in the name of
                morality. These instances seem incredible to us now; yet once again today we are
                faced with the same distortion of fundamental morals to impede the progress of human
                welfare.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">III. BALANCE THE BIRTH RATE</head>
            <p>As the late <person reg="Zinsser, Hans">Hans Zinsser</person> said: “<q who="ZINHA"
                    >What can be more immoral than to put children into the world that are unwanted,
                    that cannot be properly nourished, cared for, educated, and otherwise inducted
                    into a life with a reasonable expectation of happiness and usefulness.</q>”</p>
            <p>And I should add to that: what can be more immoral than that scientific knowledge
                should be distributed on the basis of ability to pay? Contraception under medical
                supervision is available to those who can pay for it -- here in Massachusetts just
                as much as anywhere else in the country. That is why here in Massachusetts the
                mothers least able to bear healthy children into healthy, happy surroundings are
                having the most children. That is why the invocation of that ancient blue law bears
                most heavily upon the poor, the ignorant -- the portion of the population that
                really needs scientific knowledge of contraception.</p>
            <p>This to me is immoral. this to me is a violation of the fundamental meaning of
                democratic <add>Christian</add> living.</p>
            <p>The birth control movement is well aware of the problems involved in this unbalanced
                birth-rate. It recognizes the need to balance births -- to bring about those
                conditions that will encourage childbearing by those most fitted to undertake the
                responsibility of parenthood. But it <add>is</add> also aware that this can never be
                done by denying mothers the right to plan their families.</p>
            <p><person reg="Hitler, Adolf">Hitler</person> and <person reg="Mussolini, Benito"
                    >Mussolini</person> have tried it. There, in those totalitarian countries, we
                see motherhood prostituted before the altar of war; we see mothers urged, forced, to
                bear more and more babies because the state needs cannon fodder. The dictators have
                failed, as any authority will testify. But whether they had succeeded, such a
                debasing of parenthood has no place in a democratic nation.</p>
            <p>Yet here in Massachusetts, in the name of morality and religion, you are forcing
                mothers to bear children they do not want and cannot care for by denying them the
                right to medical contraception.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">IV. The PROBLEM IN MASSACHUSETTS</head>
            <p>This situation in Massachusetts today is not the fault of the people. By political
                pressure a minority group has forced action which is contrary to the wished of the
                majority of the citizens of this Commonwealth. Only recently a scientific poll of
                opinion in the state proved that. The poll, I am informed, showed that <gap
                    extent="one word"/> per cent of the voting public in Massachusetts favored the
                right of physicians to prescribe contraception for the health and welfare of their
                patients. Even more convincing is the fact that the poll showed that, although the
                closing of the clinics has been laid to the door of a minority group within the
                    <org>Catholic Church</org>, <gap extent="one word"/> per cent of Catholic voters
                cast their vote of approval for medical rights on this issue.</p>
            <p>As you know an initiative petition, signed by 10 outstanding citizens in this state,
                has been presented at the <org reg="Massachusetts Legislature">State House</org>.
                Before this petition can be presented as a bill and voted on by the 1941
                Legislature, 20,000 registered voters must sign it. The signatures must be obtained
                from not less than 4 counties and not more than 5,000 of the signers can be
                residents of any one county.</p>
            <p>To obtain these signatures before December 4, it is necessary to enlist a large force
                of volunteers. It is a big task that faces you in Massachusetts, but it is a task
                that can be accomplished easily if you who believe in this task will work
                whole-heartedly for it.</p>
            <p>If the Legislature of this state then continues to flout the wishes of the majority
                of its citizens, you have the means at your disposal to bring the issue before the
                general public.</p>
            <p>Let me remind you that the cause of human freedom, which is really what this cause is
                that faces you today, can never for long be stopped. That is the challenge you face
                today in Massachusetts. And much more rests upon your acceptance of that challenge
                than <add>simply</add> the repeal of an ancient blue law.</p>
        </div>



    </docBody>
</doc>
