<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Autograph draft article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2012-04-03 AW Initial Tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2012-04-04 CH Proofed Tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-08 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1922-00-00"><supplied resp="MSPP">1922</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Women</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236435</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S73:0265</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>The following are speech fragments likely from the early 1920's.</p>
        <index level1="women" level2="freedom and rights of"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head rend="underline">Women</head>
        <div>
            <p>1. Freedom to do any work for which she is fitted. To prove her fitness; to receive
                instruction, to be given responsibility &amp; initiative in any industrial,
                administrative or professional capacity.</p>

            <p>2. Special protection of the child &amp; child bearing mother--</p>

            <p>3. The entire individual responsibilities of women in regard to the acceptance or
                refusal of motherhood. The fundamental human right of the mother to bear life gladly
                &amp; proudly or not at all and of the unborn to be wanted &amp; welcomed.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <p>Women should birth control the unfit out of existence a programme to strive for.</p>
            <p>Darwinian principle which demands the minimum of interference with competitive
                struggle which claims it to be the only true test of fitness or unfitness.</p>
            <p>I differ with this &amp; claim that we should in a civilization lay our struggles
                &amp; competitive effort upon other qualities than the maternal needs of competing
                against our brothers for food as the animals have done &amp; do, let our struggles
                be for art &amp; science &amp; greater moral qualities of our spiritual nation thus
                developing in mankind a higher moral than those qualities of cunning, cheating,
                getting the best of your neighbor or selling him something he does not want etc
                etc.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <p>2. The maximum of liberty for individual effort maintained at all cost.</p>
            <p>Those who fail through disease, accident, or inability to gain a livelihood are the
                unfit, whose lives may be preserved, but only at the price of renouncing the right
                to perpetuate their type.</p>
            <p>If this system were adopted for one generation universally, there would be such an
                improvement in the human race that the complete structure of society would
                automatically be changed. There would then be with out doubt the co-operative system
                leaving the competitive struggle to be in control only in the higher arts &amp;
                science &amp; literary developments.</p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
