<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Autograph draft speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-08-19 KH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-08-20 CH proof tags</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1938-00-00">1938</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP"/>Notes on Controlling the Unfit</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236414</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Sophia Smith Collection</title>#S71:1050</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>No final version of this text found; unclear if ever published or
            delivered.</p><index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/><index
            level1="birth control" level2="definitions of"/><index level1="birth control"
            level2="health benefits and risks of"/><index level1="birth control"
            level2="politicians and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="population and"/><index level1="birth rate"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="consequences on"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="decline in"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="increase in"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="efforts to increase"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="efforts to reduce"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="population growth and"/><index level1="England"
            level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="England" level2="birth rate in"/><index level1="immigration" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="immigration" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="immigration" level2="U.S. policy"/>
        <index level1="England" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="England" level2="population policies of"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <p>Bc has become the keynote of a New Social &amp; racial responsibility. It is the
            consciousness of a New Individual responsibility not only for the children already born
            but for the welfare of children not yet conceived.</p>
        <p>This attitude marks a new &amp; superior sense in the history of mankind. It marks a cew
            social era as being not only a health expedient but a Social principle which is
            intermingled &amp; tied to the spiritual progress &amp; advancement of the race + its
            future.</p>
        <p>Its practice makes for a resistant race, maintaining initiatives &amp; responsibility.
            Today 1/3 of the population are creating conditions for dependency killing initiatives
            &amp; responsibility.</p>
        <p>The only people who can afford larger families are those who can't support them.</p>
        <p>Many good people are fearful of Communism + would depart from our shores all these with
            such political + social ideas but I say that the most revolutionary Communist is not as
            great an <del>danger</del>
            <add>enemy</add> to our nation as the fanatic who opposes all efforts to decrease the
            multiplication of the defectives criminal &amp; unfit populations of this country.</p>
        <p>Here is the real enemy. Insidious &amp; <del>powerfulful</del>
            <emph rend="underline">&amp; dangerous</emph> &amp;of Foreign <emph rend="underline"
                >extraction</emph>.</p>
        <p>I wish they would take over + pay the cost of their <add>own</add> increasing hordes
            &amp; maintain this large unfit population thus relieving the tax payers of increasingly
            heavy burdens.</p>
        <p>Our politicians attack the communists &amp; urge their deportation because they fear
            their ideas will destroy our form or system of government. But our system of gov’t can
            be maintained, changed, defended if we have a population of men &amp; women <del>able
                to</del> with # <del>an</del><add>the</add> intelligence to deal with it.</p>
        <p>But with 85% of our population mentally under the age of a juvenile 14 years
                <del>old</del>, we can expect all the problems which <del>a family expect</del>
            parents face with their own adolescents. </p>
        <p> But the real criminal to be feared is not the Communist or fascist or any other growth
            to interfere or change our cities or external life. It is the man or woman or group who
            encourage the increase of defectives &amp; criminal breeding &amp; prevents others from
            doing their civic duty to the state in attempting to curtail their increase.</p>
        <p>Opponents of Bc are responsible for their dysgenic birth rate. 80&percnt; mental
            equipment of 14 year old juveniles. <person reg="Jordan, David Starr">David Starr
                Jordan</person>’s <place reg="Princeton, NJ">Princeton</place>: 25,000,000 mediocre
            15,000,000 intellectuals 90/130 under 14<emph rend="underline"/><emph>130</emph></p>
        <p>Medical Professional’s duty should be extended beyond saving life of the individual today
            to preserving the health of the nation &amp; future generations.</p>
        <p>The most important task before our health + gov’t officials today is to find effectual
            means of controlling &amp; limiting the propagation of the mentally unfit, including
            feebleminded, psychotic &amp; unstable, mentally retarded individuals.</p>
        <p>Infant mortality <emph rend="underline">$800,000</emph> to be requested</p>
        <p>Over 2,000,000 born annually</p>
        <p>75,000 stillborn</p>
        <p>69,000 die first month</p>
        <p><del>Studies </del>1,000,000 no nursing care after birth. &frac14; million have no Dr.
            Maternal &amp; infant deaths 147,000 a year. Maternal death 12,500 from child birth.
            &frac12; to &frac34; could have been saved. <place reg="Washington, D.C.">D.C.</place>
            Maternal deaths higher than <place>England</place> &amp; <place>Wales</place>-5.7-3.7
            (1937) lowest on record in England.</p>
        <p><emph rend="underline">Children</emph></p>
        <p>13,000,000 Children are families on relief 10,000,000 children are handicapped mentally
            or physically. 65&percnt; of births (1937) came from families on relief or income less
            than $1,000 a year. </p>
        <p>Only those can afford large families who can't support them.</p>
        <p><person reg="Wells, H.G.">HG Wells</person> prophecy mind of mass slavery grows. Prolific
            powers of increase-chaos.</p>
        <p>(1938) Over 500,000 persons are in hospitals (1928) for mentally diseases about 50,000
            beings are on parole while 150,000 patients are admitted or readmitted to these
            institutions every year. 75,000 are in institutes for the feebleminded &amp; epileptic
            while another 900,000 mental defectives are outside institutional care. (Creating
            problems + having babies) $150,000,000 of public funds over &frac14; of all health &amp;
            medical services by the gov’t are expended annually for their maintenance.</p>
        <p>Over 2,000,000 births Each year. 75,000 infants still borne 69,000 “” die first month.
            12,500 women die from causes due to birth or pregnancy &amp; T.B. heart or kidney
            disease leaving 35,000 children left motherless for institutions or charitable causes.
            Very little decline in the last 20 years in the maternal death rate in <place
                reg="United States">USA</place>.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
