<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed draft article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2012-06-20 AW Initial Tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-17 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1925-00-00"><supplied resp="MSPP">1925</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Social Selection</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236444</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm: Smith College Collections</title>
                S73:0229</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="eugenics" level2="positive"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="civilization and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <p>It is one of the tragedies of civilization that its tendency is to destroy or eliminate
            those mental and physical superiorities by which it has been built up and which are
            essential for its maintenance and progress.</p>
        <p> The development of civilization has brought mankind under influences which have never
            before come into play. There have arisen various agencies which tend to favor or reduce
            the prevalence of certain types according to the nature of the institution and the time
            and place.</p>
        <p>Our friend <person reg="Vacher de Lapouge, Georges">Lapouge</person> has described the
            operation of several forms of social selection</p>
        <list>
            <item>Military</item>
            <item>Political } All brought into play as a consequence of the development</item>
            <item>Religious } of civilization. </item>
            <item>Moral</item>
            <item>Legal</item>
            <item>Economic</item>
        </list>
        <p>Military selection eliminates the best male population of the race.</p>
        <p>Political selection through the effects of the Civil War, the prison, the scaffold and
            exile gets rid of more independent and courageous spirits and tends thereby to render
            the population submissive and tractable.</p>
        <p>Religious selection through celibacy of the clergy and persecution, tends to affect the
            elimination of the more intelligent and independent minds.</p>
        <p>Moral and legal selection in general produce dysgenic effects.</p>
        <p>The economic selection has a most destructive effect upon the superior elements of the
            race. It makes machines of rare souls. It starves our artists, musicians and poets and
            reduces the artisan to the state of the unskilled.</p>
        <p>The racial influence of civilization is bad and the feeble force of natural selection
            seems powerless to stay the havoc brought by the agencies which result from the
            development of civilization.</p>
        <p>Add to these disconcerting facts amount of care, attention, money, effort and energy
            devoted to the care and perpetuation of the insane, feebleminded and inferior types and
            one gasps for breath as no remedy appears to grapple with the problem. </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
