<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Autograph draft article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2012-06-20 AW Initial Tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-17 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="0000-00-00">n.d.</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Continence</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236467</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm: Smith College Collections</title> S73:0041</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>No additional versions or further information was found on this text.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="continence"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="sterilization"/>
        <index level1="marriage"/>
        <index level1="men" level2="sexual fulfillment of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <p>Continence is <emph rend="underline">one</emph> of the methods of BC.</p>
        <p>So is Sterilization, so is the Mechanical or Chemical Method.</p>
        <p>Any one of which may be advised or chosen <del>by</del> to suit individual lives.</p>
        <p>But--no one can impose <emph rend="underline">any one</emph> method upon a whole
            population.</p>
        <p>Continence--partial or absolute is a Method which for some people, especially the
            Unmarried may be practiced with very little strain on the nervous system but for married
            lovers, full of life, vitality, vigor, with a deep love for each other <del>such</del>
            to impose upon this couple a condition of continence is wrought with serious dangers not
            only to the nervous system but to the harmony &amp; peace of the home.</p>
        <p>Young couple, husband truck driver told to practice continence.</p>
        <p>Morality comes from within Ford’s <gap extent="one word" reason="illegible"/> houses.</p>
        <p>The desire for continence if it comes from sublimating of the sex forces, usually means
            there is a lowering of vitality or an increasing interest in some other activity using
            up the creative forces. This may happen to either one of the married persons, but seldom
            does it the desire come to both at the same time for any long period.</p>
        <p>No good night kisses. No tenderness, no cuddling, no holding hands, danger signal
            all.</p>
        <p>Premium on barrenness where sex</p>
        <p>sex communion without desire for children can be akin to music or prayer, almost never is
            sex desire accompanied with the desire for children. That comes with love, respect etc.
        </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
