<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed draft article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2012-04-27 AW Initial Tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-08 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="0000-00-00">N.d.</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">The Unmarried Girl</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236472</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S73:0254</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="SHAWI">Shakespeare, William</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="children" level2="unwanted"/>
        <index level1="motherhood"/>
        <index level1="marriage"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="health of"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <div>
            <p> 1. Is she entitled to knowledge? Just as we admit that the conditions around the
                married woman entitle her to knowledge so must we analyze the unmarried girl.</p>
            <p rend="blockquote"> There are three kinds of girls who go wrong:</p>
            <p rend="blockquote"> 1. The innocent, ignorant girl who puts her trust and faith in the
                man and finds herself a mother.</p>
            <p rend="blockquote"> 2. The ignorant girl who thinks by giving herself to the man she
                likes will thereby hold him or get him to marry her.</p>
            <p rend="blockquote"> 3. The ignorant girl classes as moron with full physical sex
                development, but mental growth not above <add>a</add> child of nine or ten years; no
                moral standard, no control, no modesty; just goes with the man who asks her and
                takes what she gets, money or good time.</p>
        </div>

        <div>
            <p> 1. In the first case, this innocent girl should be as protected by society as the
                mother who suffers with tuberculosis, heart disease, or any other ailment of
                sickness which renders her weak against the consequences of pregnancy.</p>
            <p> So should innocence and ignorance be regarded. Society should protect the innocent
                and ignorant, as it protects the diseased by giving all knowledge to protect
                themselves against attacks. Should this weak girl be made to endure the “<q
                    who="SHAWI">slings of outrageous fortune</q>” because of her innocence? Is this
                punishment justifiable, and is this the attitude that society takes with other
                examples of crime by innocence?</p>
            <p> 2. This girl a little wiser and more knowing than her sister leans a bitter lesson,
                and could learn it just as well by not going through the bitter experience of
                motherhood. Such men are plentiful and girls are learning by examples that without
                love and tenderness there is no bond. This is the girl who aborts, and the man is
                more helpful in obtaining this release than he is when marriage and motherhood are
                suggested.</p>
            <p> Think of the innocent child in both cases and the effect of the mind of the mother
                upon its nine months’ journey to birth.</p>
            <p> 3. This type of girl is our national and social problem. She may be promiscuous, but
                is bright enough to escape jails or institutions. She is everywhere, in every walk
                of life--in all classes. When married, she is three times as prolific as the normal
                woman. While her illicit relations do harm only to herself or the man in question,
                should she be permitted to bear children?</p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
