<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Autograph draft article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2012-06-19 AW Initial Tag</prepDate><prepDate>2014-04-17 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="0000-00-00">n.d.</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Toward Peace</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236468</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm: Smith College Collections</title> S73:0241</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>No other versions or additional information has been found about this text.</p>
        <index level1="famine"/>
        <index level1="peace" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="war"/>
        <index level1="war" level2="causes of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <p><place>Germany</place> is benefitting today by the efforts from scientific achievements
            &amp; free experiments allowed &amp; developed under the former system which allowed a
            the intelligence of her people free reign to seek truth &amp; happiness without fear
            &amp; imprisonment. The world war thrust upon us a new <unclear resp="MSPP"
                >Internationality</unclear>. Ever since that historic &amp; Sad event the world has
            been united not by Music, Art, Science &amp; brotherly love, but by Fear. Fear of
            Invasion, of Starvation, &amp; Uncertainty, Insecurity &amp; another War. Various &amp;
            Sunday groups offer Solutions for this woeful situation. The Politicians &amp; political
            minded offer--The <org>League of Nations</org> the first essential in Solving any
            problem is to recognize the factors involved. One of the fundamentals factors which
            reflects these essential but <add>incomplete</add> phases of the problems is the factor
            of hunger &amp; reproduction. Hunger is the driving force behind all our economic
            industrial &amp; commercial organization. Limitation of armaments, Militaristic offer
            schemes of Competitive armaments. Marxians &amp; Socialists offer The Third
            International Industrial Revolution &amp; Equality of Distribution.</p>
        <p>Theologists offer <add>love</add> charity, Philanthropy &amp; good will. While Nations
            rearm, hatred &amp; fear increases &amp; these situations grow from bad to worse. Then
            there is the reproductive impulse in constant conflict with one Economic political &amp;
            Social system--All of which are at the mercy of changes thru the terrific rise in
            population. </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
