<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Autograph draft speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014-08-19 KH</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-08-20 CH proof tags</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1924-00-00">1924</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Birth Control and Progress Speech Fragment</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp236459</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</bibl>
			<bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Sophia Smith Collection</title>#S70:1064</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name/>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>No additional information found on this speech draft.</p>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="civilization and"/>
		<index level1="England" level2="birth rate in"/>
		<index level1="England" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="England" level2="population policies of"/>
		<index level1="population control" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="population growth"/>
		<index level1="United States" level2="overpopulation in"/>
		<index level1="United States" level2="population growth in"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<p>Birth Control has become the mark of a superior service of moral responsibility. Someone
			has recently said that it is the most momentous fact in the history of Mankind.
			Certainly it is the keynote of a new social era. Because it is not only an expedient of
			health and economy but it is also a principle which is interlocked with the spiritual
			progress of the race &amp; the future. B.C. is the conscious control of the birth rate
			by means that prevent contraception. It is the natural method because it prevents rather
			than destroys. It does not interfere with the development of pregnancy because
			contraception is <del>to be</del> prevented. Consequently no life has been allowed to
			begin. It is the logical outgrowth of a century’s work at improving the conditions of
			life. The 19th century is known to be the greatest period in our history for
			humanitarian &amp; ameliorative efforts. When we look back at the social conditions
			which existed at the end of the 18th century, our gasps with wonder &amp; amazement with
			the thought that we have come through life at all. <place reg="United States"
				>America</place> of course was mostly a wilderness with a hand full of people, but
				<place>Europe</place> was fairly well <add>over</add> populated then &amp;
				<place>England</place> in particular with her huge civilizations can best serve as a
			typical example. Streets never unpaved. There were no sewers, refuse garbage &amp; dirt
			were <gap extent="rest of speech"/></p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
