<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Autograph Draft Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2012-06-20 AW Initial Tag</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="0000-00-00">n.d.</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">England's Birth Control Movement</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236443</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S73L0074</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>No further information has been found for this drafted article.</p>
        <index level1="England" level2="birth control clinics and leagues in"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="history of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="international"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="efforts to reduce"/>
        <index level1="England" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="England" level2="birth rate in"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <p><place>England</place>--the home of the B.C. movement has during the past ten years shown
            tremendous advance.</p>
        <p>From the time of the <person reg="Besant, Annie">Besant</person> &amp; <person
                reg="Bradlaugh, Charles">Bradlaugh</person> in 1878 the theories of <person
                reg="Malthus, Thomas">Malthus</person> were advocated by a small intelligent
            fearless group of idealists who labored through the years to educate -- not the
            masses -- but the educators. This process has certainly been successful as is seen by the
            differential birth rate of not only England but of <del>nearly all English speaking
                    <place>France</place></del> Western <place>Europe</place> as well.</p>
        <p>The work now is to <del>spread</del>
            <add>direct</add> the information to that class of the population called 3-C class for
            health as well as Economic <del>needs</del> reasons.</p>
        <p>While there are 22 clinics operating in England under private auspices, this is not
            sufficient to cover the huge population &amp; especially to reach these mothers whose
            physical condition or that of their childrens show the necessity of controlling the size
            of the family. There are in England hundreds of centers known as Maternity &amp; Infant
            Welfare which are partly or wholly supported by grants from the government. The Movement
            is now directed toward getting governmental approval of alluring the Doctors in charge
            of these centers to advise &amp; instruct the mothers who ask for such instruction. This
            is the only way the quality of the population can be raised by directing the knowledge
            of B.C. to those whose physical &amp; Economic conditions <del>demand it</del> would be
            benefitted by it.</p>
        <p>The <org>House of Lords</org>
            <del>voted</del>
            <add>through</add> Lord <person reg="Buckmaster, Stanley">Buckmaster</person> passed a
            resolution, in favor of this act. This lead a most profound influx on British public
            opinion . The <org reg="House of Commons">Commons</org> turned it down, but it will be
            brought up again at an early date. </p>
        <p>The birth rate of England is the lowest in Europe, its death rate is also correspondingly
            low. 16 . . <place>France</place> 18.</p>
        <p>With <place>Australia</place> &amp; <place>Canada</place> refusing her slum populations,
            but desiring her better quality citizens--England has set her face to improve her
            quality--I believe she will be the first government in the world to sanction openly
            &amp; fearlessly the practice of birth control. Instead of looking to the future--she
            mourns on the past. France--who sees that within the last 50 years.
                <place>Germany</place> has increased her population 28 million. <place>Italy</place>
            16 millions while she has 2 millions.--70,000 Poles 1926 to France. </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
