<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Autograph Draft Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/06/28 CE</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1938-00-00"><supplied resp="MSPP"
            >1938</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Population and
                    Immigration</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236464</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith
                College</bibl>
            <bibl><title>MSM</title> S73:0140</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="efforts to reduce"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="population growth and"/>
        <index level1="eugenics" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="Europe" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="feeble-minded persons" level2="fertility and birth rate of"/>
        <index level1="immigration" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="mentally disabled and diseased" level2="fertility and birth rate of"/>
        <index level1="population growth" level2="natural resources and"/>
        <index level1="population growth" level2="regulation of"/>
        <index level1="population growth" level2="standard of living and"/>
        <index level1="population growth" level2="war and"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="population policies"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        
            <p>In a democratic society where the vote of one is a good as that
                of another, it is a dangerous procedure to accept a way of life
                where the poor, ignorant, diseased and mentally and socially
                unfit maintain the stock of the population. Poverty and
                ignorance seem to be the factors to stimulate a high birth rate.
                We must abolish these factors as part of Sound National Population Planning. Increase
                pop for 1936 8,634,000.</p>
            <p>77% of the American people approve of B.C. as a part of our
                public health program.</p>
        
        
            <p>Gallup Poll</p>
            <p>Before we attempt to increase our own population and raise the
                birth rate, lets begin at the bottom and definitely cut down the
                birth rate of the feebleminded and mentally deficient -- cut
                down the increasing institutional population. This should be
                mandatory and those in charge made to answer for this. It has
                been secretly states at the <org
                    reg="American Public Welfare Association">American Public
                    Welfare Assn</org>. by <person reg="Haber, William">Wm
                    Haber</person> Prof. of Economics at <org>University of
                    Michigan</org> that 10% of the population 13,500,000 will
                    continue on relief at a cost
                of $2,500,000,000 yearly to federal, state and local welfare
                bodies (tax payers). 22,000,000 persons on relief in 1937.
                    level it down to
                14,000,000.</p><p><person reg="Lippman, Walter">Lippman</person></p>
            <p>It is not colonies, or disarmaments or new territory that is
                going to establish Peace in <place>Europe</place>. Just handing over colonies to any nation
                with a high birth rate simply postpones the crisis a generation
                &amp; with every nation in <place>Europe</place> <add>spawning</add> competition already unable to provide an outlet for their surplus
                population.</p>
            <p>The great pressure of surplus population is in <place>central
                    Europe</place>. Within 100 years 1800 to 1914 population of
                Europe increased from 180,000,000 to 480,000,000. At that period
                over 60,000,000 Europeans migrated to other continents about
                half came to the <place reg="United States">U States</place>.</p>
            <p>Since 1824 to 1930 immigration had practically closed in U.S.A.
                &amp; <place>South America</place> &amp; British Dominions. It was this decade that
                saw the explosion of <place>Italy</place> into
                    <place>Ethiopia</place> &amp; <place>Germany</place> into
                Central Europe. With persecution and expropriation as National
                policies-- The end is not is sight.</p>
            <p>Mass emigration of Jews out of Germany or Central Europe is not
                the solution. It will need a new Continent with pioneer
                conditions &amp; natural resources to relieve the needs of Central
                Europe. To squeeze into a settled community this surplus will
                only react against the both native and alien groups--</p>
            <p>Is there such a continent? If so who will it up and does it mean
                Peace? If so how long? If the spawning competition of Central Europe <del>will</del> continues it is only another
                tomorrow before another continent will be needed &amp; demanded
                for the surplus population of that decade.</p>
            <p>It must be apparent to all Statesmen that the time has come to face the facts
                of population. It’s no use asking one nation to slow down their
                birth rates or armaments while other nations speed up their own-- It’s got to be all equal distribution of birth rights to
                inherit the <place>Earth</place> --</p>
        
    </docBody>
</doc>
