<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Autograph speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-02-09 JC transcribed and encoded</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-02-10 CH proof</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-02-13 JC corrections made</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1933-03-00"><supplied resp="MSPP">Mar 1933</supplied></docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Population Control Speech Notes</supplied></titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp236480</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</title> S
				71:437</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="WELHG">Wells, H.G.</name>
			<name id="HUGVIO">Hugo, Victor</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<index level1="population growth" level2="impact of"/>
		<index level1="population size" level2="and birth rate"/>
		<index level1="population size" level2="regulation of"/>
		<index level1="family size" level2="and poverty"/>
		<index level1="fertility rates"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>

		<p>We are all in the throes of troubled times. Few of us can gauge its depths or realize its
			significance.</p>
		<p>Recently the <person reg="Norman, Montagu Collet">Pres</person> of the <org>Bank of
				England</org> after a visit to <place>Canada</place> &amp; <place
				reg="United States">US</place> is reported to have said, that no man or group of men
			are born who care to solve our problems or lead us out of our Social &amp; Economic
			Chaos. This brought to my mind one of the early prophecies of that brilliant &amp; far
			sighted man <person reg="Wells, H. G.">H G Wells</person> who said <q who="WELHG">"There
				are two natural forces at work which may make or destroy Civilization. The first is
				the rapid growth of <add>mans</add> fertility-- The second the slow growth of the
				mans mind. One couple may produce within a lifetime over 100 beings. The mind is of
				slow growth &amp; development &amp; can not cope with conditions &amp; problems
				arising out of population pressure. Much of the chaos today stems back to the
				prolific breeding of our forbears. We have continued to multiply our numbers while
				we have lent every effort to install machines to take mans place to do his work
				&amp; throw him on the scrap heap of the jobless."</q>
		</p>
		<p>Coal mines, glass works, silk &amp; woolen mills all are products of an age where man's
			labor is no longer necessary for Social purposes. Demand for mans labor has
			decreased.</p>
		<p>Machinery has taken his place. Human reproduction has increased from these same groups,
			the unskilled, the illiterate.</p>
		<p>1 man loads 10 tons coal a day in old days or 300 tons a month.</p>
		<p>Now-- 4 men load 300 tons in 8 hours.</p>
		<p><person reg="Hugo, Victor">Victor Hugo</person>. <q who="HUGVI">'no force in the world so
				great as that of an idea whose hour has struck'</q> no subject has so large a
			practical significance which at the same time cuts so deeply into the foundation of
			Social Evolution as bc.</p>
		<p>Bc in the keynote of a new social &amp; moral awakening. It is not only a health &amp;
			Economic expedient its a great social principle interlocked with the spiritual advance
			of woman &amp; the <add>moral</add> progress of the race. </p>
		<p>Bc is the conscious control of the birth rate by means that prevent the corruption of
			life-- Prevent not destroy, not interfere. No more an interference with life than living
			in celibacy, continence of remaining single or unmarried.</p>
		<p>Control not limit-- furnace, motor car traffic, conduct, temper, life &amp; behavior.
			Conscious-- not <add>an</add> accident &amp; reckless abandon to the moment with regrets
			tears &amp; broken lives in its trace. Conceived in love, choice not chance. Form
			conscious desire deliberate intentional given the heritage of sound body &amp; mind</p>
		<p>Two <add>fundamental</add> problems confront Civilization</p>
		<p>Pressure of population upon means of existence, job markets, machines</p>
		<p>Reconciling humanitarian efforts with race improvement.</p>
		<p>Billions are being spent in charities the effect of which is to increase the dysgenic
			types, the derelicts, the morons &amp; to tax the normal &amp; intellectual for their
			maintenance. </p>
		<p><person reg="Ross, Edward Alsworth">E A Ross</person> claims that over 200,000,000 new
			human beings came into being last year 50,000 a day.</p>
		<p><person reg="Meyers, William Starr">Wm Starr Meyers</person> claims that only 15% of our
			population can be said to be intellectual of the remaining 85% he says that 45% is
			subnormal 15% feebleminded &amp; 20% mediocre.</p>
		<p> History tells us that our Civilization is tending to kill off the very types that
			have.</p>
		<p>3 Considerations</p>
		<p>Mothers health, fathers earning power, standard of living you wish to maintain.</p>
		<p>Population control</p>
		<p>Increase death rate</p>
		<p>Decrease birth rate</p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
