<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011-07-27 NC</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>SHE Magazine</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1945-04-00"><supplied resp="MSPP">Apr 1945</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>An Authority on Family Life Says: Save War Marriages</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236413</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>SHE Magazine: Page Extra Clip Sheet</title>April 1945</bibl>
            <bibl><title>MSM</title>S72:0499</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>The following clip sheet summarizes Sanger's article "War Marriages Are
            Worth Saving" that appeared in <title>SHE Magazine</title> April/May 1945 issue. No
            published or unpublished copy of the article has been found. For similar articles see
                <xref from="226160.xml">"Lasting Peace for the War Marriage"</xref>, July 1944 and
                <xref from="236035.xml">"How to Avoid Post War Divorces"</xref>, July 19,
            1944.</p><index level1="war" level2="marriage and"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>An Authority on Family Life Says: Save War Marriages</head>
        <head type="sub">Advice available to those who find their post war problems are leading to
            separation, divorce</head>

        <p>War marriages made headlines right after <place reg="Pearl Harbor, HI">Pearl
                Harbor</place>, when the marriage rate took a sharp up-swing. They are still making
            headlines, but they are no longer such cheerful ones. Two-thirds of the wartime
            marriages are doomed to end in the divorce courts, according to one prediction. Another
            more conservative estimate is that thirty-eight out of every one hundred will fail.</p>
        <p>How many of these marriages can really be salvaged? <person reg="Sanger, Margaret"
                >Margaret Sanger</person>, whose courageous fight for birth control has made her
            name famous throughout the world, has some ideas on the subject which she sets forth in
            an article in <title>SHE Magazine</title>'s current issue.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger has no magic words of advice which can save the marriage born solely of war
            emotion and found in the sober light of afterthought to be completely wrong. But she
            does believe that with the proper effort and cooperation a great many war marriages
            otherwise destined to go on the rocks, can be saved. </p>
        <p>Women should realize that their soldier husbands have become distinct individuals, men
            who are tired of all restraints, apron strings, commands. The don't want to be bossed,
            or even advised in many cases. Old occupations seem unbelievably dull and routine.</p>
        <p>Take the case of Mrs. Bill who became a successful business woman while her husband was
            fighting. She liked it. She didn't dream Bill would be anything but proud and delighted.
            He wasn't at all. He wanted her to quit, and was horrified and hurt at her earning more
            than he had at his pre-war job.</p>
        <p>Fortunately, both of them were willing to take advice and consulted Dr. <person
                reg="Burr, Emily T.">Emily T. Burr</person>, Director of the <org
                reg="New York City Vocational Adjustment Bureau">Vocational Adjustment Bureau</org>
            of <place reg="New York, NY">New York City</place>. Dr. Burr suggested that Mrs. Bill
            continue on at her job but that Bill's salary take care of all routine household
            expenses. Mrs. Bill could save for that baby they were planning to have as soon as they
            could afford it. This made sense to Bill and a quarrel that threatened to break Bill's
            spirit and a splendid marriage was averted.</p>
        <p>On a train recently Mrs. Sanger talked with a young girl who carried a fretful baby. Her
            husband will return at the war's end, but not to the appreciation he no doubt feels he
            deserves. She wants that appreciation for herself. She wants to be told how noble she
            has been to bear his child in that overcrowded hospital during his absence, to stay home
            with the baby night after night, scrimping on her allotment pay. After all, she argued,
            Phil was having plenty of excitement mixed in with the danger. Unless both give a
            little, and the girl-wife stops nursing her growing resentment, this particular marriage
            will be among the doomed.</p>
        <p>Frequently couples who have been married only a few weeks before they are separated tend
            to idealize each other during the period of separation, and are both completely
            disillusioned when faced with an average human being. When once they are made to realize
            this they are usually willing to let the other step down from the pedestal. </p>
        <p>Marriage is both a concession and a demand; a living thing that is never static, even
            during long absences. If one partner has had a chance to develop and grow, it is up to
            him or her to wait for the other to catch up.</p>
        <p>There are numerous organizations ready to serve the serviceman and to give expert advice.
            He should seek them out when problems seem too great to cope with. They may save a
            marriage!</p>

    </docBody>
</doc>
