<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed draft speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2009/08/03 LL</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2010/04/08 CH proof and enter</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-11 CH clean regs and errors</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1928-01-01">
            <supplied resp="MSPP">ca. 1928</supplied>
        </docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Opening</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236532</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Sophia Smith Collection</title>, Smith College.</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title>, S71:0152.</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>The conference that Sanger addressed has not yet been identified. The last page(s) may be
            missing. Handwritten additions and corrections were made by Margaret Sanger.</p>
        <index level1="birth control movement"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="class-based"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <p>It is my pleasure to express a cordial welcome on behalf of the <org>American Birth
                Control League</org> to the delegates, visitors and others who have come from other
            states to attend this Conference and to assist us by their counsel, experience and
            advice.</p>
        <p>Great and significant events have taken place in the world since the formation of the
            first American Birth Control League less than ten years ago.</p>
        <p>Up to that time, while the practice of family limitation had been already established
            among the well to do and more educated classes in this country, there had been no
            attempt on the part of any group or individuals to crystallize the idea into a movement
            or to encourage the practice among the poor, diseased or unfit.</p>
        <p>The population among the well to do was stationary <add>not a problem</add>. I found them
            healthy, happy, clean, <del>contented</del>
            <add>comfortable</add> with their children <add>well cared for</add> tho there were but
            few in each family. <add>It is from this class that the colleges are filled &amp; that
                the best positions of State &amp; Society are filled.</add> While the population of
            the <del>latter</del>
            <add>poor</add> was increasing. Here I found miseries unequaled, poverty, slums,
            overcrowding, were perpetuated, while society shook its head and blamed the causes on to
            various agents,–nature, God’s will, etc.</p>
        <p>All about me I saw mothers die, children born doomed to death or born dead, wasted energy
            and precious lives snuffed out. <gap extent="page(s)" reason="missing"/></p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
