<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Draft Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/06/28 CE</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/11/30 CH Correct typo</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-01 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1938-00-00"><supplied resp="MSPP">1938</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Pressure of Population as a Cause of War</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236531</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S71:1124</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="DIXAR">Dix, Arnold</name>
            <name id="BERFR">von Bernhardi, Friedrich Adolf Julius</name>
            <name id="COPFR">Coppola, Francesco</name>
            <name id="GOEHE">Goering, Hermann Wilhelm</name>
            <name id="MUSBE">Mussolini, Benito</name>
            <name id="NYEDA">Nydea, Professor [unidentified]</name>
            <name id="PEARA">Pearl, Raymond</name>
            <name id="PUIPO">Pius XI</name>
            <name id="THOWA">Thompson, Warren S.</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
            <name id="MSPP">Margaret Sanger Papers Project</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>For draft versions, see <title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title>
            S71:1064, 1070, 1082, and 1091. For excerpts see Library of Congress Microfilm 130:509
            and <title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S71:1014. Handwritten insertions and
            emphasis added by <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>.</p>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="population growth and"/>
        <index level1="Europe" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="Germany" level2="population policies of"/>
        <index level1="Italy" level2="overpopulation and"/>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="overpopulation and"/>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="population policies of"/>
        <index level1="Mussolini, Benito" level2="policy of"/>
        <index level1="overpopulation" level2="emigration and"/>
        <index level1="population" level2="food supply and"/>
        <index level1="population" level2="war and"/>
        <index level1="population growth" level2="natural resources and"/>
        <index level1="population growth" level2="regulation of"/>
        <index level1="war" level2="causes of"/>
        <index level1="world peace" level2="MS on"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head><add>Pressures of Population as a Cause of War</add></head>
        <div type="section">
            <p>The Causes of War are manifold and diverse. There have been wars of aggression and
                wars of defense.</p>
            <p>Motives have been hidden behind religious and dynastic interests. Today more than
                ever before in the history of our complex civilizations is it difficult to attribute
                a given war to any one particular cause.</p>
            <p>It is certain that the official reasons given are seldom the actual causes which
                plunge nations and peoples into war. One stands appalled at the trumped up motives
                of despots, tyrants dictators, for which tens of thousands <add>of able bodied
                    men</add> have been slain in battles, while cities, towns, even countries of
                beauty and wealth have been sacked and destroyed.</p>
            <p>The reasons given (if given at all) for this wholesale mad destruction are usually
                “blinds” or “leads” for popular prejudice to inflame the masses into action.</p>
            <p>Reasons for “wars of defense” are manipulated by diplomats.</p>
            <p>Wars to end wars become an occasion and a pretext.</p>
            <p>Wars of Idealistic and Religious motives seem more righteous and worthy than motives
                of economic rivalry for markets and world trade. So these sordid motives are kept in
                the background.</p>
            <p>We acknowledge that racial and religious differences have been the cause of war, and
                though religion teaches the duty of loving our neighbors as ourselves, “religious
                wars” have continued unabated.</p>
            <p>In <place>Ireland</place> it is the Catholics against the Protestants.</p>
            <p>In <place>India</place> the Mohammedans against the Hindus who continue to attack
                each other in savage fury, and while we realize that religious and racial
                animosities have been the cause of war in many parts of the world in the past, it is
                now generally accepted by experts in the field that <emph rend="underline">economic
                    factors</emph> have been preeminent in causing wars and that religious or racial
                differences have become subjected to the all-important factor of economic rivalry,
                which <emph rend="underline">was</emph> the dominant factor in the World War, as it
                has continued to be in World Politics at the <emph rend="underline">present
                    time</emph>.</p>
            <p>From 1910 to 1914 German authorities were issuing statements of warnings to the world
                that her population was increasing to the explosion point, and that her needs of
                expansion were dominating her every political and economic move.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="Section">
            <p> 1901 -- “<title type="book">In Conquest and Kultur</title>” by <person
                    reg="Dix, Arthur">Arthur Dix</person>:</p>
        </div>
        <div type="Section">
            <p>“<q who="DIXAR">Because the German people nowadays increase at the rate of 800,000
                    inhabitants in a year, they need both room and nourishment for the
                surplus</q>....</p>
            <p>“<q who="DIXAR">As a world power in the world market we must assert our place and
                    make it secure in order that the younger hands may find room and opportunity for
                    employment</q>.”</p>
            <div type="section">
                <p><person reg="von Bernhardi, Friedrich Adolf Julius">Von Berhardi</person> in his
                        “<title type="book"><place>Germany</place> and the Next War</title>”
                    published in 1911 states:</p>
                <p> “<q who="BERFR">Strong, healthy, flourishing nations increase in number. From a
                        given moment they require a continual expansion of their frontiers</q>.</p>
                <p>“<q who="BERFR">They require new territory for the accommodation of their surplus
                        population</q>.</p>
                <p>“<q who="BERFR">Since almost every part of the globe is inhabited, new territory
                        must be obtained at a cost <emph rend="underline">to its possessors</emph>
                        -- that is to say <emph rend="underline">by conquest</emph> which thus
                        becomes a law of necessity.</q> Again in 1912 -- <emph rend="underline">von
                        Bernhardi wrote:</emph></p>
                <p>“<q who="BERFR">We must endeavor to acquire new territories throughout the world
                            <emph rend="underline">by all means in our power</emph>, because we must
                        preserve to <place>Germany</place> the millions of Germans who will be born
                        in the future, and we must provide for them food and employment. They ought
                        to be able to live under a German sky, and to lead a German life</q>.”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <p>These statements by German writers and statesmen <add>express</add> a simple,
                        <emph rend="underline">universal</emph> and eternal truth. That the growth
                    of population with the resulting desire and need for economic expansion was a
                    necessary cause of war <emph rend="underline">Yesterday</emph> is <emph
                        rend="underline">Today</emph> and will be <emph rend="underline"
                        >Tomorrow</emph>, unless we recognize that vital factor and do something
                    about it.</p>
                <p>The World War had brought out startling facts regarding population growth .</p>
                <p><emph rend="underline">While</emph> the birth rate of Europe has steadily
                    declined during the last 100 years, the population from 1800, which was
                    200,000,000 rose to 600,000,000 by the year 1914, and during this period -- from
                    1845 to 1914 -- (or a period of 70 years) 50,000,000 persons emigrated from
                        <place>Europe</place> to other parts of the globe, and yet we have as an
                    example of this 70-year period the <emph rend="underline">explosion of the
                        dynamic power of fertility</emph> which ended ina World War and nearly
                    destroyed our civilization!!!</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <p><emph rend="underline">Emigration is not the answer to prevent war.</emph></p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub">General Population Facts</head>
                <p>Before taking up the problem of the separate nations, which we will designate as
                        <emph rend="underline">high pressure</emph> and <emph rend="underline">low
                        pressure</emph> countries, I would like to state the following:</p>
                <p>Man’s inherent capacity to incrrase his numbers is practically unlimited, while
                    the earth’s tillable surface and its natural resources are definitely limited.
                            <add><person reg="Wells, H. G.">H. G. Wells</person></add></p>
                <p>before the 19th Century the growth of population was everywhere slow even
                    stationary in some places.</p>
                <p>While accurate population statistics for the whole world are lacking, a
                    conservative estimate would indicate the following:</p>
                <p>That the population of the world is approximately 2,000 million people, It has
                        <emph rend="underline">increased 27,000,000 in 8 years,</emph> (or from 1924
                    to 1932).</p>
                <p>The density of population was estimated 1932 to be about 40 per square mile.
                    Later we will see that this is conservative
                            <add><unclear>underestimate</unclear></add>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <p>“<title>MULTIPLYING MAN</title>” by <person reg="Pearl, Raymond"
                    >Pearl</person></p>
                <p>“<q who="PEARA">In the last analysis the living of every human being must come
                        out of the earth</q></p>
                <p>“<q who="PEARA">Each individual now living has available about 16 acres of land,
                        half of which is useless</q>.”</p>
                <p>Pearl then turns to the chemical aspect of the population problem -- Carbon, the
                    most important element for the maintenance of life -- The most serious aspect of
                    the problem is not food production but the rapid rate at which industrial and
                    commercial modes of life are using up basic resources.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub" rend="underline">ACREAGE AND FOODS</head>
                <p>100 acres of wheat land will support 208 persons a year</p>
                <p>100 acres of milk producing pasture supports 41 persons</p>
                <p>100 acres beef producing pasture supports 9 persons</p>
                <p>About one-half the population of the world lives on rice or cereal, and know
                    nothing of meat, cheese and milk <add>eggs or fruits</add>.</p>
                <p>According to Prof. <person reg="East, Edward Murray">E.M. East</person> there are
                    13 thousand million acres of tillable soil available, of which two-fifths is now
                    under cultivation.</p>
                <p>And since it takes 2 1/2 acres of land, according to our own present standards of
                    living, to support each individual in countries like the <place>United
                        States</place>, <place>England</place> and <place>France</place>, it is
                    clear that these standards cannot be maintained if the population continues to
                    increase, and that even on a lower standard of living the world cannot sustain
                    more than <emph rend="underline">5 thousand million</emph> at the most.</p>
                <p>If we deduct from this area now under cultivation the mountains the deserts, the
                    rivers, streams, towns, roads, forests, far less than two-fifths would be
                    left.</p>
                <p>It is safer to say that the density of population in the world is 80 people per
                    square mile today.</p>
                <p>The <org reg="United States Department of Agriculture">U.S. Department of
                        Agriculture</org> has published <emph rend="underling">four</emph> dietetic
                    scales, with the necessary land to support them. the <emph rend="underline"
                        >lowest diet</emph> necessary to keep <emph rend="underline">very poor
                        people</emph><add> Germany 9 months of war</add> from starving on a <emph
                        rend="underline">temporary</emph> basis, requires 1.2 acres of land an
                    adult.</p>
                <p>The next <emph rend="underline">minimum</emph> diet consistent with the average
                    health is 1.8 acres of land.</p>
                <p>And the third ordinary diet of the <emph rend="underline">middle-class</emph>
                    standard is 2.3 acres.</p>
                <p>And the <emph rend="underline">ideal</emph> for <emph rend="underline"
                        >health</emph> and vitality demands 3.1 acres per individual.</p>
                <p>The <org>League of Nations</org> statistics on the facts of living show that the
                    highest standards of life are maintained for the largest number of people in the
                        United States, <place>Canada</place>,
                        <place>Australia</place>, <place>New Zealand</place> -- all which have a
                    thin population and low birth rate.</p>
                <p>We must know that the majority of the population of the world, especially in
                    countries like India and <place>China</place>. <add>Even</add>
                    <place reg="Soviet Union">Russia</place> with high birth rates, live permanently
                    on the lowest standard, which only “low pressure” countries like the United
                    States, France, England, New Zealand, Australia, Canada, low birth rate
                    countries, can maintain the ideal diet.</p>
                <p>So much for the diet and the food possibilities and the land!</p>
                <p>And now let us take <add>up</add> some of the vital factors in our population
                    growth:</p>
                <p>Population experts have recently been shedding crocodile tears and issuing grave
                    warnings to the people of the “low pressure” population countries, because the
                    birth rates of these countries <emph rend="underline">are declining</emph>.</p>
                <p>They emphasize the declining birth rate but they fail to tell us that the
                    population of these countries are nevertheless increasing.</p>
                <p>Let me give you a simple example of birth rates and how to compute them.</p>
                <p>Interest 40% on $1000. would equal $400.</p>
                <p>Interest 2% on $1,000,000 would give you $20,000.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub">“High Pressure” -- “Low Pressure” Countries</head>
                <p><add>High</add> Germany, <place>Italy</place> and <place>Japan</place> constitute
                    what is now termed the “<emph rend="underline">high pressure</emph>”
                    nations.</p>
                <p><add>Low</add> England, United States, <place>South America</place>, Australia,
                    Canada, <place reg="Scandinavia">Scandinavian countries</place> constitute the
                    “low pressure” nations.</p>
                <p>In 43 years or from the end of the <name type="war">Franco-Prussian war</name> to
                    1910, Germany’s population increased 24,000,000.</p>
                <p>At the beginning of the World War in
                    1914 her population was approximately 68,000,000 with an area of 208,780 square
                    miles.</p>
                <p><add><emph rend="underline">20 years later</emph></add>Today, nearly twenty years
                    later, or 1933 her population is approximately 66,000,000 in an area of 186,000
                    square miles.</p>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="sub">COSTS</head>
                    <p>The World War costs Germany 27,000 square miles thru her territorial loss and
                        deaths approximately 10,000,000 in population.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="sub">DENSITY</head>
                    <p>In 1914 the density of population was 404 per square mile -- the danger
                        signal for any nation. In her density is 256 per square mile!!!</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <p><add>What does density mean.</add></p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub">ACREAGE: per person</head>
                <p> When we remember that there are 640 acres to the square mile and it takes at
                    least 2 1/2 acres to feed every individual, you can figure out for yourselves
                    what is bound to happen if this condition continues.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub">Birth Rates</head>
                <p> The birth rate in Germany went up in 1934 to 18.9 and her death rate went down
                    11.8. <add>In spite of Heroic Efforts.</add> The birth rate thruout the world
                    seemed to take a step upward in that year 1934, <emph rend="underline">except in
                        Italy</emph>.<add>!!</add></p>
                <p><del>Depression.</del></p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub">AGRICULTURE</head>
                <p>Any further agricultural development in Germany <add>is</add> impossible as even
                    in <add>as far back as</add> 1914 she had already utilized all fertile land.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub">EMIGRATION</head>
                <p> Emigration, however, was her release. All doors of the world were open to German
                    emigrants up to the World War.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub">NATIONAL ASSETS</head>
                <p>A German was an asset to any nation Educated robust, strong, intelligent,
                    thorough in his undertakings and habit, clean, highly trained mechanics, experts
                    in all lines of industry, linguists in the various languages of Europe and the
                    Balkans; scientists taking no second place with any nation; advanced in
                    medicine, the arts and chemistry.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub">NO RETURNS</head>
                <p>For all this training from childhood by the <org reg="Germany Government"
                        >Govt.</org> Germany had no returns on this human investment, because she
                    did not have sufficient colonies to utilize this human equipment.</p>
                <p><add>While</add> Few Germans went to <place>South Africa</place>
                    <emph>colonies</emph>, Large numbers went elsewhere. <add><place>Brazil</place>,
                            <place reg="Argentina">Argentine</place> USA</add></p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub"><emph rend="underline">Industrial People</emph></head>
                <p>Today the only country in the world that has not <add>yet</add> banned emigrants
                    is South America. But a large <emph rend="underline">industrial</emph>
                    population such as might emigrate from Germany is not useful where <emph
                        rend="underline">agricultural</emph> needs are urgent and required.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub"><emph rend="underline">RAW MATERIAL:</emph></head>
                <p> Germany like Italy and Japan needs raw material for her industries, the
                    manufacturing of which she will exchange for food.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub">LACKING</head>
                <p> She lacks oil, rubber, cotton, steel, and copper as well as food.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <p>The <emph rend="underline">condition of Germany today</emph> is that she is not
                    ready for war. She is not going to be trapped in isolation again as she was in
                    the World War.</p>
                <p>Her new program of rearmament is not only <emph rend="underline">military</emph>
                    preparedness by <emph rend="underline">industrial</emph> as well and she is
                    bending all her efforts on a system of <emph rend="underline"
                        >self-sufficiency</emph> for these necessities which she is lacking.</p>
                <p>Nevertheless she <emph rend="underline">does not intend</emph> to <emph
                        rend="underline">decrease</emph> her birth rate nor to control her
                    population growth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head><add>Gen Goering</add></head>
                <p>In November, 1936, <person reg="Goering, Hermann Wilhelm">General
                        Goering</person> stated:</p>
                <p>“<q who="GOEHE">The territory in which the Germans live is too small for the
                        66,000,000 inhabitants and will soon be too small for the 70,000,000,
                        80,000,000, 90,000,000 which we <emph rend="underline">want</emph> to
                        become</q>.”</p>
                <p>Where is the League of Nations and what is their reply to this challenge to
                    International Peace?</p>
                <p><emph rend="underline">ABSOLUTE  SILENCE</emph></p>
                <p>Had the jurists, lawyers, professors, soldiers, politicians, who made the Treaty of <place reg="Versailles, France"
                        >Versailles</place> been less ignorant of concrete <emph
                        rend="underline">realities</emph> that after having disarmed Germany,
                    instead of providing a safety valve against the day when the population boiler
                    would again <emph rend="underline">bubble</emph> and <emph rend="underline"
                        >explode</emph>, they had either made provision for Germany’s expansion or
                    insisted that she restrain her increasing fertility to the territory assigned to
                    her. Voluntary controlled population was the best <emph rend="underline">war
                        debt</emph> the <org reg="Entente Powers">Allies</org> could have demanded
                        <add>of the <org>Cental Powers</org></add>.</p>
                <p>Let all peace-loving people remember that the greatest asset to militarism is the
                        <emph rend="underline">uncontrolled prolific</emph> breeding among the
                    laboring classes. Without this, <emph rend="underline">militarism</emph> could
                    not exist. So much for Germany.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub"><emph rend="underline">ITALY</emph></head>
                <p>Italy became a “high pressure” zone as soon as the United States and other
                    nations raised barriers against emigration.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub"><emph rend="underline">Emigration previous to 1914:</emph></head>
                <p>Italy had been sending into this country more than 90,000 Italians a year. As
                    soon as this was no longer possible she had to come face to face with the
                    problem of her own surplus numbers. She has had to feed, educate, and maintain
                    them, arrange for their employment in so short a time that that is why her
                    problems become suddenly so acute.</p>
                <p>The present territory of Italy is approximately 120,000 square miles. Only 9,000
                    square miles of this was attained thru the World War.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub">DENSITY</head>
                <p>Her population in 1933 was 43,000,000</p>
                <p>Her density population <emph rend="underline">344</emph> persons to the square
                    mile. <add>higher today.</add></p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub">EMBITTERED</head>
                <p>Italy <del>thru >Mussolini</del> was embittered by <del>its</del>
                    <add>small</add> spoils of the World War. She wanted much more territory from
                    the Allies and like Japan decided to become a military force where “<emph
                        rend="underline">might would make right</emph>.”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub">MARRIAGE</head>
                <p>She set herself a policy to increase her population. The age of marriage was
                    reduced from 18 years to 16 years for boys, and from 15 years to 14 years for
                    girls. <add>Barbaric &amp; <emph rend="underline">Sadistic</emph></add></p>
                <p> But in spite of all provisions made for larger famillies and the medals and
                    doles to fathers, Italy’s birth ratehas steadily decreased.</p>
                <p><add>Angry, embittered rattles the sword &amp; in</add>
                    <emph rend="underline">Desperation</emph> makes War <add>&amp; enters <emph
                            rend="underline"><place>Ethiopia</place></emph>!</add></p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <p><list>
                        <item>1921: Birth rates: 29.7 Death rates: 17.3</item>
                        <item>1926: Birth rates: 26.8 Death rates: 16.0</item>
                        <item>1931: Birth rates: 24.9 Death rates: 14.8</item>
                        <item>1932: Birth rates: 23.8 Death rates: 14.6</item>
                        <item>1936: Birth rates: 23.3 Death rates: 13.9</item>
                    </list></p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub" rend="underline">EMIGRATION:</head>
                <p>650,000 persons left annually <add>previous to 1914.</add></p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub" rend="underline">United States Emigration:</head>
                <p> 90,000 Italians settled permanently each year -- almost 1,000 a day.</p>
                <p>25% of her natural yearly increase came to the U.S.A.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub" rend="underline"><org reg="Italy, National Institute of Statistics"
                        >Government Bureau of Statistics</org></head>
                <p>of 1931 claimed 10,000,000 Italians reside outside of Italy. Riviera, USA</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub" rend="underline">Unemployment increased</head>
                <p>1922 -- 541,775</p>
                <p>1935 -- 638,100</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub" rend="underline">Illiteracy</head>
                <p>1/3 of population</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub" rend="underline">Standards of Living</head>
                <p> close to subsistence level.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub" rend="underline">Agriculture</head>
                <p>cannot support her population -- one acre of tillable land to each adult person
                    in Italy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub" rend="underline">Poor agricultural country</head>
                <p>Soil dry, poor, stony.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub" rend="underline">Mountains and non-tillable</head>
                <p>About 1/3 of territory useful (only)</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub"><add>Has to</add>
                    <emph rend="underline">Import</emph></head>
                <p>cereals and cotton. <add>Soil</add> Cannot support these. <add> needs</add>
                    <add>Natural</add><del>Needs</del> resources <add>few</add>. Especially lacking
                    coal, iron ore petroleum.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub" rend="underline">Minerals:</head>
                <p>Italy like Japan is not rich in minerals or <del>natural</del> chemicals.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub" rend="underline">Water Power:</head>
                <p>excellent, uses to fullest extent. <place reg="Milan, Italy">Milan</place>,
                        <place reg="Turin, Italy">Turin</place>, manufacturers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub" rend="underline">Textile Industry:</head>
                <p> good but not enough to develop national industry by <emph rend="underline">this
                        means</emph>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub" rend="underline">Labor:</head>
                <p>Cheap, unskilled but cannot compete with China, India, or Japan, without natural
                    resources will not enable her to produce as <emph rend="underline"
                        >cheaply</emph> as manufactured goods in other countries.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub" rend="underline">Hand Work:</head>
                <p>compete with Belgians and French, India and China.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub" rend="underline">Colonies -</head>
                <p> chiefly poor grazing lands and deserts.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub" rend="underline">Eyes on Asia Minor</head>
                <p> -- <place>Syria</place> and <place>Mesopotamia</place>.</p>
                <p><add>But</add> She will <emph rend="underline">need to reckon</emph> with France
                    and <place>Great Britian</place>. <add><person reg="Moussolini, Benito"
                            >Mussolini</person></add>
                    <emph rend="underline">Science applied and swamp lands reclaimed</emph> -- wheat
                    production increased to fullest capacity, but not enough for her people.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <p>If Italy can <emph rend="underline">bluff the statesmen of Europe</emph> to give
                    her outlets for her bursting hordes she will feel that she has the right to go
                    on <emph rend="underline">breeding</emph> and <emph rend="underline"
                        >swarming</emph> until the same explosive point is reached again.</p>
                <p>When a nation <emph rend="underline">has deliberately</emph> brought about
                    conditions through encouraging an increasing population, <add>for War</add> it
                    cannot justify a course of action <emph rend="underline">which it would not have
                        done</emph> had the population been stationary or controlled.<add>Pope
                        Pious</add></p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub">POPE PIUS</head>
                <p><person reg="Pius XI">Pope Pius XI</person>, great champion of Peace,
                    defending Italy’s action in Ethiopia, is quoted as saying in August, 1935:</p>
                <p>“<q who="PIUPO">We cannot think of an unjust war. We cannot envisage this
                        possibility and we discard it deliberately ------ On the other hand, in
                        Italy there is a question of a <emph rend="underline">just war of
                            defense</emph> to secure frontiers against continual and incessant
                        dangers -- <emph rend="underline">a war made necessary by a population which
                            increases day by day</emph> -- a war undertaken to defend or assure
                            <emph rend="underline">material security</emph> of a country -- such a
                        war is justifiable</q>.”</p>
                <p>Intellectual dishonest is <emph rend="underline">unworthy</emph> of one, in so
                    exhalted a position.</p>
                <p><emph rend="underline">So we see the future in these terms!</emph></p>
                <p><add>That</add> Populations are to be <emph rend="underline">increased</emph> to
                    make war, and <emph rend="underline">wars</emph> are justifiable to <emph
                        rend="underline">increase</emph> populations.</p>
                <p>Mankind is doomed to extinction if this continues or is tolerated.</p>
                <p><add>Predictions</add></p>
                <p><emph rend="underline">Italy</emph> -- quote from <person reg="Thompson, Warren S."
                            ><emph rend="underline">Warren Thompson</emph></person>,
                            <add><title type="book">Danger Spots World and Population</title>, 1925</add>.</p>
                <p>“<q who="THOWA">It appears then, that Italy has neither the agricultural nor
                        industrial resources to care for the present growth of population for more
                        than a few years</q>.</p>
                <p>"<q who="THOWA">If they must remain at home the pressure of population will
                        shortly become intolerant and we may look for some kind of an
                    explosion</q>.”</p>
                <p><person reg="Coppola, Francesco">Francesco Coppola</person> “<title>Land of
                        Italy</title>” -- 1931. <org reg="Harvard University">Harvard</org>.</p>
                <p>“<q who="COPFR">There is only one solution for Italy’s problem -- <emph
                            rend="underline">Land</emph>. Colonial land for Italy or at least land
                        under Italy’s political control -- land for Italian people who are too
                        crowded in their own country; land for her power; <emph rend="underline"
                            >land for her freedom</emph> on the Mediterranean</q>.”</p>
                <p>1927 -- Mussolini before the <org
                        reg="Italy Chamber of Deputies">Chamber of Deputies</org> outlined his plans
                    for Greater Italy: (<place reg="Geneva, Switzerland">Geneva</place> <org>World
                        Population Conference</org>)</p>
                <p> “<q who="MUSBE">If Italy is to amount to anything it must enter into the second
                        half of this century with a population of at least 60,000,000
                        inhabitants</q>.”</p>
                <p>“<q who="MUSBE">We must at a given moment be able to mobilize 5,000,000 men <emph
                            rend="underline">thoroughly</emph> armed. We must strengthen our Navy,
                        while aviation must be on such a large scale, and <emph rend="underline">so
                            powerful</emph> that the noise of its motors <emph rend="underline">must
                            surpass any other noise</emph> and the are of the wings of our airplanes
                        must obscure the sun from our land</q>.”</p>
                <p>“<q who="MUSBE">Then between 1935 and 1940 we will be able to make our voice
                        heard</q>.”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub">JAPAN</head>
                <p>The tendency on the part of all nations since the War to be self-sufficient, and
                    create their own industries, and build up walls of protective tariffs, has
                    created a world situation which <emph rend="underline">continues to baffle
                        statesmen</emph>.</p>
                <p>This condition has spread to other countries like Japan. Standards of living,
                    wants and demands increase with industrial growth and education. People will
                    refuse to remain docile and starving as they awaken to educational
                    advantages.</p>
                <p>The choice between death, with starvation and hard work, and death from battle,
                    and a chance of better living, thru expansion, is not hard to make.</p>
                <p>Japanese seem destined to expand and to acquire lands for her needs.</p>
                <p>Like Italy -- Doors <add>the world were</add> closed against her surplus
                        numbers.<add>MS in Japan 1922</add></p>
                <p><emph rend="underline">Japan proper</emph>
                    <emph rend="underline">Danger Zones</emph></p>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="sub" rend="underline">Territory:</head>
                    <p>148,756 square miles</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="sub" rend="underline">Population</head>
                    <p>- 1935 - 69,254,148 <del>7% increase since 1930</del> 4,804,143 increase in
                        1934) <add>deaths about half</add>
                        <add>Or</add> 4 babies a minute a year <add>1934</add>
                        <del>Increase</del> on a territory scarcely able to sustain 20,000,000.</p>
                    <p> Japan has <emph rend="underline">tripled</emph> its population in 50 years
                        to 70,000,000.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="sub" rend="underline">Density population</head>
                    <p> -- 404 per square mile. <emph rend="underline">Danger mark.</emph></p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="sub" rend="underline">Tillable soil</head>
                    <p>-- 23,000 square miles <emph rend="underline">only</emph>, moderately
                        fertile</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="sub" rend="underline">Mountainous</head>
                    <p>-- Three fourths (3/4) cannot be cultivated - about the size of
                            <place>California</place>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="sub" rend="underline">Fishing</head>
                    <p>-- 1,500,000 employed at this (<place>Alaska</place>)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="sub" rend="underline">Minerals</head>
                    <p> -- lacks iron ore, petroleum, coal, steel, seeks control over latent ore
                        deposits in <place>Northern China</place>. Poor quality and not sufficient
                        for shipping or <org reg="Imperial Japanese Navy">Navy</org> -- grave
                        problem for military authorities.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="sub" rend="underline">Labor</head>
                    <p> -- cheap, plentiful, literate 98%</p>
                    <p>Industrial development not <add>easily</add> possible -- <add>as she</add>
                        lacks natural resources.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="sub" rend="underline">Emigration</head>
                    <p> = Doors of world (except <place>South America</place>) closed <add>to
                            Japan</add>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="sub" rend="underline">Import</head>
                    <p>-- Not sufficient food for increasing population 1,000,000 a year.</p>
                    <p><add>”Bandits” in <place>Manchuria</place></add></p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="sub" rend="underline">Manchuria</head>
                    <p> -- Supposed to be rich in coal and iron, excellent quality, easily mined --
                        Disappointment Railroad well organized for mining.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="sub" rend="underline">Disappointment</head>
                    <p><emph rend="underline">Great disappoint</emph> over these resources.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="sub" rend="underline">1931 Manchuria</head>
                    <p>-- Japanese statesmen “<q who="UNK">viewed with alarm</q>” the doings of “<q
                            who="UNK"><emph rend="underline">bandits</emph></q>” -- walked in to
                        form to puppet state of <place>Manchuko</place>.</p>
                    <p>This action was supposed to</p>
                    <list>
                        <item>(1) increase her area of <emph rend="underline">tillable</emph>
                            land</item>
                        <item>(2) given her room for expansion</item>
                        <item>(3) given her access to minerals and fuel. railroads which were to
                            enable Japan to become an Industrial Center for the <place>Far
                                East</place>.<add rend="underline">Disappointed</add></item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="sub"><emph rend="underline">POWER HAS GONE TO HER HEAD</emph></head>
                    <div type="section">
                        <head type="sub" rend="underline">General Education</head>
                        <p>- <emph rend="underline">Public Health</emph>, higher standards of
                            living, Western influence has created demands. <add>Tremendous <gap
                                    reason="illegible" resp="MSPP"/> of Population</add> Chick
                            inside egg -- inevitable -- Explosion.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="section">
                        <head type="sub" rend="underline">Racial Pride, Political Arrogance, Loose
                            Face.</head>
                        <p>
                            <add>Aggressive</add> The natural resources of Manchuria are not what
                            were hoped for.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="section">
                        <head type="sub" rend="underline">Goal</head>
                        <p>Latent ore deposits of North China are now the <emph rend="underline"
                                >goal</emph>.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub">The Way Out <del>Before Manchuria</del><add>Japan</add></head>
                <list>
                    <item>(1) Lower the standard of living like China and India. <add>will try to
                                <emph rend="underline">avoid</emph></add>
                    </item>
                    <item>(2) Encourage and adopt the general practice of Birth Control and
                        sterilization, rapidly and generally for stationary Population <add>great
                            interest -- Military against</add></item>
                    <item>(3) Colonize and use more territory in her own possessions --
                            <place>Korea</place>, <place>Formosa</place>.</item>
                    <item>(4) Expand into <add>low Pressure Country</add> territories where ready
                        access to fuel and iron supplies and other mineral resources through which
                            <add>her</add> industry might be built to provide for her rapidly
                        growing population. <add>Manchuria, China, This means Tyranny, Despotism,
                            &amp; War</add>.</item>
                </list>
                <p>“<q who="UNK"><emph rend="underline">Foreign trade</emph> is the way out; <emph
                            rend="underline">foreign markets</emph> will be open to our
                        manufacturers</q>.”</p>
                <p>“<q who="UNK">We need not decrease our numbers but must be able to provide
                        employment for our increasing population</q>..”</p>
                <p>1933 <person reg="Nyeda, Professor">Prof. Nyeda</person>, Professor of Economics
                    at <org>Tokyo University</org>, <org>Institute of Pacific Relations</org>, says
                    --</p>
                <p>“<q who="NYEDA">It is unfortunate for our country which is so thickly populated,
                        and whose inhabitants are increasing so rapidly that no suitable territory
                        lies open to which we can send a large number of emigrants, while to the
                        more thinly populated countries entrance is refused despite the fact that
                        these countries are in no danger of becoming over-populated by their own
                        people</q>.”</p>
                <p>“<q who="NYEDA">To bottle up a growing nation, such as the Japanese, in narrow
                        islands and to refuse them to expand overseas is not only unreasonable but
                        also to court <emph rend="underline">danger for the world</emph>, for if the
                        lack of food and other raw materials should <emph rend="underline">become
                            the cause</emph> of suffering no one can predict a future of internal
                        and external peace</q>.</p>
                <p><emph rend="underline">Four remedies suggested</emph>
                    <add>by liberal statesmen in Japan</add></p>
                <list>
                    <item>(1) Reorganization of economic system</item>
                    <item>(2) Expansion of export industries</item>
                    <item>(3) Emigration to own territory</item>
                    <item>(4) Slow down birth rate through Birth Control and sterilization -- for
                        Culture and Peace</item>
                </list>
                <p>Birth Control has made its way into Japan. It has already begun to work by later
                    marriage and small families. Experts predict that by 1945 her population will
                    become static and will not go beyond 80,000,000 -- never reach the 100,000,000
                    goal her Militarists have set for it.</p>
                <p>It has become clear that the population of the earth is fast arriving at its
                    possible maximum; that its density is badly distributed; that redistribution of
                    space can only be rectified by displacements; and that Birth Control in
                    over-populated countries is the first and surest method whereby the balance may
                    be peacefully restored.</p>
                <p><emph rend="underline">Consequently</emph> --</p>
                <p>There must be action on the part of “low pressure” nations.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub" rend="underline">Way Out for “Low Pressure” Nations</head>
                <p>For immediate action:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>1. Open gates of “low pressure” countries for selected quotas. U.S.A.
                        Russia South America New Zealand Canada Australia</item>
                    <item>2. <add>Allow</add> the purchase of unused lands by “high pressure”
                        countries for surplus, not only land but natural resources are
                        essential.</item>
                    <item>3. Raise tariff bars and encourage exchange of products -- Thus “Live and
                        Let Live.”</item>
                    <item>4. Also form a League of low birth rate countries to create cultural
                        interests and defend intellectual entities <del>as</del>
                        <add>who are</add> a product of civilization which no one nation has a right
                        to destroy. <add>Germany Russia Japan &amp; Italy</add></item>
                    <item>6. World Congress to set up a special University for study of Population
                        problems, its rate of growth, its distribution, its quality. <emph
                            rend="underline">This University</emph> should be composed of men and
                        women representing the various branches of science and medicine from all
                        countries. <add>International in scope. Thus truly lay</add>
                        <del>Truly</del> a Foundation for International Peace <add>on Earth. Good
                            Will to <emph rend="underline">men</emph> over the entire face of the
                            globe.</add></item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
