<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Autograph Draft Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/06/29 NC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-24 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/04/30 VS clean tags, corrected text</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1929-06-06">06 June 1929</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>
                <supplied resp="MSPP">Civic Club Dinner Introductory Remarks</supplied>
            </titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236534</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title/>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophie Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S71:0165</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>Sanger gave these introductory remarks at a dinner at the <org>Civic Club</org> in <place
                reg="New York, NY">New York City</place>, attended by the staff of the <org>Birth
                Control Clinical Research Bureau</org>. For another draft see MSM 271:165.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="medical community and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="morality of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="goals and strategies"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <p>It is my great pleasure &amp; privilege to welcome you all here tonight.</p>
        <p> My pleasure to greet those old friends -- tried &amp; true who have stood by the ship
            during these <del>years</del> long, lean years of struggle &amp; hardship.</p>
        <p> It is my privilege to welcome you on this occasion when we shall pay honor &amp; tribute
            to those valiant workers who have fought on many fronts, against ignorance &amp;
            suppression.</p>
        <p>But especially are we here to rejoice in the most recent &amp; far reaching victory. This
            victory was gained for us through the valiant efforts of these intrepid supporters
                Dr.<person reg="Stone, Hannah Mayer"> Hannah Stone</person> &amp; <person
                reg="Ernst, Morris L.">Morris Ernst</person>.</p>
        <p>Victory in the <supplied><person reg="Moskowitz, Grover">Moskowitz</person></supplied>
            majority decision conferred by the <org reg="United States Circuit Court of Appeals"
                >Circuit Court of Appeals</org>. The era of clearing away the legal rubbish of
            obscenity from the path of the Medical profession is now brought to a close.</p>
        <p>To have classed a subject like BC with obscenity in our laws has caused prodigious
            suffering to millions of women -- to countless men &amp; children as well. </p>
        <p>These laws have never conferred upon our Civilization one iota of benefit or been the
            means of helping us as a nation progress.</p>
        <p>These laws represent a debt loss to the credit side of human happiness.</p>
        <p>The ignorance, passion &amp; foundation which gave use to them have promise to be an
            unmitigated &amp; irredeemable Evil.</p>
        <p>Because they have planted in the minds of millions, the seeds of a fake &amp; harmful
            belief that BC is the same as abortion. BC is obscene, pornographic &amp; indecent. </p>
        <p>It has taken many thousands of us over twenty years of time, energy &amp; devotion to
            offset &amp; undo that evil &amp; to shake these laws apart. To pay honor &amp; tribute
            to those who are directly responsible for bringing about this separation in our laws we
            are gathered together tonight.</p>
        <p> We have the good fortune to have one of our earliest pioneers with us tonight who has
            graciously consented to be the Toastmaster of this momentous occasion. I am glad &amp;
            proud to present to you all of these staunch friends of our cause. Among whom there is
            none more consistent, more forceful, more courageous, more contemptuous of idle
            flattery, more respectful of sincere effort than the man who I take pleasure in
            presenting to you. </p>
        <p>
            <person reg="Wile, Ira S.">Dr. I. Wile.</person>
        </p>


    </docBody>
</doc>
