<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2010/03/02 AC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2013-11-17 CH changed title.</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-13 EK clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1935-02-13">13 Feb. 1935</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Birth Control Comes of Age</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236525</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Papers Microfilm, Smith Collection
                Collections</title>S71:0708</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>

            <resp>
                <name id="NIEFR">Nietzsche, Friedrich</name></resp>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Federal"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="MS on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="opposition to"/>
        <index level1="politicians" level2="birth control and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Copy of Speech of Mrs. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>, to be
            given Tuesday night, February 12, before the "Birth Control Comes of Age" dinner, <place
                reg="Washington, D.C.">Washtington, D.C.</place></head>
        <p>If any of you think that it was the birth control advocates who suffered defeat when our
            Bill was tabled by the <org reg="United States Congress, House Judiciary Committee"
                >House Judiciary Committee</org> a week ago today, you are greatly mistaken. The
            fifteen men who voted against discussion of the Bill did not defeat us; they defeated
            themselves. They defeated themselves by going on record as petty politicians, some of
            them without vision, others without courage or moral stamina, thinking only of
            elections.</p>
        <p> Someone has said that the difference between a statesman and a politician is that the
            statesman thinks of the next generation and the politician thinks of the next election.
            By <add>that</add> definition, I wonder how many statesman we can claim to have in this
            country in our present condition of relief and unemployment chaos, where billions are
            being spent to relieve poverty, unemployment and misery, only to increase the population
            which increases poverty, unemployment and misery.</p>
        <p> Everyone knows that we are piling up enormous debts for future generations to pay. It is
            quite likely, too, that these future generations, like Europe will refuse to pay them.
            But it is not only financial or money debts that I am referring to--such debts may be
            easily cancelled--but it will not be so simple for future generations to wipe out of
            existence the debt of inferior racial qualities that we are passing down to them, or to
            wipe out a population with millions of morons and defectives which we are handing down
            for our children’s children to manage.</p>
        <p> Black is the guilt of those thinking only of themselves and elections when they were
            delegated with a solemn trust to protect the health, happiness and well being of the
            nation and its future.</p>
        <p> Population may not be pressing upon the means of subsistence in this country as Malthus
            a hundred years ago claimed it might and could do, but population is certainly pressing
            upon our relief funds which is the means of subsistence for over 12,000,000 men and
            women unemployed in our country today. Population is pressing upon the relief agencies,
            upon the dole, upon other fellow’s job. It’s pressing upon the structure of our social
            system and upon every educational and cultural agency, the existence of which is
            threatened by increasing hordes fearful of hunger and want. Let us rid our minds that
            the vast extent of unemployment is only a temporary and transient condition. The growth,
            increase and development of mechanical appliances in production is a most significant
            factor in the problem of unemployment. It is bound to become more acute and widespread
            as science and invention continue to be applied to industry and agriculture. There has
            been for the past decade, and there continues to be, less need for manual human labor
            power in the production of the necessities of life. We have our choice of scrapping this
            machinery and all future invention of production or slowing down the birth rate.</p>
        <p> What is to become of the children? Of the million whose parents are today unemployed and
            many of them unemployable? What is to become of the millions of children who are born of
            parents equipped neither mentally or physically to support neither themselves nor their
            children? Who wants them? What is to become of them? What nation will take the moron,
            imbeciles, defectives off the hands of another nation? They are not even wanted for war.
            Many of them have already become heavy liabilities upon the nation, yet the stream from
            these sources flows on unchecked. If twenty years ago the Birth Control Movement had had
            the support of organized labor and those religious and social agencies whose mission it
            is to help to eliminate our human miseries, it is safe to say that there would be far
            healthier conditions and fewer of these social problems which we are facing today.</p>
        <p> If it is true that our population has increased from 122,000,000 in 1930 to 144,000,000
            at the end of 1934, then certainly we have a right to ask of our government, in fact to
            demand, to know from what strata of our population this increasing horde is coming from.
            If under the very eyes of our social agencies and with their help and assistance this
            increase comes from the physical and mental defectives, the diseased, helpless and
            destitute, then truly they and those governmental agencies behind them are creating a
            national Frankenstein. There are some basic truths which should form the cornerstone of
            any plan for permanent national security, one of which is, that we can never permanently
            improve the general standard of life until we greatly lessen the precaution of
            physically and mentally unfit to the general population.</p>
        <p> The Birth Control Movement is designed and organized to do just that. It is designed and
            organized to make available to the poorest and most afflicted of our people, scientific
            information, to regulate and control the size of the family. It is in my estimation the
            greatest and most important single and immediate means that scientific thought has
            devised to raise the mass population to a higher intelligence and level of life.</p>
        <p> “Oh,” say some of our opponents, “it can never do that, because people who now practice
            birth control are the wealthy and intelligent of the population, who practice birth
            control for selfish reasons.”</p>
        <p> Well, why should it not be practiced by the intelligent--for any knowledge or means
            which will enhance the beauty, happiness, and fulfillment of life, will always be more
            readily accepted by the intelligent of all classes. That’s the natural place for Birth
            Control to begin, but it need not end there!</p>
        <p> To say that it is practiced from selfish motives is not true. The desire for birth
            control knowledge and its practice comes from a higher and much more permanent cause
            than that. It is due to increased respect for the sanctity of life and an increased
            regard and responsibility for the welfare and education of children. Such parents are
            inspired by the hope that by having fewer children whom they can educate and properly
            care for, that they may help them escape the grinding poverty and hardships they
            themselves have endured due to the accident of birth.</p>
        <p> These same opponents glibly tell us about the enobling effects upon parents in the
            struggle of poverty. People who talk like that know nothing about poverty. To me it is
            the most degrading, demoralizing struggle that a human being can encounter, and we find
            the very people who so loudly praise its noble effects upon character spent their
            energies and efforts in trying to escape it for themselves. Who are the people that we
            are trying to legislate for, and why is this legislation necessary? We ask an amendment
            to the existing law, to allow physicians, hospitals, clinics, public health agencies to
            be exempt from the present law. We know that an enormous part of our population apply to
            these agencies for medical aid. If passed, this bill would open the doors and unite the
            hands of physicians in these institutions so that people coming to them could receive
            adequate information suitable to their individual problems and conditions.</p>
        <p> Are we too optimistic in hoping for success? No--for we know that the people thruout the
            country are thinking of family planning as never before. We know that we can win if we
            can arouse these people out of their lethargy and indifference and inform them how this
            law interferes with their obtaining adequate scientific knowledge. We want to organize
            in every state of the union. We want to put fifty field workers into action within the
            next thirty days. We are circulating petitions asking <org reg="United States Congress"
                >Congress</org> and the President of the United States to help us. We expect to get
            not less than 1,000,000 signatures. The action of the Judiciary Committee of the House
            of Representatives has inspired this action. It was a springboard for us to leap into a
            wider area and extend our activities thruout the nation.</p>
        <p> Ten years ago I addressed a letter to President <person reg="Coolidge, Calvin"
                >Coolidge</person>, urging the formation of a Federal Birth Control Commission. I
            suggested that this commission be composed of impartial scientists distinguished in the
            fields of biology, genetics, economics, medicine and philanthropy, and should be given
            free access to all facts and statistics relative to the racial health of this nation.
            This appeal was ignored. I now suggest to the present administration the organization of
            a Federal Population Bureau as an immediate and imperative necessity to survey our human
            resources. This Bureau should be scientifically equipped and empowered to diagnose the
            population problems confronting the Nation today, with the aim of formulating a Federal
            Population policy. This policy must be determined upon the primary considerations of
            public health and racial conservation. This survey and analysis would be concerned with
            our liabilities as well as our assets out of which our future population must be
            recruited.</p>
        <p> Through such a Bureau, it would be possible to correlate and co-ordinate the findings of
            scientists and their bearing upon the problems of crime, delinquency and other related
            problems that now threaten to engulf the nation. I am sure you will agree with me that
            what this nation needs is a definitely crystalized population policy by which we may
            acquaint ourselves with the population problems and solve them on the basis of human
            conservation.</p>
        <p> No program for the future can command an enduring respect unless it can prove that it
            can eradicate the evils of the present. “<q who="NIEFR">Beyond thyself shalt thou
                build,</q>” said a great modern prophet, “but first of all, thou must thyself be
            built strong and wholesome in body and soul.”</p>
        <p> Looking over this audience tonight, seeing friends gathered here after years of struggle
            and sacrifice, I am convinced that on this 21st Anniversary of the Birth Control
            Movement, it is sound of body and spirit and we may count on it to build beyond itself a
            true civilization in <place reg="United States">America</place>. </p>


    </docBody>
</doc>
