<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Autograph draft speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2010/02/03 AC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2010/04/07 CH proof and correct</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011-11-21 CH correct typo</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2013/10/30 CH added excerpt from news. added more headnote description</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-08-21 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1932-12-09">9 Dec 1932</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>
                <supplied resp="MSPP">Wesleyan University Speech notes and excerpts</supplied>
            </titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236563</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Papers Microfilm, SMith College Collections</title>
                S71:0432</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="HUGVI">Hugo, Victor</name>
            <name id="SHAGE">Shaw, George Bernard</name>
            <name id="WELHG">Wells, H. G.</name>
            <name id="CSL">Connecticut State Law</name>
            <name id="HC">Hartford Courant</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person> gave an address as
        part of a <org>Wesleyan University</org> undergraduate conference on marriage, held in
            <place reg="Middletown, CT">Middletown, Connecticut</place>. Other speakers included
            <person reg="Harris, Erdman">Erdman Harris</person>, Father <person
            reg="Cooper, John M.">John M. Cooper</person>, Dr. <person reg="Terhune, William B."
            >William B. Terhune</person>, Rev. <person reg="Chamberlain, Roy B.">Roy B.
            Chamberlain</person>, and Dr. <person reg="Campbell, Clarence G.">Clarence G.
            Campbell</person>. A complete version of Sanger's talk has not been located, but
        additional quotes reported in "<title type="article">Mrs. Sanger Says State Law
            'Stupid'</title>," <title type="journal">Hartford Courant</title>, Dec. 10, 1932, p. 2,
        have been added at the bottom of Sanger's draft notes. For reports of a similar speech, also
        not found, on Dec. 10, 1932, see "<xref from="421046.xml">Speech to the <org>Hartford Branch
                of the Connecticut Birth Control League</org>,</xref>" at the <org>St. John's Church
            Parish House</org>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="definitions of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits and risks"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="economic benefits and risks of"/>
        <index level1="Connecticut" level2="birth control" level3="laws and legislation"
        /></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <dateline><place reg="Wesleyan, CT">Westleyan</place><date value="1932-12-12">Dec
                12/32</date></dateline>
        <div>
            <p><person reg="Hugo, Victor">Victor Hugo</person>–- <q who="HUGVI">No force in the world
                    so great as that of an idea whose hour has struck.</q> I believe that the hour
                for birth control has struck, because there is no subject that has so large a
                practical significance which at the same time cuts so deeply into the foundations of
                social evolution as birth control.</p>
            <p>There is probably no other subject of equal importance, left so long in equal
                obscurity &amp; yet none which can show so unequalled a rise on our National horizon
                as this question has done within the past few years.</p>
            <p>
                <person reg="Shaw, George Bernard">G B Shaw</person> says it’s the <q who="SHAGE"
                    >most revolutionary idea of the present century</q>
                <person reg="Wells, H. G.">HG. Wells</person> says <q who="WELHG">it’s the most
                    momentous fact of modern life.</q></p>
            <p>The most intelligent English opinion of Church &amp; the professions have claimed it
                to be of <add>immediate </add>importance in solving the Social &amp; Economic
                problems of the world.</p>
            <p>Birth Control is the signal of a new Social &amp; Moral awakening. It is not only a
                health &amp; economic expedient it’s a great Social principle, interlocked with the
                    <add>future</add> development of women &amp; the spiritual progress of the race.
                Birth Control is the conscious control of the birth rate, by means that prevent the
                conception of life. The emphasism is placed on prevention &amp; not on interferrence
                or destruction of life.</p>
            <p> The emphasism is placed on Control &amp; not on limitation.</p>
            <p>It is also placed on conscious control instead of the reckless abandon to the moment
                with children the result. (haphazard, accidental conceptions) A generation ago it
                cost $10 to bring a baby into the world –- today because we have limited the output
                &amp; placed a higher value on child life, we have increased its value &amp;
                prepared the way for its higher development.</p>
            <p> Birth Control will prevent children from being born to become <emph rend="underline"
                    >buffers</emph> between two discordent parents, or become victims of marriage, of
                immature persons who make chattels of them for their own personal satisfaction or
                exploit them as wage earners to support an increasingly large family.</p>
            <p>There are seven <add>obvious</add> reasons to practice birth control</p>
            <p> 1st When ever either man or woman has a transmissable disease. Insanity,
                feeblemindedness, epilepsy etc.</p>
            <p>2nd. When the woman has any disease in which pregnancy complicates the cure such as
                tuberculosis, heart or kidney diseases.</p>
            <p> 3rd- When parents tho aparently normal have already produced subnormal or defective
                children, deaf mutes, cleft palates, mental <unclear>defectives</unclear>.</p>
            <p> 4 To allow two or three years between births in order to space the children to give
                the mother a chance to recuperate &amp; prepare for the next child.</p>
            <p>5<emph rend="underline">th</emph>. Birth control should be practiced until often the
                adolescent period is passed– even tho’ early marriage is advised or councelled.</p>
            <p> 6<emph rend="underline">th</emph> BC should be practiced for economic reasons– parents
                should not have more children than they can decently provide for.</p>
            <p>7<emph rend="underline">th</emph>. BC should be practiced for two or three years after
                marriage in order to make a better adjustment &amp; to strengthen &amp; cement the
                marriage bond, through understanding &amp; knowledge of each other &amp; through the
                development of mutual <del>interests</del> play &amp; cultural interests.</p>
            <p> There are Three ways to control the birth rate or the size of the family.</p>
            <p> 1 Continence</p>
            <p> 2 Sterilization</p>
            <p>3 Chemical or mechanical means of preventing conception.</p>
            <p>None of these should be advised by laymen– not even the clergy.– all methods to be
                safe, reliable &amp; harmless must be individually considered by qualified persons
                with knowledge of psychology anatomy &amp; physiology.</p>
            <p>The Medical Profession</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <p> Conn. State law Sec 6246 makes it a crime for any one to <emph rend="underline"
                    >use</emph> any <del>drug</del>
                <add>chemical or mechanical</add> for the purpose of preventing conception.</p>
            <p><rs reg="U.S. Criminal Code, Section 211">Fed law Sec 211</rs>. Prevents Physicians
                or anyone from using the US mails or Common carriers <del>to</del> in purchasing
                books, literature, supplies Conn State law is unique in <del>its</del> that it
                stands alone in the 48 States as an example of <hi rend="underline">bad</hi> law
                which can not be enforced– &amp; insults the intelligence of its citizens by
                classing this law as “<q who="CSL">offences against Humanity and Morality.</q>”</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <p><supplied resp="MSPP">Additional quotes taken from "<title type="article">Mrs. Sanger
                        Says State's Law 'Stupid</title>'</supplied>:</p>
            <p>"It is high time to take the question of birth control out of the gutter where <org
                    reg="United States Congress">Congress</org> placed it 60 years ago, and to put
                it on a scientific plane where it belongs..."</p>
            <p><q who="HC">Defining birth control, a term she declared to have been her privilege to
                    coin, as "the conscious control of the birth rate by means that prevent the
                    conception of human life," Mrs. Sanger vehemently denied that advicates of the
                    movement desire to interfere with life, or to destroy it.</q> "Where there is no
                life there can be no destruction or interference...Those who claim that birth
                control interferes with potential life forget that all who remain single are, in a
                sense, interferring with potential life... "</p>
            <p><q who="HC">Mrs. Sanger expressed amazement over the fact that
                        <place>Connecticut</place>, </q>"with more colleges and universities than
                any other state," <q who="HC">and therefore the most intelligent, should have
                    the</q> "stupidist" <q who="HC">laws concerning the dissemination of birth
                    control information.</q> "How can a law that says it is a crime for anyone to
                use contraceptive devices be enforced? <q who="HC">she asked. Mrs. Sanger said that
                    while <place>New York State</place> Law is almost as</q> "stupid," <q who="HC"
                    >many states do allow the propoer spread of birth control information and she
                    desplored the law making it illegal to use the mails to notify people as to
                    where they may secure the necessary information. She cited cases to show that
                        <rs reg="New York State Criminal Code, Section 1142">New York's law</rs>,
                    which allows information to be given to women to who childbirth would mean
                    death, operates unjustly in many instandes when no definite proof can be given
                    of actual danger. She listed seven reasons for birth control, which included the
                    elimination of insanity, the proper spacing of children, the protection of
                    health in adolescent marriages, the protection of women when they have such
                    ailments as consumption, the development of companionship in marriage and
                    economic factors.</q></p>
            <p>"No person,"<q who="HC"> Mrs. Sanger declared, </q>"has a right to bring children
                into the world when he cannot provide for them." <q who="HC">She concluded with a
                    brief discussion of the three ways of limiting the size of families, continence,
                    sterilization, and contraception.</q></p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
