<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed draft speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2007-10-01 EK</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2008/01/07 CH correct type</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2011/03/11 CH Entered corrections suggested by Andy Carloff.</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2012/03/03 CH clean up</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-04-02 CH clean regs</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-22 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1927-00-00 ">
			<supplied resp="MSPP">1927</supplied>
		</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Changing Status of the American Family Speech
					Fragment</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp 236506</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl> Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smth Collection. </bibl>
			<bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Smith College Collections </title>
				S71:137</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<index level1="women" level2="freedom and rights of"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<p>There are many causes attributed to the changing status of the American family.</p>
		<p> The 19th century saw the beginning of a vast change in conditions of <add>family</add>
			life. There are four causes which stand out preeminently as basic factors in this vital
			change.</p>
		<p>1st The Industrial Revolution which destroyed the old fashioned rough but simple life of
			rural industry under the domestic roof. </p>
		<p> 2nd Womens entry into commercial &amp; Industrial life caused a tremendous upheaval in
			the <add>our</add> social structure. The effects of which we are still feeling
			today.</p>
		<p>3rd This naturally led to Womans independence &amp; higher Education life with its many
			&amp; various ramifacations.</p>
		<p>3 Womans higher education &amp; independence.</p>
		<p>4 lastly but not less important is the <del>growing</del><add>increasing</add> knowledge
			of birth control around which so much controversy is waged.</p>
		<p>There is perhaps no subject which has so large a practical significance, which at the
			same time cuts so deeply into the foundations of Social evolution as bc.</p>
		<p>No other subject left so long in social obscurity &amp; now which can show so unequaled a
			leap upon our nat. and Intl horizon as this subject has done during the past ten
			years.</p>
		<p>4. Lastly but of no less significance is the increasing knowledge of birth control around
			which so much controversy is waged the future, progress development of the family
				<unclear resp="MSPP"><del>savings</del></unclear> evolve.</p>
		<p>THere is perhaps no subject which has so <gap extent="rest of document" reason="missing"
			/></p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
