<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed document">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2012-04-23 AW Initial Tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-08 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="0000-00-00">N.d.</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Birth and Death Rates</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236501</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S73:0015</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="xxxx"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <p><q who="DRYCH">The best approximate guide to the progress of the general health of a
                community or country is the variation of the death rate. In the annual report of the
                    <org reg="United Kingdom General Register Office">Registrar-General</org> of
                births, deaths and marriages of <place>England</place> and <place>Wales</place>,
                tables are given which show the birth and death rate and the infant mortality rates
                in no less than twenty-nine countries over the world.</q> The statistics used in
            these tables include twentieth century statistics, through the year 1911.</p>
        <p><q who="DRYCH">If artificial limitation of births were productive of either direct
                physical or even moral injury to the community</q>, the result would be recorded
            certainly by a rise of the death rate. <q who="DRYCH">It will be noticed, however, that
                although the announcement has been made with monotonous regularity for years that
                each successive birth rate was the lowest on record, it has been followed no less
                monotonously by the statement that the death rate was also the lowest recorded</q>.
            It should perhaps be stated that facts concerning the birth and death rates are more
            accurately known than any other social phenomena. The figures which follow are
            government statistics and it is necessary to make allowances for only trifling
            inaccuracies. </p>
        <p>Let us first take the case of England. In the year 1861 the birth rate was 34 ½ per
            1,000, the death rate 21 1/2, which gives an increase in population of about 13 per
            1,000. The birth rate in England rose steadily from the year 1853 up to the year 1876
            when it was more than 36 per 1,000. In 1876, however, the famous trial of <person
                reg="Bradlaugh, Charles">Charles Bradlaugh</person> and <person reg="Besant, Annie"
                >Annie Besant</person> took place. This trial attracted enormous attention to the
            question and means of family limitation and undoubtedly had a very great affect on the
            birth rate which began at that time a rapid and steady decline. In 1910 the birth rate
            had fallen to 25 per 1,000 but the death rate in the same period fell to less than 14
            per 1,000 so that the population of the country is now increasing almost as fast as it
            did before the fall of the birth rate set in. Something like 400,000 fewer births now
            take place every year in England and something like 400,000 fewer deaths.</p>
        <p>In the case of the <place>Germany</place> Empire we have no statisticians over as long a
            period, but before the year 1876 the birth rate was rising very rapidly and since that
            year it has declined nearly as rapidly as that of England. At its highest the birth rate
            of Germany was nearly 41 per 1,000 in 1876, but with the birth rate of 41 per 1,000 went
            a death rate of nearly 26 so that the increase per 1,000 was only 13. In 1910 the birth
            rate had fallen to about 31 per 1,000 but the death rate had fallen to 17 which gives a
            slightly higher rate of increase, and while the German birth rate is higher than that of
            England, its death rate, it will be noted, is higher and its infant mortality rate is
            very much higher.</p>
        <p><place>France</place> is one of the most interesting countries in this connection because
            France is continually held up to us as a dying nation owing to the fact that it has the
            lowest birth rate known and that it occasionally has had fewer births than deaths in a
            year. In 1881-84 the birth rate of France was 38.9 per 1,000, nearly as high as the
            highest recorded in Germany. By 1910-06 the birth rate had fallen to 21.1, but observe
            what happened to the death rate; in the period when the birth rate was the highest the
            death rate was no less than 37 per 1,000 and it has since fallen to 19.6. In other
            words, with the highest birth rate, the rate of increase was only 1.9 per 1,000. With
            the lowest birth rate the rate of increase was 1.5, a difference so slight that it is
            almost negligible. There is no doubt that the health of the French people has enormously
            improved during the whole period of the falling birth rate.</p>
        <p><place reg="Netherlands">Holland</place> is another example of a European country with a
            falling birth rate. The essential point about Holland is that it is the only country in
            which artificial restriction has been extended to the poor to any great degree. In
            Holland, the birth rate rose as usual up to the year 1876 when it was about 37 per
            1,000. By the year 1910 it had fallen to about 29. The death rate in Holland in 1876 was
            about 26 per 1,000 which would give a rate of increase of about 11. In 1910 the death
            rate had fallen to 34 which gives an increase of about 15 per 1,000, as against 11 in
            1876. The infant mortality rate in Holland is lower than that of any other European
            country and it was stated at a recent <name reg="International Eugenics Congress"
                >Eugenics Congress</name> that the stature of the Dutch people had increased by no
            less than four inches within the last fifty years. </p>
        <p>A general summing up of the twenty-nine countries given in the report of the
            Registrar-General shows:</p>
        <p> 1. There are eighteen countries in which the birth rate has fallen. In fifteen of these
            the death rate has fallen by an amount nearly corresponding to the fall in the birth
            rate; in two--<place>New Zealand</place> and <place>Australia</place>--the death rate
            has only fallen slightly, but their death rate is already the lowest in the world.</p>
        <p> 2. There are four countries in which the birth rate has remained approximately
            stationary (<place>Russia</place>, <place reg="Romania">Roumania</place>,
                <place>Jamaica</place> and <place>Ireland</place>). In these four countries the
            death rates and infant mortality have remained practically stationary (except that there
            may be a small fall of the death rate in Russia). Russia with the highest birth rate in
            Europe (nearly 50 per 1,000) has the highest death rate, about 36 per 1,000, and the
            highest infant mortality, 26 per cent, that is, 260 babies out of every 1,000 die before
            the age of one year. The infant mortality rate of Holland is only about 70 per 1,000.
            That of the United States is about 140. In the other three countries the general and
            infant mortalities are lower, the lower their birth rates.</p>
        <p> 3. There are four countries only in which the birth rate has risen
                (<place>Bulgaria</place>, <place>Ceylon</place>, <place>Japan</place> and <place
                reg="Ontario, Canada">Ontario</place> (<place>Canada</place>). In every one of the
            four the death rate and infant mortality have risen, and in close correspondence with
            the rise of the birth rate. Is it not most remarkable that even in Canada, (a new and
            promising country) a rise in the birth rate has not increased numbers--except in the
            grave-yards?</p>
        <p> 4. When we compare different countries or towns, or different parts of the same country
            or town, we find as a whole that high birth rates are accompanied by high rates of
            general and infant mortality, which low birth rates are accompanied by lower mortality
            rates. </p>
        <p>5. The two extreme variations of the birth rate which have been shown among the great
            towns, are in the case of <place reg="Berlin, Germany">Berlin</place>, where it has
            risen from 32 to 45 per 1,000 between 1841 and 1876, and has since fallen to 21 per
            1,000. The death rate and infant mortality have risen with the rising birth rate and
            have fallen with its fall in almost exact correspondence, except for occasional
            irregularities due to war and epidemics.</p>
        <p><place reg="Toronto, Canada">Toronto</place>, on the other hand, is the only example of a
            town in which the counsels of the moralists appear to have been taken seriously to
            heart, and which has returned to a high birth rate after joining in the general fall.
            The death rate fell step by step as the birth rate declined--and to practically the same
            extent, but rose again immediately the birth rate began to go up, and in 1909 was higher
            than in 1880-85.</p>
        <p>What do we learn from these incontrovertible facts? Not only that medical science has
            succeeded in bringing down the death rate when family restriction has been practised,
            but that it has utterly failed to do so when the birth rate has been maintained. Worse
            still, in every case where the command to increase and multiply has been obeyed by more
            rapid reproduction, the whole power of medical science has failed to prevent the death
            rate from rising. And in Toronto, where for some reason the people have stopped in their
            downward path and have restored their birth rate to its former high value, they have
            been rewarded not by greater health, but by a steady increase of the death rate. In face
            of this it is difficult to find words adequate to deal with the attempt of the medical
            profession to stem the tide of the declining birth rate. If the aim of the medical
            profession is to allay suffering and to prolong life, the facts show that the whole
            profession is practically incompetent to effect this for the community as a whole,
            unless helped by family restriction.</p>
        <p>There are these who will attempt to escape from this conclusion by appealing to
            “corrected” statistics, so it may be well to repeat that although the question is
            rendered more complicated by such modifications, the general conclusion is unaffected,
            or indeed strengthened, that family limitation is a decided advantage for the health of
            the community. France, for example, which is always held up as such a dreadful object
            lesson, comes out much better when its corrected death rate is given.</p>
        <p><person reg="Ellis, Havelock">Havelock Ellis</person> adds that every country without
            exception which has a progressive or educated population and a fairly high state of
            social well-being present a birth rate below 30 per 1,000, and that every country in
            Europe in which the mass of the people are primitive, ignorant or in a socially
            unsatisfactory condition, shows a birth rate above 30 per 1,000. France, <place>Great
                Britain</place>, Germany, <place>Belgium</place>, Holland, the <place
                reg="Scandinavia">Scandinavian countries</place> and <place>Switzerland</place> are
            in the first group. Further, that the eight countries with the highest birth rate have
            the highest death rate and that the eight countries with the lowest birth rate have the
            lowest death rate.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
