<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Autograph draft speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2003/10/10 NS</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-04-10 ch Clean regs</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-20 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1925-01-26">26 Jan 1925</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Des Moines Address Notes</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp236564</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
			<bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Smith College Collections</title> S70:952</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name/>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>Sanger gave two speeches in <place reg="Des Moines, IA">Des Moines</place>, these notes
			were likely for the <org>Des Moines Birth Control Committee</org>. For coverage of her
			speech to the <org reg="Des Moines Federation of Women's Clubs">City Federation of
				Women's Clubs</org>, see <xref from="431935.xml">Regulation of Fit Children of the
				World</xref>, Jan. 27, 1925. No final version of this speech was found.</p>
		<index level1="birth rate" level2="efforts to reduce"/>
		<index level1="child labor"/>
		<index level1="child welfare"/>
		<index level1="mortality rates" level2="infant"/>
		<index level1="working classes"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<dateline><date value="1925-01-26">Jan. 21-25</date> Des moines</dateline>
		<p>Mans progress seems to have begun backward-- We have paid special attention to his
			environment, while little attention has been given to his heritable traits.</p>
		<p>In the early part of the 18th Century we began to take cognizance of mans environmental
			needs. We began to pave the streets, install sewerage systems, collect the garbage &amp;
			refuse, wipe out epidemics by the organization of public health boards. By the end of
			the 18 Century we invaded the home &amp; workshop. So enthusiastic had we become in
			cleaning up the environment of the individual--we purified the drinking water,
			superintended the wholesomeness of the milk supply we legislated the conditions of his
			working hours, cleaned up the factories &amp; mills, gave him protection against
			machinery &amp; the hazardness of his employment, shortened his labor hours, increased
			his pay &amp; provided for his general environmental improvement &amp; longevity. During
			all this period little attention was paid to the condition of the child--</p>
		<p>Birth rate was higher--the death rate of children was high. Child labor took its toll of
			child life &amp; damaged &amp; blighted those little ones who were to carry on the torch
			of civilization.</p>
		<p>Early in the 19th Century, the child began to come into its own.</p>
		<gap reason="missing" extent="two pages"/>
		<p>If you could look into some of the faces of the parents of children who are forced to
			toil &amp; labor--you would see that laws were not enough. That you would see that these
			parents had not sufficient earning power to provide for their own existence-- How could
			they provide for eight ten or twelve?</p>
		<p>Such children are forced to work as soon as they can toddle or to die-- Children of such
			parents should not be born. Child labor laws are not enough-- Societies for the
			Prevention of Cruelty to Children are not enough. </p>
		<p>We want to prevent the cruelty of children being born in cruelty.</p>
		<p>Could any thing be more cruel than to be born of disease, ignorance misery. If we are to
			make this world safe for childhood, safe for future generation, safe for Civilization we
			have got to check the endless stream of unwanted death doomed babies. This stream can
			not be swept back with the broom of pallative legislation--nor with the feather duster
			of Organized Charity. It must be checked at the Source by Birth Control.</p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
