<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/06/13 CE</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-21 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1937-08-04">04 Aug 1937</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Birth Control in Hawaii</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236540</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title>, S71:0950</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="AMA">American Medical Association</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues" level3="in US"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="economic benefits and risks of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits and risks"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="legal cases"
            level3="U.S. V. One Package of Japanese contraceptives'"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="legalization of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="medical community and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="American"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="socioeconomic benefits of"/>
        <index level1="China" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Hawaii" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="physicians" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="settlement movement" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="government" level3="public health programs"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <dateline>Aug 6/37</dateline>
        <p>With keen reluctance, I am leaving your hospitable Islands where I have received so
            cordial a welcome. But my promise to several of the <org>Chinese Medical
                Associations</org> to return to complete the work begun there in 1928 and left
            unfinished last year compels me to hasten to <place>China</place>.</p>
        <p>I cannot leave, however, without a word of comment on the really outstanding work which
            Hawaii is doing in giving scientific medical advice and treatment on these vital human
            problems of child-spacing, family limitation, and sickness and death prevention among
            mothers.</p>
        <p>Quietly and unassumingly, with due consideration of the scruples of some, this work has
            progressed with general community approval, under the able leadership of <org>Palama
                Settlement</org>. Financed by private funds in 1931 and with the full backing of the
            Settlement’s strong Board of Trustees, the work of its birth control clinic has been
            wisely and ably directed by <person reg="Lam, Joseph Wincy">Dr. J. W. Lam</person> and
                <person reg="Cass, Muriel">Dr. Muriel Cass</person> for the past six years. Much of
            its emphasis has been directed to the demonstration of contraceptive methods and
            techniques to physicians and it has served as a center of information so that today a
            large number of local as well as plantation physicians throughout the <place
                reg="Territory of Hawaii">Territory</place> are well qualified to give the advice
            and treatment so earnestly sought after by the majority of conscientious mothers.
                <person reg="Larsen, Nils Paul, Dr.">Dr. N. P. Larsen</person>, as medical
            consultant to the <org>Hawaiian Sugar Planters’ Association</org>, has done much to
            stimulate the interest of plantation physicians, so that now Hawaii as a whole is
            probably better prepared to receive modern scientific service in this field than <gap
                reason="missing" extent="unknown"/></p>
        <p>From intimate knowledge of hundreds of birth control clinics in our country as well as in
            the countries of <place>Europe</place> and <place>Asia</place>, I consider that <place
                reg="Honolulu, Hawaiian Territory">Honolulu</place> and Hawaii has been especially
            fortunate in having the leadership of the birth control movement under so strong and
            representative an organization as Palama Settlement and more particularly in having the
            birth control clinic, under a representative medical committee, a part of a medical
            out-patient department of a public health and social welfare institution, with its
            general medical, gynecological, prenatal, child welfare and venereal disease
            clinics.</p>
        <p>The <org reg="United Kingdom, Ministry of Health">Ministry of Health of <place>Great
                    Britain</place></org> in 1930 required that every one of its hundreds of
            maternal and child health clinics be prepared to give contraceptive advice to the
            mothers needing such advice. Now that the <org>American Medical Association</org> has
            officially recognized the birth control movement and specifically has committed itself
            not only "<q who="AMA">to investigate the various for contraception with a view to
                disseminating authoritative information on the subject to the medical profession,
                but also that the Association promote the teaching of proper methods of birth
                control in the medical schools</q>", The day is not far distant, <del>that</del>
            <add>when</add> contraceptive advice will be available from physicians in America’s
            maternal and child welfare clinics, out-patient departments and hospitals, as it has
            long been in the physicians’s private office.</p>
        <p>The decision of the <org>United States Circuit Court of Appeals</org> legalizing the
            physician’s use of contraceptives for general health as well as for disease prevention
            reasons and the acceptance of this decision by the <person reg="Cummings, Homer Stille"
                >Attorney-General</person> of the United States has removed all question of the
            illegality of the use of such methods by physicians of the importation of contraceptive
            articles by physicians or the use of the mails. And this applies to Hawaii as well as to
            the mainland.</p>
        <p>As the public comes to recognize the incalculable benefits that follow the wise and
            conservative use of these medical techniques as prescribed by competent physicians, for
            the preventing of disease, for reducing the number of dangerous abortions, for
            preserving the health of the mother, for increasing the happiness of the home and family
            relations, for bestowing the gift of voluntary parenthood and for improving the quality
            of future generations, the people of Hawaii will be increasingly grateful for the
            tremendous contribution the medical profession, both privately and through Palama
            Settlement, is bestowing upon these blessed Islands.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
