<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/05/02 YG</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1939-08-15">15 Aug 1939</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>This is Why I Fight for Birth Control</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236611</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Look Magazine</title></bibl>
            <bibl><title>MSM</title>LCM 572:97</bibl>
            <bibl><title>MSM</title>LCM L130:624</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="LM">Look Magazine</name>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">According to the editor's note - Sanger has written the text to the
        photos, which were taken from "Why Let Them Die" <index level1="birth control"
            level2="morality of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"
            level3="negative consequences of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>This is Why I Fight for Birth Control</head>
        <p><q who="LM">Editor’s Note: These pictures are from “Why Let Them Die,” a documentary film
                treating the moral, social and economic aspects of birth control. It is being
                released for private showings by <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret
                    Sanger</person> and her colleagues of the <org>Birth Control Federation of
                    America</org>. The captions have been written for Look by Mrs. Sanger.</q></p>
        <p>1. <person>Martha Hayes</person>was 18 when she and <person reg="Hayes, Tom"
            >Tom</person>were married. For Martha, marriage was a blessed means of escape; escape
            from a home so crowded with children that there was scarcely room to lie down at night,
            escape from an embittered father and from the everlasting drudgery that had made her
            mother’s life a curse. </p>
        <p>2. But here is the record of Martha’s married life. Eleven children in 14 years. One of
            them a stillbirth, one a miscarriage. Finally, pregnant and deserted, she took the
            desperate step which cost her life. The story of suffering and privation which lies
            behind Martha’s case history card (above) is not an unusual one. her tragedy is all the
            worse because birth control could have prevented it. </p>
        <p>3. At first life went smoothly. But when babies started coming with scarcely seven months
            between birth and pregnancy, Martha and Tom found themselves hating the home and family
            they had created. Tom became a hard-driven, hopeless father. </p>
        <p>4. And Martha was a housebound, work-worn mother, entangled in the web which she had
            married to escape. Four of her babies died in infancy. There was never enough food for
            those that lived. Tom’s earnings, year after year, averaged about $400. </p>
        <p>5. Tom grew to dread coming home to his squalid two-room shack, to the wistful hungry
            faces of his children. One day syphilis appeared in Martha’s case history card, and
            finally, in drunken hopelessness, Tom Hayes abandoned his family. </p>
        <p> 6. Tom and Martha had not wanted so many children. They had known that they could not
            feed nor clothe them, that their babies would grow up-if they grew up at all- weak in
            mind and body. But Martha and Tom were ignorant of birth control methods, as Martha’s
            mother had been. Not long after Tom deserted her, Martha discovered that another baby
            was on its way. </p>
        <p>7. Martha Hayes’ last desperate step was one taken by millions of American women every
            year. From a neighbor trying to be helpful, she learned the name of a so-called “doctor”
            who could “help her.” She took what money she had-the fee is usually whatever the
            patient can scrape together- and paid it in advance. She didn’t even know the “doctor’s”
            name. They took her behind a hanging sheet. </p>
        <p>8. Martha Hayes never recovered from the illegal operation. She died at the hands of the
            abortionist- as some 8,000 American women die each year-simply because she was ignorant
            of how to plan her family. I have known thousands of women like Martha, known their
            needless suffering and the heartaches of their husbands. That is why I fight for birth
            control. </p>
        <p>I Fight for Birth Control not only for the sake of Tom and Martha, but for the sake of
            the community. I would prevent subnormal parents from having children like these, and
            other parents from having children whose birth may cost a mother’s life. Proportionately
            more mothers die in America in childbirth than in 15 other countries.</p>
        <p>Birth Control Makes for Happy Children and happy families by preventing the conception of
            unwanted babies. It also saves infant lives. When babies are born one year apart, 147 out
            of every 1,000 infants die. When births are two years apart, 100 out of every thousand
            die. When there is three years between births, only 87 die. </p>
        <p>Since the Beginning of civilization, man has tried to devise ways to keep teeming
            population within bounds. Where man has failed, nature has stepped in with controls as
            pitiless as they are inflexible. War, pestilence, famine, these are nature’s way. Even
            today in the Far East these forces are inexorably at work. </p>
        <p>These Two Pictures Illustrate the Difference between planned and unplanned parenthood.
            Below is a happy, well planned family, with the children properly spaced. Above is a
            family which knows nothing about birth control and will continue to know nothing about
            it until it is incorporated in our public health services and made available to the
            lowest income groups. How urgently this is needed today is shown by the fact that
            families on relief are now producing 60 per cent of our next generation. For every two
            babies born to parents not on relief, relief families are having three. </p>
        <p/>
    </docBody>
</doc>
