<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011-07-29 NC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-01 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1951-09-18">18 Sept 1951</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Historical Interview with Cardinal
                Tisserant</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236643</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S77:0066</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>For a draft version see <title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title>
            S77:0055. No published version was found.</p>
        <index level1="Catholic Church" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="Catholic Church" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="Tisserant, Eugene"/>
        <index level1="Italy" level2="population policies of"/>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="overpopulation and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="opposition to"/>
        <index level1="Blanchard, Paul"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="safe period"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>HISTORICAL INTERVIEW</head>
        <dateline><date value="1951-09-18">Sept. 18, 1951</date></dateline>
        <p>At 3:30 today, Sept. 18th. I arrived promptly at the address--<org>St. Phillip’s
                Church</org>----to meet again the now Cardinal <person reg="Tisserant, Eugene"
                >Tisserant</person>. <person reg="Macdonald, Angus">Angus Macdonald</person> has
            been anxious for several years to have us meet to discuss the possibility of getting the
                <org>Vatican</org> to a better understand of the harm done to the world by the Roman
            Catholic opposition to Birth Control. I had met Mnsr. Tisserant some years ago before he
            was a Cardinal----As he is French--a rather handsome head and face with hair and beard
            turning grey. His red cap and belt, rather impressive with the surroundings of priests
            in black robes, ushering, quietly and softly, into the presence of the Cardinal.</p>
        <p>We talked of Angus and his business problems. Then I launched into the population of
                <place>Italy</place>. He talked on and on for at least the first thirty or forty
            minutes with scarcely a stop for a question. I let him talk as no one could stop him.
            Italy was not overpopulated except in spots--plenty of land if people would only move
            out in it. <place>India</place> not overpopulated if they would not allow the cows, the
            scared cow to eat their produce. Lots of space in India for the population--get rid of
            the cows. <place reg="United States">America</place> thru the Colorado River project
            will soon be able to send water to all the land and supply food for another 75,000,000
            people (million if you please). He rambled over the world.
                <place>Spain</place>--<place>South America</place>, <place>Africa</place>, then
                <place>Japan</place>. I looked surprised at all this and repeated-Japan? Yes, he
            said, that’s the only country thats overpopulated. <person reg="Blanchard, Paul">Paul
                Blanchard</person>’s book is all wrong, he said. Catholics do not insist that people
            have large families, but pleasure without pain can not be countenanced by the
            church----! ! No chance to check on that one. He skipped over that fact. I do not
            believe he believes that tale either.</p>
        <p>When I got a chance to inject an idea, I remarked that it only needed one pleasure in a
            whole year to give a couple a baby every year. Oh no, said he, some women have a
            difficult time to get pregnant! ! We were going on a merry--go--round. His replies were
            so stereotyped and false--it became laughable to take him sincerely. Then he was
            concerned that the negro population of U.S.A. was increasing faster than the white race.
            My fault for Birth Control work among the intelligent, while the less intelligent were
            increasing. I said, “No,” not my fault. Your church is the cause of a birth rate. By
            denying the right of people to get Birth Control. <place reg="South Carolina"><place
                    reg="North Carolina">Carolina</place></place> has no Catholics,
                <place>Connecticut</place> has few Catholics. But I retorted, it’s the political
            Catholics everywhere who block our progress--long time in that safe period--injuries to
            women--Catholic women at Clinic are not Catholic. Mexicans had Catholic.</p>
        <p>I hope to jot down as memory comes back the various things talked about. We left each
            other in a friendly spirit. Russian new experiment--breeding mules with pigmies,
            questionable if I got that correct. His English began to wane. An hour had passed--I
            hope I got under his skin on the safe period. When I said a cow, a mare would kick male
            to hell if he came near her when she was not ready. The safe period is for the man--not
            for the women. He was interested in this: rather</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
