<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/06/02 CE</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-24 ch clean regs</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-24 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1936-12-00">Dec 1936</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>The Soviet Union's Abortion Law</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236705</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">The Woman Today</title> (Dec. 1936), pp. 8, 30</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S71:0874</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="KRUNA">Krupskaya, Nadezhda Konstantinova</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>For additional copies, seee Library of Congress Microfilm 143:0707A and C16:0396</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="legalization of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="Soviet Union"/>
        <index level1="Europe" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Soviet Union" level2="laws"/>
        <index level1="Soviet Union" level2="women" level3="freedom and rights of"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="treatment of" level3="in Soviet Union"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>The Soviet Abortion Law</head>
        <byline>by <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></byline>
        <div type="section">
            <p><place reg="Soviet Union">Russia</place> was probably the
                first country in the world to give official sanction to abortion. By so doing it
                courageously faced a world wide evil, and took the first ethical and scientific
                step, so it appeared, in solving it. For the greatest danger in abortion, when it is
                forbidden, is that women must place their lives in the hands of quacks and submit to
                unhygienic conditions at a time when all the safeguards of science should be at
                their disposal.</p>
            <p>However, even when Russia enacted the law permitting abortions, providing that they
                must be performed under scientific and hygienic conditions by physicians in
                hospitals, it was recognized that this method of family limitation was a tragedy at
                best. <person reg="Krupskaya, Nadezhda Konstantinova">Krupskaya</person>, <person
                    reg="Lenin, Vladimir Illyich">Lenin</person>’s widow, writing in 1920, pointed
                out that it is only bitter necessity that compels a woman to give up motherhood. “<q
                    who="KRUNA">We need only see the agitated and sad looks of the women who have
                    had abortions</q>,” she said, “<q who="KRUNA">to understand the price which a
                    mother pays to obtain freedom in this way. Those who seriously want to remove
                    these nightmare questions of child murder and abortion must work constantly to
                    build up the new life where motherhood will occupy its proper place</q>.”</p>
            <p>The Russian law sanctioning abortion had three objectives: to safeguard the lives of
                women by placing this operation in qualified hands, to control population, and to
                free the individual woman for other work. Over and above these objectives it carried
                out, logically and fearlessly, the Soviet idea of granting to every woman the power
                of individual choice as to whether she should or should not have a child.</p>
            <p>But birth control, i.e., the prevention of conception, is unquestionably preferable
                to abortion, the destruction of the foetus after conception has taken place. It is
                preferable for both physical and psychological reasons. No woman who has submitted
                to an abortion, even when performed under the most ideal conditions, can fail to be
                aware of her weakened physical condition, of a sense of guilt or profound and bitter
                depression. She has halted the forces of nature in mid-channel, and nature is
                exacting her price.</p>
            <p>Thus it seems strange that Russia sanctioned and provided for abortion first, and
                birth control second, as a sort of after-thought. Birth control was initiated,
                according to statements by Dr. <person reg="Lebjedewa, W.">W. Lebjedewa</person> of
                the <org reg="Soviet Union Research Institute">Research Institute</org> and other
                authorities, as a means of combating the spread of abortion, not as another and
                better method of controlling population.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <p>The new law on <name type="law">Abortions and Aid to Mothers</name> is at once a
                reversal of the earlier libertarian philosophy and a seeming contradiction within
                itself. Coupled with clear cut and adequate provisions for state aid to mothers and
                children, in the form of maternity allowanced, confinement care, nurseries,
                kindergartens and so on, is a section forbidding abortions except for therapeutic
                reasons, that is, when the continuation of pregnancy endangers the life or threatens
                serious injury to the health of the pregnant woman.</p>
            <p>The government provides for the woman’s care in her career of motherhood to a degree
                which puts other countries to shame. It provides her with all she needs save the
                most important thing--knowledge of how to plan and space her children, and the
                right, if she wishes to exercise it, of <emph>not</emph> bringing a child into the
                world.</p>
            <p>Why this reversal in attitude, this contradiction? According to the Russian records,
                there has been very small loss of life from abortions under the former more liberal
                policy. Hence the change cannot have been made to check maternal deaths or as a
                health measure in any form.</p>
            <p>During my trip to Russia two years ago, I found that very little actual clinical
                birth control work was being done, though posters and printed literature proclaimed
                its value. Supplies were inferior and almost non-existent, and methods at present
                recognized as the most reliable could not be used for lack of manufacture of
                importation of materials. American physicians visiting Russia since that time bring
                back reports indicating that these conditions have not changed much for the
                better.</p>
            <p>The Soviet government has understood the problem. Why did not Russia develop its
                birth control program, and make this method of control as effective and well
                organized as the opportunities for procuring abortions?</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <p>I seek for an explanation of the forces behind the new law. At the beginning of the
                Soviet regime, women were taken out of their homes and put into industry, because
                all available adult labor was needed to build up the country. Women were needed as
                workers more than as mothers. Hence every available help was given them to avoid and
                postpone motherhood when they wished to do so. Today, after almost two-score years,
                the Russian regime rests on firm foundations, and the first major objectives have
                been achieved. The Soviet government no longer acutely needs women as laborers. It
                passes now into a second phase where women are needed as mothers. Their usefulness
                to the state is greater in the field of reproduction than in the field of industry.
                Hence the new law which provides every incentive for the career of motherhood, in
                the shape of adequate care for mother and child, and at the same time clinches the
                matter by making it difficult to avoid childbearing.</p>
            <p>If this be the explanation of the new law, it is understandable but nevertheless a
                step backward. Russia is the one country, to my knowledge, which cannot be accused
                of injustice and arrogance in asking women to bear children, for it gives them
                assurance of protection and adequate care, medical, economic and social. Viewed in
                this way, the juxtaposition of provisions depriving women of the right to abortion
                and provisions for maternity and child care are logical and tenable.</p>
            <p>The law is reactionary, none the less. As a feminist, I protest against any woman
                having children if and when she does not want them. As a woman I believe that women
                do by nature want children, given the assurance that they will have a proper chance
                in life.</p>
            <p>Interesting experimentation has been done in Russia in developing new methods of
                contraception. There is here an opportunity to supply a world need in discovering a
                contraceptive which can be used by the masses; that is, one which is simple,
                inexpensive, and which does not need the detailed personal instruction which present
                methods demand.</p>
            <p>Let Russia further develop its estimable program of maternal and child care. Let it
                hold courageously to its former policy of abortions properly performed if need
                arises, and let it lessen that need by providing and developing adequate birth
                control service. With such a well-rounded course of action, Russian women may well
                become the envy of women in less “enlightened” countries.</p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
