<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/06/11 MM</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/11/21 EK clean regs and correct proof</prepDate>
        <docAuthor><person>Margaret Sanger</person></docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1914-00-00">1914</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Forward, <title>The Supressed Obscene Articles</title>, pp. 2-3</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236723</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title>, S76:869</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>This is the foreward to a booklet <title type="journal" rend="ital">The
                Suppressed Obscene Articles</title> that included reports of: <title type="article"
                >The Prevention of Conception</title>, March 1914, "<title type="article">Open
                Discussion</title>" by <person reg="Cole, Ethel">Ethel Cole</person>, May 1914,
                <title type="article">Abortion in the United States</title> May 1914, <title
                type="article">Can You Afford a Large Family</title>, <title type="article">The
                Birth Control League</title>, July 1914, <title type="article">The Marriage
                Bed</title>, by <person reg="Groff, Alice">Alice Groff</person>, July 1914, <title
                type="article">Are Preventive Means Injurious</title>, July 1914, and <title
                type="article"> A Defense of Assassination</title>, by <person reg="Thorpe, Herbert"
                >Herbert Thorpe</person>, July 1914.</p>
        <index level1="Woman Rebel, The" level2="suppression of"/>
        <index level1="Woman Rebel, The" level2="legal case"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="Post Office"/>
        <index level1="censorship"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="arrests and trials"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>THE SUPPRESSION OF "<title type="journal">THE WOMAN REBEL</title>"</head>
        <p>The articles in this booklet (including the paragraph on the next page) were the ones
            which caused the suppression and confiscation of seven out of nine issues of <title
                type="journal">The Woman Rebel</title>. The Post Office Department declared them to
            be unmailable, and thereby unmasked itself as an enemy of the free discussion of birth
            control. </p>
        <p>The power of Post Office censorship, with the subtle despotism involved, is the greatest
            menace to liberty in the United States. When Congress was authorized to establish a
            public mail carrying service, it was never intended that the latter should pass upon the
            political, religious or moral opinions of the matter to be conveyed. The Post Office
            was supposed to be mechanically efficient, and nothing beyond that. That it should now
            dictate on ethical questions is as absurd as if the railroads and street car companies
            were legally empowered to refuse to accept passengers whose ideas they did not like.</p>
        <p><title type="journal">The Woman Rebel </title> was a voice trying to deliver a message to
            the working women of America. That message--Birth Control--was objected to by
            officialism running riot. Let the issue be clear. It was the idea of birth control, not
            the language used, that the Post Office was determined to suppress. But it branded the
            articles as being "<q>obscene</q>" under the law, and therefore
            unmailable. A Federal Grand Jury took the same view and indicted me for publishing them. </p>
        <p>The case was one that threatened woman's freedom. If the people of the United States had
            been willing to concede the power of censorship demanded by the Post Office and the
            District Attorney's office in connection with <title type="journal">The Woman
                Rebel</title>, it would have meant silencing the most urgent human and economic
            demand of our day. Fortunately, the power was not conceded in this particular instance,
            though it remains, to be invoked legally at any time. Defeated by public opinion, the
            Government dismissed its case against me, but it has never released the seized copies of
            the magazine. I reprint the censored articles, with their message of birth control, and
            challenge any one to find matter in them that could cause the simplest minds to become
            depraved.</p>
        <p>MARGARET SANGER</p>
            </docBody>
</doc>
