<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "file:/S:/TRANSCRIPTIONS/XML%20Drafts/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Autograph draft review">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2010/04/07 AC</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1936-00-00">1936</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Response to 'My Gandhi' by J. H. Holmes</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236724</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</bibl>
            <bibl><title>MSM</title>S71:880</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp>
                <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
            </resp>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">Add text if needed. <index level1="xxxx"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>My Gandhi by <person reg="Holmes, John Haynes">J. H. Holmes</person></head>
        <p>The interesting story of <add>Mr. Holmes</add> meeting Gandhi is not only delightful in
            its details but gives one such a vivid picture of Mr. Holmes--No one could possibly
            believe, that one who has met over the years thousands &amp; thousands of people from
            all <unclear reason="illegible">stations</unclear> &amp; from all nations classes &amp;
            casts confessed to have “missed the excitement of <gap reason="illegible"
                extent="one word"/> great <gap reason="illegible" extent="one word"/> because of my
            reluctance to grasp &amp; seize for my own Satisfaction some portion of their meager
            stores of time &amp; strength.”</p>
        <p> All through the book is this same humility of a great Soul--(as J H H certainly is) not
            only could he not venture or trespass on the time of Gandhi in person but was reluctant
            to take his time in reading his letters. I agree with Mr. Holmes in describing
            Gandhi--not as a King with the material personally &amp; pageantry of a King--“<q
                who="UNK">For it was the Spirit not the flesh which clothed this man in more than
                majesty</q>” How splendid that the author met some of Gandhis dearest friends
                <person reg="Slade, Mirabehu">Mirabehu Slade</person>, <person reg="Nardu, Lawrence Housman Saronjin">Lawrence Housman Saronjin
            Nardu</person>, and others. Nehru Splendid too that <gap reason="illegible" extent="one word"></gap> his advice Gandhi did not come to
            America.</p>
        <p> It was my good fortune to visit Gandhi for three days in 1936 at his ashram at Warda. I
            am forever grateful to Mr. Holmes for sending a letter to the Mahatma before my arrival
            telling him what I was in India to do.</p>
        <p> Even tho Gandhi &amp; I did not see eye to eye on methods to control the birth rate, our
            ideas on nearly every other subject clicked.</p>
        <p> Just after reading My Gandhi--someone kindly sent me <person reg="Sheean, vincent">Vincent Sheean</person>’s book on
            Gandhi.</p>
        <p> There too one finds a modesty &amp; humility in his approach--which it is good to know
            has feet by two outstanding Americans. </p>


    </docBody>
</doc>
