<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011-07-28 NC</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1950-10-25">25 Oct 1950</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Lasker Award Address</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp236716</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Supplement to the <title>Malthusian</title>Jan. 1951</bibl>
            <bibl><title>MSM</title>S72:0607</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="WELHG">Wells, H. G.</name>
            <name id="WEBWA">Webb, Walter Prescott</name>
            <name id="WEIIG">Weis, Ignace Semmel</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Sanger gave this speech at the annual meeting lunch of the Planned
            Parenthood Foundation election of America meeting at the <org>Hotel Roosevelt</org> in
            New York. She was presented with the Albert and Mary Lasker Foundation's Award in
            Planned Parenthood.</p>
        <p>For draft versions see LCM 128:0258, 130:0028, MSM S72:0598, 0601, and
            C19:0424.</p><index level1="birth control" level2="population and"/><index
            level1="population growth" level2="regulation of"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>ADDRESS</head>
        <byline>By MARGARET SANGER</byline>
        <p>Reunited here to-day among so many co-workers, friends old and new, the conviction
            springs full grown into my mind that the most deserving of any award for courage,
            initiative, vision, and keeping alive the torch of our cause, are our friends, <person
                reg="Lasker, Mary">Mary</person> and <person reg="Lasker, Albert">Albert
                Lasker</person>. I cannot begin to tell you how much we and numerous other national
            health associations owe to Mary and Albert Lasker. Such progress as we have made in <org
                reg="Planned Parenthood Federation of America">Planned Parenthood</org> Movement,
            which more than once has been denied and crushed to earth, has been due to those with
            the vision and courage of the Laskers. Thanks to them, this truth has managed to rise
            again and march on. In humbly accepting this award, I do so in the hope and trust that I
            may apply this generous cheque to help women, especially the women of
                <place>Japan</place>, to control and guide their own biological destiny.</p>
        <p>The interest of the Lasker family in birth control goes quite far back. Even before
            Albert had demonstrated his special interest, his two <person reg="Lasker, Florina"
                    ><person reg="Lasker, Loula">sisters</person></person>, having been the
            executors for a bequest from their <person reg="Lasker, Nettie Heidenheimer Davis"
                >mother</person>, came to look into our work. They told me that it was the request
            of their mother that a part of a special fund was to go to a cause that was helping
            women. And so our cause in those early days received a generous contribution which
            helped us to go out into the field and be heard. It seems to me that a new and special
            award of honor from national health and peace organisations could appropriately be given
            to Albert and Mary Lasker.</p>
        <p>It is difficult for me to look into the future without being reminded of my good, dear
            friend, <person reg="Wells, H. G.">H. G. Wells</person>. Doubtless you know how
            completely discouraged and disillusioned he was in his last unhappy years. He said to me
            upon one occasion:</p>
        <p>"<q who="WELHG">Mankind is not the privileged favourite of mother nature and in spite of
                all my lifelong optimism it now seems to me that the Universe is utterly bored by
                the whole species of mankind. I can see the human race sweeping along the stream of
                fate to defeat, degradation and final extinction. Mankind is likely to breed itself
                clean out of existence.</q>"</p>
        <p>He pointed out further there were pre-historic monsters which were too powerful for their
            environment and became extinct. He further expressed the belief that any pattern for the
            future without birth control would be absolutely lost. I would not have you think that I
            have become such a pessimist as H. G., even in my maturity, but H. G. was not the only
            one who predicted the destruction of our civilization. Many other historians and
            philosophers are frank to say that, if civilisation is destroyed, it will come by the
            release of man's destructive fury, and the first thing to be destroyed will be the
            creative vision of the future. Without this basic creative vision, the whole birth
            control movement would lose its meaning. The basic truth that we insist upon, despite
            the prejudices and the ethereal promises of our beknighted enemies, is that there is a
            population problem and we know that this problem involves the whole human race, both
            living and potential.</p>
        <p>I do not intend to torture your ears with statistics, but it is well to repeat one point,
            one fact: that according to the latest available statistics, the human race now numbers
            2,344,727,000 living creatures who must be fed. Let us not forget that these billions,
            millions, thousands of people are increasing, expanding, exploding at a terrific rate
            every year. <place>Africa</place>, <place>Asia</place>, <place>South America</place> are
            made up of more than a billion human beings, miserable, poor, illiterate labor slaves,
            whether they are called that or not; a billion hungry men and women always in the famine
            zone yet repoducing themselves in the blind struggle for survival and perpetuation.</p>
        <p>I will not attempt to point out to you the wastefulness of the resources of our plundered
            planet but I would rather refer you to the books by <person reg="Osborn, Fairfield"
                >Fairfield Osborn</person> and<person reg="Vogt, William">William Vogt</person>,
            both masterful studies of our resources and our population needs. Our mass production
            via machinery has meant the production of masses for wars. We prize and boast of our
            civilization because it is characterized by ever-increasing mass populations. The
            brains, initiative, thrift and progress of the self-supportig, creative human being are
            called upon to support the ever-increasing and numerous dependent delinquent and
            unbalanced masses. </p>
        <p>There is an old saying that a hungry man is an angry man and this is no less true of
            famished populations. These masses, too, are victims of the demagogues and the agitators
            whether it be the Soviets or a <person reg="Hitler, Adolf">Hitler</person> or a <person
                reg="Mussolini, Benito">Mussolini</person>. Everything is promised in the way of
            security with never a suggestion of a corresponding self-reliance, respect and spacing
            of the progeny. Professor <person reg="Webb, Walter Prescott">Walter Prescott
                Webb</person> of <place>Texas</place> has pointed out that in our twentieth century
            for the first time in 500 years the amount of land available to man's use per capita is
            decreasing. This condition deprives the ambitious, blod, pioneering individual of one
            main corridor to freedom. If freedom is gone, the institutions which were designed to
            preserve and ensure freedom cannot long survive.</p>
        <p><q who="WEBWA">"If a society becomes crowded</q>," says Professor Webb, "<q who="WEBWA"
                >it will become more and more collective</q>."</p>
        <p>It seems to me that this unpleasant prospect should demand immediate and serious thought.
            Back in my childhood days we talked in terms of cents (even common cents), later on in
            terms of thousands of dollars, then millions. Now we talk of billions. You see the
            inflation of money, the inflation of words and the inflationary number of human beings.
            Inflation means devaluation, and we witness the widespread devaluation of human lives.
            Human beings are herded into concentration camps, into vast slave labour prisons. Whole
            nations are made homeless and displaced. These manifestations are symptoms of a complete
            lack of population policies and of political foresight as to the value and meaning of
            dignified human living on this earth.</p>
        <p>We pride ourselves upon our high standards of living, ignoring the low standards of dying
            that prevail in other teeming continents. Our government by its maudlin, benevolent
            extravagences tries to solve the problem of world war by throwing billions of dollars
            away. Population pressure will prevail against this generosity.</p>
        <p>Some of you may think that I am given to exaggerating this question of over-population
            and its result on the condition of the world to-day. I wonder how many of you realize
            that the population of the <place>British Isles</place> in <person
                reg="Shakespeare, William">Shakespeare</person>'s time was scarcely more than six
            millions, yet out of these few millions came the explorers, the pioneers, the poets, the
            pilgrims and the courageous founders of these <place reg="United States">United States
                of America</place>. What is <place>England</place> producing to-day with her hungry
            fifty million human beings struggling for survival? She had then a race of quality, now
            it's merely quantity. One forgets that the <place>Italy</place> of the Renaissance, of
            the painters, the sculptors, the architects, was a loose collection of small towns -- a
            tiny population that was yet the nursery of geniuses. There again quality rises supreme
            above quantity.</p>
        <p>This twentieth century of ours has seen the most rapid multiplication of human beings in
            our history, quantity without quality, however. And it is significant as well as
            profoundly symptomatic that parents are no longer held responsible for the birth, the
            development or the survival of their children</p>
        <p>In closing there are two suggestions I would like the Planned Parenthood Federation to
            consider. First, stress quality as a prime essential in the birth and survival of our
            population. Birth? Yes. In the recently added project of helping couple to have
            children, I am convinved that seven out of ten of these couple would not pass muster by
            an adoption agency. Were these would-be parents to apply to any adoption organisation in
            this <place reg="New York">State</place>, their qualifications as parents-to-be, would
            be sieved and classified for the protection of the child. High protection standards
            prevail in these agencies. Doctors directing our infertility projects could well apply a
            few of these standards for the sake of the children's security and happiness. Parenthood
            can be an emotional, temporary, superficial desire as well as an accidental event.
            Children's welfare should be our first consideration.</p>
        <p>The second suggestion I would offer as one worthy of national consideration is that of
            decreasing the progeny of those human beings affiliated with transmissable diseases and
            dysgnic qualities of body and mind. While our present Federal Governmental Santa Clauses
            have their hands in the taxpayer's pockets, why not in their generous giving mood be
            constructive and provide for sterilizing as well as giving a pension, dole -- call it
            what you may -- to the feeble-minded and the victims of transmissible, congenital
            diseases? Such a programme would be a sound future investment as well as a kindness to
            the couples themselves by preventing the birth of dozens of their progeny to become
            burdens, even criminals of another generation. It would save innocent children from the
            cruelty of being born to such parents.</p>
        <p>It is reported of <person reg="Weis, Ignace Semmel">Ignace Semmel Weis</person>, the
            great pioneer of preventative medicine, that he cried to the doctors in the hospitals of
                <place reg="Vienna, Austria">Vienna</place>, "<q who="WEIIG">Wash your hands, just
                wash your hands</q>." So I would cry in our modern confusion and chaos, "Cleanse
            your minds of cant and hypocrisy." Recognize the source of this vast conflict that
            threatens the survival of the human race. We have gone far in the field of preventative
            medicine, let us no have a little preventative politics and a system of thinking that
            will probe to the roots and heart of this human problem. We must induce men and women to
            strive for a better civilisation for themselves and their children's children. We cannot
            give them freedom on a silver platter but we can awaken in them the demand for a free,
            self-disciplined life and consciously controlled birth rate and population.</p>

    </docBody>
</doc>
