<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed draft article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2012-03-28 AW Initial Tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2012-04-04 CH Proofed Tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2012-04-05 AW Corrected Tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-08 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1959-00-00">1959</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Population for Peace</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp237313</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S72:0991</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>This article was drafted for Margaret Sanger, possibly by a <org>Planned Parenthood of
                America</org> staffer, to be published in <title type="jouranl">Reader's
                Digest.</title> The article was not published.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="international"/>
        <index level1="population control" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="Catholic Church" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="Catholic Church" level2="freedom of speech and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>POPULATION FOR PEACE</head>
        <head type="sub">or Peace Through Population Planning</head>
        <p>Less population will bring less war. Fewer people mean more Peace. Leaders of Asian
            nations have learned this lesson. They are acting on this belief, voluntary agencies,
            scientists, teachers, and government officials, all are responding to the message of
            birth control. Prime Ministers <person reg="Nehru, Jawaharlal">Nehru</person> of
                <place>India</place>, and <person reg="Kishi, Nobusuke">Kishi</person> of
                <place>Japan</place> are in the forefront. They are making population limitation
            part of National Policy. Birth Control is one of the basic health services provided
            officially by the Health and Welfare departments. The ministers of Health and Welfare
            are setting up programs all over the nations to see that such knowledge and service
            reaches all the people. The Government Budgets include funds appropriated for carrying
            these birth control programs for peace and for health. [Statistics here from Asia,
            India, Japan, etc.]</p>
        <p>Straggling along behind, our <place>United States</place> is coming finally to realize
            that population limitation must be a part of our national policy, as well as of world
            policy. Birth control must be one of our fundamental public health services, Federal and
            State. Strangely, we find our government authorities coming to this understanding
            through “the back door.” Only by seeing the need and activity about this program for
            peace in Asia, have our national leaders been awakened. The recent <person
                reg="Draper, William H., Jr.">Draper</person> report to President <person
                reg="Eisenhower, Dwight">Eisenhower</person> climaxed the situation by recommending
            that population limitation and birth control information and aids should be given as
            part of our foreign aid to nations around the world. Our Foreign Aid program is intended
            wholly to promote peace, to prevent another war of atomic proportions. This <org>Draper
                Committee</org>, outstandingly staffed, recognizes and reports that Peace depends
            upon Population Limitation. Still, the language of American officials is “sneaking”,
            with “weasel words”, because to the shame of progress, the pressure of <org
                reg="Roman Catholic Church">Roman Catholic Hierarchy</org> keeps officials from
            forthrightly using phrases Birth Control and Population Limitation.</p>
        <p>The shortsightedness of fanatic Roman Catholic hierarchy in the United States of America
            is the sole remaining block to the worldwide use of this path to peace, birth control.
            The Roman Catholic members do not fight the program of contraception. In fact, Roman
            Catholic church members use the birth control devices and contraceptives just as much as
            do Protestants and Jews. Roman Catholic members also use the Roman Catholic Official
            method of (unreliable) “safe-period”, or so-called rhythm. Even many of the United
            States Roman Catholic Priests, and a few Bishops do not object to the use of modern,
            effective birth-control methods. But when the Archbishop and Cardinal level is reached,
            comes the fanatic clawing tooth and nail against the apparent truth that contraception
            must be used to bring Peace in the World in our time. Even among Cardinals in other
            nations, we have not found such short-sighted interference with the practice of
            contraception among non-Roman Catholics as exists in this country, at the Federal level,
            and notably in <place>Connecticut</place> and <place>Massachusetts</place>.</p>
        <p>On some occasions I’ve been told by some high in the <org
                reg="Roman Catholic Church, Councils of the">Councils of the Roman Catholic
                Church</org> outside the United States, that the Roman Catholic authority at the
                <place>Vatican</place> would be ready now to modify its official pronouncements
            opposing birth control and population planning because the Roman Catholic authority
            there is realistic and aware that Peace can come only through Population control. The
            informants have told me their hands are tied, however, because the Roman Catholic
            Archbishops and Cardinals of the United States stand flatly against such a change! The
            group in this country is small, but its unenlightened thinking on this subject is extra
            powerful at Rome because it gathers to the coffers of the whole Roman Catholic Church
            the largest money contributions in the world.</p>
        <p>So the blight on progress towards Peace -- that we see in the United States so vividly
            closing over Connecticut and Massachusetts -- because of the Roman Catholic domination,
            also spreads out into the world by holding off the Agenda of the United Nations and its
            agencies, the <org reg="United Nations World Health Organization">World Health
                Organization</org>, and the <org
                reg="United Nations Food and Agricultural Organization">Food and Agricultural
                Organization</org> even any discussion of birth control and population limitation.
            The <org>United Nations</org> cannot become an effective organ for Peace until it can
            take into consideration and action population planning programs.</p>
        <p> Our United States government must decide soon to act on the recommendations of the
                <title type="article">Draper Report</title>, to give contraceptive aid as an
            essential part of foreign aid to peace. We must give birth control training, advice, and
            materials as a service to Peace and a service to Health. We need to set the example for
            our friends in Asia, and not keep trailing behind them. We must make birth control and a
            Population Policy part of our own Health and Welfare Department services, and part of
            our own National Policy. We must press for United Nations adoption of population
            limitation and contraception as a part of world policy. Only by such honest, clearly
            expressed action can the United States be a true leader for Peace now.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
