<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2003/06/30 SB</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/02 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/08/06 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-01 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1920-05-00">May 1920</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Women and the Rail Strike</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp237463</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title> May 20, 1920, p. 3</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S70:842</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="socio-economic benefits of"/>
        <index level1="labor movement" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="labor movement" level2="strikes"/><index level1="United States"
            level2="descriptions of"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="socio-economic conditions in"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Women and the Rail Strike</head>
        <byline rend="italics">By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></byline>
        <p>The most important thing about the April railroad strike to women is that it is not the
            last of the gigantic struggles, but only the beginning of a long series of them.
            Virtually every other organized trade in the country is in exactly the same position.
            There is and will be for some years to come a terrific battle between the employer and
            the employee. While these two are fighting it out and the employee is battling to get
            enough money to keep his family in comfort in the face of rising prices, there must of
            course be increasing industrial disorganization, and in the case of rail strikes, the
            period when millions of the people of the <place reg="United States">United
                States</place> must lack sufficient food, will be immensely hastened.</p>
        <p>The rail strike brought the prospect of famine nearer than most of us realize. Other and
            greater rail strikes are coming. Moreover, it came very close to precipitating a
            financial panic that would have plunged the entire industrial fabric of the nation into
            chaos. For, as explained in this magazine some time ago, the financial position of the
            world is today "faked" and unsound.</p>
        <p>All that we have undergone thus far is but a faint foretaste of the disorganization that
            is to come. It now appears that no power on earth can prevent the money panic of which
            everyone is talking and if this comes, no power on earth can prevent idleness, want and
            starvation. And these things the United States seems to have earned--they are coming to
            us and apparently we are going to get the full benefit of them within the next few
            years.</p>
        <p>It is probably that we must all, in one degree or other, pay the penalty for our failure
            to meet our social problems as they developed. Nevertheless, the present mess is a
            manmade muddle. It was created by man's brains--and by something else. That something
            else was our unchecked breeding capacity.</p>
        <p>Life has become so cheap in the United States that it is not worth one man's while to
            give a thought to another man's health or general wellbeing. This is particularly true
            of the exploiter of labor and the profiteer. And this is not the man's fault but ours.
            We have not made children scarce enough--we have not made them valuable enough.</p>
        <p>This is the beginning of a great day of reckoning. Matters have gotten so bad that they
            must get worse and we must learn our lessons before we can make them better. But it is
            for women to make them better and to make eternally sure that this state of affairs will
            not occur again.</p>
        <p>Labor's weakness has been its numbers, pitted one against another in competition for
            jobs. The exploiter weakness is that he does not understand that he and the profiteer
            cannot continue their course forever without labor striking back.</p>
        <p>The great numbers of children we have brought into the world have made this situation
            possible. It is now our duty to begin to undo the evil we have done. We must make
            children scarce and valuable--to valuable to be mistreated, overworked, or starved. We
            must refuse to bring more children into the world until it is made safe for them-- until
            they are no longer exposed to the danger of want, are no longer turned teacherless away
            from schools, are no longer oppressed. When we do that, there will be no more such
            periods as we are now going through and must go through for some years.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, no woman with the feelings of a true mother, will bring a child into being at
            a time like this. There is no assurance that any child born now can have the care and
            the food to which a child is entitled. There is no assurance that it can be properly
            educated. The woman who comprehends the situation will wait five years before giving
            birth to another. She owes it to her children, herself, her husband and to society.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
