<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<doc type="Published article">
<mepHeader>
<prepDate>2003/06/25 RK</prepDate>
<prepDate>2004/07/27 CH</prepDate>
<prepDate>2004/08/09 CH</prepDate>
<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
<docDate value="1919-06-00">Jun 1919</docDate>
<docTitle>
<titlePart>Western Women Demand Information</titlePart>
</docTitle>
<idno>msp237561</idno>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl><title>The Birth Control Review</title>, June 1919, 5</bibl>
<bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S70:0823</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
<respStmt>
<resp></resp>
<name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
</respStmt>
</mepHeader>
<headNote resp="MSPP"><index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="in California"/><index level1="United States" level2="western region"/></headNote>
<docBody>
<head>Western Women Demand Information</head>
<byline rend="italics">By Margaret Sanger</byline>
<p>After all, it's an ill wind that blows nobody good.  <place>California</place> authorities are so busy keeping <person>Tom Mooney</person> in jail, fighting labor unions, rounding up <org reg="Industrial Workers of the World">I.W. W.</org>, arresting and deporting Hindus and
chasing Bolsheviks, that they don't have time to stand guard over
advocates of Birth Control.  That was the reason, perhaps, why two
lectures in which information concerning contraceptives was given,
were not interfered with by these same authorities.</p>
<p>California women are anxious for practical knowledge of Birth
Control.  They do not care so much for the theory--what they want to
know is how to avoid having children.  I have visited a number of
cities and towns in the state and have found the same feeling
prevailing everywhere.  There is a weariness of indirect methods. 
There is a lack of interest in legislative measures.  Only women who
are the heads of clubs are still hopeful of having the laws changed. 
The rest simply refuse to think about laws any more.  They want the
information.</p>
<p>The attitude of a group of workers in <place reg="San Francisco, CA">San
Francisco</place> is an accurate indication of the attitude of women
generally in the state.  I was invited to lecture before this body and
did so on the night of April 26th.  It had become plain to me that
these women had lost faith in legislation, just as they had lost faith
in courts.  They demanded something more than they demanded four years
ago or two years ago.  Then they had been satisfied to know the
relation of Birth Control to life's social problems.  Now they want
the relief that Birth Control can bring and they don't want anything
less.</p>
<p>It was suggested that I might be arrested for giving information
regarding contraceptives from the public platform.</p>
<p>"<q who="UNK">Go ahead</q>," said the women, "<q who="UNK">we're <emph rend="italics">with</emph> you--not <emph rend="italics">behind you</emph></q>."</p>
<p>That spirit was reflected everywhere.</p>
<p>In the period allotted for answering question, ten or fifteen
women were upon their feet at once--not to discuss generalities, but
to ask advice upon their own practical problems.  Four years, and two
years ago, when I lectured in California, hardly a woman would rise in
public to ask for personal advice about Birth Control.</p>
<p>The demand for actualities rather than theories exists not only in
regard to Birth Control but in regard to other matters as well.  For
example, the decided shift to direct action indicates how thoroughly
they have put aside their faith in the machinery of law making and law
enforcement.</p>
<p>California women know what they want from the Birth Control
movement and they are not afraid to demand it.  They will stand by any
person, group or organization in action.  And they are interested only
in action.</p>
</docBody>
</doc>
