<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2003/11/07 amc</prepDate>
		<prepDate>5/09/12 AW</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-04-10 CH clean regs</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-20 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1925-01-00">Jan 1925</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>Book Review, Contraception: A Medical Review of the Situation</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp237978</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title>, Jan. 1925, pp. 20-21</bibl>
			<bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Smith College Collections</title> S71:15</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="DICRO">Dickinson, Robert Latou</name>
			<name id="FRE">French</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote><index level1="American Birth Control League"/>
		<index level1="Book Review"/>
		<index level1="Committee on Maternal Health"/>
		<index level1="Netherlands" level2="birth control clinics in"/></headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>CONTRACEPTION: A MEDICAL REVIEW OF THE SITUATION</head>
		<byline>Reviewed by <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></byline>
		<div>
			<p>The <org>Committee on Maternal Health</org> of <place reg="New York, NY">New
					York</place> is to be congratulated upon the appearance of Dr. <person
					reg="Dickinson, Robert Latou">Dickinson</person>'s report, which is perhaps the
				first essay of its kind to be published in this country. Even among those members of
				the medical profession who have taken the time and trouble to inquire into the
				actual present status of the practice of Birth Control in this country, definite
				scientific and statistical knowledge has been woefully scant. "<q who="DICRO">The
					gist of what is known is here given,</q>" states Dr. Dickinson at the outset,
					"<q who="DICRO">together with an account of the attempts to secure clinical
					data.</q>" The investigator reiterates the appeal that has so often been voiced
				in these pages--for the need of investigation by the medical profession. He agrees
				(though perhaps unconsciously) with the aims of the <org>American Birth Control
					League</org>, and with Lord <person reg="Dawson, Bertrand E.">Dawson</person> of
				Penn, that "<q who="DICRO">the medical profession alone can determine many physical
					questions bearing on structure, function, and abnormal or diseased states.</q>"
				In addition to this mechanical side, the various mental and moral reactions that
				come chiefly to the knowledge of the doctor, as the father-confessor in matters of
				sex, should be taken from available records for consideration. He repeats the appeal
				of the American Birth Control League for the correlation and co-ordination of
				medical records and clinical data. Not the least illuminating phase of this study is
				to be found in his appended diagrams, which throw considerable and valuable light on
				this hidden phase of human life.</p>
			<p>With these outstanding virtues, it is the more lamentable that Dr. Dickinson has been
				unable, or has not seen fit, to publish fuller information about the birth control
				clinics in <place reg="Netherlands">Holland</place>. There is evident in his report
				an inclination to discredit statements made concerning the "52 clinics" of Holland.
				As, since my visit to Holland in 1915, I have been guilty of making these statements
				again and again I feel called upon here to say something in defense of them.
				Although in person I visited only five of these clinics, I would refer those
				interested in this matter to the Annual Report of the <org
					reg="Nieuw-Malthusiaansche Bond">Nieuw-Malthusian Band</org> for the year 1920.
				Dr. <person reg="Rutgers, Johannes">Rutgers</person> was then president of the Dutch
				League, and in his report stated that a new board of directors had been formed. Dr.
				Rutgers at that time relinquished the presidency and the new board of directors,
				"more democratic" in spirit, took charge of the work. A period of disintegration
				seems to have set in, temporarily, and subsequent reports of the work have been less
				encouraging. But it is not enough to judge the work in Holland, which has covered
				such a long period of years, by a temporary depression due undoubtedly to the
				resignation and subsequent death of Dr. Rutgers, whose indefatigable devotion and
				tireless efforts, obtained notable results. The report of the Dutch League reported
				not 52, but 54 clinics, 8 doctors and 56 nurses in charge, and admitted that the
				year 1920 had been a difficult one for the <supplied resp="MSPP"
				>Bund</supplied>.</p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<head type="SUB" rend="italics">"<q who="DICRO">Without Bias</q>"</head>
			<p>"<q who="DICRO">Our search discovers no investigation of 'Birth Control' made in a
					scientific and ethical spirit approaching the subject "<emph rend="italics"
						>without bias</emph></q>," asserts Dr. Dickinson. I regret that I must agree
				with this statement. But I am even more sorry that his own report, despite its
				protestations of impartiality, should itself be tainted with bias, the more so as he
				has the advantage of scientific training and should approach the problem without
					<foreign lang="FRE" rend="italics">parti-pris</foreign>. On page 20 of his
				report he speaks of "<q who="DICRO">the <org reg="Clinical Research Bureau"
						>clinic</org> run by Dr. <person reg="Bocker, Dorothy">Dorothy
						Bocker</person> next to the office of Margaret Sanger's Birth Control
					League.</q>" Surely it cannot be devotion to scientific precision that has led
				Dr. Dickinson to this combination of misstatements. Such lack of precision is hardly
				in accordance with the spirt of scientific impartiality which is, in the opinion of
				the present authority, the great present need in investigation of clinical data. In
				the first place, the organization to which Dr. Dickinson refers, is not "Margaret
				Sanger's;" it is the American Birth Control League, legally incorporated under the
				laws of the state of New York. In the second place, the "clinic run by Dr. Dorothy
				Bocker" is a research bureau conducted under the personal direction of Margaret
				Sanger, with Dr. Bocker as a medical director. Merely in the interest of accuracy
				and impartial fairness we offer these corrections here. Without a recognition of the
				manifold difficulties under which such pioneer work must be carried on in these
					<place>United States</place>, our aims and limitations may be misinterpreted by
				future investigators. </p>
			<p>The whole subject of contraception, as Dr. Dickinson so rightly concludes, is
				susceptible of handling as clean science, with dignity, decency and directness. This
				indeed has from its inception been the aim of the American Birth Control League.
				Because of its unswerving adherence to these principles, it has won a place of
				respect among impartial scientists both here and abroad. Despite the complexity and
				menacing aspects of the problem it has attacked, despite its limited resources,
				despite the intellectual inertia of the medical profession and the languid interest
				of the American clergy, the League is gradually enlisting the competent co-operation
				of cool headed, impartial and unbiased scientists, and because of its irrefutable
				claim for respect, it will continue to do so. </p>
		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
