<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2009/08/03 LL</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2012/06/18 AW Corrected Tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-16 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1932-04-00">Apr 1932</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>A News Letter from Margaret Sanger</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp238045</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm: Smith College Collection</title> S71:0430</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="MECCPC">Methodist Episcopal Church City Planning Committee</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
            <name id="HFC">Hartford Federation of Churches</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret " level2="speaking tours" level3="1932 (U.S.)"/>
        <index level1="Catholic Church" level2="political influence of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="State"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="resolutions" level3="local"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>A NEWS LETTER FROM <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">MARGARET SANGER</person></head>
        <p> My recent experiences, while on a speaking tour, have shown me the extent to which the
                <org>Roman Catholic Church</org> dictates the policy of the municipal authorities in
            many of our cities. I was scheduled to speak in <place reg="Albany, NY">Albany</place>,
            March 6th, at the <org reg="Albany Jewish Community Center">Jewish Community
                Center</org>. A week before the lecture, several Catholic officials tried to bring
            pressure to bear through the Albany social agencies to get the Jewish Community Center
            to rescind their invitation. Fortunately, the Auditorium belonged to the Jewish group
            and the <person reg="Thatcher, John Boyd, II">Mayor</person> was unable to revoke the
            license.</p>
        <p>The same forces tried to break up the meeting at <place reg="New Haven, CT">New
                Haven</place> on March 8th. I was scheduled to speak at the <org>Troup Junior High
                School</org> under the auspices of the <org
                reg="Albany Young Men's Christian Association">Young Men’s and <org
                    reg="Albany Young Women's Christian Association">Young Women’s Hebrew
                    Association</org></org>. Following a protest by the Reverend <person
                reg="Mereto, Joseph">Joseph Mereto</person> of <place reg="Chicago, IL"
                >Chicago</place>, a missionary conducting a Lenten mission at <org>St. Anthony’s
                Roman Catholic Church</org>, the permit for the use of the Auditorium was revoked at
            noon on Saturday. An informal protest committee was hastily formed headed by Dr. <person
                reg="Creadick, A. N.">A. N. Creadick</person>, president of the
                    <org><place>Connecticut</place> Birth Control League</org>. Among the many
            distinguished citizens who rallied to my support were Dean <person
                reg="Winternitz, Milton C.">Milton C. Winternitz</person>, of the <org
                reg="Yale University Medical School">Yale Medical School</org>; Dr. <person
                reg="Thomas, Herbert">Herbert Thomas</person>, associate professor obstetrics and
            gynecology at the Yale Medical School; Attorney <person reg="Watrous, Charles E."
                >Charles E. Watrous</person>, Professor <person reg="Cooper, James Wayne">James
                Wayne Cooper</person> of the <org reg="Yale University Law School">Yale Law
                School</org>; Dr. <person reg="Miller, James R.">James R. Miller</person> of <place
                reg="Hartford, CT">Hartford</place>; <person reg="Merviss, Jacob">Jacob
                Merviss</person>, executive director of the Y. M. and Y. W. H. A., and <person
                reg="Ives, C. P.">C. P. Ives</person>, 2nd, associate editor of the <org
                rend="italics">New Haven Journal-Courier</org>.</p>
        <p>A large delegation called at the <org reg="Murphy, John W.">Mayor</org>’s office early
            Monday morning to demand a license for the meeting. This was finally granted for the
                <org>Fox College</org> theater. In view of the widespread indignation, the
            opposition did not dare push the matter further. According to the newspaper reports,
            2000 people were present at the meeting.</p>
        <p>In <place reg="Boston, MA">Boston</place> I addressed a group of medical students, under
            the auspices of the <org>Lancet Club</org>. The majority of those present were third
            year students; several had graduated and were doing internship, but my address was the
            first information on contraception that they had received.</p>
        <p>On my <place>West Virginia</place> trip, it was again a story of Catholic opposition
            bringing pressure to bear. The result was that the <org>Cabell County Medical
                Society</org> of <place reg="Huntington, WV">Huntington</place> rescinded their
            invitation to me. However, thanks to the courage and fine spirit of Dr. <person
                reg="Klumpp, James S.">James S. Klumpp</person>, Dr. <person reg="Strange, William"
                >William Strange</person> and others, I was asked to speak under the auspices of an
            independent group of twenty physicians, and the meeting was held at the <org>Pritchard
                Hotel</org> and was open to the public. Fully 1000 people attended and approximately
            400 were turned away. I have great hopes that the interest aroused may shortly result in
            the establishment of a clinic.</p>
        <p>I also spoke to several mining groups in West Virginia and found there conditions that
            would horrify us were we living in a foreign land. The women were most interested and
            very intelligent. The men were more silent and opinion seemed somewhat divided among
            them. As a result of these meetings, however, another meeting was arranged the following
            week by the Catholic group to offset, no doubt, the favorable reaction toward birth
            control that a proper presentation of the subject arouses.</p>
        <div type="Section">
            <head type="Sub">CONNECTICUT</head>
            <p>The <org>Hartford Federation of Churches</org> went on record at its annual meeting
                on February 23rd in favor of the dissemination of information about birth control to
                those who desire it. The following resolutions were adopted, as recommended by Dr.
                    <person reg="Miller, James R.">James R. Miller</person>, chairman of the
                Federation’s committee on social welfare, which had been requested to make a study
                of birth control:</p>
            <p>
                <q who="HFC">Birth control is merely one phase of the eugenic problem. Protestant
                    faiths claim not only the right but a duty for mankind to exercise intelligent
                    supervision over this problem. Sexual relations should be regarded as entirely
                    natural, and sinful only as they are abused.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
                <q who="HFC">In our land, where free speech and free education have been made the
                    foundation of our democracy, it is peculiarly false teaching that anyone should
                    be denied by statute, access to any information which he may desire.</q>
            </p>
        </div>
        <div type="Section">
            <head type="Sub">
                <place reg="NJ">NEW JERSEY</place>
            </head>
            <p><person reg="Jones, Eleanor Dwight">Mrs. F. Robertson Jones</person>, president of
                the <org>American Birth Control League</org>, debated with <person
                    reg="Shea, Albert J.">Albert J. Shea</person>, <place reg="Hoboken, NJ"
                    >Hoboken</place> attorney, on <title type="article">Is Birth Control a Benefit
                    to Humanity?</title> before the Forum of the <org reg="Secaucus American Legion"
                    >American Legion of Secaucus</org>. A record attendance of over 500 followed the
                argument with interest and asked numerous questions. No vote was taken.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="Section">
            <head type="Sub">
                <place>NEW YORK</place>
            </head>
            <p>A comprehensive survey of Methodism in <place reg="New York, NY">Manhattan</place>,
                the Bronx and Westchester County has recently been published by the <org>Methodist
                    Episcopal Church City Planning Committee</org>, and includes the results of a
                questionnaire on birth control. 740 laymen against 138 voted that they agreed with
                the action taken by the <org
                    reg="Methodist Episcopal Church, New-York East Conference">New York East
                    Conference</org> of the church in passing a resolution that “<q who="MECCPC">the
                    law preventing doctors from furnishing birth control information should be
                    changed.</q>”</p>
        </div>
        <div type="Section">
            <head type="Sub">
                <place reg="PA">PENNSYLVANIA</place>
            </head>
            <p>A Marriage Council service has been initiated by <person reg="Mudd, Emily Hartshorne"
                    >Mrs. Stuart Mudd</person> at 1831 Chestnut Street, <place
                    reg="Philadelphia, PA">Philadelphia</place>. It is offered “<q who="UNK">to help
                    young married couples, or those contemplating marriage, to a better
                    understanding of common requisites for a happy and healthy companionship in
                    married life--to help them avoid some of the causes of marital
                difficulties.</q>” Among the distinguished sponsors are Dr. <person
                    reg="Allen, Frederick H.">Frederick H. Allen</person>, director,
                    <org>Philadelphia Child Guidance Clinin</org>, Dr. <person reg="Dewees, Lovett"
                    >Lovett Dewees</person>, attending physicians, <org>Bryn Mawr Hospital</org> and
                president of the <org>Pennsylvania Birth Control Federation</org>, Rabbi <person
                    reg="Fineshriber, William H.">William H. Fineshriber</person>, <org>Keneseth
                    Israel Synagogue</org>, <person reg="Kind, Bessie">Mrs. Philip Kind</person>,
                vice president, <org>Women’s International League for Peace and Freedom</org>,
                    <person reg="Wood, Helen Foes">Mrs. George Bacon Wood</person>, member of the
                Board of Directors, <org reg="Philadelphia Young Women's Christian Association">Y.
                    W. C. A.</org>
            </p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
