<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2003/07/15 SR</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2003/07/23 SR</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/01 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/11/28 CH correct typos</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011-11-30 CH typos</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-01 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1921-11-18">18 Nov 1921</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>The Morality of Birth Control</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp238254</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="Journal">The Morality of Birth Control</title>, (New York,
                1921)</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S70:917</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>Originally scheduled to be delivered at the close of the <org
                reg="American Birth
            Control Conference, 1st">First American Birth
                Control Conference</org> on Nov. 13, 1921, this address was made on Nov. 18 after
            the police raided the <org>Town Hall</org> and arrested Sanger. This speech was given at
            the <org>Park Theatre</org>, in <place reg="New York, NY"> New York City</place>. For a
            typed version, including other speakers, see the <title type="book">Proceedings of the
                First American Birth Control Conference</title> (<title>Margaret Sanger
                Microfilm</title> S67:902-918).</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="class-based"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="medically controlled"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="morality of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="opposition to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="socio-economic benefits of"/>
        <index level1="Catholic Church" level2="birth control and abortion and"/>
        <index level1="censorship"/>
        <index level1="children" level2="rights of"/>
        <index level1="family size" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="First American Birth Control Conference (1921)"/>
        <index level1="fit (to reproduce)" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="physicians" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="population" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="&quot;unfit&quot; to reproduce" level2="descriptions of"/>
        <index level1="&quot;unfit&quot; to reproduce" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="enslavement of"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="freedom and rights of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>The Morality of Birth Control</head>
        <byline>By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></byline>
        <p>The meeting tonight is a postponement of one which was to have taken place at the Town
            Hall last Sunday evening. It was to be a culmination of a three day conference, two of
            which were held at the Hotel Plaza, in discussing the Birth Control subject in its
            various and manifold aspects.</p>
        <p>The one issue upon which there seems to be most uncertainty and disagreement exists in
            the moral side of the subject of Birth Control. It seemed only natural for us to call
            together scientists, educators, members of the medical profession and the theologians of
            all denominations to ask their opinion upon this uncertain and important phase of the
            controversy. Letters were sent to the most eminent men and women in the world. We asked
            in this letter, the following questions:--</p>
        <list rend="blockquote">
            <item>1. Is over-population a menace to the peace of the world?</item>
            <item>2. Would the legal dissemination of scientific Birth Control information through
                the medium of clinics by the medical profession be the most logical method of
                checking the problem of over-population?</item>
            <item>3. Would knowledge of Birth Control change the moral attitude of men and women
                toward the marriage bond or lower the moral standards of the youth of the
                country?</item>
            <item>4. Do you believe that knowledge which enables parents to limit the families will
                make for human happiness, and raise the moral, social and intellectual standards of
                population?</item>
        </list>
        <p>We sent such a letter not only to those who, we thought, might agree with us, but we sent
            it also to our known opponents. Most of these people answered. Every one who answered
            did so with sincerity and courtesy, with the exception of one group whose reply to this
            important question as demonstrated at the Town Hall last Sunday evening was a disgrace
            to liberty-loving people, and to all traditions we hold dear in the <place> United
                States</place>. (Applause.) I believed that the discussion of the moral issue was
            one which did not solely belong to theologians and to scientists, but belonged to the
            people. (Applause.) And because I believed that the people of this country may and can
            discuss this subject with dignity and with intelligence I desired to bring them
            together, and to discuss it in the open.</p>
        <p>When one speaks of moral, one refers to human conduct. This implies action of many kinds,
            which in turn depends upon the mind and the brain. So that in speaking of morals one
            must remember that there is a direct connection between morality and brain development.
            Conduct is said to be action in pursuit of ends, and if this is so, then we must hold
            the irresponsibility and recklessness in our action is immoral, while responsibility and
            forethought put into action for the benefit of the individual and the race becomes in
            the highest sense the finest kind of morality.</p>
        <p>We know that every advance that woman has made in the last half century has been made
            with opposition, all of which has been based upon the grounds of immorality. When women
            fought for higher education, it was said that this would cause her to become immoral and
            she would lose her place in the sanctity of the home. When women asked for the franchise
            it was said that this would lower her standard of morals, that it was not fit that she
            should meet with and mix with the members of the opposite sex, but we notice that there
            was no objection to her meeting with the same members of the opposite sex when she went
            to church. The church has ever opposed the progress of woman on the ground that her
            freedom would lead to immorality. We ask the church to have more confidence in women. We
            ask the opponents of this movement to reverse the methods of the church, which aims to
            keep women moral by keeping them in fear and in ignorance, and to inculcate into them a
            higher and truer morality based upon knowledge. (Applause). And ours is the morality of
            knowledge. If we cannot trust woman with the knowledge of her own body, then I claim
            that two thousand years of Christian teaching has proved to be a failure.
            (Applause.)</p>
        <p>We stand on the principle that Birth Control should be available to every adult man and
            woman. We believe that every adult man and woman should be taught the responsibility and
            the right use of knowledge. We claim that woman should have the right over her own body
            and to say if she shall or if she shall not be a mother, as she sees fit. (Applause.) We
            further claim that the first right of a child is to be desired. (Applause). While the
            second right is that it should be conceived in love, and the third, that it should have
            a heritage of sound health.</p>
        <p>Upon these principles the Birth Control movement in America stands.</p>
        <p>When it comes to discussing the methods of Birth Control, that is far more difficult.
            There are laws in this country which forbid the imparting of practical information to
            the mothers of the land. We claim that every mother in this country, either sick or
            well, has the right to the best, the safest, the most scientific information. This
            information should be disseminated directly to the mothers through clinics by members of
            the medical profession, registered nurses and registered midwives. (Applause.)</p>
        <p>Our first step is to have the backing of the medical profession so that our laws may be
            changed, so that motherhood may be the function of dignity and choice, rather than one
            of ignorance and chance. (Applause.) Conscious control of offspring is now becoming the
            ideal and the custom in all civilized countries.</p>
        <p>Those who oppose it claim that however desirable it may be on economic or social grounds,
            it may be abused and the morals of the youth of the country may be lowered. Such people
            should be reminded that there are two points to be considered. First, that such control
            is the inevitable advance in civilization. Every civilization involves an increasing
            forethought for others, even for those yet unborn. (Applause.) The reckless abandonment
            of the impulse of the moment and the careless regard for the consequences, is not
            morality. (Applause). The selfish gratification of temporary desire at the expense of
            suffering to lives that will come may seem very beautiful to some, but it is not our
            conception of civilization, or is it our concept of morality. (Applause).</p>
        <p>In the second place, it is not only inevitable, but it is right to control the size of
            the family for by this control and adjustment we can raise the level and the standards
            of the human race. While Nature's way of reducing her numbers is controlled by disease,
            famine and war, primitive man has achieved the same results by infanticide, exposure of
            infants, the abandonment of children, and by abortion. But such ways of controlling
            population is no longer possible for us. We have attained high standards of life, and
            along the lines of science must we conduct such control. We must begin farther back and
            control the beginnings of life. We must control conception. This is a better method, it
            is a more civilized method, for it involves not only greater forethought for others, but
            finally a higher sanction for the value of life itself.</p>
        <p>Society is divided into three groups. Those intelligent and wealthy members of the upper
            classes who have obtained knowledge of Birth Control and exercise it in regulating the
            size of their families. They have already benefited by this knowledge, and are today
            considered the most respectable and moral members of the community. They have only
            children when they desire and all society points to them as types that should perpetuate
            their kind.</p>
        <p>The second group is equally intelligent and responsible. They desire to control the size
            of their families, but are unable to obtain knowledge or to put such available knowledge
            into practice.</p>
        <p>The third are those irresponsible and reckless ones having little regard for the
            consequence of their acts, or whose religious scruples prevent their exercising control
            over their numbers. Many of this group are diseased ,feeble-minded, and are of the
            pauper element dependent entirely upon the normal and fit members of society for their
            support. There is no doubt in the minds of all thinking people that the procreation of
            this group should be stopped. (Applause.) For if they are not able to support and care
            for themselves, they should certainly not be allowed to bring offspring into this world
            for others to look after. (Applause.) We do not believe that filling the earth with
            misery, poverty and disease is moral. And it is our desire and intention to carry on our
            crusade until the perpetuation of such conditions has ceased.</p>
        <p>We desire to stop at its source the disease, poverty and feeble-mindedness and insanity
            which exist today, for these lower the standards of civilization and make for race
            deterioration. We know that the masses of people are growing wiser and are using their
            own minds to decide their individual conduct. The more people of this kind we have, the
            less immorality shall exist. For the more responsible people grow, the higher do they
            and shall they attain real morality. (Applause.)</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
