<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Review">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/05/23 CE</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/05/24 CE Corrections</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/06/21 CE Corrections</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1928-07-00">Jul 1928</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied>Book Review of HAVELOCK ELLIS: PHILOSOPHER OF
                    LOVE.</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp238642</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>The Birth Control Review</title>July 1928, pp.
                210-211.</bibl>
            <bibl><title>MSM</title>S71:0142</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="ELLHA">Ellis, Henry Havelock</name>
            <name id="LAT">Latin</name>
            <name id="PETHO">Peterson, Houston</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="Book Review"/>
        <index level1="Ellis, Havelock" level2="MS on"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Havelock Ellis.</head>
        <byline><ital>By</ital>MARGARET SANGER</byline>
        <p>In that “open letter to biographers” which he dashed off upon the
            completion of his <ital><title>Study of British
                Genius</title></ital>, <person reg="Ellis, Henry Havelock"
                >Havelock Ellis</person> pointed out that many biographies were
            often merely “<q who="ELLHA">slices of misplaced history</q>,” and
            warned all future biographers to study the roots of the lives they
            recorded. “After the age of twenty, your task becomes easier and
            more obvious; after thirty, if so far you have fulfilled that task,
            what is there further left to tell? The rest is but the liberation
            of a mighty spring, the slow running down of energy. The man recedes
            to give place to his deeds, whether such deeds be the assault of
            great fortresses, or the escalade of mighty sentences.”</p>
        <p><person reg="Peterson, Houston">Houston Peterson</person>, who has
            valiantly undertaken to write the life of <ital>Havelock
                Ellis</ital>* who at sixty-nine is still keenly sensitive to the
            dangers of this difficult art, has evidently taken to heart this
            warning. The result is that, intentionally or not, the first
            chapters, dealing with the hereditary background, with the
            childhood, youth and early manhood of his subject are far more
            important to our fuller understanding of this life-giving spirit
            than, say, the final five chapters, which, in our humble opinion,
            seem to rely too completely upon quotations from the works of Ellis
            himself- quotations significant in themselves, but revealing nothing
            new to any of us who have drunk deep at the spring of wisdom which
            Havelock Ellis has liberated to irrigate the arid wastes of our
            Anglo-Saxon world.</p>
        <p>But before proffering even these tentative criticisms of Mr.
            Peterson's significant biography, we must first express unqualified
            admiration for the thoroughness which he has documented himself, and
            for the keen incisive scholarship which has gone into the creation
            of this book. Instead of carping on its limitations, let us rejoice
            in the painstaking preparation, the indefatigable research, and the
            skilful reconstruction fo a life, fascinating and unique in every
            phase, which this volume reveals to us.</p>
        <p>The heredity, the birth, the development of the boy and his early
            blossoming into a grave maturity, are all recounted with a distinct
            narrative gift, and practically never with any slurring of the
            significant steps onward. The excerpts from the early notebooks and
            diaries, which Havelock Ellis began at the age of ten, are
            especially interesting. They reveal the remarkable precocity of
            genius. His admirations and his enthusiasms during his adolescence
            were indeed immature, but already he was able to articulate and
            express his thoughts with unclouded clearness.</p>
        <p>Mr. Peterson makes us realize that this son of <person
                reg="Ellis, Edward Peppen">a British sea-captain</person>
            inherited much of the valiant courage of a race of mariners.
            Resolutely he dared to voyage alone through uncharted seas of
            forbidden research. With the uncanny self-reliance of genius, he
            decided upon this life-voyage when he was a lad scarcely past
            sixteen. “<q who="PETHO">He would explore the dangerous ocean of sex
                and perhaps find for humanity an Earthly Paradise!</q>” So
            exclaims Mr. Peterson, in relating that early decision of young
            Henry Havelock Ellis, adding Ellis's own testimony to the effect
            that he never deviated form this adolescent resolution: “<q
                who="ELLHA">... in all that I have done, that resolve has never
                been very far from my thoughts</q>.” In 1926 Ellis commented
            further: “<q who="ELLHA">I am sure that I never for a moment
                anticipated that my efforts in that direction would arouse so
                wide an echo in the world</q>.”</p>
        <p>The far-flung schemes of adolescence, the biographer sagely point
            out, are often little more than laughable, but here was the decision
            of a sixteen-year-old, destined to be carried out through a long
            lifetime. The only satisfactory explanation, I believe, can be
            discovered when we realize that, like all authentic geniuses, the
            lonely sixteen-year-old youth, strolling under the feathery
            eucalyptuses of an Australian village, had developed intellectually
            and spiritually far beyond what is ordinary considered normal.</p>
        <p>Particularly interesting is Mr. Peterson's account of Ellis's early
            perusal of <person reg="Drysdale, George">George Drysdale</person>'s
                <emph rend="italics"><title>Elements of Social
                Science</title></emph>, and the support the youth found in that
            anonymous book for his own grave convictions regarding the
            importance of sex, and his conversion, before his twentieth year, to
            the doctrine of contraception.</p>
        <p>Without wasting space to go further into the many fascinating details
            unearthed by this industrious biographer, let us recommend Houston
            Peterson's book at once as <foreign lang="LAT">sine qua non</foreign>
            to everyone who looks upon Havelock Ellis as one of the outstanding
            heroes of western civilization. Having done this, and having thanked
            Mr. Peterson for his generous recognition fo ourselves and the
                <title>BIRTH CONTROL REVIEW</title> as a source of certain
            materials, we may turn to a consideration fo certain phases of this
            biography which please us less than the specific chapters we have
            noted.</p>
        <p>Our criticism is not directed specifically toward this book; it is to
            all biographers which seek to portray a living man. Evidently in the
            preparation fo such an interpretation as the present, the biographer
            finds himself brought into much closer personal contact with his
            subject than when, in the first flush of enthusiasm, his decision to
            undertake a biography comes upon him. As he prepares his literary
            portrait, he is like a painter who must study the anatomy of his
            sitter, who must approach so closely that he sees details and
            defects and finally, as so often happens, temporarily loses his
            vision fo the inner animating spirit- of the movement behind that
                “<q who="ELLHA">liberation of a mighty spring</q>.” The
            successful biographer must regain the thrill of his initial
            inspiration- he must not only study every phase of his subject, but
            must master his own relation to that subject.</p>
        <p>With all his competence, and masterly scholarship, I cannot escape
            the feeling that somehow or other Houston Peterson has failed to
            sustain the stability of his relationship to Havelock Ellis. Facts
            he gives us in abundance- details of his life, his friends, his
            predilections. But after all, we are not so much interested in the
            elderly literary man who lives in <place reg="Brixton, England"
                >Brixton</place>, and does his own cooking, as we are in that
            living and eternal spirit who seems to dwell serenely above the
            limitations of time and space, whose radiance, like that of the
            life-giving sun, has penetrated beyond oceans and continents, and
            has performed miracles in creating hope and joy where despair and
            melancholy had existed before. I am not trying to indulge in poetic
            fancy. Before the advent of the radio, before the achievements of
            aviation, the message of Havelock Ellis- “broadcasted” despite the
            many obstacles put in its way- has been “picked up” in far-away
            corners of the earth, as innumerable letters from obscure people
            have testified. It is almost as though- to continue our analogy-
            provided with a receiving set, these sensitive minds had “picked up”
            a distant station, and from it had received a deep and beneficent
            message of human salvation. Those who have had this experience can
            never look upon Havelock Ellis as a mere mortal. Through him, as
            through <person reg="Francis, Saint">Saint Francis</person>, is
            irradiated the wisdom of divinity.</p>
        <p>Houston Peterson will undoubtedly laugh at this “pseudo-mysticism.”
            But those of us who find in Ellis a god can never be quite satisfied
            with a realistic portrait, which, from a distance, slightly
            diminishes his true stature.</p>
        <note>*<title>Havelock Ellis: Philosopher of Love</title>. By Houston
            Peterson. <place reg="Boston, Massachusetts">Boston</place> and
                <place reg="New York City, New York">New York</place>:
                <org>Houghton Mifflin Company</org>, 1928.</note>
    </docBody>
</doc>
