<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/06/03 RT initial tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/06/03 CH proof</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/06/10 RT corrections</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1937-01-00">Jan 1937</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Women of the Future</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp238614</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Smith College</bibl>
            <bibl><title>MSM</title> S17:912</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>For draft versions, see <title>MSM</title> S71:908 and LCM 131:456.</p>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="efforts to increase"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="population growth and"/>
        <index level1="mentally disabled and diseased" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="population" level2="war and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>WOMEN OF THE FUTURE</head>

        <p>We have the wisdom--We have the skill--as demonstrated by man’s
            explorations and war against microbes and germs where we find all
            the miracles of the atom and of radio-activity.</p>
        <p>In brief, during the last 100 years our wisdom and skill have taken
            remarkable steps in the conquest of the external forces of Nature.
            Man has tamed and harnessed many natural energies and directed them
            for his own use.</p>
        <p>But before we boast too loudly of these achievements of wisdom, let
            us evaluate them in terms of woman’s future as the basis of a higher
            and finer civilization. How can we boast of the conquest of the air
            or the marvels of chemistry when nation after nation compels its
            innocent women and children to protect themselves against these by
            wearing gas masks?</p>
        <p>Why should we take pride in the advance of medical and surgical
            skill, when its use is to be the salvaging of the defectives, the
            morons and prolonging the lives of the diseased millions whose very
            existence depends upon the continuation of private or public
            charity?</p>
        <p>Consider the vast fortunes--millions--nay billions--of dollars we
            continue to shovel into the bottomless pit of so-called
            relief--charity. Philanthropy, like the rose by any other name, it
            smells the same.</p>
        <p>This effort to keep alive and increase the population of the
            diseased, delinquent, defective, who in all compassion should never
            be brought into the world at all, is futile extravagance. Its a
            luxury to salve the conscience of the present generation for not
            using their brains while heaping up mountains of debts for our
            children’s children’s children to pay.</p>
        <p>We women of today are too content with our conquests to visualize
            fully the dangers of the future.</p>
        <p>Its one thing to have and another thing to hold what you have.
            Women’s freedom is endangered. All that she has fought for and
            gained in <place>Germany</place> has been lost and sacrificed to the war mad
            militarists of that sad country. In <place>Japan</place> and <place>Italy</place> it is the same.
            While women in these countries had not made the same strides in the
            profession and in individual achievement as their sisters in
            Germany, nevertheless what they were aiming for has been stopped and
            they, as a class and sex, have been put back to compete with pack
            animals in the class of servants to man’s comfort and instruments of
            his pleasure.</p>
        <p>Its the day of masculine psychology, dedicated to the needs of
            men.</p>
        <p>Shall women of today be able to hold the freedom they have so far
            gained? Not unless they cease being incubaters for war mad
            dictators. Not unless they, as a Sex, a Class, a United Mass, refuse
            to waste or allow the misuse of the greatest creative force within
            human nature itself--the creative energy--the force and power of
            Motherhood. The control of the power of woman’s creative function.
            Fertility is the main portal to the future. Only through the
            emancipation of her creative energy--Motherhood--can humanity redeem
            itself.</p>
        <p>Civilization is marking time. It is at the cross roads, for in spite
            of all the miraculous achievements of the past century, science,
            philanthropy, statesmanship, has not succeeded in getting humanity
            out of the man made muddle in which the world finds itself today. In
            fact never has our civilization been nearer to the brink of
            destruction and never in the whole history of this planet has
            woman’s place in the creation of the structure of the future been so
            important as it is now today, today! !</p>
        <p>Thanks to the opponents of scientific Birth Control, who keep women
            and men in ignorance of contraception, each day reveals that 50,000
            extra babies survive--150,000 are born, 100,00 die and 50,000
            survive each day. These 50,000 who survive contribute to the
            330,000,000 which have been added to the world’s population of 2,000
            millions since 1920--an increase almost as large in 10 years as the
            population of <place>India</place>.</p>
        <p>The militarists of Germany, Italy and Japan are clamoring for
            population increase for land and land because of population increase
            our babies are starving but give us more babies is the slogan of mad
            men to which women should turn a deaf ear.</p>
        <p>For let us not forget that in all the successful achievements to
            conquer the universe that man’s civilization is in bankruptcy. While
            Successfully spanning the ocean, flinging railroads and airlines
            across continents, circling the globe in the fraction of a second
            with the radio--everything accomplished in the desire to unite
            peoples and nations and to bring them closer together in unity,
            harmony and understanding, yet because of the ceaseless hordes of
            human beings ever multiplying and increase their numbers regardless
            of quality or place or aim--we find mankind goaded on to a frenzy of
            exploitation and war. A war for land--for markets--for power to
            destroy, to subjugate other nations and races--because of hungry
            mouths to feed. Millions of women are crushed under their burden of
            poverty and childbearing. They are all too inarticulate to call
            out--too poor to help themselves--too weak to demand their
            liberties. They look to you to help them. Sympathy is not
            enough--palliative help is not enough--philanthropy is not enough.
            Nothing less can you do than help to set them free--free so that
            they may help themselves and grow in wisdom and enlightenment.</p>
        <p>Instead of a world created and managed by irresponsible hordes in
            hatred and antagonism--let woman hold their present freedom--extend
            it to all women and guide humanity into a future created by all
            embracing Peace on Earth Good Will to Men through the consciousness
            of Birth Control.</p>


    </docBody>
</doc>
