<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Autograph Draft Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/07/07 NC</prepDate><prepDate>CH 7/22/2011 one correction</prepDate><prepDate>2011-11-30 CH correct typo</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="0000-00-00">n.d.</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Standards of Living</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp238619</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>SSC</title>S73:0232</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>This draft was likely written in the late 1930's or early 1940's.</p><index level1="birth control"/><index
            level1="birth control" level2="economic benefits and risks of"
            /><index level1="birth control" level2="socio-economic benefits of"
            /><index level1="birth rate" level2="efforts to reduce"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="population growth and"/><index
            level1="family planning"/>
        <index level1="family size"/>
        <index level1="family size" level2="class-based"/><index
            level1="population" level2="birth control and"/><index
            level1="population growth" level2="standard of living and"
        /></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <p>If the people of the <del>world</del>
            <add><place reg="United States">USA</place></add> will accept
            Asiatic level of living in order to keep the promises of our
            <person reg="Unidentified">President</person> well &amp; good-- a most noble sacrifice(??) But let us
            accept it consciously &amp; know that not we alone but other Nations
            with our food standards must share our noble sentiments so that
            three billion of the <place>Earth</place>'s inhabitants may live on
            a survival quota.-- </p>
        <p>Perhaps this suggestion will arouse <del>the</del> our opponents'
            curiosity let us see how willing they are to tighten their belts to
            see an <add>world</add> increased population decrease our own
            standards of living within the life time of those in this room.</p>
        <p>In other words we ask a people with reserve &amp; resources
            sufficient to yield a permanent basis for a healthy population to
            live joyfully &amp; prosper to sacrifice that condition for
            themselves &amp; their unborn children in exchange for a large
            recklessly concerned population of illiterate miserable, people
            constantly threatened by <add>large</add> families, malnutrition
            &amp; ever increasing poverty.</p>
        <p>USA &amp; <org reg="United Nations">UN</org> should have a Population
            &amp; Eugenic Policy with two experts in the President's Cabinet and
            policy established that there are certain eugenic qualifications for
            reproduction &amp; definitely lay down the law--that these couples
            who cannot meet those qualifications <emph rend="underline">must not
                reproduce</emph>.</p>
        <p>Such qualifications &amp; requirements for reproducing will make the
            children born symbols of honor to our civilization.--</p>
        <p>Another suggestion I once made at a Social tea in the
                <unclear>drawing</unclear> room of <person
                reg="Mesta, Perle Skirvin">Mrs. Mesta</person> in <place reg="Newport, RI">Newport</place>--when
                <person reg="Blank, Mrs.">Mrs. Blank</person> said she objected
            to BC because her lovely niece &amp; brilliant nephew each had only
            one child while all the “<q who="UNK">riff raff</q>” were having dozens--</p>
        <p>I made the gentle suggestion to Mrs. Blank that perhaps her brilliant
            &amp; lovely relatives were also endowed with natural qualities of
                <emph rend="underline">Responsibility</emph> toward educating
            &amp; rearing children they were not able financially to rear
            adequately--Then I said suppose Mrs. Blank instead of your
            contributing large sums of money every year to the community chest
            to orphanages, Red Cross &amp; other charities &amp; Philanthropies
            but gave that total divided equally to your two relatives you might
            find they would be happy to launch a few more babes in this world if
            you agreed that the added offspring, maintenance was secured--</p>
        <p>She said “<q who="UNK">That is a New Idea</q>”-- while a few
            Medical Schools, a very few have classes &amp; lectures on
            contraception. No college or university has a Population Department
            as they have departments of History department a or <add>Dept.</add>
            <unclear>Mar</unclear> etc. yet Population conditions pressure &amp;
            rate of growth are the basis of today's world miseries &amp;
            problems &amp; threaten to grow worse.</p>


    </docBody>
</doc>
