<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011-08-04 NC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2012-04-04 CH Proofed Tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-08 EK</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1952-00-00"><supplied resp="MSPP">1952</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Foreword to <title type="book">Menopause</title></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp238941</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Dorothy Brush Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S77:0070</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger</person> wrote this foreword for "<title>How to
                Survive Menopause by Fifty Women Who Did</title>," an unpublished manuscript written
            by <person reg="Brush, Dorothy">Dorothy Brush</person> and <person reg="Hoffman, H">H.
                Hoffman</person>. For draft versions see <title>MSM</title> S77:0068 and 0069.</p>
        <index level1="menopause"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head rend="underline">FOREWORD</head>
        <p> The menopause is, of course, a normal part of every woman’s life. Nevertheless, while
            her glandular readjustment is, for the majority, unattended by serious discomfort, few
            women are fortunate enough to escape all awareness of the “change” and some, like the
            authors of this book have a very difficult time. Advance in medical knowledge of late
            years has done much to alleviate symptoms. The authors have found that there are other
            aids also, largely discovered by women themselves, some of which may seem trivial but
            which experience has proved helpful. It is their purpose to include in the book
            everything they have discovered of this nature. Medical information has been carefully
            checked by physicians.</p>
        <p>Neither author is a physician but for that very reason an approach on this subject as of
            one woman to another may be illuminating. One is married, the other unmarried.</p>
        <p>I am honored to vouch for their honesty, integrity and seriousness of purpose. I believe
            their book will be encouraging to many women who face the menopause with unnecessary
            fears and dreads.</p>
        <byline>Margaret Sanger</byline>
    </docBody>
</doc>
