<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article ">
<mepHeader>
<prepDate>2003/07/02 SB</prepDate>
<prepDate>2003-07-28 CH</prepDate>
<prepDate>2004/07/01 CH</prepDate>
<prepDate>2004/07/26 CH</prepDate>
<prepDate>2014-03-04 CH correct regs and other</prepDate>
<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
<docDate value="1921-11-00">Nov 1921</docDate>
<docTitle>
<titlePart>Impressions of the Amsterdam Conference</titlePart>
</docTitle>
<idno>msp238949</idno>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl><title>Birth Control Review</title> Nov. 1921, 11</bibl>
<bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S70:922</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
<respStmt>
<resp/>
<name id="INBCD">International Neo-Malthusian Bureau of Correspondence and Defence</name>
</respStmt>
</mepHeader>
<headNote resp="MSPP"><index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="international"/>
<index level1="International Medical Congress on Contraceptives (1921)"/>
<index level1="Netherlands" level2="birth control clinics and leagues"/>
</headNote>
<docBody>
<head>Impressions of the Amsterdam Conference</head>
<byline>By Margaret Sanger</byline>
<p>The first great truth that I bring home from the international congress on contraceptives, held
in <place reg="Amsterdam, Netherlands">Amsterdam</place> August 29-30, is this: that our movement in
the theoretical aspects is far in advance of the practical phase. There was unanimous agreement upon
principles,--upon the economic, the social and the hygienic, the political and international
necessity for Birth Control. But the practical methods and devices offered by the various delegates
from practically every country in <place>Europe</place> were new and untried by other delegates, and
questioned by them. Each country offered its individual method which was unknown to the rest of the
delegates.</p>
<p>One of the most instructive and enlightening phases of the conference was the opportunity it
offered to delegates to visit the clinics, where demonstrations of the various methods were given
under the auspices of the <org reg="Nieuw Malthusiaansche Bond">Dutch League</org> and proved of
practical values. They vindicate our claim for clinics in all countries.</p>
<p>The conference took place in the Hotel Hollandia, in Amsterdam, on Aug. 29th and 30th, and was
attended by <person reg="Drysdale, Charles Vickery">Dr.</person> and Mrs. <person
reg="Drysdale, Bessie Ingham">Drysdale</person> and Dr. <person reg="Haire, Norman">Haire</person>
(<place>England</place>), Mme. <person reg="de Beer-Meijers">de Beer-Meijers</person>, Mynheer and
Mme. <person reg="Kiersch de Jung, Madame">Kiersch de Jung</person>, Mr. <person reg="DeVries, Jan"
>de Vries</person>, Mr. <person reg="Cate, S. Ten">S. Ten Cate</person> and Dr. <person
reg="Risselada, Dr.">Risselada</person> (<place reg="Netherlands">Holland</place>), and Dr. <person
reg="Goldstein, E.">E. Goldstein</person> (<place>Germany</place>). Mr. <person
reg="Giroud, Gabriel">G. Hardy</person> (<place>France</place>, treasurer of the Bureau, and Dr.
<person reg="Rutgers, Johannes">Rutgers</person> (late hon. sec.), wrote expressing regret at being
unable to come, and others were prevented from doing so by various engagements.</p>
<p>A very useful and full discussion on all the best known preventive devices took place, and
decisions were arrived at concerning the most effective devices and the technique connected with
them. Demonstrations were kindly given by Mme. Kiersch de Jung and Mme. <person
reg="van Huevel, Mme.">van Huevel</person>, two of the ladies trained by Dr. Rutgers and on the
Dutch League's list of helpers, to the medical and lady members of the conference on the fitting of
certain preventive devices. A cordial vote of thanks was accorded to Mme. de Beer-Meijers at the
conclusion of the conference, for her greatly appreciated arrangements, and it was decided that a
full International Neo-Malthusian Congress should be held in the last week of August in next
year.</p>
<p>The following resolution was unanimously passed at the conference, at the instance of M.G.
Hardy:</p>
<q who="INMBCD"><p rend="blockquote">This conference of the <org>International Neo-Malthusian Bureau
of Correspondence and Defence</org> wishes to register a strong protest against the laws and
measures repressing neo-Malthusian or Birth Control propaganda which have existed or recently been
enacted in various countries, and against the prosecutions which have been instituted against such
propagandists. It wishes to point out that such propaganda, provided that it is carried out with due
regard to public decency and on eugenic lines, is of the utmost value to every nation as a means of
reducing poverty and social unrest, and of improving the quality and viability of the race.</p></q>
<p>It was felt that the conclusions arrived at would be of great service in the preparation of
practical handbooks or leaflets, but that several points needed further study and settlement, and
various members undertook to obtain information on these points with the view of bringing them
before a committee on contraceptive devices, which it was decided should meet at the time of the
International Congress.</p>
</docBody>
</doc>
