<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2003-07/10 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/26 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/08/09 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007/06/276 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2001/03/11 CH Entered corrections suggested by Andy Carloff.</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011-11-30 CH typos</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-01 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1918-11-00">Nov 1918</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>An Open Letter To Alfred E. Smith</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp239056</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title>, Nov. 1918. 3-4</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S70:803</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="ERVCH">Ervin, Charles V.</name>
            <name id="SMIAL">Smith, Alfred E.</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="Smith, Alfred E."/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="New York "/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="socio-economic benefits of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="opposition to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/>
        <index level1="Ervin, Charles W."/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>AN OPEN LETTER TO ALFRED E. SMITH</head>
        <p>HON. <person reg="Smith, Alfred E.">ALFRED E. SMITH</person>, <emph rend="italics"
                >President of the <org reg="New York City Board of Aldermen">Board of
                Alderman</org>, City Hall,</emph>
            <place reg="New York, NY">New York</place>.</p>
        <p>MY DEAR MR. SMITH:-–</p>
        <p>On September 26th, I addressed to you the following letter: "The subject of birth control
            is of vital importance to the women voters who are casting their first vote in the
            coming election of this state.</p>
        <p>For the benefit of the thousands who are interested in this subject will you not state
            your position regarding it, inasmuch as Governor <person reg="Whitman, Charles S."
                >Whitman</person> has already gone on record for a Commission to investigate the
            necessity of changing the anti-birth control laws.</p>
        <p>I will greatly appreciate hearing from you at your earliest possible convenience."</p>
        <signed>Very truly yours, [<emph rend="italics">Signed</emph>] <person
                reg="Sanger, Margaret">MARGARET SANGER</person>.</signed>
        <p>At the same time I addressed a letter in identical language to <person
                reg="Ervin, Charles W.">Charles W. Ervin</person>, Socialist nominee for governor.
            Mr. Ervin has replied as follows:</p>
        <q who="ERVCH">
            <dateline>NEW YORK CITY <date value="1918-10-02">October 2, 1918</date>.</dateline>
            <p> MY DEAR MRS. SANGER:–- </p>
            <p> Replying to your letter of September 26th, it is almost needless to state that I
                think that woman should be mistress of her own life, both economically and
                physically, and further, I think it is a crime for children to be brought into the
                world unless there is positive assurance that they can be given the best physical,
                moral and mental surroundings from birth until they blossom into manhood and
                womanhood. </p>
            <p> Believing this, I therefore am certainly in favor of a commission to investigate the
                necessity of changing the anti-birth control laws. I would, however, be most
                emphatically opposed to having this commission composed of a majority of men, but,
                on the contrary, I should just as emphatically favor the appointment of a majority
                of women on such a commission. </p>
            <signed>Very Very Truly, [<emph rend="italics">Signed</emph>] CHARLES W.
            ERVIN.</signed></q>
        <p>Thus far I have received from you no reply to my query in behalf of the women who have
            written to me asking where the various candidates for governor stand upon the question
            of Birth Control.</p>
        <p>I have noted, however, your interview in the <title rend="italics" type="journal">New
                York American</title> of October 13th. In that interview, you declare yourself in
            favor of these policies and measures, among others: </p>
        <p>LAWS REGULATING HOURS of employment for men, women and children.<lb/>Extension of
            Workingmen's Compensation law to include "occupational diseases."<lb/>Extension of labor
            laws "<q who="SMIAL">to take care of women and children forced into new lines of
                endeavor because of the war.</q>"<lb/>Minimum wage for women and
            children.<lb/>Widow's pensions.<lb/>Maternity insurance.<lb/></p>
        <p>Under present conditions, these are excellent palliatives, but are you aware, Mr. Smith,
            that they are only palliatives?</p>
        <p>And are you aware that they touch only superficially "the solution of the problems
            affecting men, women and children?"</p>
        <p>If we are to judge a candidate upon a few pleasant sounding superficialities, uttered
            with the unction born of the necessities of a political campaign, many of the women of
            New York would doubtless be moved to vote for you. But in these days an awakened
            womanhood is beginning to pay attention to the fundamentals. We are more interested in
            the removal of causes than in the application of palliatives. We care less for the
            multiplication of hospitals than we do for the prevention of sickness and wounds.</p>
        <p>Laws regulating the hours of employment for men, women and children are all very well,
            Mr. Smith, but do you know that most of the women and children now forced into toil in
            the state of New York would not be there, war or no war, if it were not for the fact
            that the family of the average workingman is too large for the husband to support?</p>
        <p>Are you aware that the high infant death rate is due principally to the family too large
            to afford proper living quarters, proper food and proper physical attention? Do you know
            that each year 300,000 children in the United States die of diseases due to poverty and
            neglect? Are you aware that there are upon the statute books certain "dark age" laws
            which make it a crime to convey to the over-burdened mothers the knowledge by which she
            can limit her family to the size which makes it possible to give it proper care, proper
            food, proper clothing and proper medical attention?</p>
        <p>Are you aware that the well-to-do and more highly educated almost universally practice
            family limitation, more popularly and accurately known as Birth Control, while the wives
            of workingmen are denied this knowledge?</p>
        <p>And are you aware that the cost of the care of the insane alone in New York state last
            year was $8,320,000, while the economic loss, due to insanity, according to the annual
            report of the <org reg="New York State Hospital Commission">State Hospital
                Commission</org>, was $35,000,000?</p>
        <p> Do you know that most of the 37,069 persons in the state institutions for the mentally
            defective, came from large families reared in poverty? And do you know that unchecked
            breeding of these defectives has already overcrowded the state institutions to the
            extent of 10,000 persons?</p>
        <p>Are you aware that the repeal of the statutes prohibiting the dissemination of the
            knowledge of Birth Control would in a few years rid the state of this burden, to say
            nothing of freeing women of the most abject of all forms of slavery, that of unwilling
            motherhood?</p>
        <p> And do you know that there are hundreds of thousands of women in New York crying for the
            knowledge which shall enable them to have smaller but healthier, better-cared for
            families?</p>
        <p> We are not asking you at this time to go on record in favor of Birth Control. But we are
            asking you to go on record in favor of a commission to ascertain, scientifically,
            accurately and without prejudice, whether under present economic conditions the
            unchecked birth rates in certain elements of society is responsible largely for the need
            of prisons and institutions for the mentally defective. We are asking you to pledge
            yourself to an impartial commission to ascertain the relation between too large families
            and the health and death rates. We are asking you to name a commission which shall
            discover whether the repeal of the anti-Birth Control statutes will in a few years
            remedy these conditions.</p>
        <p>Maternal insurance is, after all, but small relief to women whose lives have been wrecked
            by too frequent childbearing. Workingmen's compensation does not go far toward the
            support of a family of five or six or seven. You may find that Birth Control, which
            prevents the multiplication of children who can not have proper food, proper clothing
            nor proper shelter will do more to solve the problem than even strict child labor laws
            and regulation, which we all favor.</p>
        <p>I am well aware, as are all women who have devoted their attention to this cause, that it
            is not the custom of candidates for office to go deep into the fundamental causes of
            intolerable conditions. But, whatever you may think of it, Mr. Smith, the women of New
            York know where the trouble lies. They know that legislative palliatives mean little to
            women, until they are freed form this most degrading servitude. They know whence come
            the inmates of prisons and reformatories, the inmates of institutions for defectives.
            And they know whence comes the child labor evil.</p>
        <p>Governor Whitman, prior to America's entry into the war, promised a state commission to
            investigate the need of the repeal of the anti-Birth Control statutes. Charles W. Ervin,
            Socialist nominee for governor, has gone one step further. He has pledged himself to a
            commission of which a majority shall be women.</p>
        <p>In behalf of the women who have written to me, in behalf of the thousands of New York
            women who believe in making the knowledge of Birth Control accessible to the wives and
            mothers of toilers, I ask you again, Mr. Smith, where do you stand upon this matter so
            vital to the well being of hundreds of thousands of New York women, and therefore so
            vital to the well being of society?</p>
        <signed>Very truly yours, [<emph rend="italics">Signed</emph>]MARGARET SANGER.</signed>
    </docBody>
</doc>
