<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2003-07-07 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/02 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/08/13 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-25 EK clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1920-07-00">Jul 1920</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Clinics the Solution</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp239112</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Birth Control Review</title>, July 1920, pp. 6-8</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Smith Collehe Collections</title>, S70:843</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>This article was introduced by a short recap of
        Sanger's trip to <place>England</place> by the editor.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues" level3="need for"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="opposition to"/>
        <index level1="Church of England" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="England" level2="birth control clinics and leagues in"/>
        <index level1="labor movement" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="Malthusian League (British)"/>
        <index level1="Malthusian theory" level2="opposition to"/>
        <index level1="Marxism and Marxists" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="speaking tours" level3="1920 (England)"/>
        <index level1="Stopes, Marie Carmichael"/>
        <index level1="Women's Cooperative Guild (England)"/>
        <index level1="woman suffrage" level2="MS on"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Clinics the Solution</head>
        <byline rend="italics">By Margaret Sanger</byline>
        <dateline><place reg="London, England">London</place>.</dateline>
        <p>Clinics -- Clinics in which women can be given direct and individual
            instruction in contraceptive methods, are the solution of the
            problem of getting the Birth Control message to those who most need
            it. Theories and philosophies are quite all right for the educators.
            Printed matter will carry the message to those who have been
            educated. But the woman who has been denied such advantages, and
            whose toil so thoroughly saps her energies that she cannot absorb
            what is written in the simplest fashion, needs personal instruction.
            She must be told by word of mouth and shown by demonstration what to
            do and how to do it. Otherwise much of our labor, so far as direct
            results go, is in vain. The answer is clinics.</p>
        <p>I had these facts deeply impressed upon me once more, when on May
            28th here in <place reg="London, England">London</place>, I delivered one of a series of lectures before
            a branch of the <org>Woman's Co-operative Guild</org>. This
            organization is much interested in Birth Control. Its membership is
            by far the most intelligent and wide-awake of any body of women
            workers here. Despite the fact that the <org>Malthusian League</org>
            has distributed many thousands of leaflets carefully setting forth
            practical information regarding contraceptives, and <person
                reg="Stopes, Marie Charmichael">Marie Carmichael Stopes</person>
            has distributed other thousands of similar pamphlets from her own
            pen, these women were not satisfied. They demanded the information
            from the platform and it was given. </p>
        <p>If pamphlets could have met their needs fully, those needs would have
            been met by the leaflets of the Malthusians and these by Dr. Stopes,
            herself an advocate of clinics. But, weary from their day's work,
            these women found even pamphlets unsatisfactory. They wanted to be
            told by word of mouth. More, they need direct instruction at the
            hands of persons competent to give such instruction. They need
            clinics.</p>
        <p>Clear-sighted individuals in <place>England</place> are quick to see
            the necessity of Birth Control clinics when the subject is presented
            to them. When I spoke at the university town of <place
                reg="Cambridge, England">Cambridge</place>, Mr. <person
                reg="Porter, Noel">Noel Porter</person>, a friend of the
            movement, opened his home for the meeting when it was discovered
            that there was no hall vacant for the date. This gave him an
            opportunity to invite specially many persons of influence and
            importance, including many who had never heard of Birth Control as a
            solution for social problems. The meeting was highly enthusiastic
            and successful. When it was suggested that a clinic be opened at
            once in one of the midland towns where women are killing themselves
            and their unborn children with poisonous drugs, in order to prevent
            the birth of unwanted babies, the audience responded eagerly.
            Contributions amounting to ℒ60, or $300, were made on the spot, as
            the nucleus of a fund to establish the first Birth Control clinic in
            England. </p>
        <p>Several factors have operated to prevent the principle of England and
            especially the working people, who need family limitations most,
            from getting the full benefit of the efforts of the Malthusian
            League, and had it not been for the powerful deterring influence of
            some of these factors, there would not only be plenty of Birth
            Control clinics in England today, but there would certainly also be
            a far different state of society. Some of these factors are worth
            considering for the light they will shed upon problems encountered
            by the movement elsewhere.</p>
        <p>The Malthusian League which was founded in 1879, has definite aims
            and principles which, if they had been applied, would have long
            since brought about a better order of society. Its program, however,
            is in opposition to that of the Labor Movement, and as a
            consequence, the working people, to whom the League's message is
            addressed, and who need it most, have been reluctant to accept the
            Malthusian principles.</p>
        <p>The attempt of <person reg="Marx, Kael">Marx</person> to refute the
            theory of <person reg="Malthus, Thomas">Malthus</person> has also
            interfered with the beneficial effects of the work of the League.
            There seems to have been a bitter quarrel among the economists,
            especially in <place>Germany</place> and England, growing out of the
            attitude of Marx toward the Malthusian principle. Judging the matter
            now, it seems safe to say that but for the apparent refutation by
            Marx, the doctrine of family limitation applied to social problems
            would have ere this produced a new order of society.</p>
        <p>Happily, a change is apparent now.</p>
        <p>Many of the old Marxians who, ten years ago, believed absolutely that
            Marx had refuted Malthus and that "supply" was not so important if
            sufficient attention were given to "distribution," have changed
            their views. They are cautiously but courageously admitting part, at
            least, of the Malthusian principles.</p>
        <p>The state has not stood in the way of the advance of the Birth
            Control movement in England as it has in <place reg="United States"
                >America</place>, but the church has exercised a powerful
            opposing influence.</p>
        <p>There have been no vicious laws in England to brand the communication
            of information regarding contraceptives as a crime. On the other
            hand, the influence of the church, which still has its tentacles
            deeply imbedded in the psychology of the English working people, has
            been so strong that it is only within the past few years that such
            information has been given openly.</p>
        <p>There is a certain religious attitude of mind among the workers which
            those in power well understand and make use of. They have taken
            advantage of it to sway the English worker as they could not have
            swayed a body of people of like intelligence in any other country in
            the world. An example of what is happening is afforded by <person
                reg="Lansbury, George"> George Lansbury</person>, editor of the
                <title type="newspaper">London Herald</title>, one of the most
            powerful of all labor papers. He lectures and debates upon such
            subjects as "<title>The Church and the Social Crisis</title>,"
            hoping to influence the church to take part in the Labor Movement.
            Naturally when those of influence in the Labor Movement are anxious
            for the support of the church, they are not going to antagonize
            churchmen who oppose Birth Control by pushing that idea forward.
            This is particularly true since the Labor Movement has not
            apparently awakened to Birth Control while the church, as a whole,
            has opposed it.</p>
        <p>The suffragists have not yet given the cause of Birth Control the
            support that they might have given. These women who have created
            world-wide fame for themselves and their cause are mostly mothers of
            small families or have no children at all. They have not as yet made
            it their task to share with their sisters who toil, the information
            by which they have limited their own families. The men workers, like
            the suffragists, have fought their own battles, but they have
            overlooked the basic problems of their wives. Thus, in England as in
            America, the women workers and wives of workers have been forced to
            bear children as fast as the children could arrive. Church, state,
            the Labor Movement and their own more fortunate sisters have alike
            left them to the doom of enforced and excessive maternity.</p>
        <p>It is true that they have been afforded hundreds of palliative
            measures to help them bear this burden cheerfully. Society must not
            hear their groans. Most of the working women are figuratively
            enfolded in these agencies and the guardians in charge have
            developed the instinct of warding off anything not pleasing to the
            delicate ears of the upper classes. The result is a "moral
            protection" that has robbed the working woman of the knowledge that
            would have given her freedom from poverty and unwilling
            motherhood.</p>
        <p>In spite of all this, the natural intelligence of the English women
            workers is making itself felt. The economic pressure, is helping to
            make workmen's wives think. As they begin to think, they begin to
            ask insistently what they can do to prevent bringing to birth
            children who are not wanted and who die in infancy.</p>
        <p>These women are the hope of England. They want to help themselves.
            They want to be free to love the children they have. They want to
            take some part in life other than as slaves. And it is among such
            women that I have been working.</p>
        <p>The English people need a stirring up of interest in
            fundamentals,--particularly in Brith Control. The church, however,
            stands porter at the door of light and it is hard to open that door
            and let the light through without conflict. Moreover, the retrograde
            report of the <org reg="National Birth-Rate Commission">Birth Rate
                Commission</org> and the fact that the war has been over but a
            short while are made excuses for the plea that this is not the best
            time to put forward the issue of Birth Control.</p>
        <p>The press wails that "<q who="UNK">only the poor are having children,
                while the middle classes are remaining stationary in
                numbers.</q>" Recommendations of emigration and other
            reactionary remedies for overcrowding among the poor have aroused no
            enthusiasm among the workers, but the subject of Birth Control
            remains taboo among the workers themselves. The Malthusian League
            has had as its subject, mainly, the education of the legislative and
            professional classes, and of the thinkers. Considering these facts,
            in addition to the opposition of the church, and the indifference
            and opposition of Socialist and Labor leaders, it is remarkable that
            the Malthusian movement has attained its present stage.</p>
        <p>Every day, however, brings fresh proof to the advocates of Birth
            Control that they are right. Every day brings evidence that the
            clearest thinkers are coming to agree with them.</p>
        <p>The suffragists are still tinkering with politics or the <org>League
                of Nations</org>, but could these women, the most courageous and
            fearless of the earth, be aroused for Birth Control, they would make
            short work of the obstacles in the path of woman's freedom. They are
            cautious and slow going, but they, too, are thinking this way, and
            when once the political habit of thought has been cast off and a
            fundamental human interest is taken up, there is no doubt that Birth
            Control is the idea that they will set themselves to put into the
            social fabric. </p>
        </docBody>
</doc>
