<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011-08-04 NC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2012-03-12 CH proofed tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-08 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1954-01-00">Jan 1954</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Happy Birthday</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp239110</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">News of Population and Birth Control</title> No. 21, Jan.
                1954, pp. 1.</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S72:0880</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="birth control" level2="international conferences on"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Happy Birthday</head>
        <p>This modest international monthly bulletin is two years old today. It has certainly lived
            up to its title. At the <org reg="International Conference on Planned Parenthood, 3rd"
                >Third International Planned Parenthood Conference</org> in <place
                reg="Bombay, India">Bombay</place> friends, delegates and sponsors truly from
            “around the world” were enthusiastic and grateful for this regular source of news and
            names of persons active in population and planned parenthood work. Another joyous,
            thankful expression was for sending the News free of charge, which, owing to
            difficulties of exchange, would otherwise deprive friends and workers of this condensed
            yet “inspiring” monthly.</p>
        <p>Small in volume, but “meaty” in content, our <title type="journal">News</title> is read
            from page to page with high interest and the growing conviction that one belongs to this
            world movement. An <person reg="Unknown">Indian reader</person> has said it was like “<q
                who="UNK">a well-boiled and well-flavoured stew, pleasing to the palate and greatly
                appetizing.</q>” Another comment made time and time again at both the Bombay and
                <place reg="Stockholm, Sweden">Stockholm</place>
            <org reg="International Conference on Planned Parenthood, 4th">Conference</org>s was
            that the bulletin “<q who="UNK">exuded</q>” progress, confidence and enthusiasm.</p>
        <p>We can all lift up our voices in thanks to <person reg="Brush, Dorothy Hamilton">Dorothy
                Brush</person>, the editor, whose love for this work pulsates throughout each issue
            to all who read it. May the <title type="journal">News</title> continue to “increase and
            multiply” to the far ends of the world for years and years to come!</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
