<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011-07-15 NC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/11/14 CH corrected doc type.</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-30 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1944-05-00"><supplied resp="MSPP">May 1944</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Tomorrow's Children</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp239372</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Records of PPFA, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S72:387</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="UPHJO">Upham, John H. J.</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
            <name id="FORTU">Fortune</name>
            <name id="FAIHE">Fairchild, Henry Pratt</name>
            <name id="GER">German</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>No published version has been found.</p>
        <index level1="Sachs, Sadie (story)"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Italy" level2="overpopulation and"/>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="overpopulation and"/>
        <index level1="Germany" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="China" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to" level3="international"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues" level3="in US"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="medical community and"/>
        <index level1="physicians" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="Planned Parenthood Federation of America"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Tomorrow's Children</head>
        <p>“<q who="UPHJO">An award of $500 will be given in 1944 to the scientist who has made the
                most significant contribution to research in human fertility--either in the control
                of conception or the correction of sterility.</q>”</p>
        <p>This announcement of the <person reg="Lasker, Mary Woodard">Mary Woodard Lasker</person>
            Award made recently by <person reg="Upham, John H. J.">Dr. J. H. J. Upham</person>,
            President of the <org>Planned Parenthood Federation of America</org> brought a long
            forgotten picture to my mind. I was back in the year 1912 in a <place reg="Brooklyn, NY"
                >Brooklyn</place> tenement where I had just watched a <person reg="Sachs, Sadie"
                >young woman</person> die needlessly. She had three young children, whom she and her
            husband supported with difficulty. The advent of another child would mean deeper
            poverty, worse circumstances for the half starved youngsters she had already born. Twice
            she had taken the situation into her own hands. After the first self-induced abortion
            she had begged me for knowledge I was unable then to give her--how to space her babies,
            how to gain a little respite to restore her health, to save a little money, so that the
            next baby wouldn’t be a dreadful burden to all of them. The doctor’s advice had been
            that still given cruelly by too many backwoods doctors, “<q who="UNK">Have <person
                    reg="Sachs, Jake">Jake</person> sleep on the roof</q>”. It was no joke to this
            poor woman. As I folded her hands cross her breast, still hearing her pleading voice in
            my ears, I made a solemn vow. I was resolved to seek out the root of the evil that had
            destroyed this woman, and so many others, to do something to change the destiny of
            mothers whose miseries were vast as the sky.</p>
        <p>That was the beginning of the “birth control movement”. The announcement by Dr. Upham of
            the award gave me a quick glimpse of how that movement has widened its scope, how
            far-reaching it has become. Primarily of course it is still concerned with helping
            others mothers to space their babies healthfully, to make this service part of public
            health in all <place reg="United States">states of the union</place>. But beyond that
            the planned parenthood movement, whose very name indicates its broader range, means
            better complete maternity cure. It is a part of social welfare, an aid to the minister
            and the psychiatrist in marriage counseling; it is education for doctors young and old
            in contraceptive techniques. Also it offers aid to the childless couples who want
            children to obtain the assistance of medical experts. Some of the more than 800 child
            spacing services in the country, not only give sterility referral service, but advice
            concerning the adoption of children. This is planned parenthood in its fullest sense. No
            one knows better than I the long slow struggle to achieve this recognition in the worlds
            of medicine, of sociology, of psychiatry, of religion.</p>
        <p>Less than thirty years ago, the first birth control clinic in America was opened by my
                <person reg="Byrne, Ethel Higgins">sister</person>, Miss <person
                reg="Mindell, Fania">Fannie Mindell</person> and myself in Brownsville, Brooklyn,
            and immediately closed, with all three of us arrested for “Maintaining a public
            nuisance”. Today seven states have made child spacing part of their state health program
            with several other states considering this move.</p>
        <p>Not until 1937 did the <org>American Medical Association</org> officially accept birth
            control as an integral part of medical practice and education. Since that time however,
            medical acceptance has increased so much that more than 100,000 physicians, nurses and
            medical schools have received copies of Dr. <person reg="Dickinson, Robert Latou">R. L.
                Dickinson</person>’s “<title>Techniques of Conception Control</title>” at their own
            request, Although courses in medical schools were cut sharply since the war began, 45%
            of the Grade A medical schools were beginning to give students some instruction in
            methods of child spacing.</p>
        <p>The Federation has also become an associate member of the <org>National Health
                Council</org>, taking its place with the organizations for the control of
            tuberculosis, cancer and heart disease in the field of preventive medicine.</p>
        <p>One of the most significant advances planned parenthood has made in recognition by
            physicians is a report issued by the <org
                reg="American Medical Association, Council of Pharmacy and Chemistry">Council of
                Pharmacy and Chemistry</org>, the first of its kind for the medical profession in
            the <title type="journal">A.M.A. Journal</title>, establishing standards for reliable
            and effective contraceptives. A study <add>of mechanical devices</add> by the <org
                reg="American Medical Association, Council on Physical Therapy">Council on Physical
                Therapy</org> has also been begun. This is a significant beginning of intelligent
            regulation for what <title type="journal">Fortune</title> once designated as “<q
                who="FORTU">a 250,000,000 legitimate and semi-legitimate industry.</q></p>
        <p>One of the most important functions of the Federation is now a widespread educational
            program. It is amazing how many people still speak of planned parenthood scornfully as
                “<q who="UNK">killing babies</q>”, “<q who="UNK">keeping babies from being
            born</q>”, as negative “<q who="UNK">prevention</q>”. To bring the truth to people the
            Federation has available for distribution more than 100 pamphlets and reprints, directed
            toward physicians, social workers, toward minister, toward women in industry, toward the
            average mother. One of the most interesting of the pamphlets is called “<title
                type="book">Better Health for Thirteen Million</title>” including the results of a
            two year experiment to demonstrate the need of child spacing for Negro mothers to help
            reduce pitifully high death rates of mothers and newborn babies, to help raise health
            and living standards of depressed members of this race.</p>
        <p>There are psychiatric pamphlets written for lay use to demonstrate the emotional harm to
            an individual and through him to society of the status of being “unwanted.”</p>
        <p>Requests for aid and literature from professional groups in 1943 alone came from 1,959
            clergymen, from 3,216 social workers, from almost 50,000 doctors, and 19,295 nurses.</p>
        <p>Results of a recent <title type="journal">Fortune</title> Poll have been publicized to
            show the ever increasing recognition of and desire for planned parenthood among American
            women. Of the women in child bearing ages questioned, <del>84%</del>
            <add>84.9%</add> wanted child spacing made part of public health and of the Roman
            Catholic women questioned 69% declared themselves favoring planned parenthood.</p>
        <p>Increasing stress is being laid on that very positive phase of planned parenthood, help
            for the one in ten childless couples who believe themselves to be sterile. The <org
                reg="Margaret Sanger Research Bureau">Margaret Sanger Bureau</org>, oldest in the
            country, which recently celebrated its twentieth anniversary, has been giving sterility
            referral service since it opened, estimating that an average of two women a day have
            asked for this advice. The women are referred to doctors or clinics within their means
            and the bureau keeps a record of successes and failures. Almost all the happy women who
            ultimately bear babies telephone the Bureau and report the joyous event, for mutual
            congratulations.</p>
        <p>Dr. <person reg="Stone, Abraham">Abraham Stone</person>, Medical Director of the Bureau
            and author, with his late wife, <person reg="Stone, Hannah Mayer">Hannah Stone</person>
            of the Perennial best-seller, “<title type="book">A Marriage Manual</title>” had a
            recent request which he believes tops everything in unique requests from childless
            couples. A young woman whose husband is fighting in <place>Italy</place> wrote asking if
            it would be scientifically and medically possible for her to be artificially inseminated
            by her husband, so that she could bear a baby in his absence and be sure of having a
            child by him in the event he never returned to her. Unfortunately science and public
            opinion have not advanced sufficiently to help the young woman and her soldier
            husband.</p>
        <p>There was another incident at the annual meeting of the Federation last January at the
                <org reg="Waldorf-Astoria Hotel">Waldorf-Astoria</org> in <place reg="New York, NY"
                >New York</place>. During the impressive luncheon meeting one of the doctors was
            paged and called from the dining room. Reporters were eager to know if she was called
            for the birth of an infant. Later she said it was even more planned parenthood than
            that. A sterility patient believed the ovulation was occurring and wanted to be
            artificially inseminated immediately, feeling that she couldn’t even wait for the doctor
            to finish her luncheon.</p>
        <p>It has been estimated that in spite of the difficulties, the expanse and frequent
            failures of this last resort in the case of a fertile wife and sterile but acquiescent
            husband, there are many more than 10,000 babies in this country, carefully guarded in
            secrecy who owe their much wanted existances to artificial insemination.</p>
        <p>Dr. Stone who is receiving registrations for the contestants for the Lasker award said
            that among those who have applied are many outstanding scientists who have worked in the
            field of sterility as well as contraception. The idea of the award is to recognize with
            a prize any important scientific contribution to our understanding of the physiology or
            control of reproduction. He doesn’t expect an improved contraceptive, although that
            would be welcome indeed, but primarily an increase of our understanding of the processes
            involved in reproduction, which might aid us in controlling human fertility, either
            through prevention of conception or cure of sterility.</p>
        <p>An example of the type of knowledge that might come to light through the contest, is the
            recent application of the temperature curve to determine the exact period of ovulation.
            Knowledge of the exact time of ovulation can be helpful both for those who wish to
            control conception and also for those who want to become pregnant. The contest should
            also help further research in a subject which has always lagged behind other major
            branches of preventive medicine in research. This has been due to pressures, to
            misunderstanding of motives, to the general hush hush attitude of anything pertaining to
            sex.</p>
        <p>The date for the award has been extended to December 31st, 1944. Any scientist anywhere
            in the world will be eligible. In addition, a number of plaques will be granted to
            others who have done important work in this field, to signalize their achievements. A
            distinguished panel of medical men who will judge the works submitted, include, besides
            Dr. Stone, Dr. <person reg="Pierson, Richard N.">Richard N. Pierson</person>, Dr. Robert
            L. Dickinson, Dr. <person reg="Eastman, Nicholson J.">Nicholson J. Eastman</person>, and
            Dr. <person reg="Portis, S. Bernard">S. Bernard Portis</person>.</p>
        <p>Another contest closing June 15th, and sponsored by the <org>Virginia League for Planned
                Parenthood</org> emphasizes a very important function of planned parenthood, the
            need for it as part of our world post-war planning, the need to bring it to those
            fast-producing countries which are continually threatening to bursting their borders and
            being brought back in check by famine, disaster and war. The subject of this essay
            contest is “<title type="article">Planned Parenthood: its Contribution to Lasting Peace</title>”.</p>
        <p>It will avail us nothing in the end if we bring help to mothers and fathers in America,
            if we maintain a favorable balance between population and resources here, and allow
            other countries, particularly those in the far east to go on breeding indiscriminately.
            The men who dictate the peace terms will have to remember this, to compel
                <place>Japan</place>, <place>Germany</place> and Italy to control their birthrates,
            to prevent the three nations from throwing the world into war again in another twenty
            years with the cry of “<foreign lang="GER">lebensraum</foreign>”.</p>
        <p>The Japanese militarists as far back as 1921 were fighting dissemination of birth control
            information, fearful that a lowered birth rate would block their plans for war.</p>
        <p>Help must be given to <place>China</place>, to <place>India</place>, to prevent the
            horror of famine and suffering. The need for such effort will be even greater once
            industrialization and subsequent improvement in sanitation reduce the high mortality and
            morbidity rates and in turn contribute to excessive population increases.</p>
        <p>It is true that some contraceptive supplies are being sent even now to stricken lands for
            the relief of war-weary mothers there. And all indices point to the fact that among
            thoughtful leaders of the postwar era there will be increasing awareness of the need of
            making birth control available through national and international health programs
            directed toward safeguarding the health and lives of the children to be born into the
            next world generation.</p>
        <p>The 1943 annual meeting of the Federation stressed this fact, with the dinner theme
                “<title type="article">Is Overpopulation a Threat to Permanent Peace</title>”, the discussion
            including America’s leasing demographers, among them, Dr. <person
                reg="Fairchild, Henry Pratt">Henry Pratt Fairchild</person>, of <org>New York
                University</org>, Dr. <person reg="Thompson, Warren S.">Warren S. Thompson</person>
            of the <org>Scripps Foundation of Research in Population Problems</org>, Dr. <person
                reg="Notestein, Frank">Frank Notestein</person> of <org>Princeton
            University</org>.</p>
        <p>Dr. Fairchild called attention to the graphic example of what havoc uncontrolled human
            reproduction can create. “<q who="FAIHE">The recent horror in India shows all too
                clearly what can happen in a country where an uncontrolled birth rate is out of
                proportion to the country’s resources. In ten years India has added 52,000,000
                people to its population. The best developed and resourceful country in the world
                could not experience such an increase as that without facing extreme disaster
                whenever an emergency situation such as that created by the present war,
            arose.</q>”</p>
        <p>It was further pointed out that <place reg="Soviet Union">Soviet Russia</place> enjoyed
            the highest white birth rate in the world, despite the fact that contraceptive
            information has never been denied to any of its people, and in fact that the people of
            Russia are encouraged to plan their families intelligently. <place reg="Netherlands"
                >Holland</place> and <place>Sweden</place> and other forward-looking countries were
            demonstrating the advantages of freely given contraceptive advice when war descended on
            them.</p>
        <p>The vision which began that day at dawn in a tenement, with the needless sacrifice of a
            young woman who had begged for the knowledge that was her right, won’t be fully realized
            until every mother in the world is given the right to plan her children intelligently
            and healthfully.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
