<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published statement">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2012-03-23 AW</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2012-03-28 CH proofed tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-02 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1959-01-00">1959 Jan</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>The President's Message</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp239318</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person> and <person
                    reg="How-Martyn, Edith">Edith How-Marytn</person>, <title type="book">Around the
                    World News of Population and Birth Control</title> [71] Jan. 1959, p. 1</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S72:0982</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="birth control" level2="international"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="international"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>The President's Message</head>
        <p>I send my greetings and best wishes for 1959 to all our friends and co-workers. As we
            begin this New Year, I survey the progress our movement has made around the world and
            find much to praise. Nations are making birth control services part of their National
            policy, and of their Public Health and Welfare programmes. Better methods of
            contraception, the birth control pill or tablet for oral use, and hormone contraceptives
            for injection are coming into widespread use. So I find many advances about which we all
            can be pleased.</p>
        <p>While much remains to be done as our movement must reach out to every part of the world
            and take the family planning message and services to everyone, we have made many long
            steps forward since the term “birth control” first appeared in my publication of <title
                rend="italics" type="journal">The Woman Rebel</title> in 1914!</p>
        <p>At this New Year's time, again let me express my gratitude to friends who have given me
            confidence and spiritual support in our movement, and let me wish for each one of you
            the best of success in your efforts for our cause and in your own personal
            endeavors.</p>
        <byline>Margaret Sanger</byline>
    </docBody>
</doc>
