<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014-5-22 MM</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-06 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-21 EK Correct proof</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1915-04-00">Apr. 1915</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">To the Editor of <title type="journal">Mother
						Earth</title></supplied></titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp239384</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="journal">Mother Earth</title>, Apr. 1915, pp. 75-78</bibl>
			<bibl><title type="mf">Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Smith College
				Collections</title>S1:420</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="GOLEM">Goldman, Emma</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p/>
		<index level1="Woman Rebel, The" level2="suppression of"/>
		<index level1="Woman Rebel, The" level2="legal case"/>
		<index level1="free speech and free press"/>
		<index level1="Modern School"/>
		<index level1="censorship"/>
		<index level1="United States Post Office"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>A LETTER FROM MARGARET SANGER</head>
		<div>
			<p><emph rend="italics">Dear Comrade</emph>-- In the November number of your
				publication, I have read with pleasure an article by <person
					reg="Breckenridge, Harry">Harry Breckenridge</person>on my case. Through your
				columns I wish to thank Comrade Breckenridge for his article and also the other
				comrades of the <org>Ferrer School</org> who, I understand, have also attempted to
				get up some agitation on the case.</p>
			<p>It may not be known to the readers of <title type="journal">MOTHER EARTH</title> that
				there are three federal indictments against me, based on the March, May and July
				issues of <title type="journal">The Woman Rebel</title>. It may be supposed that
				though I might get away with these three indictments based soley on an opinion of
				obscenity, there remains the August, September and October issues, which were
				suppressed, and contain material for further forthcoming indictments. So that if I
				were to fool about defending myself in the courts, I would be forced to spend half
				the winter dallying about at the beck and call of a few officials. </p>
			<p>When the case first came up in August before <person reg="Hazel, John Raymond">Judge
					Hazel</person>, I was not placed under bail, but allowed to go on my own
				recognizance. When the case was called in October before <person
					reg="Foster, Warren W.">Judge Foster</person>, I had no objection to the case
				going on the day it was fixed on the calendar, and said that I was ready to proceed.
				When, however, day after day dragged on, and I was supposed to sit at the end of a
				telephone awaiting the call of the <person reg="Content, Harold A.">District
					Attorney</person>, I objected.</p>
			<p>I asked for a postponement in order to do many things I had to do. The Judge refused
				a postponement. Thrice he refused it, and the only natural thing for me to do was to
				take it myself, which I did.</p>
			<p>There is other work more important to me than fussing over an opinion of obscenity,
				which is all the case against me was based on. There was no information concerning
				the prevention of contraception given in the columns of my papers; consequently the
				only things the case was based on were the questions or articles in those three
				issues which advocated the prevention of conception--articles considered "obscene"
				"filthy" and "vile."</p>
			<p>So far as the freedom of the press is concerned, it is a most important issue, and
				one which concerns everybody in the <place>United States</place>. Especially does it
				concern us in the revolutionary movement, for it is here that we need the freedom of
				expressing our ideas and our thoughts, because they are in direct oppositiion to the
				prevailing and stagnant ideas of the day.</p>
			<p>But I began a fight for the right of giving out information on the prevention of
				contraception. That is my present and immediate work; and I am not to have that work
				sidetracked by an opinion on "obscenity"-- even though it involves Free Speech, I
				shall do this first. When I have said all that I have to say and all others have
				said on this subject, I shall turn to take up the fight of the suppression and
				confiscation of the five issues of <title type="journal">The Woman Rebel</title>,
				and fight for its continuation.</p>
			<p>We who have lost faith in the justice of the Courts of law are bound to work out a
				different method to achieve our purposes than those who still fall into the trap of
				its ponderous machinery. So that if the way I work may not be along the lines that
				other comrades have followed, I can only ask your patience and faith in my sincerity
				in doing what I consider the best and quickest way to accomplish my object. There
				are always various opinions on these questions and all that we can ask is that each
				comrade do that which out of his or her years of experience and reflection seems the
				cleanest and most direct from the revolutionary standpoint.</p>
			<p>Again, some of the comrades have sighed and criticized me for mixing the issues, as
				they say--declaring that had I not published the article on the defence of
				assasination by <person reg="Thorpe, Herbert A.">Herbert H Thorpe</person>, that all
				the rest would have been easy. I take this opportunity to state that I have no
				apology to make for publishing that article. There would have been no objection to
				an article against assassination, and if free speech and free press mean anything in
				the United States, certainly that article, reasoning and scientific, has a right to
				be published and read and discussed. That one may or may not agree with the material
				in the article is not the point. The point is that Mr. Thorpe had an opinion on a
				question which at that time was the cause of throwing all of <place>Europe</place>
				into a state of war. And he has the right to express his opinion.</p>
			<p>The work I am at present engaged in will take at least several weeks longer, I shall
				then continue the trial.</p>
			<p>There is one fact which naturally assuages my conscience, and that is that the
				Federal Authorities will always be there to receive me at any time I decdie to turn
				up. I think I can safely say they will still be "on the job: to gather me into their
				"fold."</p>
			<p>I will frankly say that I was keenly disappointed at the silence of <title
					type="journal">MOTHER EARTH</title> in regard to this outrageous tyrannical
				attitude of the <org reg="United States Post Office">Post Office</org> authorities
				toward <title type="journal">The Woman Rebel</title>. I expect very little publicity
				on this "delicate subject" from the capitalist press, but naturally I look for an
				attitude of solidarity and comradeship from the radical press. </p>
			<p>But as the indictments were returned in August and there were three suppressions
				since March--and not a word in any paper until November, it makes one feel quite
				alone in a fight that so concerns the workers and all of us. However I wish to
				express my thanks to those comrades who have written me encouraging and sympathizing
				letters, and to those who are furthering and spreading the propaganda. Gather
				together all those interested in its spreading influence and together we will fight
				for the open and free discussion of this subject which so vitally concerns every
				working man and woman.</p>
			<p>Fraternally, MARGARET H. SANGER</p>
			<p>The financial burden of <title type="journal">The Woman Rebel</title> and all this
				propaganda has been carried on almost alone. I can not continue it much longer
				unless some financial help comes along. If the propaganda has been worth a little to
				you, let me know. </p>
			<p>M.H.S.</p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<p>"<q who="GOLEM"><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person> promised to
					keep <title type="Journal">MOTHER EARTH</title> posted on the status of her
					case, which she failed to do until August--too late for our issue. The September
					and October numbers of <title type="Journal">MOTHER EARTH</title> were devoted
					entirely to the unemployed and anti-militarist agitations. However, during all
					of that time, we pushed <title type="journal">The Woman Rebel</title> and
					discussed its editor's case before thousands of people throughout the country.
					Under the circumstances it seems very unfair on the part of our comrade to
					accuse <title type="journal">MOTHER EARTH</title> of indifference. But then it
					is human to feel neglected when one faces one's first great battle with the
					powers that be, in behalf of an unpopular cause.</q>"</p>
			<p>"<q>"We understand our comrade and assure her that <title type="Journal">MOTHER
						EARTH</title> and those connected with her never have and never will
					hestitate to stand by our brave friend, Margaret H. Sanger.</q>"</p>
			<signed><person reg="Goldman, Emma">EMMA GOLDMAN</person></signed>
		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
