<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2003/07/16 SR</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2003/07/23 SR</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/23 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007/06/27 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2009-03-04 CH Proofread with Erick Zimmerman</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2009-03-05 CH entered corrections</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2001/03/11 CH Entered corrections suggested by Andy Carloff.</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-18 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1917-06-00">Jun 1917</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Woman and War</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp240299</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title>, June 1917, 5</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title>, S70:790</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="World War I" level2="women and"/>
        <index level1="World War I" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="working classes" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="enslavement of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
        <index level1="working classes" level2="war and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="class-based"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Woman and War</head>
        <byline><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></byline>
        <p>Realization of the world tragedy--war--has at last been forced upon the American people.
            Two years ago the fiendish internecine strife of the militarists of
                <place>Europe</place> seemed remote enough. Today our women of the working class
            find themselves facing an outrage unparalleled in the history of this republic. Their
            husbands, sons and brothers are to be herded to the front as conscript fighters, in
            violation of every human instinct fostered in them by the great libertarians who founded
            this country.</p>
        <p><person reg="United States"> America</person>'s participation in the war has been brought
            about by interested groups, not in response to the will of the majority. Not fifty per
            cent. of the men could have been induced to vote Yes in a war referendum, not five per
            cent. of the women. In <place>Australia</place>, a colony of the <place
                reg="United Kingdom">British Empire</place>, where democracy was respected to the
            extent of submitting the question to a referendum, the votes of the women defeated
            conscription overwhelmingly.</p>
        <p>Woman hates war. Her instincts are fundamentally creative, not destructive. But her
            sex-bondage has made her the dumb instrument of the monster she detests. For centuries
            she has populated the earth in ignorance and without restraint, in vast numbers and with
            staggering rapidity. She has become not the mother of a nobler race, but a mere breeding
            machine grinding out a humanity which fills insane asylums, almshouses and sweat shops,
            and provides cannon fodder that tyrants may rise to power on the sacrifice of her
            offspring.</p>
        <p>Too long has she been called the gentler and weaker half of humankind; too long has she
            silently borne the brunt of unwilling motherhood; too long has she been the
            stepping-stone of oligarchies, kingdoms and so-called democracies; too long have they
            thrived on her enslavement. Had she not been so submissive and inarticulate, the present
            war could not have been imposed upon the workers; for there would not have been the big
            battalions of superfluous humanity to be moved about like pawns on a chessboard.</p>
        <p>The great horde of the unwanted has proved to be a spineless mass, which did not have the
            courage to control its own destiny. Had woman had knowledge of birth control and brought
            into the world only such offspring as she desired and was physically and spiritually
            prepared to receive, society would have been far too individualistic to tolerate
            wholesale massacre for the benefit of money kings. Under such an order, the child would
            have been considered a priceless gift to the community. Manhood would have been too
            valuable to be sacrificed on battlefields. Motherhood would have been revered, and the
            mother's voice raised to forbid the slaughter of her offspring would have been
            heeded.</p>
        <p>But unfortunately the forces of oppression have cared nothing for the poignant grief of
            exploited motherhood. They have turned in callous indifference from her tears, while her
            flesh and blood have reddened every battlefield in history. There are statues in plenty
            to kings, statesmen and generals who have driven her sons to the universal shambles of
            slaughter. But where are the statues to Motherhood? </p>
        <p>In the present soul-trying crisis, the flower of European manhood has been sacrificed on
            the altar of Tyranny. The rulers of Europe are begging, imploring, crying to woman,
            using every subterfuge to induce her to breed again, in the old-time submission to
            man-made laws. Soon the war lords of America will be echoing the same plea.</p>
        <p>To all these entreaties the working woman must answer No! She must deny the right of the
            State or Kingdom hereafter to make her a victim of unwilling motherhood, and the
            handmaiden of militarism.</p>
        <p>Mothers of the working class, if your love for offspring, husband, sweetheart or brother
            stirs within you as deeply as the love that fired the mothers of <place>France</place>
            and <place>Spain</place> who strove to halt unjust wars by throwing their bodies across
            the railroad tracks to prevent troop trains from leaving, you too will rouse yourselves
            to action. You will make it necessary for this democracy, which has set out to conscript
            your men for foreign warfare, to take them over the dead bodies of the protesting
            womanhood of the United States.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
