<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2002-08-01</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2002-08-15</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2003/08/08 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/23 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/26 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/08/13 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007/06/27 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2001/03/11 CH Entered corrections suggested by Andy Carloff.</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-18 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1917-02-00">Feb 1917</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Shall We Break This Law?</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp240298</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title>, Feb 1917, 4</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title>, S70:0769</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="CLIJO">Clifton, John</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
        <p>For duplicate copies see <title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> C16:106.</p>
        <index level1="law breaking and direct action"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Comstock act"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="freedom and rights of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Shall We Break This Law?</head>
        <byline rend="italics">Margaret Sanger</byline>
        <epigraph>
            <p>"<q who="CLIJO">All our liberties are due to those who, when their conscience has
                    compelled them, have broken the law of the land.</q>"--Dr. <person
                    reg="Clifford, John">Clifford</person>.</p>
        </epigraph>
        <p>If some disease were found to be undermining the health and destroying the vitality of
            the women of the <place>United States</place>, I think it is safe to say that the
            manhood of the whole country would rise up and strive to abolish the plague.</p>
        <p>And yet the men of this land are to-day shielding and fostering just such a disease--a
            disease which sends mothers to an early grave, condemns wives to ill-health and
            invalidism, causes children to be born feeble in mind and body and crushes strong men
            under the weight of a burden they never asked to carry; a disease which eats into the
            very vitals of family life, tearing husband and wife asunder, crowding the divorce
            courts, depriving children of a mother's care and robbing maternity of its keenest joys;
            a disease which brings in its wake poverty, unemployment, child labor, prostitution,
            war; a disease sprung from ignorance of the means of preventing conception, an ignorance
            enforced by a law so vicious, so arrogant, so inhuman that thousands of earnest men and
            women are to-day asking themselves: "Shall we obey this law?"</p>
        <p><emph rend="italics">No law is too sacred to break!</emph> Throughout all the ages, the
            beacon lights of human progress have been lit by the law-breaker.
            <person>Moses</person>, the deliverer, was a law-breaker. <person reg="Jesus Christ"
                >Christ</person>, the carpenter, was a law-breaker and his early followers practiced
            their religion in defiance of the law of their time. <person>Joan of Arc</person> was a
            law-breaker. So, too, were <person reg="Washington, George">George Washington</person> and the heroes of the
            American Revolution and, in more recent times, <person reg="Brown, John">John Brown</person> of <place
                reg="Ossawatomie, KS">Ossawatomie</place>, <person reg="Thoreau, Henry David">Henry
                D. Thoreau</person>,<person reg="Garrison, William Lloyd"> William Lloyd
                Garrison</person>, <person reg="Phiilips, Wendell">Wendell Phillips</person>,
                <person reg="Parker, Theodore">Theodore Parker</person> and many more whose sturdy
            refusal to respect an inhuman law helped to emancipate a race and set free the chattel
            slaves of the Old South.</p>
        <p>The law to-day is absolute and inexorable--it has even set itself above justice, whose
            instrument it was intended to be.</p>
        <p>In earliest times, there was no elaborate code of law; there was but a simple idea of
            justice. As the race moved forward, its conception of Justice kept pace with the
            changing standards and customs of the times.</p>
        <p>As society became more complex, a caste arose whose duty it was to administer justice. In
            the course of time, however, the law grew up out of their decisions and accumulated a
            stolid mass of outworn tradition, until to-day legality has become so encumbered with
            lifeless relics of the past that the courts no longer express living social standards
            and the ideal of Justice, but merely the dead weight of legal precedents and obsolete
            decisions, hoary with age.</p>
        <p>The whole function of Justice has become petrified and encrusted with the barnacles of
            antiquated tradition. The people's will has been diverted into blind channels leading
            always further and further away from the fundamental principle that <emph rend="italics"
                >the will of the people is the supreme law.</emph></p>
        <p>Civilization is dynamic; our judicial system is static. The race has progressed, but the
            law has remained stationary--a senseless stumbling-block in the pathway of humanity, a
            self-perpetuating institution, dead to the vital needs of the people.</p>
        <p>Humanity and justice have been displaced by a legal despotism, the chief concern of which
            is the protection of established interests.</p>
        <p>Woman has always been the chief sufferer under this merciless machinery of the statutory
            law. Humbly she has borne the weight of man-made laws, surrendering to their tyranny
            even her right over her own body. For centuries she has been the helpless victim of
            excessive child-bearing. Meekly she has submitted to undesired motherhood.</p>
        <p>Incoherently she has spoken in the past. Her protests have been in vain. Her
            supplications have fallen on the deaf ear of the administrator of law. Her petitions
            have lain unheeded under the cold eye of the legislator, caught in the network and
            quagmire of politics.</p>
        <p>Against the State, against the Church, against the silence of the medical profession,
            against the whole machinery of dead institutions of the past, the woman of to-day
            arises.</p>
        <p>She no longer pleads. She no longer implores. She no longer petitions. She is here to
            assert herself, to take back those rights which were formerly hers and hers alone.</p>
        <p>If she must break the law to establish her right to voluntary motherhood, <emph
                rend="italics">then the law shall be broken.</emph></p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
