<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2010/03/31 Initials</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-11 CH clean regs and other errors</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1934-01-15">15 Jan 1934</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>
                <supplied>Birth Control and the National Recovery</supplied>
            </titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp240449</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title>, S71:0653</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="history of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="MS on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="MS on"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <p>I have the honor to open the <org>American Conference on Birth Control and National Recovery</org>
            which is held under the auspices of the <org>National Committee on Federal Legislation
                for Birth Control</org>, Incorporated. This is the second National Birth Control
            Conference ever held in this country since the beginning of the movement in 1914,--while
            there have been 11 State Conferences, 6 Regional, besides 6 International Conferences
            all during these twenty years.</p>
        <p> Thus we emerge into the Twentieth Anniversary of the B.C. Movement in this country which
            in a way is the Twentieth Anniversary of the R.C. Movement throughout the World.</p>
        <p> Before 1914, the problem of population was recognized by a very few intelligent thinkers
            in <place>Europe</place> , especially in <place>England</place> but they had not brought
            the subject to the masses. The slogan was to “Educate the Educators” while the slogan of
            the modern B.C. Movement is to “Instruct the Masses”. We have gone a good way toward our
            goal it is true, and it is safe to say that the masses in this country at least are
            ready and desirous to receive the instruction when it is made available for their use.
            Laws are in the way to this objective.</p>
        <p> We must enlighten our legislators to this effect. We are gathered here today--workers
            in the field from 25 States. Many of us believe that the advance of the B.C. Movement
            means the advance of our Civilization. That the direction this Movement takes from now
            on shall decide the future of our country’s welfare.</p>
        <p> We are here to help and guide in this direction and to awaken a deeper interest in order
            to arouse public opinion. We are <gap reason="missing" extent="page(s)"/>. </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
