<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type=" Typed Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011-07-27 NC</prepDate><prepDate>2014-03-30 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1949-06-20"><supplied resp="MSPP">20</supplied> June
            1949</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Principles of Birth Control</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp240467</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S72:0582</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="SANMA">Sanger, Margaret</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>A note typed at the top reads: "Article for
            Japanese Magazine <title type="journal">Mezane</title> (Awakening) - June 1949".</p><p>For another
            version, see <title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S72:0578.</p><p>The published
            version of this article was not found</p><index level1="Japan"
            level2="population policies of"/><index level1="Japan"
            level2="birth control in"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>PRINCIPLES OF BIRTH CONTROL</head>
        <byline>by <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret
            Sanger</person></byline>
        <p>Amid the difficulties of the post-war world, nothing is more
            encouraging for the future than the resurgence of
                <place>Japan</place>’s interest in birth control. Nothing gives
            more promise for peace and the well being of the people, not only in
            Japan but throughout <place>Asia</place> and therefore the whole
            world.</p>
        <p>I speak of a resurgence rather than a beginning because interest in
            birth control and the benefits it could confer was keen twenty-seven
            years ago when I visited Japan. There was then a fine, vigorous
            movement which seemed to promise the educational and medical
            progress that would enable Japanese families to limit the number of
            their children to those they could rear in health and happiness.
            Unfortunately, militarism crushed the hopes that were raised at that
            time, and we have harvested the bitter fruits which some of us
            predicted if the plain lessons of reckless population growth were
            not learned.</p>
        <p>Despite the tremendous uphevals of the last twenty-seven years,
            certain fundamentals are unaltered. I would like to quote from a
            speech which I made in <place reg="Tokyo, Japan">Tokyo</place> in
            1922 because the message I sought to give them is just as valid
            today.</p>
        <p>“...war is no longer the way to settle international disputes.
            Nevertheless we cannot hope for world peace until all nations
            recognize that there are fundamental dynamic forces at work which
            must be controlled. These forces are hunger and propagation, and we
            cannot solve one without including the other. Until these forces are
            recognized and acted upon wisely, the idea of international peace
            will remain a dream and a myth.</p>
        <p>“Japan has...a right to have her problems solved in a rational,
            humanitarian way, but until our diplomats and statesman recognize
            the causes of war and make a study of the population question in all
            its manifold departments, all our <org>Leagues of Nations</org>,
            international conferences, agreements and international treaties
            will become the proverbial ‘scraps of paper.’ Men and women of
            Japan, I appeal to you to look into this subject thoroughly. The
            women and mothers in your country are just as desirous of wiping out
            poverty, misery suffering and war as the women of the other nations
            of the world. I appeal to you to set your motherhood free! To make
            your women something more than breeding machines, such as the women
            of every nation have been during some period of that nation’s
            development. The time has come for international brotherhood and
            international emancipation, based upon free, conscious
            maternity.”</p>
        <p>Obviously the principles have not changed. The need remains, too. But
            for the achievement of the goal, there must be work, and
            intelligence. A program which would bring the decision as to the
            number of their offspring under the control of parents themselves
            would have to include:</p>
        <p>1. <emph rend="underline">Education</emph> to enlighten the public
            through its teachers, writers, ministers, commentators.</p>
        <p>2. <emph rend="underline">Organization</emph> of groups of specially
            trained field workers to bring the importance of the subject to the
            people themselves.</p>
        <p>3. <emph rend="underline">Instruction</emph> of the people in the
            methods of birth control and their application, this instruction to
            be given by properly qualified medical or nursing personnel.</p>
        <p>4. <emph rend="underline">Establishment</emph> of birth control
            clinics [--] public health services and incorporation of this
            subject in general programs of health education through all
            appropriate governmental channels.</p>
        <p>5. <emph rend="underline">Sterilization</emph> of those hopelessly
            unfit for reproduction by reason of clearly provable dangers of
            transmissable mental or physical ailments which do not unfit them
            for marriage [--] make their children unhappy helpless charges upon
            themselves, their families and society.</p>
        <p>6. <emph rend="underline">Research</emph> to improve the efficacy of
            contraceptives, to find simpler, less expensive methods than those
            now known, to correlate data on the importance of birth control in
            combating infant and maternal mortality and illness, social failure
            and over-populations.</p>
        <p>7. <emph rend="underline">Legislation</emph> to put all these
            principles into effect. These principles have not changed through
            the years; the problems, however, have magnified. Since 1922, the
            population of the world has grown more than a quarter of a million,
            of which Japan has contributed about twenty-million. Technological
            advances in the production and distribution of food have by no means
            kept pace with the population increase. Yet all over the world
            people are coming more and more to realize that possibilities for a
            decent standard of living for all exist. If we could make the best
            use of the techniques we know and at the same time end the reckless
            breeding of children who can never hope to be as well cared for as
            most animals, the possibilities would be realized.</p>
        <p>This strengthening aspiration of the masses of mankind is a hopeful
            sign. There are others. We have better educational and medical
            facilities than ever before. Through our papers, our cinema, the
            radio and all the network of communications and schooling, the truth
            can be brought to millions. We have improved our public health
            techniques. We are increasing our efforts to find improved
            contraceptives. We have amassed a tremendous body of information
            which proves to us that we are on the right track.</p>
        <p>Against these grounds for optimism we must set off realistically the
            obstacles which remain. They are prodigious. Apathy and weariness
            are the most dangerous. The mothers of all lands remain, as they
            always have been, pathetically eager to learn means for controlling
            conception. Their leaders and teachers allow themselves to become
            preoccupied with lesser problems, which problems that are insoluble
            unless the bigger question of population control is mastered.</p>
        <p>Then there are the forces of ignorance and fanaticism, often actively
            engaged in fighting to perpetuate the old lies that mankind must
            continue to multiply regardless of human welfare. Here the great
            danger comes from those whose egotism leads them to impose their own
            concepts of morality or even spirituality upon all their fellows.
            These fanatics arrogate to themselves all wisdom and all truth; they
            set up a doctrine of infallibility based on nothing more than their
            own assertions. Hardly anyone would seek to forbid them the right to
            practice what they wish and to seek converts to their views by
            argument and persuasion. But that is not enough for them, it is not
            enough because their cause is too weak to survive through its own
            validity. Therefore, they seek to force others to accept their
            dictates whether the others believe as they do or not.</p>
        <p>I am sure that in Japan, as in the rest of the world, these minions
            of intolerance will be defeated. I am confident that in the matter
            of conception control we will soon see Japan asserting a leadership
            which will serve all the nations of the Orient, and the Japanese
            first of all, in achieving the health and welfare of the people, a
            balance between food and natural resources and population, and the
            ultimate objective of permanent peace on earth. </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
