<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed draft statement">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2012-06-21 AW Initial Tag</prepDate><prepDate>2012/10/24 CH proof tags</prepDate><prepDate>2014-07-02 CH clean tags</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="0000-00-00">n.d.</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Real Horrors and Tragedies of
                Civilization</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp240272</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S77:0079</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt><name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>No further information has been found for this document.</p>
        <index level1="children" level2="unwanted"/>
        <index level1="society" level2="responsibility and"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="freedom and rights of"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <p>Mrs. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger</person> agrees with <person
                reg="Shaw, George Bernard">Bernard Shaw</person>, she says "that nothing that is
                admittedly horrible really matters any more, because if it is only horrible enough
                it frightens people into seeking a remedy to prevent its happening again.</p>
        <p>If a plane crashes to earth, if an automobile falls over a cliff, if a
                building caves in and kills hundreds of people,--all horrible catastrophes, we
                admit, but if these horrors arouse communities and nations out of their lethargy and
                indifference, if they bring improvements, if they bring groups together into closer
                realization and form that collective mind of humanity which adds to the community of
                world wisdom, then these have enabled and advanced the spiritual progress of
                mankind.</p>
        <p>But the real horrors and tragedies of our civilization are these, which
                happen every day, needless, useless, senseless, ceaseless, futile sufferings, which
                some good religious folks call “natural”, which take place all around us, day after
                day, year after year, and are perpetuated form generation to generation.</p>
        <p>I mean the suffering and the fear of undesired pregnancy of innocent
                women, too poor to defend themselves, too weak to rebel, too inarticulate to cry
                out.”</p>
        <p> These are the sufferings we are organized to eliminate--these are the women we are
            dedicated to defend.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
