<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
<mepHeader>
<prepDate>2003/10/29 amc</prepDate>
<prepDate>2004/07/02 CH</prepDate>
<prepDate>2014-03-04 CH correct regs</prepDate><prepDate>2014-11-13 CH clean regs</prepDate>
<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
<docDate value="1925-05-00">May 1925</docDate>
<docTitle>
<titlePart>Shrouding Sex in Mystery Brings Disaster</titlePart>
</docTitle>
<idno>msp300256</idno>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl><title type="journal">Physical Culture</title>, May 1925, 32</bibl>
<bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microifilm, Collected Documents Series</title> C16:259</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
<respStmt>
<resp/>
<name/>
</respStmt>
</mepHeader>
<headNote resp="MSPP">
<index level1="children" level2="rights of"/>
<index level1="sex education" level2="parental responsibility and"/>
</headNote>
<docBody>
<head rend="italics">Shrouding Sex in Mystery Brings Disaster</head>
<byline>By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></byline>
<p>We hear a great deal about the freedom that belongs to the children of today the freedom that is
theirs because they have demanded it. It makes us older ones tremble a little wondering what they
will do with it now that they have it. How many of us I wonder, realize that almost everything
depends upon the guidance which we, as parents, give to the children entrusted to us. Perhaps the
greatest torch that we can hand on to the young lives of today in a hope of leading their feet to
safety, is a wholesome knowledge of sex. The age-long teaching that sex is something not to be
imparted by parents to their children, but shrouded in mystery, has done more to bring disaster in
the lives of young boys and girls than almost anything else.</p>
<p>Sex is a salient thing in the life of the adolescent. Yet how many boys and girls are left to
glean this important knowledge from sources that distort and misrepresent through ignorance, the
truth that should have been given them in the same spirit that religion and integrity was given.</p>
<p>It is always the rising generation that is the material of which progress is made. It is the
ideas that we give this generation that will shape not only the lives of our boys and girls today
but the lives of those who belong to posterity.</p>
<p>We have come to know that we cannot gather perfect fruit except from perfect trees. Today we are
facing a new dawn and we must meet it with nothing less than the truth. Truth about sex, truth about
marriage, truth about parenthood. It is the only way to attain a perfect freedom.</p>
<p>Upon our shoulders rests the responsibility of creating a new sex morality. The vital difference
between a morality thus created and the so-called morality of the past is that the new standard will
be based upon knowledge and freedom while the old was founded upon ignorance.</p>
<p>When we have raised the standard of sex ideals and purged the human mind of its unclean
conception of sex, the fountain of the race will have been cleansed. We will have a race that is
morally and spiritually free.</p>
</docBody>
</doc>
