<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Testimony">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2013/12/04 JK encoded</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-08-21 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1932-05-19-20">19-20 May 1932</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Testimony Before the United States Senate on Senate
                    bill 4436</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp300446</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Statement of Mrs. Margaret Sanger, National Chairman
                    Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control</title>, <title type="book"
                    >Birth Control: Hearings Before a Subcommittee of the Committee on the
                    Judiciary, United States Senate, Seventy-second Congress, First Session on S.
                    4436 May 12-20, 1932 </title>
                <place>Washington, DC</place>, 6-11, and 135-43</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Collected Documents</title> C15:797</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="HASDA">Hastings, Daniel</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><index level1="American Medical Association"/>
        <index level1="Europe" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="politicians and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="medical community and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="legalization of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="MS on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="MS on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="rights associated with"/>
        <index level1="United States Congress"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="in marriages"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="in New Jersey"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="in New York"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="in Chicago"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues" level3="physicians and"
        /></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Hearings Before a Subcommittee of the <org
                reg="United States Senate, Committee on the Judiciary">Committee on the Judiciary
                United States Senate</org> Seventy-Second Congree First Session in S.4436</head>
        <head type="sub">Statement of Mrs. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>,
            National Chairman <org>Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control</org></head>

        <p>Mrs. Sanger: Mr. Chairman and gentlemen of the committee, this bill, <name type="law"
                reg="Senate bill 4436">S. 4436</name>, directly affects the health, the future
            development and the happiness of 25,000,000 married women of child-bearing age in this
            country. It further affects indirectly the health, happiness, and future welfare of
            45,000,000 children in this country, of which 10,000,000 are said to be handicapped,
            according to the reports of 1,400 experts who came to this city at the call of <person
                reg="Hoover, Herbert">President Hoover </person>at the <org
                reg="White House Conference on Child Health and Protection">White House
                conference</org> about a year ago. At that conference President Hoover said: (Insert
            document) Now, Mr. Chairman, you might say how does this bill affect handicapped
            children. It directly affects the handicapped children because as some of our experts
            here to-day will show the mothers of these handicapped children are needed for the care
            of these children. Furthermore, according to these reports, it is stated that a large
            percentage of these children were handicapped from causes due to ignorance, poverty, and
            neglect. Even the most optimistic of us will not claim that we are going to do away with
            poverty, ignorance, and neglect in the next few years, and yet these 1,400 experts did
            not emphasize that the parents of these 10,000,000 children should have the knowledge
            and means and instruction to prevent the coming of 10,000,000 more children, who may be
            handicapped from the same causes of poverty, ignorance, and neglect. To me it is just a
            simple piece of common sense that people who can not take care of children to-day,
            because they are ignorant, or because they are too poor, or because they neglect them,
            certainly should not be encouraged to have more children. In my own experience, both as
            the mother of three children, and as a trained nurse for many years in <place
                reg="New York, NY">New York City</place>, I came in contact with all kinds of
            people, representing the poor of all races, all creeds, and all religions. I found that
            there are a certain number of people, perhaps we can say 20 per cent of our population
            to-day, who in spite of these laws have availed themselves of some kind of knowledge by
            which they have controlled the size of their families. Of the other 80 per cent, I found
            that about half are struggling to find something to control the size of their families,
            while the other half are those generally classed as unfit, mentally and physically, and
            include morons and mental defectives who usually come upon our social vista as permanent
            unemployable and dependants. It is for this other 40 per cent, you might say, or half of
            the 80 per cent, that we are talking to-day. It is these people that this bill will
            directly affect. Mr. Chairman, you asked <person reg="Hatfield, Henry">Senator Hatfield
            </person>a few questions that I wonder if I may cover. These parents, if they can afford
            to go to a private physician, if they have a family doctor, may get some kind of
            information as to the means of controlling the size of their families. It may not be the
            best advice, but nevertheless it si something, and it has enabled a certain percentage
            of our population to control the size of their families. Is it better than nothing, but
            the majority of women, those who are too poor to have a family physician, have to go to
            the hospiitals and public institutions. They have to go to the dispensaries and to
            public wards to get their medical care and it is right here that this law operates.
            While a physician may in his private office do and say as he wishes; he may give some
            device and no one can ask him where he gets it; as soon as he is connected with an
            institution the situation is entirely changed. In the first place the hospital would
            have to order and pay for contraceptive supplies which he might prescribe. In the second
            place he would be accountable to the laws of the country for his action that
            institution, and he can not thus jeopardize his own license nor the charter of the
            institution which operate legally under the State laws. There is where this law
            operates, because the law, section 211, definitely forbids the transportation of
            articles or of information through the United States mails or common carriers. Unless
            every hospital has a manufacturing plant associated with it, or in the city where it is
            located, you will see that they must get their articles either from New York or <place
                reg="Chicago, IL">Chicago</place> or some large city where the articles are
            manufactured. The <name type="law" reg="United States Tariff Act, Section 305">tariff
                act, section 305</name>, affects such articles coming in from other countries. Many
            physicians do not know that there is a great deal of research going on in this
            particular field in <place>England</place>, in <place reg="Oxford, England"
                >Oxford</place>, and <place reg="Cambridge, England">Cambridge</place>, also the
                <org>University of Edingburgh</org>, <place>Scotland</place>. A great deal is being
            accomplished there because they are unhampered by restrictive laws and are free to do
            research, while we in this country are years behind in medical research in this
            particular field.</p>
        <p><q who="HASDA">Senator Hastings: You do not happen to have a copy of that section
                211?</q>
        </p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: I have, Mr. Chairman.</p>
        <p><q who="HASDA">Senator Hastings: Were you going to put any part of that in the
                record?</q></p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: I would like all of it to go in the record, with your permission, Mr.
            Chairman. I have not only the statutes in question, but I have some of the legal
            opinions that have recently been given by the courts, both on the tariff act and also on
                <name type="law" reg="United States Criminal Code, Section 211">section 211</name>
            as it affects the transportation of the articles in the mails, if you will permit these
            to go in.</p>
        <p><q who="HASDA">Senator Hastings: As a matter of fact I was in error when I suggested to
                Senator Hatfield that this affected only the importation of articles. The most
                important thing is the at the end of your remarks. </q></p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: All right. May I say again that the Federal law, section 211, makes no
            exception for physicians. It makes no exception for hospitals to get such supplies. It
            makes no exception for anyone. Any one convicted under this law is subjected to give
            years in prison and $5,000 fine. In this country the laws of 47 States allow a physician
            to give contraceptive information in his practice. Some of them are limited. In
                <place>New York</place> State he can only give information “for the cure and
            prevention of disease.” In <place>New Jersey </place>he can give it “for a just cause.”
            In 24 States the subject of contraception is not mentioned in their laws at all.</p>
        <p><q who="HASDA">Senator Hastings: This law does not help there, does it? </q></p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: It does by allowing them to transport the articles through the mails, also
            common carriers.</p>
        <p><q who="HASDA">Senator Hastings: Yes; but of course these State laws remain in
                effect.</q></p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: Absolutely; but there is only one State in the Union where giving of advice
            would be doubtful, and that is <place>Mississippi</place>. All the other States give a
            physician the right to give such information in his private practice provided he can get
            the things from the manufacturer. That is what our amendment provides for. When this law
            was passed in 1873 there was very little known concerning the whole subject; certainly
            there was no real information concerning the medical and sociological importance of the
            practice of contraception. The subject of birth control or contraception was wrongly
            classed with indecency, obscenity, and abortion. The passage of this law in 1873 really
            closed the avenues of proper scientific information and research by the medical
            profession, medical schools, and medical universities in this country. It has done
            untold harm to classify contraception in that category. It Is an insult to every decent
            married woman in the country who wants to bring up her family intelligently; it prevents
            her from applying the benefits of science to the cultivation of her children and the
            bringing up of her family; and, furthermore, to all intents and purposes it classifies
            every married woman in this country as a “child bearing conscript.” Unless a woman has
            some means of preventing conception and spacing her children, she is forced to bear
            children like an animal, and in fact animals are not allowed to breed in sickness and
            with diseased bodies as the women of this country are made to do to-day, as I will show
            you a little later on. This bill is simple; it is conservative; it is constructive,
            because it simply allows the physician at a hospital, or licensed clinic, to receive
            such supplies and to give such information. The passage of this bill would be the first
            attempt on the part of the Congress to place the responsibility of giving contraceptive
            instruction in the hands of the medical profession, where it rightly belongs. It would
            be the first attempt on the part of Congress to give the medical profession the control
            of such knowledge; which we know is very promiscuously scattered about to-day. It would
            let physicians regulate the kind of devices used, and thus wipe out the present traffic
            in wrong and harmful devices. The poor mothers, the people who should have the
            information, are uninformed and are denied the proper kind of devices suitable to their
            own individual requirements.</p>
        <p><q who="HASDA">Senator Hastings: If you do not mind me interrupting you-- </q></p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: No.</p>
        <p><q who="HASDA">Senator Hastings: It occurs to me paragraph numbered 3 might be a little
                uncertain “by any druggist in his legitimate prescription business.” What is
                intended by that? </q>
        </p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: That the physician would prescribe certain devices, tested by research and
            experience in our clinics. The druggist should be able to supply these devices. We have
            found that contraceptives, to be properly safe and harmless, should be prescribed
            according to the individual requirements. just as eyeglasses must be individually fitted
            by oculists.</p>
        <p><q who="HASDA">Senator Hastings: What I was interested in was whether it was intended
                that a person might apply to the druggist without going to the physician at all.
            </q></p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: No. According to that I would understand that a person must have a
            physician’s prescription.</p>
        <p><q who="HASDA">Senator Hastings: I am anxious to find out what is your intent.</q></p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: That is our intent, that it should be by prescription. </p>
        <p><q who="HASDA">Senator Hastings: By prescription only? </q></p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: Yes. I do not wish to go into great detail concerning different methods and
            devices for contraception. However, there are certain articles, which are commonly used
            as contraceptives, but which may also be used for the cure and prevention of disease.
            These articles, according to a recent court decision may be legally transmitted through
            the <place>United States</place> mails. However, there are certain other articles which
            are used only for the prevention of conception, which are now excluded from the mails.
            These articles must be prescribed by a physician, and only after a thorough physical
            examination, so that the prescription varies with the individual. It is like any other
            medical advice, highly individual and adapted to the particular requirements of the
            patient. It is to such articles that we refer, and it is for these that the law must be
            changed. </p>
        <p><q who="HASDA">Senator Hastings: There would be no objection to changing that to read “by
                any druggist upon a written prescription of a licensed physician”?</q></p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: There would be no objection whatever.</p>
        <p><q who="HASDA">Senator Hastings: I wanted to get your thought, so that after all what you
                are seeking here is all limited to physicians or medical colleges, which are really
                controlled by physicians. </q></p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: Yes; they are already controlled by physicians. In many States the medical
            colleges are free to instruct their young graduates and physicians in this particular
            art, as hey are instructed in other departments, but this has not generally been done up
            to the present time. There are comparatively few medical colleges that include a course
            in contraception in their regular curriculum. I want to say in passing that where the
            laws allow a physician within the State to give information, some clinics have been
            established. Some of the social agencies and some of the forward-looking physicians are
            to-day struggling to solve their immediate problems, not only leaht problems, but social
            problems as well. The problem of unemployment, the whole question of congestion, is
            coming before them as never before. Birth control helps to solve some of these problems,
            but even where clinics are already in operation, it is difficult to obtain ether the
            best information or supplies, under the present law. The proposed amendment would
            release the physician and make this information available, also, in public institutions
            such as clinics and hospitals. Mr. Chairman, if I may digress for a moment, I want to go
            into an even broader aspect of the question. Birth control is not a new idea. It is as
            old as nature itself. In fact, even in the period of savagery there was some means, some
            knowledge of controlling the numbrs in the tribes. It is only the methods that have
            changed. Instead of infanticide and killing off the old and sick as has been done at
            various stages in the development of civilization, the only means of controlling the
            size of her family which is left to woman is abortion. The number of abortion in this
            country is colossal, and we are convinced that only through a proper knowledge of
            contraception shall we do away with this abortion practice, one which is extremely
            detrimental to the health and happiness of women. Let us now consider the two groups of
            people, those who practice birth control and those who do not. If you will look into
            every community, and every city and every town, you will see on the one hand small
            groups who have controlled the size of their families and on the other hand you will see
            a larger group who have not even been able to avail themselves of any information
            whatever. In the first group, we have the educated, cultured, well-to-do citizens,
            professors, doctors, lawyers, ministers, scientists, artisans, and skilled laborers.
            Here we find the spacing of children an adopted rule, the mother’s health being the
            first consideration and the earning power of the father a close second. From this group
            come almost all of our social movements. Civilization is directly benefitted and
            advanced through this low birth rate group. In the other large family group we have
            overcrowding, illiteracy, ignorance, slums, infant and maternal mortality, and child
            labor. Almost all our social problems are entrenched in this group and these conditions
            and their problems are perpetuated from generation to generation. I, myself, have found
            that the mothers in both groups are equally desirous of bringing into the world only the
            number of children they can properly care for. I find that even women of the very lowest
            grade of intelligence are willing to avail themselves of information to prevent
            conception at any cost and at any trouble to themselves. I have, during the past several
            years, receive over a million letters, the great majority of these letters coming from
            mothers and from women, especially in this second group. I should like to read a few of
            these letters which are rather typical of the conditions that prevail throughout the
            country-- conditions hat the passage of this bill would help. (letter from mother here)
            Eight years in pregnancy for three children. Cruelty beyond belief! Nine little coffins.
            The <org>United States Government</org> would help her rear and breed pigs, cows,
            chickens, but makes laws to deprive mothers of knowledge to perfect and develop the
            human race. A 75 per cent loss; sordid; a business man would shut up his shop. We are
            paying to-day for these laws of nearly 60 years ago. We are paying for them by the
            multiplication of the unfit, the diseased, the feeble-minded. We are paying for them in
            our high maternal mortality, in the hordes of death-doomed infants who never see their
            first birthday, in the widespread practice of abortions, in child labor, in the waste of
            mother powr and creative energy. We are paying the cost in increasing billions and
            piling up huge debts for unborn generations to pay. </p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: Mr Chairman, and gentlemen of the committee, in consideration of the time of
            the committe and their generosity in allowing us so much time to bring this discussion
            and subject before you, I will forego the impulse to answer and refute many of the
            personal accusations and charges that were made by the opposition in their testimony
            yesterday. I just want to make this remark, that this committee, the persons in this
            work, and their character, their integrity, and their standing in the communities
            throughout the city, need no defense; and so I am going to continue this morning just on
            the merits and on the facts of the subject, as we have found them. You will notice, Mr.
            Chairman, that while those who appeared against this bill gave some very representative
            opinions, they were mostly personal. They were not backed up by facts, and they were
            theories rather than practice. For instance, <person reg="Kelly, Howard">Doctor
                Kelly</person>, a noted physician, who has won a world-wide reputation in the field
            of medicine, appeared before you, not to talk about the merits of the bill, nor to give
            any evidence from a medical point of view at all, but to defend public morals; while
                <person reg="Ryan, John">Dr. John Ryan,</person> a member of the <org
                reg="Catholic Church">Roman Catholic Church</org>, came to theorize on economics and
            the population aspect of the whole question. All of these opinions are interesting, and
            the discussions of the wider aspects of this bill are all right and good, but you will
            note there was no constructive policy offered in substitution for this bill. There was
            nothing constructive suggested as a means to do away with the various conditions to
            which they object that they claim are so prevalent in this country. As a matter of fact,
            the facts that were presented by the proponents of this bill were not refuted in any of
            the arguments or testimony, and when you sum it all up and weed out the personal
            opinions, you will find there was really no objection whatsoever made on the actual
            merits of this bill. Not one person, in opposing the bill, claimed that a physician
            should not have the right to instruct patients as he saw fit; in fact, <person
                reg="Chase, William Sheafe">Canon Chase</person> stated that no sensible person
            could oppose giving to trustworthy physicians freedom to do what is necessary to protect
            the life of a woman which would be endangered by another pregnancy, if her husband can
            not control himself. I will take up some of the objections and try to answer them
            briefly. In the first place, our opponents claim that this bill will throw the mails
            wide open to the free and illicit distribution of contraceptive information. Their claim
            is ridiculous. The bill simply asks that a physician shall have the right to send and
            receive contraceptive information and supplies by the United States mails and common
            carriers, and also that such supplies and information may be sent to hospitals and
            licensed clinics. We know that physicians do not prescribe by mail. Any physician that
            knows his business at all must have the patient before him, and I must examine the
            patient to give her the best and most suitable contraceptive instruction and means for
            her individual case. However, to do that he must first have up-to-date information
            himself, which we know in many cases is sadly lacking, because there has been no
            instruction in medical schools on the technique of contraception. Furthermore,
            information and advice alone are not sufficient. The physician must give some chemical
            or mechanical means to prevent conception, in order to protect the woman properly. We
            know that physicians differ in their opinions regarding the subject. They differ because
            to a great extent they have not been taught in their medical schools. This is especially
            true of the older physicians, many of whom in the past have been taught much more on the
            technique of therapeutic abortions; they were not taught contraception at all, and you
            will find that it is these men who oppose our bill, because they simply are ignorant of
            the whole technique of contraception. It was brought out that the <org>American Medical
                Association</org> had repudiated this bill. That is untrue. The American Medical
            Association at its annual convention in <place reg="New Orleans, LA">New Orleans</place>
            last week, took no action on any bill. One must remember that the American Medical
            Association is composed of about 150,000 doctors, of which only about 9,000 would be
            really directly concerned with this question. These are the gynecologists and
            obstetricians, and that very group of gynecologists and obstetricians went on record a
            few years ago and gave the opinion that there should be no legislation curtailing the
            freedom of the physician in his lawful practice. Their resolution was offered as
            testimony in the early part of our proceedings. I have here just an indication of what
            the medical profession feels. Here is a symposium, printed in the <title type="journal"
                >Medical Journal and Record</title> in 1927. Two hundred and seventy-three doctors
            replied to the symposium, and of this number 248 were in favor of birth control, and
            proper legislation. Nineteen were against it. Two of them were unable to express an
            opinion. One thought contraceptive methods would bring abuses. One said that methods
            should be advised only after consultation with physicians and with the sanction of the
            United States Government and the <title type="book">Bible</title>. One thought that this
            generation knows too much about such things, and the poor would not avail themselves of
            this information. Another symposium appeared lated [later] in 1929, in the same <title
                type="journal">Journal and Record</title>. One hundred and eighteen doctors replied
            to the questionnaire. Of this number 99 said they were in favor of contraception. Four
            said they were not informed sufficiently to express an opinion. Fifteen were opposed. I
            think that to a certain degree gives a brief indication, not a summary, but a cross
            section, of the general opinion of the medical profession. I have also included in the
            record a list of medical societies and medical groups, a large number of which have
            indorsed this particular bill, the rest having indorsed the principles of contraception.
            Dr. <person reg="Morgan, Gerry">Gerry Morgan</person>, as past president of the American
            Medical Association did not testify before you as a physician to discuss the merits of
            the bill but stated that he was here to speak on the “natural” laws of the universe. One
            expresident of the American Medical Association opposes this legislation while two
            others have fully supported it. The late Dr. <person reg="Jacobi, Abraham">Abraham
                Jacobi</person>, former president of the American Medical Association, made a very
            excellent pronouncement on the whole subject some years ago, and was really the first
            one to bring this subject to the attention of the medical profession. A few years ago,
            Dr. <person reg="Pusey, William Allen">William Allen Pusey</person> in his statement
            accepting the presidency of the American Medical Association also held out squarely on
            the proper dissemination and regulation of contraceptive information by the medical
            profession. Our opponents made the statement that the use of any contraceptive
            invariably had effect upon the pelvic organs and nervous system. That statement is an
            indication of the ignorance of some of the members of the medical profession. We have in
            one <org reg="Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau">clinic</org> in New York City
            cared for and instructed over 28,000 women, whose records we have. A follow-up is made
            of these women. Social workers go into the homes. We have these actual facts, and within
            a very short period– we could present the data now, although it would be voluminous– a
            detailed report covering the first 10,000 of these cases is to be published. We know it
            to be true that the great majority of these women have greatly benefitted by this
            information, or rather by the rest they have had from pregnancy. Their health has
            improved. Their family conditions have improved. The whole happiness of the family has
            been increased. The children have been better cared for. In a very few cases, of course,
            there have been failures. These constitute, however, a very small percentage of the
            total, and in a very few instances women have resorted to abortions. I would like, if I
            may, to offer for the record brief summaries of some of these cases to show you what
            their conditions are, the number of living children, and the number of dead children.
            Let me just read one. We have a number of cases like this, Mr. Chairman, but I only read
            one for your information.</p>
        <p><q who="HASDA">Senator Hastings: Do you want it put in the record?</q></p>
        <p> Mrs. Sanger: I would like to if I may.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: As for the other statement along the same line, that there is harm to women,
            there is a report here by Dr. <person reg="Butler, Lily">Lily Butler</person>, medical
            officer of the <org>Walworth Women’s Welfare Center</org>, an English group, which has
            made a careful follow up for this particular reason, to see what effect the use of
            contraceptives have upon the health of women and to see if it caused sterility: This is
            a simple statement of one of the clinics where they have followed this up. I mention
            this to show that we are after facts. We are trying to study this question, and we have
            had a long enough period now, nearly 10 years, on which to base our judgement of what
            this is going to do, what it is doing, and what it has done. One statement has been made
            many times by our opponents, and although it is beside the question, I would like to
            cover it. I think it was one of the doctors who stated that leaders of the world would
            have come from large families and that not infrequently the last child born had been the
            flower of the flock.” I have already put into the record some data relative to that,
            which I would ask the committee to read. The opponents to this bill offer continence as
            a means for limiting the family, and for doing what we claim birth control will do. We
            know the population of countries where this is advocated, and we also know that this
            population does not practice continence. When they say self-control, I would like to ask
            what they mean by self-control. As I stated before to the committee, there are three
            methods of birth-control; one is continence, one is sterilization, and the other is
            chemical or mechanical means of contraception. We refuse to say– in fact, we can not
            say– that any one method is suitable for all the population. There may be many people
            for whom continence may be the very best method to be prescribed. We have with us to-day
            a specialist who will dwell more upon this phase of the subject, but I would like to say
            this: It is intimated that self-control refers to a safe period, or a period in a
            woman’s life where she is immune to pregnancy. I think the gynecologists and most of the
            experts in this field of medicine will say that there is only a very small percentage of
            women– I have heard it stated that it is not even 1 per cent– who could be said to have
            a safe period, when they are safe from pregnancy. Moreover, if they mean abstinence,
            that is entirely out of order, for then they are claiming that there should be no
            relations whatsoever except when children are desired. We know that sexual desire is
            very seldom accompanied by a desire for children. Very seldom. It precedes the desire
            for children, and I am not going to take this up, because <person reg="Meyer, Adolf">Dr.
                Adolf Meyer,</person> professor at <org>Johns Hopkins University</org>, will discuss this
            subject and will explain it more clearly than I can. Mr. Chairman, it seems to me that
            there can be no objection to this bill as it has been drawn, and I want to say further
            that the original bill presented before the subcommittee of the judiciary last year was
            drafted by two distinguished lawyers, Mr. <person reg="Fosdick, Raymond">Raymond
                Fosdick</person> and Mr. <person reg="Tweed, Harrison">Harrison Tweed</person>, of
            New York, men who have given a great deal of study to social legislation. In order to
            conform with some of those who disagreed with that bill, we tried to get together and
            see if we could not agree upon one bill, in order to save the lives of thousands of
            women, and to settle this question. Mr. Chairman, I want to say that we cut out from our
            original bill many points so as to agree with the very people who appeared here
            yesterday against us, and as I say, they have not objected to the merits of this bill.
            This bill is conservative; it is constructive; it is going to do something more
            definitely constructive than anything that has yet been offered. Our opponents claim
            there is promiscuous distribution of supplies, articles, and information in the country.
            Of course there is; not because there are no laws, but because there are laws. As soon
            as this responsibility is given to the proper people– I believe there will be a gradual
            elimination of this promiscuous scattering of devices, and of information, which is
            mostly misinformation. That, Mr. Chairman, is my contention.</p>
        <p><q who="HASDA">Senator Hastings: Mrs. Sanger, I do not think the opponents of this bill
                make any claim that they have offered any solution. I do not remember that they did,
                certainly no legislative solution.</q></p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: No.</p>
        <p><q who="HASDA">Senator Hastings: Did you read that report of some conference, I think,
                held in England, by the <org>Episcopal Church</org>?</q></p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: Yes.</p>
        <p><q who="HASDA">Senator Hastings: What have you to say with respect to that
                opposition?</q></p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: It was not opposition, Mr. Chairman. That was the <org>Lambeth Conference of
            Anglican Bishops</org>. I think we offered that in evidence the other day; resolution 15,
            carried by 193 votes to 67. Some of the resolutions stated that continence would be the
            advisable thing, and an ideal solution to birth control. There was a further discussion
            of birth control, however, and the conference agreed that where there is a morally sound
            reason for avoiding complete continence, other methods may be used, provided this is
            done in thelight of the same Christian principles. That was the statement. </p>
        <p><q who="HASDA">Senator Hastings: I got the impression from the extract read, they
                condemned the whole idea of contraception. </q></p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: No; they did not, Mr. Chairman. If you will read it again– I read it this
            morning– they preferred continuance and moral suasion, but in resolution 15, they bring
            out very clearly that, under certain conditions, other methods may be sanctioned.</p>
        <p><q who="HASDA">Senator Hastings: Have you somebody else? </q></p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: Yes. I would like this short paper to go in the record, which reads: -- I
            would like to introduce Dr. Adolf Meyer, of Johns Hopkins University.</p>


    </docBody>
</doc>
