<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "file:/S:/TRANSCRIPTIONS/XML%20Drafts/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Testimony">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/20/12 VS innitial tagging</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/14/03 CH proof tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/14/03 VS correct tags</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1932-05-19">19 May, 1932</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Testimony Before the House of Representatives Committee
                    on Ways and Means on H. R. 11082</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp300444</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Birth Control p. 6-16, 137-143. Hearings Before the Committee on Ways and
                    Means House of Representatives Seventy-Second Congress First Session on H. R.
                    11082</title>(Washington, 1932)</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="BUTLI">Butler, Lily C.</name>
            <name id="NORMA">Norton, Mary Hopkins</name>
            <name id="HOOHE">Hoover, Herbert Clark</name>
            <name id="CRICH">Crisp, Charles Robert</name>
            <name id="MCCJO">McCormack, John William</name>
            <name id="SHEWI">Sheafe, William</name>
            <name id="CANHA">Canfield, Harry Clifford</name>
            <name id="MSPP">Margaret Sanger Papers Project</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
            <name id="IA1917">Immigration Act of 1917</name>
            <name id="HR">H. R. 11082</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">The following is an excerpt from the hearings, including only Margaret
        Sanger's testimony and speech she responded to directly. <index level1="abortion"
            level2="birth control vs."/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="and marriage"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="economic benefits and risks of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"
            level3="negative consequences of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="legalization of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="population and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="opposition to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="religion and"/>
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Comstock Act"/>
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Postal Code and Regulations"/>
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Tariff Act"/>
        <index level1="birth control movement"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="population growth and"/>
        <index level1="Catholic Church" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="Comstock, Anthony"/>
        <index level1="family size"/>
        <index level1="&quot;feeble-minded&quot; persons" level2="fertility and birth rate of"/>
        <index level1="immigration" level2="U.S. policy"/>
        <index level1="marriage" level2="reforms"/>
        <index level1="National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control"/>
        <index level1="physically disabled and diseased" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="poverty" level2="family size and"/>
        <index level1="United States Children's Bureau"/>
        <index level1="United States Congress"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="health of"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <div>
            <head>STATEMENT OF MRS. MARGARET SANGER, NATIONAL CHAIRMAN OF THE COMMITTEE ON FEDERAL
                LEGISLATION FOR BIRTH CONTROL, NEW YORK CITY</head>
            <p> Mrs. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger</person>. <person
                    reg="Crisp, Charles Robert">Mr. Chairman</person> and gentlemen of <org
                    reg="United States House of Representatives Committee on Ways and Means">the
                    committee</org>, first may I thank you in the name of <org
                    reg="National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control">our
                    committee</org> for your kindness and consideration in giving us so much of your
                valuable time this morning.</p>
            <p> I also wish to assure you that were it not for our deep conviction that <name
                    reg="H.R. 11082">the bill</name> we are trying to persuade you to enact into
                law, means so very much to millions of women in the country, we would not worry or
                trouble you to give us time at this particular period of mental distress, in the
                hurry of your own work.</p>
            <p> This bill directly affects 25,000,000 married women of child-bearing age in this
                country. It indirectly affects the health and the future development and the
                education of 45,000,000 children in this country, of which 10,000,000 are
                handicapped, mentally or physically, according to the reports given at the <org
                    reg="White House Conference on Child Health and Protection">White House
                    conference</org> called by <person reg="Hoover, Herbert Clark">President
                    Hoover</person> last year.</p>
            <p> More than 1,400 experts reported that those 10,000,000 handicapped children were
                handicapped because of conditions of poverty, ignorance, or neglect. And yet, Mr.
                Chairman, no fundamental cure was offered to prevent the coming of 10,000,000 more
                children who will eventually be handicapped, from causes of ignorance, poverty, and
                neglect.</p>
            <p> Because of the controversial nature of this subject, commonly known as birth
                control, I wish to tell you something about its general application.</p>
            <p> This movement in its modern state began in this country in 1914. I myself, as a
                mother of 3 children, a member of a large family of 11, and a trained nurse, early
                came to the conclusion from my own experience in the slum districts of <place
                    reg="New York, NY">New York City</place>, that this was one of the most vital
                factors in maternal health and in the health of children.</p>
            <p> I found everywhere women who were seeking some means, some knowledge of what they
                could do to prevent the coming of other children whom they know, owing to their
                physical defects, they were unable to bring into the world in a healthy condition;
                or, owing to their husband’s economic circumstances, they would be unable to provide
                for.</p>
            <p> So I began to wonder if we could not do something about this law, which was passed
                by <org reg="United States Congress">Congress</org> in 1873, nearly 60 years ago.
                With all the advance that women have made and with all the advance of our charities
                and our philanthropies and with all the billions that are spent upon disease and
                defects, delinquency, and dependency, we still allow – in fact, we almost force
                married persons who continue in their normal, marital lives, to bring into the world
                children for whom they themselves could not provide.</p>
            <p> So, in order to stir up interest in this question and to get this law changed, it
                was necessary to organize public sentiment, which has now grown into the
                birth-control movement.</p>
            <p> Birth control is the conscious control of the birth rate by means that prevent the
                conception of human life. We emphasize “prevent”; not interrupt, not destroy. It
                does not mean abortion. It does not mean the interruption of life after conception
                occurs. There is not more an interruption of life or a destruction of life in
                preventing conception than in remaining single or living in abstinence or celibacy.
                Physiologically speaking, there is no difference.</p>
            <p> We say “control.” When we control, we do not have to limit any more than when you
                control your furnace you have to put the fire out. We control the furnace according
                to the heat that we desire to maintain in the home, according to the season,
                according to the hour of the day or night. You control your motor car, but you do
                not have to stop the engine.</p>
            <p> So, in controlling the size of the family or controlling the birth rate, we control
                it in accordance with the mother’s health, in consideration of the quality of
                inheritance that we are going to pass on to our children, in consideration of the
                father’s income and his earning capacity.</p>
            <p> This law, Mr. Chairman, was put upon the statute books at a time when there was very
                little recognition of the value of the practice of family limitation, when there was
                very little knowledge of the technique of contraception.</p>
            <p> Birth control or prevention of contraception was classed in the obscenity clause
                with abortion, pornography, and indecency; and it does not belong there.</p>
            <p> There was no exemption for physicians. There was no exemption for hospitals or
                dispensaries.</p>
            <p> Mr. Chairman, when that law was passed, it practically closed the avenues of
                knowledge to the medical profession in <place reg="United States">this
                    country</place>; it closed out knowledge of research that has been going on in
                other countries.</p>
            <p> It has left us, in so far as the control of child bearing is concerned, practically
                as in the days of barbarism or savagery. Furthermore, to all intents and purposes,
                the day that law was passed, women were placed into the category of child-bearing
                machines. Under this law they practically become conscript mothers.</p>
            <p> President Hoover in his address before the White House conference said:</p>
            <p><q who="HOOHE">“Let no one believe that these are questions which should not stir a
                    nation; that they are below the dignity of statesmen or government. If we could
                    have but one generation of properly born, trained, educated, and healthy
                    children, a thousand other problems of government would vanish. We would assure
                    ourselves of healthier minds in more vigorous bodies to direct the energies of
                    our Nation to yet greater heights of achievement. Moreover, one good community
                    nurse will save a dozen future policemen.”</q></p>
            <p> There are altogether seven very definite reasons – perhaps more – but I shall take
                up only seven, why we claim that birth control should be practiced.</p>
            <p> First. Wherever there is a transmissible disease, either the husband or wife
                suffering from insanity, feeblemindedness, epilepsy, or any other form of
                transmissible disease, neither of those persons should consider being a parent.</p>
            <p> Second. In conditions where the mother or the woman has a temporary disease, such as
                tuberculosis or a heart or kidney disease, pelvic deformity, goiter, and various
                other conditions, pregnancy becomes a great hazard to the woman’s life. We claim
                that the mother should be protected by having contraceptive information so that she
                can regain her health before she takes upon herself the burden of pregnancy.</p>
            <p> Third. Where parents though seemingly normal themselves, yet have already given
                birth to defective children, children with cleft palates, children that are
                subnormal, that are deaf and dumb, we claim that just for the good of the State
                those parents should refrain from further child bearing, even in spite of the great
                desire and hope for a normal child.</p>
            <p> Fourth. Every mother should safeguard her health as well as that of her unborn child
                by spacing the births of children for a period of from two to three years.</p>
            <p> Mr. Chairman and gentlemen, the days are past when it was a very easy matter for
                women to give birth to children, as it was two or three generations ago. Today it is
                known that the whole organism of a woman’s life, her nervous organism, is quite
                different from what it was in her grandmother’s days, and child bearing is a greater
                hazard today than it ever was before. In many, many cases, it leaves her not only in
                a precarious condition at the time, but often in a damaged condition for the
                future.</p>
            <p> We ask that she be able to recuperate from that ordeal, to take the time to enjoy
                her baby and to take the time to prepare herself physically and mentally and
                spiritually for the coming of the next child they may wish to have. That means a
                spacing from two to three years between children.</p>
            <p> Doctor <person reg="Woodbury, Robert Morse">Woodbury</person>, of the <org>United
                    States Children’s Bureau</org>, published some very interesting data where he
                clearly shows that too short an interval between childbirths markedly affects the
                infant death rate. Where the interval between births is three years, the infant
                death rate is 86.5 (per 1,000 births); when the interval is two years, th rate is
                98.6; and when it is only one year, the infant mortality goes up to 147.7. Certainly
                a very striking increase.</p>
            <p> Fifth. There are economic considerations. We believe that it is unfair, that it is
                not right, for people to have children for whom they cannot provide, and it is just
                as unfair for a man and woman to have children that society or the community or
                their older children have to provide for as it is for one country to spill over the
                other country’s border. It is just the same morally.</p>
            <p> We know that in our work we have had women come to us who 10 years ago were unable
                to provide for 4 or 6 children and who today have 12 or 15 which the community has
                been providing for and taking care of.</p>
            <p> Mr. Chairman, we found in our records that most of these children have to go out to
                work, have to compete with their father in the labor market just as soon as they get
                old enough to get a labor certificate from the community.</p>
            <p> We claim that our young people, while they may marry, and it might be advisable for
                them to marry early, should wait until they are fully complete in their development,
                through the adolescent period, before they become parents. We believe it would do
                away with a great many questions of immorality, promiscuity, and various other
                questions that concern us all today if this were more encouraged on the part of
                society.</p>
            <p> Sixth. The adolescent period must be considered. We are learning a great deal about
                the adolescent boy and girl. In the old days the Greeks advised their young men not
                to marry until their twenty-fifth year. There was something very important in that.
                Perhaps they did not know scientifically, but today we know that a man does not
                become really a man until his twenty-fifth year and that the woman does not become a
                woman, she is a girl, practically, until after the twenty-third year.</p>
            <p> This is illustrated by other findings of Doctor Woodbury. In homes, for instance,
                where the average number of persons per room is less than 1, the infant death rate
                is 52.1; where it is two or more per room, the death rate is 135.7. Furthermore, in
                families where the per capita income from the father’s earnings was less than $50
                the infant mortality rate was 215.9, as compared with a rate of only 60.5 where the
                per capita amount averaged $400 or over. These figures clearly and strikingly
                indicate the influence of family over-crowding upon family well being.</p>
            <p> Seventh. Adjustment. – A point on which many may disagree with us. I believe it is
                very important to our young people’s future that they should take at least two or
                three years of marriage just to get acquainted. Marriage is more today than just a
                question of providing for children. When there is a fine companionship in marriage
                between men and women, a spiritual development results. We believe that if two
                people have a chance to get acquainted, a chance to adjust themselves mentally and
                spiritually and physically, before they become parents, we shall have larger
                families. That is our belief, Mr. Chairman. We have seen it come true in the past 16
                or 17 years since we have been advocating this idea.</p>
            <p> There are three main methods of contraception or birth control.</p>
            <p> The first is continence. There are no laws against it. Anyone who wishes to practice
                continence or to live in celibacy is legally free to do so. No one disagrees with
                their right to live in this way, if they wish.</p>
            <p> The second is sterilization. There are 14 States in the Union today where there are
                sterilization laws. These provide for sterilization of certain types of persons who
                are morally irresponsible, who are able to bring into the world only progeny that
                will be a detriment to society.</p>
            <p> The third is chemical or mechanical means of contraception around which most of this
                controversy is waged.</p>
            <p> As you will see from this bill, we want the medical profession to direct the
                practice of contraception. We want no promiscuous distribution or scattering of
                knowledge of supplies as there has been in the past and there is today.</p>
            <p> We want, for all time, to have this knowledge properly controlled and we believe
                that this bill provides for that. It places responsibility of giving such
                information upon the medical profession. We have further found in the 28,000 cases
                that we have advised at the <org reg="Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau"
                    >Clinical Research Bureau</org> in the city of New York, which operates legally
                under the laws of the State of New York, which permit a physician to give
                information for the cure of prevention of disease, that knowledge of anatomy and
                physiology is necessary to instruct a woman properly according to her individual
                need. We have had 28,000 women who have come to us and who have been benefitted by
                the advice given them, as their homes will show, as their children will show and as
                their own health will show.</p>
            <p> We have found from these 28,000 cases, that every woman differs. You can no more
                claim that continence is the one and only method that should be practiced than you
                can say that everyone should be sterilized. Every woman is different
                physiologically. Family conditions are different in each case and so it takes the
                trained physician with his knowledge of anatomy and physiology to advise that
                person, just as it takes a trained oculist to advise as to the proper fitting of eye
                glasses. We do not send our people to 10-cent store nor to the corner druggist to
                get their supplies for contraception over the counter.</p>
            <p> We want this thing to be put on a decent basis, to be handled in a scientific way.
                That is what we are asking.</p>
            <p> This bill does not compel anyone to use such information. It does not compel any
                physician to give information. It simply permits contraceptive information and
                supplies to be sent to doctors or to hospitals and clinics from other countries and
                through the United States mails or by common carriers and permits supplies to be
                sent to druggists for use in their legitimate prescription business.</p>
            <p> Many of you may say, “Well, is there not everything in this country that we may
                wish?” And I wish to say, “No.” There is a great deal of research going on in other
                countries, in <org reg="Oxford University">Oxford</org> and <org
                    reg="Cambridge University">Cambridge</org> in <place>England</place>, and in
                    <org>Edinburgh University</org> in <place>Scotland</place>; a great deal of
                research is going on there which, according to the laws, can not come into this
                country.</p>
            <p> I have here today a letter from the customs official of New York City saying that
                certain things were sent to me from <place>Germany</place>, two articles, that will
                be destroyed. I have sent a letter and asked that they be readdressed to <person
                    reg="Stone, Hannah Mayer">the physician</person> who is the medical director of
                our research bureau in New York City, stating that though they may articles to
                prevent conception, they also fulfill another function of preventing the spread of
                disease or protecting health. I asked that they be sent to one of our physicians.
                The answer was that they could not be sent to anyone and I would like to offer this
                letter, Mr. Chairman, if I may.</p>
            <p> The Acting Chairman. You may put the letter in the record.</p>
            <p><q who="MSPP">[The correspondence between Margaret Sanger and <person
                        reg="Stuart, H. C.">H. C. Stuart</person> was omitted.]</q></p>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger. The law, <name reg="Section 305 of the Tariff Act of 1930">section
                    305</name> (a) of the tariff act does not allow any article of that kind to come
                into this country, and we are thus denied the results of research. We are denying
                our medical profession the benefit of knowledge obtained in various other countries
                where a great deal has been going on in the way of research, where they are
                unlimited in their research. There are only two countries in the world that have
                laws such as ours and they were patterned after our laws, unfortunately. Those
                countries are <place>France</place> and <place>Italy</place>.</p>
            <p> We have in this country nearly 100 clinics, birth-control clinics, that are legally
                operating in the various States. Forty-seven States allow the physician to protect
                the woman’s health and to give contraceptive advice as he sees fit. At the same time
                these physicians, while they may give information orally, have to bootleg their
                supplies from New York or <place reg="Chicago, IL">Chicago</place> or some place
                where they are manufactured in order to do what they should to protect the health of
                the woman in their own State.</p>
            <p> In the State of <place>California</place>, in <place reg="Los Angeles, CA">Los
                    Angeles</place>, under the county medical department 11 birth-control clinics
                have been established. If I should write and tell a woman in Los Angeles where one
                of those clinics is, or send her the address or name of the director of those
                clinics, I subject myself to the possibility of five years’ imprisonment and $5,000
                fine under <name reg="Section 211 United States Penal Code">section 211</name>; even
                to write her where she may go to obtain that information.</p>
            <p> It is preposterous; it is absurd. This whole situation is preposterous. Our laws are
                tangled and confused and as long as they remain as they are on the books, the
                situation will continue to be as it is.</p>
            <p> I myself have received over a million letters, a great majority of them from
                mothers. I am going to conclude by asking you if you will listen patiently to just a
                few of them, because I want to analyze them, to show you what the real condition
                is.</p>
            <p> Here is one that says:</p>
            <p><q who="UNK">I am the mother of 12 children, 6 of which are living. I have had 8
                    miscarriages in 20 years. I have been married and have a husband that does not
                    support his family like he should. If you can and it is in your power, please
                    tell me something to keep me from getting pregnant. I think I will die if I ever
                    have another baby. So please help me if you can. And may God bless you as long
                    as you live.</q></p>
            <p> Now, that is a 50 per cent loss. That woman has had 12 children and only 6 of them
                are living. She has had 8 miscarriages. Think of the wasted time, think of the loss
                to that woman; think of the loss of the power of motherhood when we make this woman
                go through such a ghastly ordeal.</p>
            <p> Here is another letter:</p>
            <p><q who="UNK">I have six children, my youngest 2 months old, and I am just scared to
                    death for fear I will get that way again, for I never can live to go through
                    with it again. I came near dying this time. For three months before my baby was
                    born, I could not get any shoes on my feet and I could hardly get my eyes open
                    to see. I was bloated up so bad. The doctor wanted to take the baby away when I
                    was 8 months, but I said no, I did not care if I lived or died and I did not
                    have the least idea of living, but the <name type="deity">Lord</name> spared me
                    probably so I could go through it all again. But I live on the banks of
                        <place>Lake Erie</place> and just as sure as I get in a family way again I
                    will end my troubles and be at rest. Now, if you can tell me of any way, I would
                    bless your name forever.</q></p>
            <p> That is another one. You can imagine that mother with that fear in her mind, with
                that sword hanging over her head.</p>
            <p> I want to say, Mr. Chairman, that since this law was passed, 1,500,000 mothers have
                passed out in the great beyond from causes due to child bearing.</p>
            <p> There is just one more that I want to read to you, because these are the women who
                are urging us to pass these laws to give them some relief from the evil condition
                from which they have been suffering.</p>
            <p><q who="UNK">I just passed my 21st birthday August 5th (this year). I am already the
                    mother of five little children, the oldest six, and the baby three months. My
                    husband has been out of work over a year and a half now. We would have starved
                    to death long ago but for our relatives who, among them, gave us $5 a week. It’s
                    awful hard, Mrs. Sanger, to live like this, and my husband got so down and blue
                    when he found I was that way last time, that he wanted to go away and live in
                    another place, but his folks wouldn’t let him do that. My children are well,
                    thank <name type="deity">God</name>, but I’m awfully weak, only weighing 90
                    pounds. I do all the work, and if only I could get strong and not have any more
                    babies, I’d take hope and so would my husband. Won’t you help me, please? I know
                    that God will bless you if you do.</q></p>
            <p> One more. This is a classic:</p>
            <p><q who="UNK">I am only 34 years old and have given birth to 12 children, only 3 of
                    them living. They die so quickly after they are born, it seems they don’t have
                    strength to live long. My husband is a good hard-working man, but the best he
                    ever made was $1.50, and never for long. We’re poor people, Mrs. Sanger, and the
                    coffins of the last two are not paid for yet. It’s hard on a woman to see them
                    go like that, and I think that if I did not have any for a while I could keep
                    the three I’ve got and give them better than we had.</q></p>
            <p> Is there any man in the world that would continue a business that shows a 75 per
                cent loss? Of course not. And yet these mothers are not only losing live babies, but
                they are interrupting pregnancies, thereby sapping their health and strength.</p>
            <p> One woman is only 34 years old, the other is only 21. Can you see, gentlemen, what
                it means to look ahead? Can you see that these women have years and years ahead of
                them of child bearing, of hopelessness, of despair? Why, the very entrance of a
                smiling, loving husband is a terror to these woman. Is it any wonder that homes are
                broken up? Some of the speakers will tell you something about the attitude of men.
                The young husbands have their problems too. They are trapped. They do not know what
                it is all about. They do not know what to do. They do the best they can, and yet the
                only thing they can do when they find their wives in a pregnant condition, with
                their hopelessness for the future, is to abort. In many of our cases we have brought
                them back again so that we can teach the husband and wife that it is not necessary
                to continue to bring children into the world that they can not take care of, and we
                have made many of these homes happier by proper instruction.</p>
            <p> These are the facts. These are the conditions; and there is just one thing that we
                must realize: <org>The United States Government</org> has already recognized that
                there is a population problem, at least as far as the quality is concerned, for you
                know that the Government has claimed the right to exclude immigrants whose condition
                is likely to be a serious danger to the well-being and happiness of the country. A
                very important law was passed, and there are now excluded by the <name
                    reg="Immigration Act of 1917">immigration act</name> of February 5, 1917 (39
                Stat. 874), regulating immigration of aliens to and residence of aliens in the
                United States, which reads as follows:</p>
            <p><q who="IA1917">Sec. 3. That the following classes of aliens shall be excluded from
                    admission into the United States: All idiots, imbeciles, feeble-minded persons,
                    epileptics, insane persons; persons who have had one or more attacks of insanity
                    at any time previously; persons of constitutional psychopathic inferiority;
                    persons with chronic alcoholism; paupers; professional beggars; vagrants;
                    persons afflicted with tuberculosis in any form or with a loathsome or dangerous
                    contagious disease; persons not comprehended within any of the foregoing
                    excluded classes who are found to be and are certified by the examining surgeon
                    as being mentally or physically defective, such physical defect being of a
                    nature which may affect the ability of such alien to earn a living; persons who
                    have been convicted of or admit to having committed a felony or other crime or
                    misdemeanor involving moral turpitude; polygamists, or persons who practice
                    polygamy or believe in or advocate the practice of polygamy; prostitutes, or
                    persons coming into the United States for the purpose of prostitution or for any
                    other immoral purpose; persons who directly or indirectly procure or attempt to
                    procure or import prostitutes or persons for the purpose of prostitution or for
                    any other immoral purpose; persons who are supported by or receive in whole or
                    in part the proceeds of prostitution; persons likely to become a public
                    charge.</q></p>
            <p> There are also provisions for the exclusion of illiterates, or of persons 16 years
                of age, physically capable of reading, but who cannot read English or some other
                language. All are refused admission into the United States of America.</p>
            <p> Mr. Chairman, I think it is a good law, and all that we are asking is, that if such
                persons and such types are not good for the country, to come in from the outside,
                that they also, by birth control, be prevented from coming into the world. If these
                types are not good for a country, and are a source of danger to our well-being and
                happiness, then I say, shall we not have the right to have these types of persons in
                this country excluded from birth?</p>
            <p> I thank you.</p>
            <p><q who="CRICH">The Acting Chairman. Are there any questions?</q></p>
            <p><q who="MCCJO">Mr. <person reg="McCormack, John William">McCormack</person>. Mrs.
                    Sanger, I was rather interested in your statement that you think a married
                    couple should wait two or three years just to get acquainted after marriage.
                    What did you mean by that – a probationary marriage or trial marriage? I think
                    you ought to explain that.</q></p>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger. No; I mean a permanent marriage. I think marriages would be more
                permanent if there were a proper adjustment and opportunity for getting acquainted
                at the beginning.</p>
            <p><q who="MCCJO">Mr. McCormack. Suppose they do not become acquainted?</q></p>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger. Of course we are going to give them a better chance to become
                acquainted; far better than they have today. If I may just digress a moment, what
                opportunity is there for young people to get acquainted? In the first year after
                marriage a woman’s whole physiological condition is changed. There may be some
                opportunity for the man – he does not have to have his whole physiological condition
                changed, but for the woman who comes back from her honeymoon with headaches, morning
                nausea, and a new nervous strain – not only is marriage a new condition for her, but
                the process and the possibility of motherhood entirely changes her whole being.</p>
            <p> Now, I say that those young people have not the first chance to get really
                acquainted. The man never knows his wife as a woman. He only knows her as a girl
                before marriage, and then he knows her as preparing for motherhood. I say it is
                unfair to the relationship of marriage. It is unfair to the child that is about to
                be born, and we know that it makes a great difference, and that marriage can be more
                permanent if there is the opportunity to become adjusted.</p>
            <p><q who="MCCJO">Mr. McCormack. You made reference to some statements made by President
                    Hoover. Did you intend thereby – I am sure you did not, but I would like to have
                    it in the record one way or the other – did you intend thereby to let the
                    inference be drawn that he was supporting this movement?</q></p>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger. Not at all. I simply made a statement that he believes in a healthier
                childhood, and that children should be given the opportunity to be born well.</p>
            <p><q who="MCCJO">Mr. McCormack. Continence is the exercise of the affirmative mind, is
                    it not?</q></p>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger. Not always.</p>
            <p><q who="MCCJO">Mr. McCormack. What was that conference at which President Hoover made
                    that statement?</q></p>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger. The White House Conference on Child Health and Protection, in 1931.</p>
            <p><q who="MCCJO">Mr. McCormack. Continence is the existence of the affirmative mind by
                    the individual; that is true, is it not?</q></p>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger. Not always the affirmative mind. It may be an exercise of a negative
                mind.</p>
            <p><q who="MCCJO">Mr. McCormack. But in an affirmative direction?</q></p>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger. Not altogether. I think it is negative just as it is affirmative. It is
                denial.</p>
            <p><q who="MCCJO">Mr. McCormack. Well, denial. It has to be an exercise of an
                    affirmative mind to deny themselves something that their inclination desires,
                    does it not?</q></p>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger. Well, it is a denial of a positive function, I should say.</p>
            <q who="MCCJO"><p> Mr. McCormack. Now, as to the chemical means of contraception, what
                    is meant by drugs, or the use of drugs? I notice this bill says:</p>
                <p><q who="HR">Any article, instrument, substance, drug, medicine, or thing that may
                        be used for the prevention of conception.</q></p>
                <p> What kind of drugs do you have in mind?</p></q>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger. Chinosol, quinine, and various other things that may form a suppository
                which will kill the spermatozoa.</p>
            <p><q who="MCCJO">Mr. McCormack. What kind of instruments has this bill in mind?</q></p>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger. Condoms and pessaries of various kinds.</p>
            <p><q who="MCCJO">Mr. McCormack. Of course, the purpose of those is for use prior, with
                    the purpose of preventing conception?</q></p>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger. Absolutely; no interference afterwards.</p>
            <p><q who="MCCJO">Mr. McCormack. In other words, it is a means of affording
                    self-satisfaction and preventing the consequences thereof by the use of
                    artificial means?</q></p>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger. If you wish to put it that way.</p>
            <p><q who="MCCJO">Mr. McCormack. Mrs. Sanger, in your statement you referred to “this
                    law.” Which law do you refer to?</q></p>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger. Sections 211, <name reg="Section 245 United States Penal Code"
                    >245</name>, and <name reg="Section 312 United States Penal Code">312</name> of
                the Criminal Code and section 305 of the tariff law.</p>
            <p> Mr. McCormack. Is that the Comstock law which Congressman <person
                    reg="Hancock, Clarence">Hancock</person> referred to?</p>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger. Yes. They were enacted by Congress at the instigation of Mr. <person
                    reg="Comstock, Anthony">Comstock</person> in 1873.</p>
            <p><q who="CRICH">The Acting Chairman. We thank you, Mrs. Sanger, for your presence and
                    your contribution to the hearings.</q></p>
            <p><q who="MSPP">[The matter submitted by Mrs. Sanger was omitted]</q></p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <p> FURTHER STATEMENT OF MRS. MARGARET SANGER</p>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger. Mr. Chairman and gentlemen of the committee, I wish it had been
                possible, without going into the personalities, to take a vote and to have shown the
                number of children born to and reared by those who appeared for and against this
                bill. It would be amusing were it not tragic in its significance to see a <person
                    reg="Norton, Mary Hopkins">childless woman who is a Member of Congress</person>
                appear here against this bill when she herself, were she obeying the laws of nature,
                would probably be at home attending to her 10 or 12 children.</p>
            <p> I have found in the arguments presented here that it as been a case of personal
                opinion against facts, theories against practical knowledge.</p>
            <p> For instance, I can illustrate that with some of the remarks made by Dr. <person
                    reg="Kelly, Howard Atwood">Howard Kelly</person>. When he was asked about
                contraceptives he knows – everybody who knows anything at all about this subject –
                that a douche is not a contraceptive but a cleansing agent, used more for hygienic
                purposes than for contraception. It means simply that Doctor Kelly has not been in
                school in the last 20 or 30 years, where he might have learned something of the
                modern technique of contraception.</p>
            <p> That is a case illustrative of the point I wish to make, the opponents of this bill
                do not know the facts. Here is a man like Doctor Kelly who has made his reputation
                in medicine, through long years of great achievement, coming here and talking not on
                the merits of the bill, but on a defense of “morals.” That is amusing, particularly
                when taken in conjunction with the statement of Dr. <person
                    reg="Ryan, John Augstine">John Ryan</person>, who is a theologian, a
                representative of the <org>Catholic Church</org>, who comes to theorize on economics
                and the population aspect of this question.</p>
            <p> That is all very right and proper. They may express their opinions, but Mr.
                Chairman, the merits of the bill have not been discussed by the opponents of the
                bill.</p>
            <p> As a matter of fact, when you weed out the personal opinions expressed, no one has
                said that the physician should not have the right to use the United States mails and
                common carriers. No one has dared to say that the physician has not the right to
                give contraceptive information where he sees that it is right and where he sees that
                a woman really needs it.</p>
            <p> That is the sum and substance of what this is all about.</p>
            <p> Canon <person reg="Chase, William Sheafe">Chase</person> made a statement for which
                I think he owes and apology to the Federal committee, when he said that this is a
                    “<q who="SHEWI">crook’s bill</q>.” I am not going to take the time to refute
                these stupid, senseless, futile, personal accusations. I want to say that he did say
                one good thing. He said, “<q who="SHEWI">No sensible person can oppose giving the
                    trustworthy physician freedom to do what is necessary to protect the lives of
                    women which would be endangered by another pregnancy if their husbands can not
                    control themselves</q>.”</p>
            <p> I thank him for that statement.</p>
            <p> Some people have said here that this bill would infringe upon State rights. That is
                not true. We included a statement in the proceedings yesterday to show that there
                are 47 States that give the physician the right to give information on the
                prevention of conception. About 24 States do not classify the prevention of
                conception in the obscenity laws at all. That is, there are 24 States where any one
                could give information. We are trying to direct public opinion so that it shall look
                to the physician to get such information and we are trying to make it possible for
                the physician to have the best information to give. There is only one State where
                there is any doubt about it.</p>
            <p><q who="CANHA">Mr. <person reg="Canfield, Henry Clifford">Canfield</person>. What
                    State is that?</q></p>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger. <place>Mississippi</place>. This bill does not open the mails to
                promiscuous distributions so that anyone can have information. It simply asks that
                the physician shall have the right of the <org reg="United States Postal Service"
                    >United States mails</org> and the common carriers, and that licensed clinics
                and the hospitals shall have the same right.</p>
            <p> Mr. Chairman, I do not know whether the bill as it has been amended has been offered
                or not. Mr. Hancock made some changes.</p>
            <p><q who="CRICH">The Acting Chairman. Those changes are a part of this testimony and as
                    the committee considers this measure they will consider all that has been said
                    with reference to it.</q></p>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger. I want to say that the physician will not use the United States mails
                to advise or prescribe for patients. Let me try to make that clear to you. Every
                physician who knows his job at all will see the patient, will study the indications.
                He will advise her as to her personal needs and personal requirements. He will take
                into consideration not only her health but her whole gynecological formation and
                condition. He will take into consideration her economic situation, and he will
                advise her then, and that will come under the State law. But before he can advise he
                must have information, he must know what is available in the world in this regard.
                The medical schools of the past have not given this knowledge to him.</p>
            <p> Not only shall the doctor advise the patient orally, but he must then give her a
                prescription by which she can get the articles recommended. That is why he must use
                the United States mail.</p>
            <p> In many cases he himself will give her the article or device and in some cases he
                will give her a prescription for the drug store.</p>
            <p> In my estimation this is the only way that the present promiscuous scattering of
                information and devices can be corrected. I consider this the sanest way of trying
                to correct the misuse of knowledge or misinformation that has been and still is so
                prevalent throughout the country and which both proponents and opponents
                deplore.</p>
            <p> There are 150,000 physicians in the United States who belong to the <org>American
                    Medical Association</org>. There is some difference of opinion among them. The
                American Medical Association as a whole has never gone on record for or against this
                measure, but a few years ago the <org
                    reg="American Medical Association Section on Obsetrics, Gynecology, and Abdomibal Surgery"
                    >section on obstetrics and gynecology and abdominal surgery</org> did go on
                record by a resolution to the effect that they recommended “the alteration of
                existing laws whenever necessary so that physicians my legally give contraceptive
                information to their patients in the regular course of their practice.” That
                resolution, Mr. Chairman, was submitted in record yesterday and is printed elsewhere
                in full.</p>
            <p> To give you a brief idea of how the medical profession regards this question, I
                shall cite from a questionnaire sent out by the <title type="journal">Medical
                    Journal and Record</title> in 1927. Two hundred and seventy-three doctors
                replied and out of the 273, 248 were in favor of birth control or proper legislation
                leading thereto; 19 were against; 2 of them said they were unable to express an
                opinion. One said that he thought that contraceptive methods would be abused. One
                said that methods shall be advised only after consultation with a physician, with
                the sanction of the <org>United States Government</org>, and the <title type="book"
                    >Bible</title>; and one thought that this generation knows too much about such
                things, and that the poor would not avail themselves of this information.</p>
            <p> Those in favor represent a pretty large proportion of the number that expressed
                themselves in this symposium.</p>
            <p> Following that up, the <title type="journal">Medical Journal and Record</title> in
                1929 sent out another questionnaire, and 118 doctors replied to that, of which
                number 99 said that they were in favor and only four said that they were not
                informed sufficiently to express an opinion. Fifteen were opposed.</p>
            <p> I just mention this to show you that there is a division of opinion, but there is a
                very much larger number of physicians who are for this than are against it.</p>
            <p> Evidence was presented yesterday of the large number of county and city medical
                organization in favor of this particular legislation and also of many who are in
                favor of the principles of birth control. </p>
            <p> Two ex-presidents of the American Medical Association have made statements in our
                favor – Dr. <person reg="Jacobi, Abraham">Abraham Jacobi</person> and Dr. <person
                    reg="Pusey, William Allan">Allan Pusey</person>.</p>
            <p> It has been stated that contraceptive measures or practices left a harmful effect
                upon the pelvic organs upon the nervous system of those who practiced it.</p>
            <p> Again these statements are made by people who have an opinion but who have not the
                facts. We have the facts. We have been following up cases not only in New York but
                throughout the country where there are a hundred or more clinics. There have been
                28,000 patients in one clinic in New York, the <org>Birth Control Clinic Research
                    Bureau</org>, whose case records reveal facts to the contrary. We have had the
                patients come back to us, and we have a detailed study and analysis made of the
                first 10,000 of those cases, a record which is too voluminous to bring here today;
                but we have the actual facts from which to substantiate our conclusions.</p>
            <p> I am going to ask, Mr. Chairman, if I may, to present one case that I took at random
                as an illustration.</p>
            <p> An <person reg="Unknown">Italian woman</person>, 29 years old on first visit
                (married at 15 years). Diagnosed as “high-grade moron” with husband classified as
                “mental case.” Three children, youngest an infant; two miscarriages, both due to
                overwork. Five pregnancies in all. Clinical contraceptive advice now successful for
                four years. This family able to carry on without help from social agency by whom she
                was referred to us.</p>
            <p> It seems to me that that tells something of what the actual practice of
                contraception can do; how it will relieve the tremendous and growing burdens of
                charity now resting on society.</p>
            <p> Here is a report by Dr. <person reg="Butler, Lily C.">Lily C. Butler</person>,
                medical officer of the <org>Walworth Woman’s Welfare Center</org>, presented before
                the <org reg="International Birth Control Conference, 7th">Seventh International
                    Birth Control Conference</org> held last September in <place
                    reg="Zurich, Switzerland">Zurich</place>, which reads as follows:</p>
            <p>
                <q who="BUTLI">So much is stated by opponents of birth control as to contraceptive
                    subsequently producing sterility that the figures we have obtained on going
                    through our cards at Walworth and East <place reg="London, England"
                        >London</place> are interesting. We note that 101 patients have wanted
                    another child after periods varying from one to five years, and in 98 of these
                    cases they have become pregnant on discontinuing the use of the
                    contraceptive.</q></p>
            <p> That shows that when proper means are applied to protect the individual woman there
                is no question that it is helpful to her and that it does not make her sterile.</p>
            <p> To answer Mrs. Norton’s challenge regarding my statement that 1,500,000 women have
                died from causes due to childbearing since this Comstock law was passed, I wish to
                state that this estimate was based on the figures of the <org>United States Census
                    Bureau, Department of Vital Statistics</org>.</p>
            <p> I wish to refute directly one other statement made by Mrs. Norton. In a reference to
                the sale of contraceptives, Mrs. Norton used the words “<q who="NORMA">commercially
                    profitable to their advocates</q>.” Never have I, nor to my knowledge have any
                members of the committee, of which I am the national chairman, been interested in
                contraceptives for commercial profit. Mrs. Norton has seen fit to say that several
                of the statements made by me and other witnesses appearing for this bill were not
                supported by fact. I wish to say the same regarding her statement which I have
                quoted.</p>
            <p> There is one other phase of this matter that is rather amusing. I think it was
                briefly stated yesterday that the geniuses, the flower of the family usually came at
                the end of a long line of children in large families.</p>
            <p> I have here a study of over 700 persons of personalities who have come down to us
                through history.</p>
            <p> I will mention these briefly, and then if I may, I will put this list in the
                record.</p>
            <p><q who="CRICH">The Acting Chairman. You have that permission.</q></p>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger. Ninety-six of these were the only child; 204 were the first child; 113
                were the second; 64 were the third; 50 were the fourth; 43 were the fifth. This goes
                right on down until you get to the eighteenth and nineteenth. <person
                    reg="Wesley, John">John Wesley</person> was the fifteenth and <person
                    reg="Caruso, Enrico">Caruso</person> was the eighteenth, but a pitiful number of
                the other children in these families had died in infancy.</p>
            <p> There are only two or three among those men and women who can be classified as
                “great” who were born late in the family’s life, while those that were second or
                third make up a much larger portion.</p>
            <p><q who="MSPP">[The document referred to has been omitted]</q></p>
            <p> The further we look into these things, Mr. Chairman, the more there is to be said
                for the care and the consideration that parents can give to 1 or 2 children or 3 or
                4 children according to their means, according to their health. Further evidence is
                found in the Bible:</p>
            <p><person>Isaac</person>, in whose seed all the nations were to be blessed, was an only
                child, born after long years of preparation. <person>Sarah</person>, his mother, was
                a beautiful, talented woman, whose counsel was highly valued. Isaac’s only children
                were twins – <person>Jacob</person>, the father of all of <place>Israel</place>, and
                    <person>Esau</person>. Isaac’s wife, <person reg="Rebekah">Rebecca</person>, was
                also a lovely woman of fine character, whose opinion was sought and valued.
                    <person>Joseph</person>, the child of <person>Rachel</person>, was born late in
                her life, and she had but one other child. <person>Samuel</person>, who judged
                Israel for 40 years, was an only child, born after years of prayer and supplication
                on the part of <person>Hannah</person>. <person>John the Baptist</person> was an
                only child and his parents were well along in years when he was born.</p>
            <p><person reg="Jesus Christ">Jesus</person> was the first born of
                    <person>Joseph</person> and <person>Mary</person> and had no children.</p>
            <p> So that even on the question of the place of great men in the family, our position
                is much stronger than that of our opponents.</p>
            <p> Mr. Chairman, I want to yield the rest of my time to Doctor <person
                    reg="Meyer, Adolf">Meyer</person>, because of the statement that has been made
                by the opponents with regard to the question of continence. Continence, Mr.
                Chairman, is something on which there has been recent study by a large group of
                medical men. They have come to know something about continence and its effects upon
                the human being and I now ask Dr. Adolf Meyer, professor of psychiatry in <org>Johns
                    Hopkins University</org>, to take up that part of our presentation.</p>
            <p><q who="MCCJO">Mr. McCormack. Mr. Chairman, if Mrs. Sanger is yielding to Doctor
                    Meyer because of the limitation of time, I ask unanimous consent that she be
                    given an additional five minutes.</q></p>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger. Thank you, Mr. McCormack, but I think I have finished my statement and
                I would rather the committee heard Doctor Meyer.</p>
            <p><q who="CRICH">The Acting Chairman. Thank you, Mrs. Sanger, for your statement. We
                    shall be pleased to hear Doctor Meyer.</q></p>
            <p><q who="MSPP">[Statement by Dr. Adolf Meyer was omitted.]</q></p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
