<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published statement">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/06/26 CH proofed</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2015 clean regs + correct proof EK</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1912-03-05"> 5 Mar. 1912</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Testimony on the Strike at Lawrence</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp300421</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>House of Representatives Records,</title> National Archives</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Collected Documents</title> C15:19</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="POUWI"><person>Pou, William</person></name>
            <name id="FOSDA"><person>Foster, David Martin</person></name>
            <name id="STAAU"><person>Stanley, Augustus Owsley</person></name>
            <name id="WILWI"><person>Wilson, William Warfield</person></name>
            <name id="LENIR"><person>Lenroot, Irvin Luther</person></name>
            <name id="HARTH"><person>Hardwick, Thomas William</person></name>
            <name id="HENRO"><person>Henry, Robert Lee</person></name>
            <name id="SANMA">Sanger, Margaret</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Sanger was asked to testify before the House of Representatives in
            Washington, D.C. about her role in supporting the striking workers in Lawrence, MA.</p>
        <index level1="labor movement" level2="strikes" level3="Lawrence, MA (1912)"/>
        <index level1="labor movement" level2="strikes"/>
        <index level1="child labor"/>
        <index level1="child welfare"/>
        <index level1="United States Congress" level2="House of Representatives"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="as a nurse"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>TESTIMONY ON THE STRIKE AT LAWRENCE, MASS.</head>
        <byline>STATEMENT OF MISS <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">MARGARET SANGER</person>.</byline>
        <dateline><date value="1912-03-05"/> March 5, 1912</dateline>
        <p><person reg="Pou, William">MR. POU</person>. <q who="POUWI">You are from <place
                    reg="New York, NY">New York</place>, are you?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">Yes.</q></p>
        <p>MR. POU. <q who="POUWI">You were instrumental in taking a number of children away from
                    <place reg="Lawrence, MA">Lawrence</place>, were you not?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">Yes.</q></p>
        <p>MR. POU. <q who="POUWI">I will be obligated to you if you will just go ahead and state in
                your own way what took place.</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">Well, I helped to take the first section of children, when
                there was no difficulty in getting them away. We brought them to New York and gave
                them supper; we took them to the <org>Labor Temple,</org> where people were waiting
                to take them to their homes; there they had a supper and they were distributed, and
                that was all there was to think about.</q></p>
        <p>MR. POU. <q who="POUWI">How long was that before the day we have been talking about, the
                24th of February, I think it was?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">I think that was two weeks.</q></p>
        <p>MR. POU. <q who="POUWI">How many of the children were taken to New York?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">One hundred and nineteen at this time and 92 a week
                afterwards.</q></p>
        <p>MR. POU. <q who="POUWI">Altogether that would be something over 200?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">Yes, sir.</q></p>
        <p>MR. POU. <q who="POUWI">Well, you had no trouble with the police?</q>
        </p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">No; we had no trouble.</q></p>
        <p>MR. POU. <q who="POUWI">They had not decided to prevent the children from leaving when
                you took these away? </q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">No; not at this time.</q></p>
        <p>MR. POU. <q who="POUWI">Did you talk with those children about their manner of living in
                Lawrence and about the food they got?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">Yes, sir. I am a trained nurse, and I was especially
                interested in the condition of the children.</q></p>
        <p>MR. POU. <q who="POUWI">Now, as a rule, is it true that the children of the working
                people in Lawrence--the class we are investigating now--only got meat once a
                week.</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">Those were the assertions of not only the children but of the
                parents that I interviewed.</q></p>
        <p><person reg="Foster, David Martin"/>MR. FOSTER. <q who="FOSDA">How long were you in
                Lawrence?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">I was only there one night.</q></p>
        <p>MR. FOSTER. <q who="FOSDA">You arrived in Lawrence in the evening and left the next
                morning?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">Yes.</q></p>
        <p>MR. FOSTER. <q who="FOSDA">You did not visit any of the homes of the strikers?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">No. When the people brought the children to the hall the next
                morning to be taken away I inquired of some of the parents about the
            children.</q></p>
        <p>MR. FOSTER. <q who="FOSDA">You say you are a trained nurse?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">Yes, sir.</q></p>
        <p>MR. FOSTER. <q who="FOSDA">And what was the physical appearence of these children that
                you took to New York? You know something about how they should look; were they
                properly nourished?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">Well, the condition of those children was the most horrible
                that I have ever seen.</q></p>
        <p>MR. FOSTER. <q who="FOSDA">Tell the committee something about how they looked.</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">In the first place, there were four little children who had
                chicken pox that we kept there; we would not allow them to go away; and then one of
                the children had just gotten over chicken pox, and the father begged us to let the
                child come; he had one 2 years old and another 3 1/2 years old, I believe, and he
                begged us to let those children come, because he was a widower and had no wife or
                anyone to take care of these children; he left them with the neighbors during the
                day. So I took these little children, and we isolated them on the way to New York,
                and when we got there they were placed under the doctor's care. All of these
                children were walking about there apparently not noticing chicken pox or diphtheria;
                one child had diphtheria and had been walking around, and no attention paid to it at
                all, and had been working up to the time of the strike. Out of the 119 children four
                of them had underwear on, and it was the most bitter weather; we had to run all the
                way from the hall to the station in order to keep warm; and only four had
                underwear.</q></p>
        <p>MR. FOSTER. <q who="FOSDA">You say only four had underwear?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">Yes.</q></p>
        <p>MR. FOSTER. <q who="FOSDA">What was the character of their outer clothing; was it
                wooolen?</q></p>
        <p><person reg="Stanley, Augustus Owsley">MR. STANLEY</person>. <q who="STAAU">Were the
                people working in a woolen mill?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">Yes, sir.</q></p>
        <p>MR. STANLEY.<q who="STAAU">Where they make underwear?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">Yes, sir.</q></p>
        <p>MR. FOSTER. <q who="FOSDA"> How about the outer clothing?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">It was almost in rags; their coats were eaten off as though
                they were simply worn to shreds.</q></p>
        <p>MR. FOSTER. <q who="FOSDA">Was it woolen clothing?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">No, sir; I do not think that any one of them had on any
                woolen clothing; that is, to my own knowledge.</q></p>
        <p>MR. FOSTER. <q who="FOSDA">What was their color? Did they seem to be well
            nourished?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">They were very much emanciated; every child there showed the
                effects of malnutrition, and all of them, or almost all of them, according to the
                doctor's certificate that night, had adenoids and enlarged tonsils. They were all
                examined at the station. We had a little time in the morning, and they were examined
                before they left.</q></p>
        <p>MR. FOSTER. <q who="FOSDA">They all looked thin and pale?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">Yes. I would like to say that when they had this supper it
                would bring tears to your eyes to see them grab the meat with their hands and eat
                it.</q></p>
        <p>MR. FOSTER. <q who="FOSDA">They ate the meat as though they really enjoyed it?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">Yes; decidedly.</q></p>
        <p>MR. FOSTER. <q who="FOSDA">And you say there were only four out of 119 that had any
                underclothing?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">Yes, sir; and it was the bitterest weather we have had this
                year.</q></p>
        <p>MR. FOSTER. <q who="FOSDA">And the outer clothing was ragged?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">In rags. I think perhaps 20 of them had overcoats.</q></p>
        <p>MR. FOSTER. <q who="FOSDA">What kind of shoes did they have?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">Almost on the ground, except some of the older girls, who had
                been working in the mills; they had better shoes; but the little ones, who had to
                depend on others, were in a most deplorable condition.</q></p>
        <p>MR. FOSTER. <q who="FOSDA">Did they have on woolen stockings?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">I do not think any of them had a bit of wool on their
                bodies.</q></p>
        <p>MR. FOSTER. <q who="FOSDA">And yet working in woolen mills?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">Yes, sir.</q></p>
        <p><person reg="Henry, Robert Lee">THE CHAIRMAN</person>. <q who="HENRO">Kindly read the
                letter I now hand to the committee.</q></p>
        <p>MR. FOSTER. <q who="FOSDA">May I ask Miss Sanger what organization she represents in New
                York City.</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">I was previously the Woman organizer of the <org>Socialist
                    Party</org>.</q></p>
        <p>New York, February 1, 1916. To whom it may concern: We, undersigned Italian doctors
            invited to make a preliminary physical examination of the Lawrence strikers' children,
            verified that all children were of poor physical build, defective, and underfed. The
            majority of them had enlarged glands, throat, nose, eyes, defective, and affected. All
            were poorly clad even against the rigor of the season. (And signed by six
            physicians.)</p>
        <p>THE CHAIRMAN. <q who="HENRO">Can you read their names?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA"><person reg="Petilex, Diamede">Diamede Petilex</person>,
                M.D., 56 Mulberry Street; Dr. <person reg="Jeseau, Exore">Exore Jeseau</person>, 175
                Worth Street; Dr. <person reg="De Filipi, Alfredo">Alfredo De Filipi</person>, 56
                Mott Street; Dr. <person reg="Bellantoni, Rocco">Rocco Bellantoni</person>, 373
                Broome Street; Dr. <person reg="Loquito, J.">J. Loquito</person>, 200 Grand Street,
                New York City. </q></p>
        <p>THE CHAIRMAN. <q who="HENRO">Does that refer to the same children of whom you have been
                speaking?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">Yes, sir.</q></p>
        <p><person reg="Wilson, William Warfield">MR. WILSON.</person>
            <q who="WILWI"> Where did those doctors live?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA"> They were physicians of the Italian federation of New York
                City, who volunteered their services to take charge of the children while in New
                York.</q></p>
        <p><person reg="Lenroot, Irvin Luther">MR. LENROOT.</person><q who="LENIR">Can you give the
                committe any information as to how the condition of these children compared with
                that of other children in similar circumstances of life? </q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">Yes; I have been brought up in a <place reg="Corning, NY"
                    >factory town</place> where there are glassblowers and children of glassblowers,
                and I must say that I have never seen in any place children so ragged and so
                deplorable as these children were. I have never seen such children in my work in the
                Italian districts of New York City; in the slum districts, I must say, there are
                always a few of them who are fat and rugged, but these children were pale and
                thin.</q></p>
        <p>THE CHAIRMAN. <q who="HENRO">Have you any other statement you would like to make to the
                committee?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">I would like to refute the statement that has been made that
                the children appeared at a mass meeting. That is not so.</q></p>
        <p>THE CHAIRMAN. <q who="HENRO">You may make any statement you deem proper about
            that.</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">That is not so. I was on the children's committee for both
                consignments of children, and they have never appeared on a platform in New York
                City, except the second time; when the children came to New York, in order to
                prevent the terrible rush when they were going for dinner, we crossed over at Union
                Square on a little platform to get ahead of the rush, so they could get into
                    <org>Arlington Hall</org> before the rush and mob came. That was the only
                appearence they ever made on a platform, in crossing from one side to the
            other.</q></p>
        <p>THE CHAIRMAN. <q who="HENRO">Speaking for myself, I do not think that needs an apology. I
                think if they wanted to parade them before public they had a constitutional right to
                do so.</q></p>
        <p><supplied resp="MSPP">Editor's note: We have ommitted the text of a short conversation
                between the Chairman and Mr. Hardwick over whether the Committee should express
                itself on the consitutional right to parade the children.</supplied></p>
        <p><person reg="Hardwick, Thomas William">MR. HARDWICK.</person><q who="HARTH"> It is true
                or not--I am not expressing an opinion one way or the other, although I have an
                opinion on that subject, the same as my colleague, but I do not care express myself
                at present--that these children were in any way exhibited to the public during their
                stay in New York?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">Only from the time they left the Grand Central Station until
                they went to hall where they were to have their supper</q></p>
        <p>MR. HARDWICK.<q who="HARTH"> When they went to the hall, of course, there was a crowd
                there, and was that a public affair?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">No.</q></p>
        <p>MR. HARDWICK.<q who="HARTH">How many people were there?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">Well, no one was allowed there except the committee who were
                to take charge fo the children and to give them their food.</q></p>
        <p>MR. HARDWICK.<q who="HARTH">I have seen some statements in the New York papers about
                these things, and you probably have read them, too. I was under the impression that
                one of those statements was to the effect that these children were taken to some
                mass meeting of either the Socialist Party or some labor organization. Is that true
                in point of fact or not?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">No; that is not true. They have never been taken to a public
                meeting in New York.</q></p>
        <p>MR. HARDWICK. <q who="HARTH">They never were?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">No, sir.</q>
        </p>
        <p>MR. HARDWICK. <q who="HARTH"> When they came to the station natural curiosity brought a
                great crowd to see them?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">Yes; and they wrapped their coats about these little
                children; the men took their coats right off and carried them on their shoulders to
                their place of destination.</q></p>
        <p>MR. HARDWICK. <q who="HARTH">Just the natural curiosity to see these little suffering
                children?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">Yes, sir.</q></p>
        <p>MR. HARDWICK. <q who="HARTH">And outside of the usual publicity that attends such a thing
                as this there was no attempt to give it purposeful publicity?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">No; I do not think there was any special attention given to
                that; they were simply taken from one place to another--from the Grand Central
                Station to their place of destination.</q></p>
        <p>MR. HARDWICK. <q who="HARTH">They were not used at any public place or at a mass
                meeting?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">No; there was no attempt to exploit these children, as the
                papers stated.</q></p>
        <p>MR. HARDWICK. <q who="HARTH">I am very glad to hear you say that is incorrect.</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">That is absolutely untrue.</q></p>
        <p>THE CHAIRMAN. <q who="HENRO">Will you explain a little further about the index cards or
                identification cards so we may understand about them exactly?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">We first had an application blank made out in printed form.
                Any applicant who desired to have a child would make this application, stating that
                at a specified time, or whenever the parents desired, the child could be returned to
                them, or whenever the strike committee asked that the child be returned. Then there
                was another identification card; on one side was the child's name. Its parents'
                names, the place of residence and nationality, and on the opposite side of the card
                was the child's tutor or guardian. Those cards were signed by the committee from
                Lawrence. A special committee came with each nationality; the Polish people sent a
                Polish delegate, the French people sent a delegate representing their nationality,
                and so on, so that all of the children were placed in families where they could
                learn to speak their own language. And those cards were signed, and we kept them
                together. </q></p>
        <p>THE CHAIRMAN. <q who="HENRO">In other words, you had a perfect system of
                identification?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">A very good system, yes.</q></p>
        <p>MR. HARDWICK. <q who="HARTH">Those children are still in New York, you say?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">Yes, sir.</q></p>
        <p>MR. HARDWICK. <q who="HARTH">You are taking good care of them?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">Yes, sir.</q></p>
        <p>MR. HARDWICK. <q who="HARTH">Treating them nicely?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">Yes, sir.</q></p>
        <p>MR. HARDWICK. <q who="HARTH">And they are enjoying their vacation?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. <q who="SANMA">They have enjoyed it very much.</q></p>
        <p>MR. HARDWICK. <q who="HARTH">And their physical condition has improved very much?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. We have a number of letters from the people who have the childrens saying
            that they have noticed an improvement in their physical condition.</p>
        <p>MR. HARDWICK. <q who="HARTH">You seem to be very thoroughly familiar with the details of
                this thing, so far as the New York end of it is concerned. I want to ask you a plain
                question and I want a candid answer to it, and I believe you will give it to me: Was
                the purpose in carrying these children to New York single or was it twofold? Was it
                single in that its only purpose was that of taking care of the children and helping
                the strikers, or was it twofold in that it was not only for the purpose I have just
                mentioned, but also for the purposes of aiding the strikers and helping break down
                the opposition of the bosses?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. The main purpose in my estimation was that it was going to help them--</p>
        <p>MR. HARDWICK. (interposing)<q who="HARTH">Win the strike?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. Yes; win the strike. For instance, a father that I have in mind sent five
            boys with me: I said to him, "Is this going to help you?" He said, <q who="UNK">"God, I
                do not know what I would have doen with the five children if you had not taken
                them,"</q> and so on. The people all expressed themselves int he same way--that this
            was going to be of great assistance to them. </p>
        <p> MR. STANLEY.<q who="STAAU">You mean they could weather the storm if they did not have to
                provide for the children?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. Yes, sir.</p>
        <p>MR. HARDWICK. <q who="HARTH">As this is a new departure in American strike warfare I want
                to see what it means. Was it also the idea that by sending these children to other
                cities it would excite the sympathy of the people and aid the strikers in their
                warfare?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. I think it is having a great deal to do with it. </p>
        <p>MR. HARDWICK. <q who="HARTH">I thought you would answer frankly. I am not expressing my
                opinion one way or the other.</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. I think it has.</p>
        <p>THE CHAIRMAN. <q who="HENRO">Personally, was it your purpose to aid the strikers or to
                give the children a home.</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. I was first interested in it as soon as I heard the children were coming to
            New York, when I telegraphed that I desired to take care of the children; that was my
            first interest.</p>
        <p>THE CHAIRMAN. <q who="HENRO">That was your main purpose?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. Yes, sir.</p>
        <p>THE CHAIRMAN. <q who="HENRO">Personally?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. Yes, sir.</p>
        <p>Thereupon a recess was taken until 2:30 o'clock p.m.</p>
        <p>AFTER RECESS</p>
        <p>The committee met, pursuant to the taking of recess, at 2:30 o'clock p.m., Hon. Robert L.
            Henry (chairman) presiding.</p>
        <p>THE CHAIRMAN. <q who="HENRO">The committee will be in order. Miss Sanger, will you take
                the stand again?</q></p>
        <p>STATEMENT OF MISS MARGARET SANGER--Resumed </p>
        <p>THE CHAIRMAN. <q who="HENRO">Miss Sanger, it has been stated that it would have been
                cheaper to have kept the children in Lawrence than to pay the railroad fare to New
                York. What about that?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. Yes, that phase of the subject was considered by the New York committee
            before the final arrangements were made to bring them here. I myself went about a number
            of people who had volunteered through the press, their request for the children, and I
            came to the committee with an assurance of about $100 that the people would send to
            those homes in Lawrence. But after the committee figured out the number of children
            there to be taken care of, it was asserted that there would take something like a
            hundred thousand or a couple of hundred thousand dollars to care for the children there,
            and it was decided that it would not be as beneficial to the children as to bring them
            to New York and put them in families.</p>
        <p>MR. WILSON. <q who="WILWI"> May I ask you a question?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. Certainly</p>
        <p>MR. WILSON. <q who="WILWI"> You stated this morning that four of the children out of the
                one hundred and nineteen had on underclothing. It was suggested during the noon hour
                by individuals, to me, that the rest of the children were possibly in the habit of
                wearing underclothing during the cold weather, but that it had been taken off to
                create a little more sympathy, or excite a little more sympathy. Do you know whether
                or not these children were in the habit of wearing underclothing?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. My candid opinion is that the first consignment of children were not in the
            best condition, because they were simply picked out of their homes without any
            preparation, and I do not believe this is true. They were simply taken out of their
            homes, being told the night before that they had to start on the early train. Some of
            the fathers and mothers brought the, to the station with their own clothing wrapped
            around tehm to keep them from the cold.</p>
        <p>MR. WILSON. <q who="WILWI"> Do you think that these same children, when going to New
                York, wore their poorest clothing, thinking that they would be replenished when they
                got in New York by your friends, and that they left their better clothing at home
                for the purpose of getting more out of it than if they had taken their other
                clothing?</q></p>
        <p>MISS SANGER. I thought of that at the time, and I asked the children if they had any
            better clothing, and not one of them had. They wore the very best clothing they had.
            They all tried to look their very best. The girls wore their best ribbons</p>
        <p>THE CHAIRMAN. <q who="HENRO">You may stand aside.</q></p>
        <p/>
    </docBody>
</doc>
