<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "file:/S:/TRANSCRIPTIONS/XML%20Drafts/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed draft article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2010/04/07 AC</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1936-00-00">1936</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Mahatma Ghandi and Birth Control</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp301248</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Collected Documents</bibl>
            <bibl><title>MSM</title> C16:401</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp>
                <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
                <name id="GANMA">Gandhi, Mahatma</name>
            </resp>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">Add text if needed. <index level1="India"/>
        <index level1="Gandhi, Mahatma"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="sterilization"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="international"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head><person>Mahatma Ghandi</person> and Birth Control</head>
        <p> The compelling personality of Mr. Gandhi attracts many of the visitors to
                <place>India</place> to seek him out. He seems to hold the key to so many of the
            problems of India. The opinions of a man who almost singlehanded has challenged the
            imperial power of <place rend="Great Britain">Britain</place> as it holds power in India
            are considered well worth having.</p>
        <p> But politics apart Mr. Gandhi’s opinion is sought on all kinds of moral and social
            problems and to all of them he brings a point of view that is penetrating and very
            human. Mr. Gandhi does not lump people together, to him an individual is something
            unique and he has the charming gift of making you feel that his conversation with you is
            full of interest to him and it is just impossible for the moment to remember that the
            man you are talking to has taken upon himself the task of guiding the political
            destinies of 350 million people.</p>
        <p> A prominent Hindu lady said to me a few years ago, “<q who="UNK">If Mr. Gandhi would
                stand for Birth Control it would sweep India from end to end.</q>” But alas! for
            suffering women Mr. Gandhi will have nothing to do with birth control, he regards it as
            sin, as a temptation to mankind to pander to his lower nature, as an invention of the
            devil to lure men and women from the path sacrifices, the cost in human life fell
            equally on men as on women but the price paid by women and their babies is so utterly
            disproportionate to that paid by men that one would have thought Mr. Gandhi’s human
            sympathies would have made him see that in this matter there is a fundamental difference
            between the needs of men and women. Simple humanity and justice demand that the women
            shall be given the knowledge to control her motherhood and thus equipped she can listen
            to Mr. Gandhi’s teaching as an equal. If of her own free choice she renounces sexual
            intercourse except when she desires to become a mother, that is a matter for her own
            conscience. If her husband forces intercourse upon her or takes advantage of her youth
            and ignorance as happens in millions of cases today in India and other countries it is
            cruel and heartless to blame the woman or to say as Mr. Gandhi says “<q who="GANMA">If
                people will breed like rabbits then they must die like rabbits.</q>” They are dying
            today but women <gap reason="illegible" extent="two words"/> more than men due largely
            to premature and unceasing pregnancies to such an extent that though in most countries
            there is an excess of women, there are 10 million more men than women in India according
            to the 1931 census.</p>
        <p>
            <person reg="Rathbone, Eleanor">Eleanor Rathbone</person>, M.P. has rightly termed this
            sacrifice of young women and girls the Indian minotaur and I do not yet despair that Mr.
            Gandhi will find some more practicable remedy to save a large number of the 200,000
            Indian women who die in childbirth every year other than preaching abstinence from
            sexual intercourse.</p>
        <p> Mr. Gandhi is opposed to war and violence but it is not suffieciently appreciated that
            in the world every year a million women in the prime of life die in childbirth and
            millions more are damaged for life. These are the casualties in the ceaseless warfare to
            maintain the human race on the earth.</p>
        <p>
            <person reg="Pusey, William Allen">Dr. Pusey</person>, a former President of the
            American Medical Association says:--“It is women who bear the penalties of too frequent
            childbearing--penalties of injury, disease, death and mental torture. They have a right
            to know how they can intelligently, not crudely and dangerously, control their sexual
            lives. And they are justified by the highest considerations in fighting vigorously and
            persistently until they have this right granted to them.”</p>
        <p> The subjection of women in sexual as in other ways may have had a survival value for the
            human race. But with increasing knowledge, intelligence and inventions masses of human
            beings are dominated by small groups who though fewer in number are vastly superior in
            education, in discipline and in training and therefore in standards of living. Fewer but
            fitter children is the best survival policy for today.</p>
        <p> In India this is exemplified in a thousand ways and it is a tragedy that Mahatma Gandhi
            should not see it. In one direction there is hope, in reply to questions from
                M<person>rs. Kutten Nair</person> on the morality of bringing defective children
            into the world the Mahatma said, “<q who="GANMA">As regards sterilisation I consider it
                inhuman to impose it as a law on the people. But in the case of individuals with
                chronic diseases, it is desirable to have them sterilized if they are for it.
                Sterilization is a sort of contraceptive and though I am against the use of
                contraceptives in the case of women, I do not mind voluntary sterilisation in the
                case of man, since he is the aggressor.</q>”</p>
        <p> I conclude this brief glimpse of my impressions of the world figure Mahatma Gandhi with
            a self-revealing quotation from himself taken from Young India for October 1921,</p>
        <p> “<q who="GANMA">We must not surrender our reason into anybody’s keeping Blind surrender
                to love is often more mischievous than forced surrender to the lash of the tyrant.
                There is hope for the slave of the brute, non for that of love.</q>”</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
