<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2001-10-25 MH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2003/08/08 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2003/12/08 CH clean up</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007-05-30 CH Oxygen cleanup</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-05 CH correct regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1912-08-04">4 Aug 1912</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>An Evening With George De Forest Brush</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp301393</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">New York Call</title>, Aug. 4, 1912</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Collected Documents Series</title> C16:23</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="BRUGE">Brush, George De Forest</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
            <name id="WILOS">Wilde, Oscar</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
        <index level1="Brush, George DeForest"/>
        <index level1="socialism" level2="and art"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>An Evening with <person reg="Brush, George DeForest">George De Forest
            Brush</person></head>
        <byline>By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret H. Sanger</person>.</byline>
        <p>In the course of a short vacation spent roaming about on Mr. Brush's <place>New
                Hampshire</place> farm it occurred to me that the readers of <title type="journal"
                    >The Call</title>
            would be interested in the social views of our premier American painter, George De
            Forest Brush.</p>
        <p>The comrades are no doubt acquainted with his "<title type="painting">Silence
                Broken</title>" and "<title type="painting">The Sculptor and the King</title>," the
            two Indian pictures which belong to the earlier period of his career. His "<title
                type="painting">Mother and Child</title>" and "<title type="painting">In the
                Garden</title>" of which the last named hangs in the <org>Metropolitan Museum of
                Art</org>, exemplify the later period, and together with numerous other masterpieces
            have established him as a world renowned painter of the first rank. It is interesting to
            note that the views of Mr. Brush have been arrived at independent of past and
            contemporary writers, and therefore are the more interesting in as much as they are
            largely based on independent thought. An evening having been arranged to discuss "<title
                type="painting">The Soul of Man Under Socialism</title>," by <person
                reg="Wilde, Oscar">Oscar Wilde</person>, I stirred up the fire, for the evenings are
            rather chilly up here, and we fixed ourselves for the regular "wee hours of the morning"
            chat, which Socialists the world over take such keen delight in indulging in when ever
            they meet. He had the book in his hand and passed it to me, saying, "<q who="BRUGE">It's
                all so perfectly, wonderful, absolutely wrong.</q>"</p>
        <p>"What?" I said. "Wrong?" W-r-o-n-g! I could not believe my ears. An artist to disagree
            with this beautiful dream. I could conceive of nothing more fertile, no soil more
            adapted for the soul of man to develop in than this which Oscar Wilde has shown us here. </p>
        <p>While I was thus wondering, I turned the pages idly, when my eye caught a pencil mark,
                "<q who="BRUGE">Tut, tut,</q>" opposite the words of Wilde which said: "<q
                who="WILOS">All unintellectual labor, all monotonous, dull labor, all labor that
                deals with dreadful things and involves unpleasant conditions, must be done by
                machinery.</q>"</p>
        <p>"Surely, this cannot be wrong," I said. "You would not leave man continue to do the
            laborious and disagreeable work which has so enslaved and degraded him today?"</p>
        <p>He leaned back in his chair, his eyes sparkled and his whole countenance beamed as if he
            were going to thoroughly enjoy his subject. </p>
        <p>"<q who="BRUGE">Labor is the most delightful thing in the world when one does the thing
                one loves to do,</q>" he said quietly. "<q who="BRUGE">The whole outlook on labor is
                wrong today, and it is because we have been so exploited through this labor that we
                have this repugnance toward it. When man labors for the joy of it, when everything
                he does will be a thing of beauty, there will be joy in his labor.</q>"</p>
        <p>"Well of course," I said. "if we were to all paint lovely pictures and to make the
            ornaments of life beautiful, I agree with you, but there are the useful things, the
            necessary things which I am sure there will be no beauty or joy in doing."</p>
        <p>"<q who="BRUGE">Can you name some such thing, some such labor?</q>" he said softly.</p>
        <p>"Oh, yes. What about the building of roads--the excavating, paving, etc.? There's not
            much joy in that, is there, Mr. Brush?"</p>
        <p>"<q who="BRUGE">Nothing more lovely in the world. I'd like nothing better than to build
                your roads for you. I'm not sure that I'd like you to make my roads, but I'm sure
                I'd find the greatest joy in making your roads. When you look down from the Alps you
                ask what those beautiful lines are. You are told that they are <person
                    reg="Bonaparte, Napoleon">Napoleon</person>'s roads. No machinery can do joyful
                work,</q>" he continued. "<q who="BRUGE">We must do things ourselves to accomplish
                art.</q>" </p>
        <p>"But what is the use of using up good human energy? Why not conserve it for more
            important work?" I insisted. He leaned forward and continued earnestly:</p>
        <p>"<q who="BRUGE">And what is more important than making the whole world joyful and
                beautiful? For what else do you Socialists make so great and many sacrifices? Why
                should the useful things not be beautiful? Why should it be as it is today?--the
                really useful things are made ugly by machinery and only the few things of life are
                beautiful. That's all wrong. What greater joy could one have than to build beautiful
                roads, pave beautiful streets, build beautiful houses? Of course, if I had to build
                the usual modern buildings I'd not find joy in that work. When we stop building up
                fortunes for the capitalists and work to produce art, I can conceive of no work
                which cannot be both joyfully and beautifully done. Art is the result of men working
                in unison through ages.</q>"</p>
        <p>My mind had been wandering to the various departments of industry which today are
            enslaving thousands. I thought of the food question. Surely, he would not have women
            again enslaved in the household and white-wash this crime by calling it the "art of
            cookery." "Would he not hope to have our food prepared on a large scale and thus
            emancipate us from this drudgery?" I ventured, bravely certain that here at last he must
            acknowledge the necessity of machinery and the joylessness of labor. "Will there be any
            special joy in the boxing and canning of foodstuffs?" I asked. At which he burst out
            laughing.</p>
        <p>"<q who="BRUGE">Oh, you sordid American, if you're going to have canned food in your
                Socialism I'll have none of it.</q>"</p>
        <p>At this we both laughed heartily, and I agreed with him that I had indeed sordid ideas on
            this subject, for I could conceive of nothing more welcome to the thousands of working
            women than to have good pure food already prepared for them, ready at a moment's notice,
            instead of spending a lifetime in a hot broiling kitchen doing the same work, getting
            the same result. </p>
        <p>After I adjusted a log which had fallen away from its companions, he resumed:</p>
        <p>"<q who="BRUGE">The trouble is with this generation, they have been too busy producing
                wealth for others to think out a beautiful future for themselves. What can a trade
                unionist tell us of the beauties of our future? His whole thoughts are industrial.
                It will be for him to be served by the artist; only an artist can prepare the feast
                well enough for him.</q>"</p>
        <p>At this mention of the word industrial I felt here was a large field which we should not
            pass over without viewing. </p>
        <p>"Do you think there is any danger," I asked, "of the present Socialist movement, which is
            industrial in character, doing as the abolitionists did: after they accomplish the
            ownership of the industries to rest their oars and feel that all has been done?"</p>
        <p>"<q who="BRUGE">No,</q>" he said slowly but decidedly, "<q who="BRUGE">I do not think we
                will ever go through that again. That was where <person reg="Phillips, Wendell"
                    >Wendell Phillips</person> was more farsighted than the other abolitionists. He
                realized, though the black man had been emancipated in the South, that here on our
                doorstep was the slavery of labor in capital's greedy grasp. No; when once the
                economic question is solved every one will have time to think, to advance and to
                develop. There will be beauties of the mind unfolded which never before had been
                conceived of.</q>"</p>
        <p>"Do you think the master mind of each industry will hold office then, or shall we have
            any office holders?" I inquired.</p>
        <p>"<q who="BRUGE">Well, to me it is a waste of time to consider these things,</q>" he said.
                "<q who="BRUGE">With man's economic freedom there will be a higher percentage of
                intelligence developed, unrealized or unthought of today. Just as machinery and
                electricity have permeated the nation today, so in the future will it be universal
                knowledge to be skillful in the affairs of life. Every one will be a general.</q>"
            He cited an example of the government's wireless being interfered with, messages lost
            and stolen. Upon investigation it was found some small boys had rigged up a wireless on
            a vacant plot and were taking government messages. <q who="BRUGE">"Even the youth of our
                day is permeated with invention.</q>"</p>
        <p>"With the present tendency of State ownership do you think there is a possibility of our
            being caught in the meshes of State Socialism?" I asked. </p>
        <p>"<q who="BRUGE">I doubt it,</q>" he answered very earnestly. "<q who="BRUGE">Why, look at
                the rise of the labor movement in the last four years. Look at the rise of the <org
                    reg="Industrial Workers of the World">I. W. W.</org> Only a few years ago I was
                talking to a well known capitalist, who said: "Why, Mr. Brush, the working people
                have us already. All they need is a little more organization and we're done for."
                "But the police are with you," I said. "We don't give that" (snapping his fingers)
                "for the police power if the workers were organized." No, I doubt that the working
                class will let us drift into State Socialism.</q>"</p>
        <p>He told me another story which, though it does not fit just here, is certainly too good
            for our comrades to miss -- how this same capitalist, Mr. ----, said: "<q who="UNK">Why,
                Mr. Brush, there are just thousands of people who won't work. Do you Socialists
                realize this?</q>" "<q who="BRUGE">Yes, we do,</q>" said Mr. Brush, "<q who="BRUGE"
                >and they are just the people we're after. Why, look at that <person
                    reg="Lenox, James">Mr. Lenox</person> who called his son to his bedside and told
                his son that he was leaving him a little farm which would enable him and his
                children to live their whole lives long without every turning their hands to a tap
                of work. The little farm was where the Lenox Library now stands. Yes, we Socialists
                know these fellows, Mr. ----, and we're after them.</q>"</p>
        <p>We had wandered far away from Oscar Wilde, but again my eye caught a pencil mark near the
            words: "<q who="WILOS">A work of art is the unique result of a unique temperament. Its
                beauty comes from the fact that the artist is what he is. It has nothing to do with
                the fact that other people want what they want.</q>"</p>
        <p>"You agree with this?" I asked.</p>
        <p>"<q who="BRUGE">On the contrary,</q>" he said, "<q who="BRUGE">all great art came to be
                because the world wanted a definite thing, and the artist, being commanded, produced
                a great result. Art is the expression of the joy of the people, and only a happy
                nation can produce art. There is no art today, for there is no joy in our
                people.</q>"</p>
        <p>"What about the Greeks?" I ventured.</p>
        <p>"<q who="BRUGE">Yes, indeed, they were full of joy. They were overjoyed with life in
                vanquishing their foes, and gave the highest expression to art. Why, the Greek women
                took the keenest joy in combing their hair; it was leisurely, beautifully done, with
                all the new art of the age. It was never a new style, either; they continued to
                strive to make the old style more beautiful. They could not help making beauty in
                everything they did, for they were masters in art.</q>"</p>
        <p>The fire was burning low and he arose to go. He extended his hand to my good night,
            saying: "<q who="BRUGE">In my Socialism there will be no getting on without art, for
                every act of life will be an emotion and every work a piece of art.</q>"</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
