<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011-08-05 NC</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1952-12-13">13 Dec 1952</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Japan Wants Birth Control</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp301306</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>The Nation</title> Dec. 13, 1952, p. 553 - 555.</bibl>
            <bibl><title>LCM</title> C16:0440</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>For other version see <title>MSM</title> S72:0791
            and 0784. Galleys of the article are on <title>LCM</title>
            130:0020.</p><index level1="Japan" level2="over-population and"
            /><index level1="birth control" level2="in Japan"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Japan Wants Birth Control</head>
        <byline>By Margaret Sanger</byline>
        <p>In October, 1952, I visited <place>Japan</place> on my way to the
                <org
                reg="International Conference on Planned Parenthood, Third (Bombay)"
                >International Conference on Planned Parenthood</org> at
                <place>Bombay, India</place>, just thirty years after my first
            eventful stay there. I found that thinking men and women were still
            concerned with the great problem of how to curb population growth,
            how to bring the rapidly increasing number of people in their
            islands into a sane and humane balance with the country's limited
            resources. In other ways there was a vast difference between the two
            visits. The military controlled <place>Japan</place> thirty years
            ago. Officials were shocked at the idea of birth control being
            openly discussed that my lectures were greatly curtailed. I had been
            invited to Japan by a number of liberal intellectuals known as the
            Kaizo group, who planned a series of lectures to be given by four
            Western writers and leaders of thought. The first was <person
                reg="Russell, Bertrand">Bertrand, Russell</person>, the second,
                <person reg="Einstein, Albert">Albert Einstein</person>; I was
            to be the third. I was finally allowed to discus "Population and
            Peace" with the understanding I would not mention birth control from
            a public platform. The uproar in official circles over my subject
            cut short the Kaizo project. As a
            consequence <person reg="Wells, H. G.">H.G. Wells</person>, who was
            to follow me never went to Japan to give his lecture. On my recent
            visit I was warmly welcomed, invited to speak whenever possible,
            urged to help in the effort to educate the Japanese people to avail
            themselves of government-sanctioned medical means of spacing their
            babies.</p>
        <p>The population of Japan in 1922 was 66,000,000. Each year this
            hard-working, courageous, courteous, beauty-loving people was adding
            between 750,000 and 800,000 to its teeming millions -- new lives to
            care for, new mouths to feed. The available space at that time,
            although very inadequate, was much greater than it is today, since
            the military-planned expansion had allowed Japanese families to take
            up residence in <place>Formosa</place>, <place>Korea</place>,
                <place>Manchuria</place>, and the islands of the western
            Pacific. By June 1, 1952, 85,000,000 people were living in a space
            that had been greatly reduced by Japan's defeat in the Second World
            War.</p>
        <p>I firmly believe history will record the fact that no people in the
            world today are making greater sacrifices to lower their birth rate
            than the Japanese. The idea of family limitation is not new to them.
            At the time of Meiji Restoration in 1867, when the <person
                reg="Meiji Emperor, Meiji the Great">Emperor's</person> sweeping
            reforms brought the Islands into contract with Western sanitation
            and health measures, the population had been stationary for more
            than a century. The first national census in 1726 produced the
            figure of 26,000,000. The census of 1846 still showed 26,000,000.
            The number had been kept down by the practice of infanticide, high
            infant and maternal mortality, a high stillbirth rate, and numerous
            abortions. Two children were considered enough for any family to
            feed and educate. The sharp population increase began shortly after
            Commodore <person reg="Perry, Matthew C.">Perry's</person> historic
            visit to Japan in 1854, which opened some ports to foreign trade.
            The rise occurred despite continuing high stillbirths per 1,000
            births. By 1920 both the birth rate and the stillbirth rate had
            declined, the latter to 66 per 1,000.</p>
        <p>At the time of my first visit to Japan the intelligent people I met
            seemed eager for information about birth control and, more
            important, to pass on this help to those who needed it most. They
            wanted to avoid undesired pregnancies and an increasing birth rate.
            The density of population in 1920 was 380 persons per square mile of
            land area. In Japan, a country of mountains and rivers, only one
            acre in six is cultivable. This meant that if the people had been
            distributed evenly over the cultivable land, each square mile of
            such land would have contained 2, 500 persons. Thinking people knew
            that the increasing land hunger would lead to disastrous,
            humiliating war. But the military clique which was growing in power
            at that time had its own plans. Its encouragement of big families
            and denial of the knowledge of how families could be limited forced
            women into the cruel practice of abortion.</p>
        <p>In 1938 a <org>Ministry of Health and Social Affairs</org> was
            created. From this time on, physical training and population growth
            were heavily emphasized. Paradoxically, in the same year the
            Japanese government approved the <name
                reg="Race Eugenic Protection Law" type="law">Eugenic Protection
                law</name> legalizing the interruption of pregnancy for medical
            and eugenic reasons. This further increased the number of
            abortions.</p>
        <p>After the war the birth rate and stillbirth rate rose sharply in
            Japan, as in <place>Germany</place> and many other countries. At the
            present time it is difficult to differentiate between stillbirths
            and induced abortions. Many Japanese women, even though induced
            abortion is legal and since 1946 has been permitted for economic as
            well as physical reason, fail to register abortions as such. By law,
            abortions after the third month of pregnancy, when the foetus is
            viable, must be reported. Stillbirths from the fourth month to
            gestation must be reported by the family but not necessarily by the
            physician. It is hoped that a new project undertaken by Dr <person
                reg="Koya Yoshio">Y. Koya</person>, Director of Public Health,
            will produce a more reliable way of determining the number of
            abortions and still births. Despite the confusion of figures, the
            conservative estimate of most physicians is that there were one
            million interruptions of pregnancy in 1950. The number for 1952 is
            expected to be twice as large, and unless one of the new simple,
            inexpensive contraceptives is available soon, even larger the
            following year.</p>
        <p>Hunger, misery, and overcrowding are part of this desperate
            situation. Though physicians have improved their techniques of
            abortion during the past year, it is tragic that women must resort
            to this traumatic method of terminating an unborn life when they
            might be supplied with safe contraceptives, easy to use and within
            their income. Many new simple contraceptives are showing promise in
            the experimental stage -- jellies, pills, and injections that
            include vitamins, hormones, enzymes, and special chemicals. The need
            for them is great everywhere, but nowhere greater than in Japan.</p>
        <p>The government recently legalized birth control, the first in the
            world to take this step. Unfortunately an adequate educational
            program has not been worked out, one which stresses the important
            fact that abortion is not contraception, that there are better and
            safer ways of spacing pregnancies and limiting families.</p>
        <p>Several interesting health projects where brought to my attention in
            Japan. One of the most fruitful is the series of test studies being
            conducted in three rural villages; sponsored by the
                <org>Organization for Research on Population Health</org> and
            directed by Dr. Y. Koya. These studies have proved that the
            population problem in Japan has shifted from the economic to the
            public-health field, that the prevalence of abortions has adversely
            affected the health of Japanese mothers. I rejoice that the
            organization has taken the correct strong stand against induced
            abortions and hope that it will go on to favor birth control by
            contraceptive methods and so make abortions unnecessary.</p>
        <p>Abortions threaten the health of the mother without preventing
            renewed pregnancy at an early date. Next to infanticide they are the
            worst means of checking population increase. In Japan as anywhere
            the general practice of induced abortion merely replaces on evil
            with another. Let us hope that an end to this suffering, waste,
            enfeeblement, and despair is in sight. Let us hope that soon a
            simple, safe contraceptive will emerge from the research
            laboratories. Japan is ready and eager to take advantage of it.</p>
        <p>An accurate picture of the factors causing the current rapid increase
            in the world's population is urgently needed, not just in Japan but
            everywhere. Each country can cooperate in ascertaining these factors
            with the hope that the <org>United Nations</org> will eventually
            propose a sound population policy. Basic requirements are adequate
            dates on birth and death rates, evaluation of attitudes on the
            spacing of children and on family limitation, and a study of methods
            of contraception.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
