<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/06/13 CE</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-18 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1937-06-00">June 1937</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Hail and Farewell</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp301422</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">National Birth Control News</title> (June 1937), pp.
                3-5</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Micrfilm</title>, C16:0413</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="LAT">Latin</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="legal cases"
            level3="U.S. V. One Package of Japanese contraceptives'"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="medical community and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="research"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="American"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="international"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="MS on"/>
        <index level1="Birth Control Review, The"/>
        <index level1="National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control"
            level2="goals of"/>
        <index level1="New York City" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="physicians" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="government" level3="birth control and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Hail And Farewell</head>
        <p>With the adoption of the Report of its <org
                reg="American Medical Association, Committee on Contraceptive Practices">Committee
                on Contraceptive Practices</org> the <org>American Medical Association</org>,
            representing organized medicine, takes much needed and long sought for action. The work
            and wisdom, the belief and support of many thousand men and women are responsible for
            the great victory we celebrate today, the recognition by the medical profession as a
            whole of birth control as a necessary part of medical practice.</p>
        <p>All who believed in the inherent right, truth and necessity of medically directed birth
            control played their part and deserve to rejoice in this final triumph. But no moment of
            retrospect and congratulation would be complete without paying special honor to <person
                reg="Dickinson, Robert Latou">Dr. Robert L. Dickinson</person>, guiding spirit of
            the <org>National Committee on Maternal Health</org>, and now its vice-chairman and
            secretary, who did so much to give birth control professional status and to interpret it
            to his colleagues; to <person reg="Willson, Prentiss">Dr. Prentiss Willson</person>,
            chairman of the <org>National Medical Committee on State and Federal Birth Control
                Legislation</org>, who organized the demand of physicians for a clarification of the
            law; to <person reg="Upham, John H. J.">Dr. John H. J. Upham</person>, incoming
            president of the American Medical Association, who has for so many years given his help
            to our cause; to the late <person reg="Williams, John Whitridge">Dr. J. Whitridge
                Williams</person>, who organized our <org
                reg="National Committee on Federal Legislation for Bsirth Control, Medical Advisory Committee"
                >Medical Advisory Committee</org>; and to <person reg="Holden, Frederick C.">Dr.
                Frederick C. Holden</person>, <person reg="Kennedy, Foster">Dr. Foster
                Kennedy</person>, <person reg="Stone, Hannah Mayer">Dr. Hannah M. Stone</person>,
                <person reg="Stone, Abraham">Dr. Abraham Stone</person> and <person
                reg="Timme, Walter">Dr. Walter Timme</person>.</p>
        <p>As I look back on the struggle for medical recognition, waged for more than twenty years,
            I am fortified in my belief that the highest thing in life is to hold fast to a
            conviction of what is right in principle. Twenty years ago the birth control movement
            might have turned into any one of a number of channels. It might have become a free
            speech cause, an adjunct of political liberalism, a play-toy of advanced philanthropy.
            But, I do not hesitate to say, my own education as a trained nurse made me see that it
            was a medical and technical problem, over and above everything else. Through all these
            years this has been my steadfast policy. I and my co-workers with me have fought for
            medically directed clinics, for medical support and for medical endorsement and
            recognition. Time and again members of the profession, even those in high standing, have
            told us that we could never win. But individual support grew. Organized support grew.
            And today we can feel that the same principles of right have won.</p>
        <p>The action of the American Medical Association strengthens the situation created by the
                <name reg="United States vs. One Package of Japanese Contraceptives" type="case"
                >Court Decision</name> clarifying the legality of birth control. The work of the
            National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control is finished. It is done and
            well done.</p>
        <p>At a meeting of the Board of Directors held in <place reg="New York City, NY">New York
                City</place> in April, the Committee was formally dissolved by the unanimous passage
            of the following resolution:</p>
        <p>WHEREAS the purposes of the National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control,
            Inc. have been accomplished, in the light of the recent decision by the Circuit Court of
            Appeals,</p>
        <p>BE IT RESOLVED that the National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control, Inc.
            be dissolved, and that the proper certificate to effect dissolution be executed as
            advised by Counsel.</p>
        <p>Now comes the future, full of hope and challenge. The impetus of the work is doubly
            renewed. We can now consolidate the gains we have made, and move steadily forward in a
            larger program of national and international scope.</p>
        <p>All who supported the work of the National Committee should now give their help to a
            wider program of national education and research. Such a program is being developed
            under the aegis of our <org>Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau</org>. The legal and
            medical status of birth control must be publicized, organization support must be
            enlisted and the public demand for establishing birth control service in all hospitals,
            welfare and public health units must be mobilized.</p>
        <p>It seems fitting at this moment of victory in America to pause and make some survey of
            the situation on the international front. With this in mind, we have devoted the major
            portion of this issue to a summary account of “birth control world-wide.” For we are a
            part, let us remember, of universal movement, which by its human appeal should surmount
            all barriers of nationality and race.</p>
        <p>International birth control and what it can mean for mankind, is a concept to stir the
            imagination. As comrades in this world union, I greet you with thanksgiving, I call upon
            you to join with me in the inspiring work which lies before us. <foreign lang="LAT">Ave
                atque vale</foreign>.</p>
        <byline><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></byline>
    </docBody>
</doc>
