<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011-07-27 NC</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1948-00-00">1948</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Preface to "One Hundred Fifty Years of Birth
                    Control"</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp301841</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>One Hundred Fifty Years of Birth Control: Malthus (1798) to Cheltenham,
                    England (1948)</title>(New York: 1948), pp. 1.</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="history of"
        /></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Preface</head>
        <p>In the 150 years since <person reg="Malthus, Thomas">Malthus</person> expounded the law
            that population tends to outstrip available food supplies, mankind has paid a terrible
            price for the inability to heed the brilliant clergyman's warning. the reckless
            exhaustion of land, water, timber, minerals to provide inadequate subsistence for ever
            increasing people has at last forced mankind into a realization that our civilization is
            doomed, not because of the atom bomb, but because man is reluctant to bring his physical
            numbers into a sane balance with the resources of nature. </p>
        <p>We have reached the limits in spending the resources of posterity in saving ten million
            lives today so that fifty million may starve tomorrow. Not more than a fifth of this
            earth's people eat what we know is an adequate diet. More than half are chronically
            undernourished or starving. </p>
        <p>The great Movement for birth control was British in its inception, British in its
            development, an essential and integral part of our never ceasing Anglo-Saxon struggle
            for freedom and self government in every phase of living. Its advocate have all been men
            and women of vision and courage. But while the inception of birth control was British
            and one has witnessed the courageous efforts of its pioneers of birth control, history
            must record that equal efforts have been made by the pioneers of the <place>United
                States</place>. It was the pamphlet on contraception of a daring and enlightened
            physician of <place reg="Boston, MA">Boston</place> -- Dr. <person
                reg="Knowlton, Charles">Charles Knowlton</person> -- which was distributed by
                <person reg="Bradlaugh, Charles">Charles Bradlaugh</person> and <person
                reg="Besant, Anne">Anne Besant</person> that brought them to the Bar of Justice in
            England in a famous and historical trial. But in the United States while Dr. Knowlton
            was promptly and without due publicity sent to jail, the Besant and Bradlaugh trial was
            heralded throughout the land as a challenge to free speech and their victory a triumph
            of courage, and a free press. The whole modern movement for birth control still threads
            its way throughout the history of both countries. Leadership in the field has swung back
            and forth across the Atlantic until at last sufficient interest has been aroused to draw
            delegates from all parts of the globe to the <org
                reg="International Congress on Population and World Resources in Relation to the Family"
                >Congress at <place reg="Cheltenham, England">Cheltenham</place></org>. </p>
        <p>The Malthusian law has operated through the last 150 years so that we face today the
            blunt alternative between militarism and birth control. Militarism, unless the next war
            destroys civilization itself, offers no solution. Birth control does. </p>
        <p><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></p>


    </docBody>
</doc>
