<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011-07-29 NC</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1951-01-27">27 Jan 1951</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>The Paradise of Communism</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp302086</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Arizona Daily Citizen</title>27 Jan. 1951.</bibl>
            <bibl><title>MSM</title>C16:0430</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><index level1="population" level2="war and"/>
        <index level1="population growth" level2="regulation of"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>The Paradise of Communism</head>
        <byline>By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger Slee</person></byline>
        <p>Only a few years ago the peoples of <place>Europe</place> and <place reg="United States"
                >America</place>, almost for the first time in history, believed, in fact were
            confident that through united world effort an enduring peace could be achieved. But
            today the world is swept by fears, hatreds, confusion and the possibility of the most
            brutal war which in the near future may wipe out our civilization. But even during those
            years when nations were hoping, dreaming and planning for world peace; there were forces
            at work (invisible but basic human forces) that had made wars past and present and will
            make future wars inevitable. The first and second world wars were really only phases of
            a struggle which has been in progress throughout the past 50 years. Those same forces of
            destruction which are still sweeping Europe and extended their power to
                <place>Asia</place> are taking and will continue to take lives of millions of our
            best, selected, healthy, brilliant, educated manhood into wars of destruction.</p>
        <div>
            <p>The causes of wars are manifold and diverse. There have been and still are wars of
                aggression and wars of defense. Motives have been hidden behind religious, dynastic
                interests; officials and military leaders who plunge nations and peoples into wars
                never or seldom state actual dynamic causes, such as population pressure. Rather do
                these dictators, despots and tyrants trump up motives usually of defense for which
                tens of thousands will be slain and cities sacked and destroyed. The sordid motives
                of economic rivalry and markets for world trade access to waterways and colonies for
                surplus populations are seldom the leads to inflame masses into action. Rather do
                the diplomats manipulate reasons of Idealistic Religious motives as more worthy and
                righteous and the sordid causes are kept in the background.</p>
            <p><place>Germany</place> was perhaps the exception in issuing warnings to the world
                from 1910 to 1914 that her population was increasing to the explosion point and that
                her needs of expansion were dominating her every political and economic move; that
                her strong, healthy, flourishing, increasing people required continual expansion and
                new territory for her surplus numbers.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <p>Previous to 1914 the population of Europe from 1800 with 200 millions had increased
                to 600 million (a period of 70 years) even in spite of 50 millions emigrating to the
                new world. We have the example of the 70-year period exploding, through the dynamic
                power of fertility and population pressure into the First World War; such pressure
                continued to do its destruction on into the Second World War and its forces have not
                yet decreased in spite of millions of dead, mutilated and maimed in every
                country.</p>
            <p>Germany, <place>Italy</place> and <place>Japan</place> were long known by scientists
                and demographers as the “high pressure” countries. Today, through wards, they are
                mainly laid in rubble and waste. New high pressure countries rise upon the
                international horizon: <place>China</place>, <place reg="Soviet Union">Russia</place>, and
                    <place>India</place>--all over-populated but illiterate and physically
                undernourished--lacking the energy and stamina to battle for their survival, or for
                higher standards of living (as the Germans, Japanese and Italians.)</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <p>These are the facts of history. Future historians will record them and wonder how
                jurists, statesmen, politicians who wrote and designed the <title>Treaty of
                    Versailles</title>, also the <title>Atlantic Charter</title> culminating in both
                the <org>League of Nations</org> and the <org>United Nations</org> had been so
                ignorant of concrete realities; that having disarmed Germany, Italy and Japan,
                instead of providing a safety valve against the day when the population boiler would
                bubble and explode, they had either made provision for their expansion or insisted
                that they restrain their increasing fertility and birth rates to the territory
                assigned to them for voluntary population control and limitation was the best and
                most secure war debt the Allies and United Nations could have and should have
                demanded. The uncontrolled, prolific breeding among the hungry, working, laboring
                populations of the world is the Paradise of Communism. Without these millions
                communism can never exist.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <p>The problems of population are numerous, but they can be solved. One of the solutions
                is the knowledge and practice of contraception. In this, the birth rate may be
                controlled or limited. Parents throughout the world would be benefited by limiting
                the size of the family and spacing each birth in accordance to the mother’s health,
                the father’s earning capacity and the standards of living they are able to maintain.
                Let us give proper information in regard to methods of birth control and <org
                    reg="Planned Parenthood Federation of America">Planned Parenthood</org>. <place
                    reg="Tucson, AR">Tuscon</place> has for the past 10 years provided this
                information to parents at the <org reg="Planned Parenthood Clinic of Tuscon">Planned
                    Parenthood Clinic</org>, 28 East Corral st. The records give proof that this
                public utility has been of great service in the community and should be supported.
                They need $10,000.</p>
            <p>This is a basic humane investment, an investment in health for the family and the
                community.</p>
            <closer>(Margaret Sanger Slee is the founder of the modern birth control movement.)</closer>
        </div>


    </docBody>
</doc>
