<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "file:/S:/TRANSCRIPTIONS/XML%20Drafts/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Speech ">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2007/07/17 AP</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>
            <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
        </docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1928-03-15">15 Mar 1928</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>
                <supplied>Excerpt of Engineering Auditorium Speech</supplied>
            </titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp302113</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>The Birth Control Review</title> Apr. 1928, p. 108</bibl>
            <bibl><title>MSM</title> or C16:288</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"> Forms part of a longer summary of the evening, with speeches by <person reg="Wile, Ira S.">Ira S.
        Wile</person> and <person reg="Reiland, Karl">Karl Reiland</person>. For a longer draft of Sanger's comments, see "<xref from="143774.xml">Engineer's Auditorium
        Speech</xref>," Mar. 15, 1928. <index level1="population" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="eugenics" level2="birth control and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Mrs. Sanger on Population</head>
        <p>Science is now bordering on the infinite and the most powerful brain seems feeble in the
            face of tasks which are glimpsed. If one is to judge by the present predicament of the
            world, we may assume that there is no individual nor group whose intelligence is equal
            to the tasks that the international situation demands. It seems almost as if the
            knowledge required exceeds our capacity for understanding.</p>
        <p>It is to the science of population that we must now look for future guidance. It must
            point the way for population regulation which in this country, in particular, could soon
            deliver society from more than half of its terrific burdens. It could soon help us to
            eliminate the possibility of increasing dysgenic stocks, such as those with inherited or
            transmissible diseases. It could soon lessen the burden of philanthropic demands which
            are fast growing beyond the cultural needs of this generation. Sane legislation would
            indirectly direct reproduction towards adaptation to future conditions by raising the
            mean level fo brain power. The importance of numbers belongs to the past rather than to
            the future.</p>
        <p>The needs of manual labor in the future will be greatly reduced by the progress of
            chemistry, physics and the possession of unlimited sources of heat and force at a
            minimum of expenditure. On the other hand, we shall need brains highly resistant to work
            and capable of a degree of education surpassing that of the most intelligent skilled
            artisan today. Vaster memories must be forged, sharper insight must be gained and with
            the discovery of the laws of inheritance men can choose whether we shall evolve to the
            expression of the highest within us, or revert to the stage of the barbarian. It is for
            man to decide.</p>
        <p>With all the knowledge that we today posses, it is obvious that it is a crime for
            generations to come, it is a crime against our civilization to encourage the
            reproduction of mediocre, diseased or inferior types of groups. Such offspring can only
            be a burden to the future and retard the progress of the present generation.</p>
        <p>It has become clear that the population of the earth is fast arriving at its possible
            maximum; that its density is badly distributed; that redistribution of space can only be
            rectified by displacements; and that Birth Control in overpopulated countries is the
            first and surest method whereby the balance may be peacefully restored.</p>
    </docBody>

</doc>
