<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011-09-12 KG</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1956-07-00"><supplied resp="MSPP">Jul
            1956</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Asia Discovers Birth Control</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp302493</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Reader's Digest</title>, July 1956, pp. 36-38.</bibl>
            <bibl><title>MSM</title>C16:490</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="KIRES">Kirby, E. Stuart</name>
            <name id="JEPL">Japan Eugenic Protection Law</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>For draft version, see LCM 128:344.</p>
        <index level1="abortion" level2="MS on"/><index level1="birth control"
            level2="Asia"/><index level1="China" level2="birth control in"
            /><index level1="China" level2="population policy of"/><index
            level1="food supply"/><index level1="India"
            level2="birth control in"/><index level1="India"
            level2="population policy of"/><index level1="Japan"
            level2="birth control in"/><index level1="Japan"
            level2="population policy of"/><index level1="Sanger, Margaret"
            level2="speaking tours" level3="1922 (Japan)"/><index
            level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="speaking tours"
            level3="1954 (Japan)"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Asia Discovers Birth Control </head>
        <byline>by <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret
            Sanger</person></byline>
        <p>When, in 1922, I lectured in <place>Japan</place> as a guest of the
                <org>Kaizo publishing house</org>, the <org
                reg="Japanese Government">Imperial Government</org> forbade me
            to advocate birth control publicly. To do so was a violation of the
                <title type="law">Dangerous Thoughts Law</title>. But 32 years
            later, in 1954, I was invited to address the upper <org>Upper House
                Welfare Committee</org> on efficient methods of combating
            overpopulation, and last year the <org
                reg="International Conference on Planned Parenthood, Fifth (Tokyo, 1955)"
                >Fifth Conference of the <org>International Planned Parenthood
                    Federation</org></org> was held in <place reg="Tokyo, Japan"
                >Tokyo</place>. As president of the Federation, I was presented
            to the <person reg="Yoshida Shigeru">Emperor</person> as a
            benefactor of humanity!</p>
        <p>These personal experiences show how Japan has faced up to the
            challenge of overpopulation. And there is encouraging evidence of
            similar concern in the rest of <place>Asia</place>, where more than
            half of the human race is crowded upon about one sixth of its land
            area and the yearly increase is about 34 million. <person
                reg="Kirby, E. Stuart">Dr. E. Stuart Kirby</person> of <org>Hong
                Kong University</org>, an authority on the demography of the
            Eastern Hemisphere, has said: “<q who="KIRES">The P-bomb (population
                bomb) is a greater threat to the world than is the A-bomb or the
                H-bomb</q>.”</p>
        <p>In 1922 the population of Japan was estimated at 61 million. By 1945,
            despite the war, it had grown to 72 million, and today it is
            estimated at 89 million. So desperate had the population problem
            become by 1948 that a <title type="law">Eugenic Protection
                Law</title> was enacted, permitting the termination of any
            pregnancy which could “<q who="JEPL">seriously injure the health of
                the mother owing to physical or economic conditions.</q>” As a
            result, the <org
                reg="Japan Ministry
                    of Health and Welfare"
                >Ministry of Health and Welfare</org> estimates that there are
            now over one million abortions a year--about one induced abortion
            for every live birth.</p>
        <p>I have always condemned abortion as dangerous and inhuman. But what
            better method could I offer to curb overpopulation, Japanese
            officials asked me in 1954. I replied that Japan could train its
            20,000 midwives to instruct married couples in practical and
            hygienic methods of contraception; for this service they should
            receive the same compensation as they do to deliver an infant. With
            this group as the nucleus for a policy of sex education, I pointed
            out. Japan in a generation or two might well lead the world in
            creating a fit population based upon parenthood by choice and not by
            chance.</p>
        <p>Apparently this advice was not without influence. Shortly thereafter
            the advisory council on population problems of the Ministry of
            Health and Welfare made a series of recommendations to the
            government. Among other things it proposed that the official health
            services provide birth-control facilities: that medical schools
            include family planning in their curriculum; that doctors be called
            upon to induce an abortion be required to give the woman information
            about birth control for the future; and that national wage and
            taxation policies should avoid “<q
                who="Japan Ministry of Health and Welfare">encouraging large
                families.</q>”</p>
        <p>Gradually but surely the abhorrent abortion policy will thus be
            replaced by hygienic contraceptive techniques. The trend will meet
            with little opposition, since almost no Japanese religious groups
            are opposed to birth control.</p>
        <p>In <place>China</place> and <place>India</place> the situation is
            also acute. China’s population of some 600 million exceeds that of
                <place>Europe</place> (including European <place
                reg="Soviet Union">Russia</place>), <place>Africa</place>,
                <place>Australia</place> and a large section of the
                <place>Western Hemisphere</place> put together. Though not
            officially proclaimed, the importance of birth control is recognized
            even in communist China. Instructions on contraceptive methods are
            today being published in the Communist press.</p>
        <p>India, whose population grows by five million annually; has assumed a
            position of world leadership in the movement for planned parenthood.
            Its five-year plan of 1951 included provisions for the reduction of
            the rate of population growth through contraception. Under the plan,
            family limitation has now become an integral part of the government
            health services, with eight million dollars currently allocated to
            the work. More than 165 clinics or family planning centers have
            already been started, in addition to several hundred centers under
            army auspices. The Health Minister, <person
                reg="Amrit Kaur, Rajkumari">Rajkumari Amrit Kaur</person>, is
            supporting family-planning work wholeheartedly, and has agreed to
            supply contraceptives free to the poor.</p>
        <p>India is also engaged in ambitious efforts to increase food
            production to meet the needs of its growing population. But there as
            elsewhere such efforts will be doomed to failure unless there is
            population control.</p>
        <p>Already one half of the inhabitants of our planet subsist on a
            woefully inadequate diet. To insure bare adequacy, available
            foodstuffs would have to be increased 25 percent. Recently a
            population expert asserted that "<q who="UNK">efforts to increase
                the production of food cannot alone suffice to achieve any
                steady or rapid rise in nutrition levels. A firm control of the
                number of births is indisputably necessary.</q>”</p>
        <p>It seems unbelievable that in an age when we have harnessed the atom
            we still have not perfected a simple method for the control of human
            fertility. But research now under way in many parts of the world
            will surely result in important discoveries. These may provide the
            menas not only of curbing the quantity of the world’s population but
            of changing its quality to give an upward and onward lift to human
            dignity and freedom.</p>
        <p>It may be the East, which has most to gain from such a development,
            will lead the way.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
