<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "file:/S:/TRANSCRIPTIONS/XML%20Drafts/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2003/06/04 SB</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/26 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/08/13 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007/06/27 CH Oxygen update</prepDate><prepDate>2001/03/11 CH Entered corrections suggested by Andy Carloff.</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1918-10-00">Oct 1918</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Trapped!</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp302494</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>The Birth Control Review</title>, Oct. 1918, 3</bibl>
            <bibl>LCM 16:119</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="Marion, Kitty"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="arrests for"/>
        <index level1="New York Society for the Suppression of Vice"/>
        <index level1="Barnberger, Charles J."/>
        <index level1="law breaking and direct action"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="opposition to"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>TRAPPED!</head>
        <byline rend="italics">By Margaret Sanger</byline>
        <p><person reg="Marion, Kitty">Kitty Marion</person>, a devoted laborer for the cause of
            Birth Control, has been arrested for imparting information concerning contraceptives.
            She will come to trial in <place reg="New York, NY">New York</place>, October 10th.</p>
        <p>Arrest has no terrors for this woman consecrated to the freedom of her sisters. An
            actress, she left the <place reg="London, England">London</place> stage to become one of
            those militants who fought by the side of <person reg="Pankhurst, Emmeline">Emmeline
                Pankhurst</person> for the enfranchisement of English women. For that cause she went
            to prison.</p>
        <p>In prison, Kitty Marion went on a hunger strike. Of the horrors she endured while
            incarcerated, one hundred and twenty-eight forcible feedings constitute but a single
            item.</p>
        <p>Her spirit strengthened rather than broken by these experiences, she kept up the fight in
                <place>England</place> until the coming of the World War put an end to the struggle
            for suffrage, through an understanding between representatives of the English government
            and the militants. Then she came to <place reg="United States of America"
            >America</place> to resume her stage career.</p>
        <p>Birth Control, as a means of bringing women relief from the economic and physical slavery
            of large families, appealed to her as a more immediate and effective emancipation of
            woman than suffrage. To Birth Control she gave and is still giving the same
            single-minded devotion that she gave to the militant's battle. For this she has once
            more laid aside personal ambition, home and even many of the comforts of life.</p>
        <p>Only through such a devotion could Kitty Marion have been trapped. For trapped she
            was--trapped by one of those creatures who profess high ideals and practice baseness as
            a lucrative profession, one of the sort that shouts for war for democracy, but keeps
            clear of men with guns, preferring to stay at home and trap for hire women who have
            staked their all in a struggle for the freedom of their sex. </p>
        <p>After all, there is something to be said for <person>Judas</person>. To earn his thirty
            pieces of silver, he betrayed a strong man, not an over generous woman. Afterwards, he
            had the decency to hang himself. <person reg="Bamberger, Charles J. "
            >Bamberger</person>, of the mis-named <org
                reg="New York Society for the Suppression of Vice">Society for the Suppression of
                Vice</org>, betrayed a women to whom he came whining for aid for another woman, and
            he will appear in court to testify against her. This appalling brazenness is due
            doubtless to the fact that he will not receive his pieces of silver until he has sworn
            to the "<soCalled>criminal</soCalled>" generosity of Kitty Marion and thereby to his own
            shame. </p>
        <p>In order to snare this woman who had placed her all upon the altar of woman's freedom,
            Bamberger played the agent provocateur. Fortunately, this abhorrent term is not as
            familiar to American ears as it is to those of the oppressed of other countries. The
            agent provocateur is the shamed and shameless, disowned and uncontenanced spawn of the
            vilest tyranny the world has ever witnessed. Known wherever oppression flourished he
            attained the height of his vulturous activities in the reign of the unlamented <person
                reg="Nicholas II of Russia">czar</person> who quaked in his hidden chambers while he
            bargained away an enslaved people to titled parasites, to foreign plutocrats, and
            finally, in spite of his agreements with his allies, to <person
                reg="Wilhelm II of Germany">the Kaiser</person>.</p>
        <p>Conscienceless, prostitute in honor, gorging upon human misery, this creature earned
            alike the hate of those whom he betrayed and those whom he served for the monetary offal
            of his filthy trade. In America, the ironically called Society for the Suppression of
            Vice, has brought into play the native specimen of this monstrous instrument of dead and
            dying tyrannies.</p>
        <p>This is the same Society that, in the persons of one <person reg="John S. Sumner"
            >Sumner</person> and of Bamberger, who with too credulous contributors constitute its
            being, has devoted its quasi-legal activities to suppressing fearless literature,
            inspired works of art and movements for the betterment of mankind. It is the same
            Society who, in the person of the same Sumner, was pilloried recently by <person>Frank
                Harris</person> in a series of magazine articles as yet unanswered, though they
            contained charges that would have brought sleepless nights to clean men.</p>
        <p>It was upon the first day of August that the agent provocateur called upon Kitty Marion.
            He came, as his kind always comes, with a story of misfortune, with a plea to save a
            woman, his wife, from hardships unendurable. He came again, a week later. Still again he
            came, on the fifteenth day of August, repeating his tale of misery and appealing for aid
            for his wife. And then, having procured with great difficulty the information desired
            for the fictitious woman, Kitty Marion imparted the information. Her arrest followed--on
            the nineteenth day of August.</p>
        <p>Let it be said so plainly that none can misunderstand it--we have no apology to make for
            the act of Kitty Marion. We glory in her deed. It was born of a brave generosity, of an
            unfaltering determination to mitigate human suffering. It came from a heart consecrated
            to the freedom of woman--it was the fruit of a motive too fine, too holy for the
            understanding of a trapper of women. </p>
        <p>Let it also be said that neither this arrest, nor those which have been made before, nor
            all the arrests that can be made, will for a moment deter us from this fight to which we
            have committed ourselves.</p>
        <p>Agents provocateur may ply their obscene trade; misguided masculine-minded Puritans may
            oppress, the authorities may fill the jails with women, but this fight will go on. For
            every woman you jail, we will raise up ten for this struggle. Woman's right to control
            her own destiny is being established for all time and it is being establish by women, in
            and out of jail.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
