<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2003/06/25 RK</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/02 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/08/09 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007/08/28 CH Oxygen Update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-5 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1919-08-23">
            <supplied resp="MSPP">23 Aug 1919</supplied>
        </docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Prudence or Prudery in Sex Matters</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp302881</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Fairplay</title>, <supplied resp="MSPP">Aug. 23,
                    1919</supplied></bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="HIRMA">Hirsch, Max</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>This is the first of a six part series of the same title. For the conclusion of this
            article see "<xref from="302878.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control: Yes or
                    No?</title></xref>," Sept. 20, 1919. Sanger also wrote another article in the
            series on <xref from="304453.xml">Oct. 4,1919</xref>.</p>
        <p>The article was introduced by a brief editorial identification of <person
                reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>.</p>
        <index level1="abortion" level2="birth control vs."/>
        <index level1="abortion" level2="frequency of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"/>
        <index level1="Hirsch, Max"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Prudence or Prudery in Sex Matters</head>
        <p>Family limitation will be practiced. No law has yet been framed that can prevent it. The
            church has been powerless and the champions of wornout moral creeds find themselves
            trying in vain to force all women to become mothers against their wills. </p>
        <p>Abundant evidence of the futility of seeking to impose involuntary motherhood upon women
            is found in the size of the families of the rich, of the well-to-do and of the wage
            workers of larger earning capacity. The women of these classes long ago refused to be
            mere brood animals -- usually they prefer to be voluntary mothers, determining for
            themselves the number of children they shall have and when they shall have them. Family
            limitation for them is an accomplished fact.</p>
        <p>It is also an accomplished fact with many of the wives of the less highly paid workers.
            But with the latter, as well as with some of their more fortunate sisters, family
            limitation takes a far more drastic and too often a terribly dangerous course. The
            awakened woman of today will not bear unwanted children. She will not bear more children
            that she can care for. And if she is denied the knowledge of the safe, harmless,
            scientific methods of Birth Control, she limits her family by means of abortion.</p>
        <p>In the very nature of the case, it is impossible to get accurate figures upon the number
            of abortions performed annually in the <place>United States</place>. It is often said,
            however, that one in five pregnancies end in abortion. One estimate is that 150,000
            occur in the United States each year and that 25,000 women die of the effects of such
            operations in every twelve months. Dr. <person reg="Robinson, William J.">William J.
                Robinson</person> asserts that there are 1,000,000 abortions every year in this
            country and adds that the estimate is conservative. He quotes Justice <person
                reg="Clark, John Proctor">John Proctor Clark</person> as saying that there are at
            least 100,000 in the same length of time in New York City alone.</p>
        <p>Dr. <person reg="Hirsch, Max">Max Hirsch</person>, a famous authority quotes an opinion
            that there are 2,000,000 abortions in the United States every year!</p>
        <p>"<q who="HIRMA">I believe</q>," declares Dr. Hirsch, "<q who="HIRMA">that I may say
                without exaggeration that absolutely spontaneous or unprovoked abortions are
                extremely rare, that a vast majority -- I should estimate it at 80 per cent -- have
                a criminal origin.</q>"</p>
        <p>"<q who="HIRMA">Our examinations have informed us that the largest number of abortions
                are performed on married women. This fact brings us to the conclusion that
                contraceptive measures among the upper classes and the practice of abortion among
                the lower class, are the real means employed to regulate the number of
                offspring.</q>"</p>
        <p>The question, then, is not whether family limitation should be practiced. It is being
            practiced; it has long been practiced and it will always be practiced. The question now
            is whether it is to be attained by normal, scientific Birth Control methods or by the
            abnormal, often dangerous, surgical operation. That is the question which the church,
            the state, the moralist, and most of all, the woman herself, must face. </p>
        <p>The knowledge of Birth Control methods may for a time be denied to the woman of the
            working class, but those who are responsible for denying it to her, and she herself,
            should understand clearly the dangers to which she is exposed by the dark age laws which
            force her into the hands of the abortionist. </p>
        <p>Advocates of scientific Birth Control are sometimes met with the absurd statement that
            such methods are injurious to the health of the woman. It is even asserted that they
            cause cancer and other disease and that they bring about sterility.</p>
        <p>As applied to scientific Birth Control, these statements are both false and silly. In the
            light of the best authoritative information of the day, it can be unequivocally set down
            that modern Birth Control methods, properly employed, are not only not injurious but are
            often positively beneficial to the woman's health. The contrary is maintained for the
            most part by those who are mentally honest but uninformed or by such as are altogether
            prejudiced.</p>
        <p>The clergy, bound to its theological dogmas is usually opposed to Birth Control methods
            and is only too ready to accept any bald statement leveled against them. A few
            physicians who are uninformed as to modern means of Birth Control, still incline to the
            opinion that they are injurious, but these physicians have in mind the earlier, cruder
            means of preventing conception.</p>
        <p>Some of the persons who maintain that preventative measures are injurious are so ignorant
            of the whole subject that they in opposing abortion call it Birth Control. Still others
            believe that harmful drugs are given internally as contraceptives. They, of course,
            confuse abortives with the means of preventing conception. Anyone who knows anything
            about either Birth Control or abortion knows that scientific Birth Control methods would
            do away with abortions which occur in appalling numbers in America every year.</p>
        <trailer>(To Be Continued.) </trailer>
    </docBody>
</doc>
