<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011-08-05 NC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-26 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1953-11-00">Nov 1953</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>This I Believe</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp302938</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> C16:0443</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="NIEFR">Nietzsche, Frederick</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Sanger gave this radio address on a segment called <title>This I
                Believe</title> which was presented by <person reg="Murrow, Edward R.">Edward R.
                Murrow</person> in November of 1954.</p><p>For other versions see <title>Margaret
                Sanger Microfilm</title> S72:0860, 0865, 0868, 0870, 0873, 0876, 0879, C16:0444 and
            C18:0205, Library of Congress Microfilm 130:0620</p><p>This address has also been
            published in the books <bibl><title type="book">This I Believe: 2</title> (New
                York:1954), p. 130 - 131</bibl> and <bibl><title type="book">This I Believe: The
                    Personal Philosophies of Remarkable Men and Women</title> (New York: 2007), p.
                210-213</bibl> under the title <title type="article">When Children Are
                Wanted</title>.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>"THIS I BELIEVE" SCRIPT</head>
        <byline><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">MARGARET SANGER</person></byline>
        <p>This I believe, first of all: that all our basic convictions must be tested and
            transmuted in the crucible of experience–and sometimes, the more bitter the experience,
            the more valid the purified belief.</p>
        <p>As a child, one of a large family, I learned that the thing I did best was the thing I
            liked to do. This realization of doing and getting results was what I have later called
            an awakening consciousness.</p>
        <p>There is an old Indian proverb which has inspired me in the work of my adult life. “<q
                who="NIEFR">Build thou beyond thyself, but first be sure that thou, thyself, be strong
                and healthy in body and mind.</q>” To build, to work, to plan to do something, not
            for yourself, not for your own benefit, but “beyond thyself”–and when
            this idea penetrates the mind, you begin to think in terms of a future. I began to think
            of a world beyond myself when I first took an interest in nursing the sick.</p>
        <p>As a nurse, I was in contact with the ill and the infirm. I knew something about the
            health and disease of bodies, but for a long time, I was baffled at the tremendous
            personal problems of life, or marriage, of living, and of being. Here indeed was a
            challenge to “build beyond thyself.” Where was I to begin? I found the answer at every
            door. For I began to believe there was something I could do toward increasing an
            understanding of these basic human problems. To build beyond myself, I must tap all
            inner resources of stamina and courage, of resolution within myself. I was prepared to
            face opposition, ridicule, even denunciation. I had also to prepare myself, in defense
            of these unpopular beliefs, to face courts and even prisons. I resolved to stand up,
            alone if necessary, against all the entrenched forces which opposed me.</p>
        <p>I started my battle some forty years ago. The women, mothers whom I wanted to help, also
            wanted to help me; they, too, wanted to build beyond the self, in creating healthy
            children and bringing them up in life to be happy and useful citizens. I believed it was
            my duty to place motherhood on a higher level than enslavement and accident.</p>
        <p>For these beliefs I was denounced, arrested, I was in and out of police courts and higher
            courts, indictments hung over my life for several years. But nothing could alter my
            beliefs. Because I saw these as truths, I stubbornly stuck to my convictions.</p>
        <p>No matter what it may cost in health, in misunderstanding, in sacrifice, something had to
            be done, and I felt that I was called by the force of circumstances to do it. Because of
            my philosophy and my work, my life has been enriched and full. My interests have
            expanded from local conditions and needs, to a world horizon, where peace on earth may
            be achieved when children are wanted before they are conceived. A new conciousness will
            take place, a new race will be born to bring peace on earth. This belief has withstood
            the crucible of my life’s joyous struggle. It remains my basic belief today.</p>
        <p>This I believe – at the end, as at the beginning of my long crusade for the future of the
            human race.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
