<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2004/09/01 MPL</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/08/06 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/08/09 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/03/11 CH Entered corrections suggested by Andy Carloff.</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011-11-28 CH correct typos</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-01 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/04/30 VS corrected transcriptions with more complete copy</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1920-12-30">30 December, 1920</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Birth Control--The Fundamental Freedom</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp303046</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Birth Control -- The Fundamental Freedom </title><title
                    type="journal">Oklahoma State Register</title> in the Margaret Sanger Papers,
                Library of Congress.</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> C16:146</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>The article was originally published in "the <title type="journal"
                >National Suffragist</title>". For an incomplete version, see Margaret Sanger
            Microfilm C16:146.</p>
        <index level1="abortion" level2="laws and legislation"/>
        <index level1="England" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Germany" level2="abortion in"/>
        <index level1="Germany" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Germany" level2="population policies of"/>
        <index level1="Gemany" level2="socioeconomic conditions"/>
        <index level1="Germany" level2="working classes in"/>
        <index level1="Malthusian theory" level2="opposition to"/>
        <index level1="Netherlands" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Netherlands" level2="socioeconomic conditions"/>
        <index level1="Netherlands" level2="women in"/>
        <index level1="Netherlands" level2="population policies in"/>
        <index level1="physicians" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="Soviet Union" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="enslavement of"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Birth Control--The Fundamental Freedom</head>
        <p><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">I</person> have just returned from <place>Europe</place>
            having spent six months in <place>England</place>, <place>Ireland</place>,
                <place>Scotland</place> and <place>Germany</place>. I return more convinced than
            ever before of the outstanding importance to women and to the world of the conscious,
            voluntary control of the birth rate.</p>
        <p><gap reason="torn" extent="two words"/> conditions, the form of <gap reason="torn"
                extent="two words"/> customs and traditions, <gap reason="torn" extent="one word"/>
            in the countries I have just visited but in all of them one thing is evident: a
            tremendous movement of women toward intellectual and spiritual freedom. In none of these
            countries has this movement reached its goal, no matter what the economic structure. In
                <place reg="Soviet Union">Russia</place>, where the workers claim to have won
            political and economic freedom, women find themselves according to good authority,
            unable to participate fully in the advantages of the new order, because they do not
            control the function of maternity. There is no subject about which the women of Russia
            more urgently seek information today than of birth control. The same thing is true of
            women of Germany, England and <place>France</place>.</p>
        <p>The situation in Germany is peculiarly appalling. In spite of the last five years'
            desperate struggle and the lack of necessities of all kinds still existing, women have,
            at the command of the state, continued to bear large families. Babies have been born
            only to die, or to lead at best a pitiable half-existence (while authority has frowned
            upon the movement to prevent conception and to control birth).</p>
        <p>I saw more than ten thousand children in Germany, hundreds of whom could hardly hold up
            their heads and many more who, at the age of three or four years, could not walk or use
            their legs.</p>
        <p>One Saturday I visited the home of a family in <place reg="Munich, Germany"
                >Munich</place> where the father was unemployed and the family, wife and ten
            children under twelve years, were subsisting upon an unemployment dole worth, in our
            money, about one dollar a week. The food in the house had given out on Friday and the
            next payment was not due until Monday.</p>
        <p>When I arrived one child was gnawing at her mother's breast though her milk had long been
            exhausted, while another baby lay on the bed gnawing painfully, instead of food, a tiny
            thumb. The father had gone to the woods in a desperate attempt to find mushrooms on
            which they might exist over Sunday. Yet the insane cry is still--more children!</p>
        <p>It is the women of Germany who are, and have been the worst sufferers from the evils of
            war and the blockade. It is these same women through whom permanent alleviation to
            Germany will come. Already the women of Munich and southern Germany are awake to the
            horrors of their situation and they are leading in the first strike of its kind - - the
            most fundamental of all strikes - - a birth strike. Going from door to door these women
            are calling upon their fellow women to cease to bear children until their babies shall
            be assured the chance for a decent life.</p>
        <p>The women of northern Germany have gone still further and are backing a bill before the
            German <org>Reischstag</org> which would legalize abortion. To many of us this is a most
            shocking proposal, and one that would in any other country be in no way justifiable but
            the women of Germany claim that as long as the blockade exists, which they consider
            still to be the case because of the unfavorable rate of exchange and other factors, they
            cannot obtain the material for hygienic cleanliness and that therefore they are entitled
            to make use of this means of limiting the family.</p>
        <p>Strange to say, there are many among the medical profession of Germany who favor the
            abortion bill while opposing the prevention of conception. I asked one of the leading
            gynecologists there why he took this stand, and his reply was significant. "<q who="UNK"
                >I am willing</q>," he said, "<q who="UNK">to help check our population during this
                period of intense struggle, but merely as a temporary expedient. Abortion is in the
                hands of the medical profession and therefore can be controlled. To give women the
                knowledge of birth control, would be to place in their hands dangerous power, power
                which could not be recalled when conditions improve</q>."</p>
        <p>Leaving Germany, I traveled through <place reg="Netherlands">Holland</place>, where I
            found conditions by far the best of any country in the world, not excluding <place
                reg="United States">America</place>. In Holland the laws of free press and free
            speech have enabled women to obtain birth control information and to attend medical
            clinics for expert advice on this question. As a result Dutch women participate in
            public activities at the same time have a normal family life. That working woman is
            encouraged to marry early the man of her choice and not to have a family until the child
            may come into a home prepared for it.</p>
        <p>What is the result? While the birth rate of Holland has gone down the death rate has also
            been lowered and the population increased in a ratio which does not tax the country's
            resources. Had this little country not limited its birth rate for the past twenty-five
            years it would have been so involved that it must have lost its national existence in
            the turmoil of the war. As it was, the nation has, unlike most of the other warring
            countries, held its own through the most crucial period of its national life. Freedom of
            the press and of speech has been preserved. Standards of health have been improved.
            Conditions are today more nearly normal there than in any other European countries and
            today it is illegal not only to give birth control information through clinics, or
            through the mails, but even to discuss anything which would tend to sanction or
            encourage a reduction of the birth rate.</p>
        <p>In England, where I lectured to working women on the subject of birth control, I found
            everywhere intense interest. There are no laws in England preventing the working woman
            from obtaining birth control information. The obstacle to its widespread has heretofore
            been a peculiar prejudice on the part of the workers themselves. This feeling may be
            traced back to the time of <person reg="Malthus, Thomas Robert">Malthus</person> who, on
            the basis of his theory that poverty was caused by prolific breeding, advocated
            continence until a late marriage and then family limitation through abstinence. This
            proposal of Malthus was opposed by the workers who approved the Marxian conception of
            poverty as the result of the capitalist system rather than of an excess population. The
            economic after-the-war conditions coupled with the strong woman's movement in England,
            have gone far to break down this prejudice of the workers and even the communists
            attended my meetings in large numbers.</p>
        <p> News of a similar keen interest in birth control in Asiatic countries is continually
            reaching me. In <place>India</place>, the movement has already assumed dimensions which
            make it of national importance, and the Japanese government has sent officials here to
            study the subject, recognizing that it is for that over-crowded island empire a choice
            between birth control or a war of aggression within thirty years.</p>
        <p> In the United States, our movement struggles under the enormous handicap of state laws
            which place scientific birth control information in the category of the obscene and
            punish by $1,000 fine or a year in prison the giving of oral or written information on
            the subject, in addition to the <name reg="United States Penal Code">federal law</name>
            which imposes a $5,000 fine and five years in prison for sending such information
            through the mails. Until these laws are repealed, it is impossible to establish clinics
            or to give such information in any way to the thousands of women clamoring for it,
            without risking a prison sentence. Thirty-five women have so far gone to jail in their
            efforts to perform this service for their fellow women.</p>
        <p> It is evident therefore that the movement is already an international one, as the
            population question must necessarily be. Some of the ablest statesmen and economists of
            Europe are now awake to the tremendous significance of over-breeding and to its relation
            to the great world evils of child labor, unemployment, poverty and war. Until it is
            scientifically and openly understood, they contend, there can never be a real league of
            nations.</p>
        <p> The time is now ripe, therefore for the women of all nations to demand the right of
            conscious voluntary control of the birth rate through the prevention of conception and
            to insist upon the placing in their hands of the best scientific knowledge on this
            subject.</p>
        <p> Fortunately the women of the world are now stepping into government as fully
            enfranchised citizens, with the power to demand their rights. A few of us, a small
            handful in fact, have been holding the fort until women had the vote and their energies
            could be released to attack this tremendous subject. If, in our own country, one-tenth
            of the energy which has been used to win the franchise would be used to attack the
            fossilized birth control laws on the statute books in would it would only be a few years
            until the women of the United States would have the fundamental freedom which underlies
            all others, power to control their own bodies.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
