<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2009/07/08 LL</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-10 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1931-06-00 ">June 1931</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>The Progress of the Birth Control Movement</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp303109</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Mothers' Aid Message</title>June 1931, 7, 18-19.</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> C16:321</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp>
                <name id="unk">Unknown</name>
            </resp>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>For earlier typed version see MSM 0346-034</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="history of"/>
        <index level1="censorship" level2="in United States"/>
        <index level1="New York City" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="arrests and imprisionment"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="government" level3="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="Woman Rebel" level2="articles in "/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="creation of term"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation"
            level3="Postal Code and Regulations"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>The Progress of the Birth Control Movement</head>
        <byline>By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></byline>
        <p> It was in 1914 that I began an open attack on the laws of the <place reg="United States"
                >United States</place> which would withhold from woman the right to regulate the
            size of her family. For the four preceding years the battleground had been my own mind
            and soul.</p>
        <p>As a trained nurse in the slums and tenements of <place reg="New York, NY">New
                York</place> I had been brought face to face with conditions that made the so-called
            sacredness of motherhood a term of unspeakable irony. Pregnant women-- drunken
            husbands-- hungry children, children born to a heritage of disease, filth, crime-- this
            was the order of that day. As one pregnancy followed another, a family sank deeper into
            the mire. And always denied contraceptive knowledge by their doctors, these women were
            driven to other means. On Saturday evenings, they lined up before the office of a cheap
            abortionist, each waiting her turn. “<q who="unk">You would tell us nothing</q>,” they
            seemed to reproach me (I knew nothing to tell them), “<q who="unk">and here we are.</q>”
            All too often wrecked health and death followed.</p>
        <p> Weighed down and haunted by the hopeless misery of these lives, ever brooding over the
            social and economic problems involved, it became clear to me at length that the root of
            the trouble lay in uncontrolled fertility. Once convinced of this, action became
            imperative. I had no choice-- I had to do something.</p>
        <p>Under this compulsion I set about acquiring the information these women needed, a search
            which was eventually to take me to <place>France</place>, <place>England</place> and
                <place reg="Netherlands">Holland</place>. In America I had to give up the search.
            State and federal laws made the printing and circulation of this knowledge a federal
            crime. No doctors whom I approached would give me help, and no group of any kind would
            sponsor the cause. They assured me that any efforts in so dangerous a field would land
            me in jail, and advised me to drop it.</p>
        <p>At that time there was not even a language in which to discuss these questions. The
            subject was considered indecent and vulgar. Openly to advocate the prevention of
            conception-- a phrase which the <title type="journal">NEW YORK TIMES</title> would not
            allow in its columns-- meant ostracism.</p>
        <p>Such was the situation when I began my battle in 1914 in the pages of the "<title
                type="journal">WOMAN REBEL</title>" and created the term, "birth control." Seventeen
            years have passed. Three weeks ago that movement, for advocacy of which I was arrested
            by the <org>United States Government</org> in 1914 and ridiculed and insulted by
            individuals, was endorsed by the <org>Federal Council of the Churches of Christ in
                America</org>. There is no force in the world, it has been said, like that of an
            idea whose hour has come.</p>
        <p>It was my prosecution by the United States Government for articles that appeared in the
                <title type="journal">WOMAN REBEL</title> (articles advocating birth control, but
            not giving methods) that started people talking about birth control. A letter from
                <person reg="Wells, H. G.">H. G. Wells</person> as well as letters from other
            distinguished English men and women to <person reg="Wilson, Woodrow">President
                Wilson</person> in my behalf brought prestige, and the publicity became so great
            with letters to the judge and the district attorney pouring in from all parts of the
            country that the case was finally dropped. This was in 1916. In the heated period that
            followed, many champions of the cause arose. Organizations were formed, there were
            meetings, speeches, published articles, pamphlets. Many were arrested, many acquitted;
            not a few served jail sentences.</p>
        <p>My own jail term came in 1917. I had opened a "clinic" in a poor section of <place
                reg="Brooklyn, NY">Brooklyn</place> to demonstrate the direction which the movement
            should take. In Holland, I had found, there were more than fifty of these birth control
            centers, which they called clinics, where women were individually examined, fitted, and
            instructed by nurses or midwives trained for that purpose by doctors. I had returned
            from Holland convinced that instruction in contraception was the business of the medical
            profession, and that clinics should be our goal. After my coast-to-coast lecture tour in
            1916 advocating clinics in those states where the law permitted, I opened the first
            birth control clinic in America, in <place reg="New York, NY">New York City</place>. It
            was raided by the police; <person reg="Byrne, Ethel Higgins">my sister</person> and I
            were arrested and sentenced to one month in the Workhouse. Wide publicity for the cause
            and thousands of new supporters resulted. On appeal, we gained an opinion that birth
            control instruction was legal if given by doctors for the cure or prevention of disease.
            Accordingly, when, after enforced delay, another clinic was opened in 1923, we secured a
                <person reg="Bocker, Dorothy">woman doctor</person> for a medical director. This
            clinic is still in operation, with more than 4,000 patients yearly. Today there are
            fifty-nine clinics in thirteen states. Research for perfected methods is being
            constantly carried on.</p>
        <p>Meantime an unceasing campaign of education for public opinion has been going on, with
            books, lectures, articles, conferences. My own lecture engagements have taken me to
            university halls and pulpits. The <title type="journal">BIRTH CONTROL REVIEW</title>, of
            which I was editor until 1929, was started in 1917. Biologists, economists, doctors,
            clergymen, poets, novelists have contributed to its pages and given active support to
            the cause. The far-reaching implications of the movement are becoming clearer every day.
            On the other hand the toiling, overburdened mothers, the victims of our social and
            economic system, continue pouring in their heartrending letters pleading for help, each
            with its own tale of too many children, wrecked health and poverty.</p>
        <p>In 1921 we held the <org reg="First American Birth Control Conference">first national
                conference</org> and organized the <org>American Birth Control League</org>, which
            has branches in many states.</p>
        <p>In <place>Europe</place>, the movement has had fewer obstacles to overcome. Until the
            post-war period no country had laws prohibiting the giving of contraceptive information.
            Holland, with its many clinics directed by the <org reg="Nieuw-Malthusiaansche Bond">
                Dutch Neo-Malthusian League</org>, has carried on the most consistent education of
            the poor in birth control, with results already perceptible in maternal health and in
            the physique of Dutch military conscripts. There are now clinics in
                <place>Germany</place>, <place>Austria</place>, <place reg="Soviet Union"
                >Russia</place>, <place>India</place>, and <place>Japan</place>.</p>
        <p>In England it was that the modern birth control movement had its earliest beginning, with
                <person reg="Malthus, Thomas Robert">Malthus</person>’ "<title type="book">Theory of
                Population</title>," published in 1798. And in England it was that I found sympathy
            and guidance in the early days when I seemed to stand alone. At the time of my first
            visit there, in 1914, the idea was being kept alive by the <org>Malthusian League</org>,
            but it hardly touched the masses. When I was invited in 1920 to come over for a series
            of lectures the working classes were being aroused, and I addressed twenty women’s
            guilds. The following year two clinics opened, and the movement has grown by leaps and
            bounds on the foundation laid by such pioneers as <person reg="Besant, Annie">Annie
                Besant</person> and <person reg="Bradlaugh, Charles">Charles Bradlaugh</person>, the
                <person reg="Drysdale, Charles Vichery"><person reg="Drysdale, Bessie Ingham"
                    >Drysdale</person></person> family, and Dr. <person reg="Vickery, Alice">Alice
                Vickery</person>. Today there are about twenty-five clinics and the <org
                reg="United Kingdom Ministry of Health">Ministry of Health</org> allows the giving
            of contraceptive advice at its <org reg="British Maternity and Child Welfare Center"
                >Maternity and Child Welfare Center</org>s, of which there are nearly 2,500
            scattered over the country.</p>
        <p>The most imperative need for birth control today exists in the Oriental countries. In
            1922 I was invited by a <org reg="Kaizo">liberal group</org> in <place
                reg="Tokyo, Japan">Tokyo</place> to come to Japan to present the subject there. The
            enthusiasm and publicity aroused in both Japan and <place>China</place> was tremendous.
            Never has my calendar been so crowded with lectures, conferences, interviews and social
            functions. Organizations were formed, clinics have since been started, and in 1930 the
            Japanese government sent an official representative to the <org
                reg="International Birth Control Conference, 7th">international conference</org> at
                <place reg="Zurich, Switzerland">Zurich</place>.</p>
        <p>In <place>Italy</place>, <place>France</place>, and <place>Ireland</place>, Catholic
            strongholds all new laws have been passed against birth control. That same France where
            contraceptive knowledge has been handed down from mother to daughter for generations,
            where the <org reg="International Neo Malthusian Conference, 1st">first international
                conference on birth control</org> was held in 1900, has now made it a crime even to
            discuss the subject in the press.</p>
        <p>Seven international conferences have been held. A great event for the movement in America
            was the holding of the <name type="conference"
                reg="International Neo Malthusian and Birth Control Conference, 6th">sixth
                conference</name> in New York in 1925, with delegates from twelve countries. A
            contraceptive session for doctors only was attended by a thousand doctors. An American
            biologist and college president, Dr. <person reg="Little, Clarence Cook">C. C.
                Little</person>, became president of the <org>International Federation of Birth
                Control League</org>, reorganized at that time.</p>
        <p>A significant event was the <org reg="World Population Conference, 1st">World Population
                Conference</org> in <place reg="Geneva, Switzerland">Geneva</place> in 1927. While
            birth control had no direct place in its program, the connection was obvious. <orgRef
                reg="International Union for the Scientific Study of Population Problems">A
                permanent body for the study of population was formed</orgRef>. And the doctors who
            attended that conference brought about the formation of the <org>International Medical
                Group for the investigation of Birth Control</org>. This important body correlates
            and disseminates the results of scientific research on contraception in all countries.
            It has its headquarters in <place reg="London, England">London</place> where we have
            also an <org reg="Birth Control International Information Centre">international
                information center</org>.</p>
        <p>The final step for breaking down the barriers in America remains to be taken. The battle
            is not won while the present laws stand on our state and federal statute books. In 1929
            I organized the <org reg="National Committee for Federal Legislation on Birth Control"
                >Federal Committee on Legislation for Birth Control</org>, believing that the time
            had come to prepare for a vigorous campaign on <org reg="United States Congress"
                >Congress</org>. Our "doctors’ bill" was introduced in the last session of the
            Senate by Senator <person reg="Gillett, Frederick">Gillett</person>, and a most
            favorable impression was made at the committee hearing. The bill will be re-introduced,
            we hope, at the next session. This amendment would open up the mails to doctors for the
            transportation of contraceptive literature and materials.</p>
        <p>There is no question but that there is an overwhelming sentiment in the country for birth
            control, but until that sentiment becomes more articulate, Congress will not act. Once a
            matter like this is entrenched in law, only an avalanche of public opinion can free it.
            Negligence, reticence, or mere lack of social consciousness prevents people from
            speaking out. For many the old taboo of silence and secrecy still prevails and it seems
            indelicate to lift up one’s voice-- yes, even though on that depends the relief of
            untold misery and the greatest step forward for freedom and growth that woman has ever
            taken. If every mother who in her own life has reaped the benefit of this knowledge
            would do her bit to distribute it to the masses, how it would speed the victory! If
            every man and woman who believes in birth control would become articulate to the extent
            of appealing to a senator or representative, how overwhelming and immediate the victory
            would be!</p>
        <p>Then indeed my vision of a future, when motherhood will be really free, would seem on its
            way to fulfillment. For the time will come when the bearing of children, no longer an
            enforced burden, no longer haphazard and accidental, need only be undertaken as a
            cherished privilege; and every child will be a wanted child, born to its rightful
            heritage of love and care and comfort. Then truly will motherhood be the flower of
            womanhood.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
