<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-12-11 CH encode</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>
            <person>Margaret Sanger</person>
        </docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1917-04-00">Apr 1917</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>My Fight for Birth Control</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp303277</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Physical Culture</title>, Apr. 1917, pp. 16-21</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="SACSA">Sachs, Sadie</name>
            <name id="ED">Editor of Physical Culture</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>Parts of this document were later used in other articles and speeches by Sanger including
                "<xref from="306006.xml">Woman and Birth Control</xref>," Dec. 1923, and "<xref
                from="301540.xml">The Case for Birth Control</xref>," Feb. 23, 1924.</p>
        <index level1="birth control clinics and leagues"/>
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="Sachs, Sadie (story)"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="biography"/>
        <index level1="Family Limitation" level2="censorship of"/>
        <index level1="working classes" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="working classes" level2="fertility of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits and risks of"/>
        <index level1="Woman Rebel The" level2="legal case"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="mortality rates" level3="infant"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>My Fight for Birth Control</head>
        <byline>By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></byline>
        <p>For centuries woman has gone forth with man to till the fields, to feed and clothe the
            nations. She has sacrificed her life to populate the earth. She has overdone her labors.
            She now steps forth and demands that women shall cease producing in ignorance. To do
            this she must have knowledge to control birth. This is the first immediate step she must
            take toward the goal of her freedom.</p>
        <p> Those who are opposed to this are simply those who do not know. Any one who like myself
            has worked among the people and found on one hand an ever increasing population with its
            ever-increasing misery, poverty and ignorance, and on the other hand a stationary or
            decreasing population with its increasing wealth and higher standards of living, greater
            freedom, joy and happiness, cannot doubt that birth control is the livest issue of the
            day and one on which depends the future welfare of the race.</p>
        <p> Before I attempt to refute the arguments against birth control, I should like to tell
            you something of the conditions I met with as a trained nurse and of the experience that
            convinced me of its necessity and led me to jeopardize my liberty in order to place this
            information in the hands of the women who need it. My first clear impression of life was
            that large families and poverty went hand in hand. I was born and brought up in a glass
            factory <place reg="Corning, NY">town</place> in the western part of <place>New
                York</place> State. I was one of eleven children--so I had some personal experience
            of the struggles and hardships a large family endures.</p>
        <p> When I was seventeen years old my <person reg="Higgins, Anne Purcell">mother</person>
            died from overwork and the strain of too frequent child bearing. I was left to care for
            the younger children and share the burdens of all. When I was old enough I entered a
                <org reg="New York Eye and Ear Infirmary">hospital</org> to take up the profession
            of nursing.</p>
        <p> In the hospital I found that seventy-five per cent of the diseases of men and women are
            the result of ignorance and their sex functions. I found that every department of life
            was open to investigation and discussion except that shaded valley of sex. The explorer,
            scientist, inventor, may go forth in their various fields for investigation and return
            to lay the fruits of their discoveries at the feet of society. But woe to him who dares
            explore that forbidden realm of sex. No matter how pure the motive, no matter what
            miseries he sought to remove, slanders, persecutions and jail await him who dares bear
            the light of knowledge into that cave of darkness.</p>
        <p> So great was the ignorance of the women and girls I met concerning their own bodies that
            I decided to specialize in woman’s diseases and took up gynecological and obstetrical
            nursing.</p>
        <p> A few years of thsi work brought me to a shocking discovery--that knowledge of the
            methods of controlling birth was accessible to the women of wealth while the working
            women were deliberately kept in ignorance.</p>
        <p> I found that the women of the working class were as anxious to obtain this knowledge as
            their sisters of wealth, but that they were told that there are laws on the statute
            books against imparting it to them. And the medical profession was the most religious in
            obeying these laws when the patient was a poor woman.</p>
        <p> I found that the women of the working class had emphatic views on the crime of bringing
            children into the world to die of hunger. They would rather risk their lives through
            abortion than give birth to little ones they could not feed and care for. </p>
        <p>For the laws against imparting this knowledge force these women into the hands of the
            filthiest midwives and the quack abortionists--unless they bear unwanted children--with
            the consequences that the deaths from abortions are almost wholly among the
            working-class women. No other country in the world has so large a number of abortions
            nor so large a number of deaths of women resulting therefrom as the <place
                reg="United States">United States of America</place>. Our law makers close their
            virtuous eyes. A most conservative estimate is that there are 250,000 abortions
            performed in this country every year.</p>
        <p>How often have I stood at the bedside of a woman in childbirth and seen the tears flow in
            gladness and heard the sigh of "thank <name type="deity">God</name>" when told that her
            child was born dead? What can man know of the fear and dread of unwanted pregnancy? What
            can man know of the agony of carrying beneath one's heart a little life which tells the
            mother every instinct that it cannot survive? Even when it was born alive the chances
            are that it would perish within a year.</p>
        <p>Do you know that three hundred thousand babies under one year of age die in the United
            States every year from poverty and neglect, while six hundred thousand parents remain in
            ignorance of how to prevent three hundred thousand more babies from coming into the
            world the next year to die of poverty and neglect?</p>
        <p>I found from records concerning women of the underworld that eighty-five per cent of them
            come from parents averaging nine living children. And that fifty per cent of them are
            mentally defective.</p>
        <p>We know, too, that among mentally defective parents the birth rate is four times as great
            as that of the normal parent. Is this not cause for alarm? Is it not time for our
            physicians, social workers and scientists to face this array of facts and stop quibbling
            about woman's morality? I say this because it is these same people who raise objection
            to birth control on the ground that it <emph rend="italics">may</emph> case women to be
            immoral.</p>
        <p>Solicitude for women's morals has ever been the cloak Authority has worn in its age-long
            conspiracy to keep woman in bondage.</p>
        <p>When I was in <place>Spain</place> a year ago, I found that the Spanish woman was far
            behind her European sisters in readiness or even desire for modern freedom. Upon
            investigation as to the cause of this I found that there are over five thousand villages
            and towns in Spain with no means of travel, transportation and communication save
            donkeys over bridle paths. I was told that all attempts to build roads and railroads in
            Spain has been met with the strongest opposition of the Clergy and the Government on the
            ground that roads and railroads would make communication easier and bring the women of
            the country into the cities <emph rend="italics">where they would meet their
                downfall.</emph>
        </p>
        <p>Do we who have roads and railroads think our women are less moral than the Spanish women?
            Certainly not. But we in this country are, after all, just emerging from the fight for a
            higher education of women which met with the same objection only a few years ago.</p>
        <p>We know now that education has not done all the dreadful things to women that its
            opponents predicted were certain to result. And so shall we find that knowledge to
            control birth, which has been in the hands of the women of wealth for the past
            twenty-five years will not tend to lower women's standard of morality. </p>
        <p>Statistics show us that the birth-rate of any given quarter is in ratio with and to its
            wealth. And further figures prove that in large cities the rich districts yield a
            birth-rate of a third of that of the poor districts. In <place reg="Paris, France"
                >Paris</place> for every 1,000 women between the ages of 15 and 50 the poor
            districts yield 116 births and the rich districts 34 births. In <place
                reg="Berlin, Germany">Berlin</place> conditions are approximately the same. For
            every 1,000 women between the ages of 15 and 50 the poor districts yield 157 births
            while the rich yield 47. This applies also to all large cities the world over.</p>
        <p>Let me ask you: Has the State any more right to ravish a woman against her will by
            keeping her in ignorance than a man has through brute force? Has the State a better
            right to decide whwn she shall bear offspring?</p>
        <p>Picture a woman with five or six little ones living on the average working man's wage of
            ten dollars a week. The mother is broken in health and spirit, a worn-out shadow of the
            woman she once was. Where is the man or woman who would reproach me for trying to get
            into this woman's hands knowledge that will save her from giving birth to any more
            babies doomed to certain poverty and misery and perhaps to disease and death.</p>
        <p> Is this action on my part to be called immoral? Am I to be persecuted and classed as
            immoral because I advocate small families for the working class while <person
                reg="Roosevelt, Theodore">Mr. Roosevelt</person> can go up and down the length of
            the land shouting and urging these women to have large families and is neither arrested
            nor molested but considered by all society as highly moral? </p>
        <p>But I ask you which is the more moral-to urge this class of women to have only those
            children she desires and can care for, or to delude her into breeding cannon fodder for
            the munition makers and the professional jingoes? Which is America's definition of
            morality? </p>
        <p>You will agree with me that a woman should be free. </p>
        <p>Yet no adult woman who is ignorant of the means to prevent conception can call herself
            free.</p>
        <p> No woman can call herself free who cannot choose the time to be a mother or not as she
            sees fit. This should be woman's first demand. </p>
        <p>Our present laws force woman into one of two ways: Celibacy, with its nervous results, or
            abortion. All modern physicians testify that both these conditions are harmful; that
            celibacy is the cause of many nervous complaints, while abortion is a disgrace to a
            civilized community. Physicians claim that early marriage with knowledge to control
            birth would do away with both. For this world enable two young people to live and work
            together until such time as they could care for a family. I found that young people
            desire early marriage, and would marry early were it not for the dread of a large family
            to support. Why will not society countenance and advance this idea? Because it is still
            afraid of the untried and the unknown.</p>
        <p>I saw that fortunes were being spent in establishing baby nurseries, where new babies are
            brought and cared for while the mothers toil in sweatshops during the day. I saw that
            society with its well-intentioned palliatives was in this respect like the quack, who
            cures a cancer by burning off the top while the deadly disease continues to spread
            underneath. I never felt this more strongly that I did three years ago after the death
            of the patient in my last nursing case.</p>
        <p>This <person reg="Sachs, Sadie">patient</person> was the wife of a <person
                reg="Sachs, Jake">struggling working man</person>--the mother of three children--who
            was suffering from the results of a self-attempted abortion. I found her in a very
            serious condition, and for three weeks both the attending physician and myself labored
            night and day to bring her out of the Valley of the Shadow of Death. We finally
            succeeded in restoring her to her family. </p>
        <p>I remember well the day I was leaving. The physician, too, was making his last call. As
            the doctor put out his hand to say "Good-bye," I saw the patient had something to say to
            him, but was shy and timid about saying it. I started to leave the room, but she called
            me back and said:</p>
        <p>"<q who="SACSA">Please don't go. How can both of you leave me without telling me what I
                can do to avoid another illness such as I have just passed through.</q>" </p>
        <p>I was interested to hear what the answer of the physican would be, and I went back and
            sat down beside her in expectation of hearing a sympathetic reply. To my amazement he
            answered her with a joking sneer. We came away. </p>
        <p>Three months later, I was aroused from my sleep one midnight. A telephone call from the
            husband of the same woman requested me to come immediately as she was dangerously ill. I
            arrived to find her beyond relief. Another conception had forced her into the hands of a
            cheap abortionist, and she died at four o'clock the same morning, leaving behind her
            three small children and a frantic husband.</p>
        <p>I returned home as the sun was coming over the roofs of the <place reg="New York, NY"
                >Human Bee-Hive</place>, and I realized how futile my efforts and my work had been.
            I, too, like the philanthropists and social workers, had been dealing with the symptoms
            rather than the disease. I threw my nursing bag in to the corner and announced to my
            family that I would never take another case until I had made it possible for women women
            in America to have knowledge of birth control.</p>
        <p>I asked several prominent women--suffragists, feminists, etc.--if they would not help me
            in doing this work, which would strike at the very root of the evil. Many hesitated,
            waiting until "<q who="UNK">the work became better known</q>." Others gave slight aid
            and soon forgot. But the cries of thousands of suffering women would not let me wait. I
            went forward almost alone.</p>
        <p>I found, however, to my utter surprise, that there was very little scientific information
            on this question available in America. Although nearly every country in
                <place>Europe</place> had this knowledge, we were the only civilized people in the
            world whose postal laws forbade it.</p>
        <p>The tyranny of the censorship of the post office is the greatest menace to liberty in the
            United States today. The <org reg="United States Post Office">post office</org> was
            never intended to be a moral or ethical institution. It was intended to be mechanically
            efficient; certainly not to pass upon the opinions in the matter it conveys. If we
            concede this power to this institution, we might just as well give to the street car
            companies the right to refuse to carry passengers whose ideas they did not like.</p>
        <p>I was warned that the penalty for violating the post office lasw was the most severe of
            any country in the world. I need give only one illustration to show how they have been
            enfored up to the present time. This was a case of a <person reg="Unknown"
                >physician</person> who resided in the <place>Middle West</place>. He received a
            letter from a woman a few miles of the city where he lived. She stated that she was the
            mother of nine children, and that her husband was in the last stages of tuberculosis.
            She begged and implored him on the grounds of humanity to give her some information
            whereby she could prevent bringing any more children into the world. The doctor being a
            liberal-minded and sympathetic man with a conscious responsbility toward the future of
            the race did not hesitate a moment. He sent her a few simple direction to prevent
            conception. Two weeks later he received another letter from another women, who claimed
            that she had seven children and had had tecn abortions, and that her husband was
            suffering from syphilis. She, also, inmplored him to send her by return mail some
            information that would save her from a further conception. Again, the doctor did not
            hestitate. He complied with her request, and sent her simple directions to avoid further
            pregnancies.</p>
        <p>One month later, he was ordered into court and confronted by a woman, a Comstock spy, who
            was the writer of both letters. He pleaded guilty to the charge and was sentenced to ten
            years in <org reg="United States Penitentiary, Leavenworth">Leavenworth
                Penitenitary</org> and ten thousand dollars fine. In other words he received the
            maximum sentence in both cases--for each letter. His home was broken up, his
            professional standing gone, and not one word of protest from the medical profession
            against this outrage. After spending six years in prison, last year he was released. He
            is now an old man, broken in health, and requests his friends friends not to use his
            name, or give his case any publicity.</p>
        <p>The same methods, that of a spy and forged letters and misrepresentations, were used in
            the case of <person reg="Sanger, William">William Sanger</person>
            <q who="ED">[Mrs. Sanger's husband]</q>, who was conviced September 11, 1915, for giving
            a <person reg="Bamberger, Charles">Comstick detective</person> a copy of my pamphlet on
                <title type="book">Family Limitation</title>.</p>
        <p>This is only one illustration of the methods of censorship, and although <person
                reg="Comstock, Anthony">Mr. Comstock</person> has since passed away, the same
            methods are being employed as viciously as ever before.</p>
        <p>I will not take up the story of the publication of "<title type="journal">The Woman
                Rebel</title>." You know how I began to publish it, how it was confiscated and
            suppressed by the post office authorities, how I was indicted and arrested for bringing
            it out, and how the case was postponed time and time against and finally dismissed by
                <person reg="Clayton, Henry DeLamar">Judge Clayton</person> in the <org
                reg="United States District Court for the Southern District of New York">Federal
                Court</org>. </p>
        <p>These, and many more obtacles and difficulties were put in the path of this philosophy
            and this work to suppress it of possible and discredit it in any case.</p>
        <p>But I am glad to say that the very reverse of what was intended has occurred. The same
            authorities who two years ago judged me lewd and lascivious now pay me the pretty
            compliment of informing me that I am a "disorderly person." But why did the authorites
            change their minds? Because of the thousands of letters of protest which came to them
            from all parts of this country and convinced them that birth control was too vital a
            demand in the United States today to be suppressed through the persecution of an
            individual, which proves to us again that the courts, no matter how powerful, cannot
            combat a strong and intelligent opinion.</p>
        <p>My fight with the <org reg="United States Government">Goverment</org> has been to arouse
            intrest in the subject of birth control in America, and in this, I feel that I have been
            victorious. The work now before us is to crystallize and to organize this interest into
            action, not only for the repeal of the laws but for the establishment of free clinics in
            every large center of population in the country where scientific, individual information
            may be given every adult person who comes to ask it. </p>
        <p>In <place reg="Netherlands">Holland</place>, there are fifty-two clinics with nurses in
            charge, and the medical profession has practically handed the work over to nurses. In
            these clinics, which are mainly in the industrial and agricultural districts, any woman
            who is married or old enough to be married, can come for information and be instructed
            in the care and hygiene of her body.</p>
        <p>These clinics have been established for thirty years in Holland, and the result has been
            that the general death-rate of Holland has fallen to the lowest of any country in
            Europe. Also, the infanct mortality of <place reg="Amsterdam, Netherlands"
                >Amsterdam</place> and <place reg="The Hague, Netherlands">The Hague</place> is
            found to be the lowest of any city in the world. Holland proves that the practice of
            birth control leads to race improvement; her increase of population has accelerated as
            the death-rate has fallen.</p>
        <p>In <place>England</place>, <place>France</place>, <place>Scandinavia</place>, and
                <place>Germany</place>, information regarding birth control is also freely
            disseminated, but the establishment of clinics in these countries is not so well
            organized as it is in Holland, with the consequence that the upper and middle classes,
            as in this country, have ready access to this knowledge, while the poor continue to
            multiply becuase of their lack of it. This leads, especially in France, to a high infant
            mortality, which, rather that a low birth-rate, is the real cause of her decreasing
            population.</p>
        <p>We in America should learn a lesson from this, and I would urge immediate group action to
            form clinics at once. We have in this country a splendid foundation in our hospital and
            settlement work. The American trained nurse is the best equipped and most capable in the
            world, which enables us, if we begin work at once, to accomplish as much in ten years as
            the European countries have done in thirty years.</p>
        <p>The arrests of my assistants and myself and the closing of the Amboy Street Clinic in the
            Brownsville district of <place reg="Brooklyn, NY">Brooklyn</place> does not discourage
            me. It does prove, of course that all opposition to our work is not dead. </p>
        <p>The <org>Brownsville Clinic</org>, I believe, accomplished at least this: it showed the
            need and usefulness of such an agency.</p>
        <p>The free clinic is the solution for our problem. It will enable women to help themselves,
            and will have much to do with disposing of this soul-crushing charity which is at best a
            mere temporary relief.</p>
        <p>Woman must be protected from incessant childbearing before she can actively participate
            in the social life. She must triumph over Nature's and Man's laws which have kept her in
            bondage. Just as man has triumphed over Nature by the use of electricity, shipbuilding,
            bridges, etc., so must women triumph over the laws which has made her a childbearing
            machine.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
