<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2001-10-26 MH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2002-08-22 KH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/02 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/08/13 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007-05-30 CH Oxygen cleanup</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-11-18 CH cleaning regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1912-02-15">15 Feb 1912</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>The Fangs of the Monster at Lawrence</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp303459</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">New York Call</title>, Feb. 15, 1912</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Collected Documents Series </title> C16:0018</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
        <index level1="working classes"/>
        <index level1="labor movement" level2="Lawrence, MA Strike, 1912"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>The Fangs of the Monster at Lawrence</head>
        <byline>By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret H. Sanger</person>.</byline>
        <p>As soon as you board the train for <place reg="Lawrence, MA">Lawrence</place> at <place
                reg="Boston, MA">Boston</place>, you are aware that war is going on about you
            somewhere not far off. Dozens of soldiers in uniform, relieved for a few hours of such
            laborious work as waiting for trouble are seen strutting in and out of the railway
            trains, pompous and important as defenders of the bosses and private property. </p>
        <p>When you get to Lawrence, on every corner are soldiers with guns bayoneted, ready at a
            moment's notice to plunge this deadly instrument into the living flesh of the working
            men or women who have rebelled against these degrading conditions of wage slavery which
            has reduced them and their families to human machines used only to pile up enormous
            profits for the bosses of the mills.</p>
        <p>All of these soldiers were very young men, ranging in looks from 18 to 21 years of age,
            immature and unsophisticated, as characterless as any youth who longs for life and
            adventure at this age usually is. As they stood on the corners dancing up and down in
            the biting cold, it is hoped they may realize what tools they really are, and being
            hired assassins of the bosses is more adventure than they wish. One man told of the
            arrest of <person reg="Ettor, Jospeh">Ettor</person>. A large crowd of people had
            gathered together when the cry of "<q who="UNK">halt!</q>" came imperatively from the
            guards. The man said he felt the bayonet at his back, yet he was powerless to move. Had
            the crowd pushed him further this would have been plunged into his back.</p>
        <p>Many of these young men are students of <org>Harvard University</org>.</p>
        <p>The <person reg="Lowell, Anbott Lawrence">president of Harvard</person> is said to be one
            of the mill owners. </p>
        <p>Again many of these soldiers are sons of working men and women who are themselves going
            through the same poverty and struggles as the textile workers. </p>
        <p>The time has come to educate these boys, to remind them to what class they belong, and
            when they realize this they will refuse to murder their working brothers, to serve as
            hirelings to prop up the profit system, which bases its existence upon the tears and
            blood of the famished workers.</p>
        <p>The Lawrence strike is no ordinary strike. The mill owners realized this. They could see
            that it contained the essence of revolution, and knowing that, no time was wasted in
            sending the militia to the spot at once.</p>
        <p>When the Religious Forward Movement can no longer shield it from the revolutionary
            thought, after arbitration boards have been discarded by the workers, then stripped of
            all pretense and hypocrisy, capitalism shows its fangs of despotism and murder by
            appearing upon the scene to protect its tottering structure with glistening bayonets and
            rapid-fire guns to mow down the workers, if necessary, in order to cling to its stolen
            property.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
