<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2012-03-28 AW Initial Tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2012-04-04 CH Proofed Tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2012-04-24 AW Corrected Tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2012-05-14 CH Second proof</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2012-05-30 AW Corrected tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-10 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1960-03-20">1960 Mar 20</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">World Population Emergency Campaign Meeting
                    Address</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp303823</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Hugh Moore Papers, Seeley Mudd Library, Princeton University</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> C16:0506</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="EISDW">Eisenhower, Dwight</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>Sanger spoke at the one-day conference of population experts and prominent businessmen
            that kicked off the <org>World Population Emergency Campaign</org>. The event, which was
            attended by about one hundred people, was held at <org>Princeton University</org>. Other
            notable speakers included General <person reg="Draper, William H.">William H.
                Draper</person>, Lady <person reg="Rama Rau, Dhanvanthi">Dhanvanthi Rama
                Rau</person>, and <person reg="Moore, Hugh">Hugh Moore.</person> It was chaired by
                <person reg="du Pont Copeland, Lammot">Lammot du Pont Copeland</person>.</p>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="population policies of"/>
        <index level1="conferences" level2="World Population Conference" level3="1927"/>
        <index level1="World Population Emergency Campaign"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="foreign aid"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <p>Mr. Chairman, thank you. I am rather embarrassed at such an introduction, but I think
            that, just the same, once in a while we need such a blowup as we get today.</p>
        <p>You can all relax, because I am not going to make a speech. I have come here from <place
                reg="Tucson, AZ">Tucson, Arizona</place>, to congratulate you, Mr. Moore.</p>
        <p>I think he has done an unusually splendid piece of work to bring this group together, and
            if it succeeds, none of us here today can really tell what it is going to mean to the
            future of our country and to the future of the world.</p>
        <p> Mr. Moore, I brought with me today, to give to you, to present to you, the proceedings
            of, I think, the first <org reg="World Population Conference, 1927">World Population
                Conference of 1927</org> in <place>Geneva, Switzerland</place>. It took me two years
            to organize it. I was rather naive in thinking that the scientists were gods, so I had
            300 scientists come to the conference. I thought they would really sort of make our
            world a little different. They didn’t.</p>
        <p>I found them quite different from the gods that I expected them to be. Nevertheless, it
            was a very interesting conference. It lasted a week. I collected $40,000 to pay for
            their expenses over there, and the rest of it. They gave me no thanks. They didn’t
            recognize who you were or what you were, just went on with their work, did practically
            nothing to help in this movement and to steer the population question as it should have
            been, in those years. They could have done a great deal in making this meeting even here
            today something more than it may be.</p>
        <p> Nevertheless, now, with Mr. Moore’s brain, vision to bring in businessmen, I think that
            is quite a different, new, practical idea, and it will be a wonderful thing to see how
            it goes. Mr. Moore, I congratulate you.</p>
        <p> I think that the movement throughout the world today, in nearly every country --
            especially those countries that our <person reg="Eisenhower, Dwight"
                >President</person> visited -- all need birth control or population control. Of
            course, he would have nothing to do with it, and nothing to say about it. We asked him
            about it, and he said, “<q who="EISDW">That belongs not to the Government but to the
                people</q>,” private, as it has been, under private auspices, from the beginning of
            time, since we have begun it, but we have had not money enough, have not had enough
            people to help us, and so we have not done as much as we could have done and wanted to
            do. And it certainly is the duty of the <org
                reg="United States Health and Welfare Department">Health and Welfare Department of
                this Government</org> to help other countries, especially if they request it, but
            that was the President’s declaration, that the Government would have nothing to do with
            it, and it had to be turned back where it was in the beginning.</p>
        <p> In one country that I think you can well study, and I am rather proud of that country --
            that is <place>Japan</place>. She has cut her birthrate in half. When I first went to
            Japan in <supplied resp="MSPP">1922</supplied>, all of the Japanese who were with me
            were all put in jail. Today they are all senators. That is hopeful. And Japan is an
            example. She cut her birthrate in half. She has a <name type="law"
                reg="Japanese National Eugenic Law">eugenic program</name> for the people, that nobody with
            transmittable diseases can continue having children. They are to be sterilized. She has
            a eugenic program. She has a wonderful program for the future. I don’t think there is
            any other country in the world that is so intelligent about the future of their country,
            and going to make it something. The young people have declared openly and consistently
            there will never be another war, not as long as they are alive, and I think that is very
            encouraging, and we could well -- I am sorry that some Japanese has not been invited
            here today. I think we could well have invited some.</p>
        <p><q who="UNK">(It was brought to Mrs. Sanger’s attention there was a Japanese
                present.)</q></p>
        <p> I am very glad you are here. It seems to me I hadn’t heard there was a <person
                reg="Kakitsubo, Masayoshi">Japanese</person> here, and I think he could tell us
            there is a great deal going on there that we could well study and congratulate them. Of
            course, they never asked us to give anything, never asked us for money, or anything.
            They have gone on their own way, done what they thought was right for their own
            country.</p>
        <p> As I said, I am not going to make a speech, so I am going to say I am happy to be there
            to see my old friends and see so many new ones. And, again, I want to congratulate Mr.
            Moore for the splendid meeting. </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
