<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2003/08/04 SR</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-04-09 CH clean regs</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-09 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1924-00-00">1924</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>Autobiographical Sketch</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp304089</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="book">Public Opinion on Women</title>, 1924, 150-153.</bibl>
			<bibl><title type="mf">Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Collected Documents Series</title>
				C16:233</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="biography"/>
		<index level1="Sachs, Sadie (story)"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>AUTOBIOGRAPHICAL SKETCH</head>
		<byline>Mrs. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></byline>
		<div>
			<head type="sub">I.</head>
			<p>I had for my <person reg="Higgins, Michael">father</person> not only a great man, but
				a great philosopher. Both of my parents are of Irish birth and both came from a long
				line of thinking fighters. My father in particular is an idealist. At the present
				time he is fighting for the ideal of international peace and international
				understanding. My <person reg="Higgins, Anne Purcell">mother</person> was one of
				those old fashioned gentlewomen who devote their lives to the happiness of their
				husbands and the welfare of their children. She bore eleven children of whom I was
				the fifth. I was born in <place reg="Corning, NY">Corning, New York</place> State,
				in 1883. Early in my childhood days, I was instructed by my father that one's life
				must be a great effort toward accomplishing an ideal. He would often say to his
				children that what they must first attain was a dream or a vision and then make
				their life work a struggle to make that dream come true. He also taught me in
				earliest childhood days that no one can achieve happiness alone, that my happiness
				depended upon my food, my clothing, my shelter, and therfore I was dependent for
				happiness upon those who provided these necessities for me. I was in duty bound to
				consider what I in turn could do to alleviate and assist those millions of men and
				women who were providing for my comforts and physical necessities and to bring
				happiness to their lives. This philosophy was my earliest teaching and some one who
				knew my family in those days said that we were "<q who="UNK">rocked in the cradle of
					liberty and nursed at the breast of the goddess of wisdom</q>."</p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<head type="sub">II.</head>
			<p>I was always considered a child too old for my age. I was always nursing the sick
				cats, dogs, horses or other domestic animals that came within my reach. I was also
				the advisor and little mother for the homeless children in the neighborhood and my
				days, especially my play time hours, seem to have been spent nursing and bandaged
				cut fingers of my playmates. Up to the time I was sent away to a boarding school, my
				life was spent in the little country town in which I was born. This is an industrial
				city where the finest glass in the world today is produced and cut. Very early I was
				made to realize that my playmates--both boys and girls--were sent into the factories
				as soon as they were old enough to secure working certificates and were unable to
				take advantage of educational opportunities. I learned that invariably the reason
				behind this grim fact was the pressure of providing necessities for the little
				brothers and sisters at home.</p>
			<p>My own father was a highly skilled artisan. He was a sculptor carving out his vision
				in marble and granite. Even though he was highly paid, my own family was made to
				endure many privations in order to obtain the necessary education which the ambition
				of parents demanded.</p>
			<p>My reading as a child was strangely unbalanced. I had for my day time studies the
				serious philosophy of <person reg="George, Henry">Henry George</person> who wrote
					"<title type="book">Progress and Poverty</title>," <person reg="Bellamy, Edward"
					>Edward Bellamy</person> who wrote "<title type="book">Looking Forward</title>,"
					<person reg="Nietzsche, Friedrich">Nietzsche</person>'s "<title>Ecce
					Homo</title>," and <person reg="Schopenhauer, Arthur">Schopenhauer</person>'s
				essays whose philosophy angered and tormented my curiosity. There were other writers
				along these lines. While my day-time study and reading dealt with serious thought,
				my night reading around the fire-place was always devoted to fairy tales. These were
				read from the standard works of <person reg="Grimm, Jacob"><person
						reg="Grimm, Wilhelm">Grim</person></person> or were original stories of
				Irish folk-lore, the product of my father's wonderful and vivid imagination. As I
				look back upon these contradictory influences I realize that my parents wished to
				keep their children simple and yet to encourage original thinking.</p>
			<p>My boarding school days had a very great influence upon my social life. Up to this
				time I had been entirely under the influence of my parents--especially my father,
				for my mother became an invalid after the birth of her last child. Now at the
				boarding school I was thrown together with five hundred boys and girls of my own age
				and was left to my own devices--to "sink or swim" along with these various
				characters and individuals. I took very naturally to gymnastics, dancing and basket
				ball, and during four delightful years studied many social activities. I was the
				first girl at this school to deliver an address on woman suffrage. It was announced
				that I was to deliver this address in the public forum and I had much difficulty in
				practicing my delivery because of the amusement and the jokes that were played upon
				my by the students. In fact, I was compelled to go to a cemetery two miles away from
				the school to practice the delivery of my address. I succeeded, however, in
				convincing my hearers of the inevitability of women's emancipation, and later on
				there were many arguments and debates which resulted in a suffrage organization in
				that community. At this time I was only fourteen years old and the next year I
				plunged heavily into political discussion. During these years I formed many charming
				friends whose friendships have been retained up to the present time. I attempted to
				make my career that of a physical and passed examinations into <org>Cornell
					University</org>. Immediately preceding my entrance, my mother died and I had to
				give up my career in order to mother my younger brothers and sisters. After
				satisfactory arrangements were made for our home life, I entered a three year course
				of medical study in the <org reg="Manhattan Eye and Ear Hospital">New York
					Hospital</org> to specialize in medicine and nursing. It was here that all of
				philosophy of life was put into practice and here that I came into intimate contact
				with the nakedness, not only of human bodies, but of human souls. It was here that I
				saw birth and death as grim realities, and during these four years of study and
				devotion I learned to know that there are two human instincts which guide humanity
				in its destiny. These instincts are Hunger and Love. While much attention has been
				given to the former, very little attention has been directed toward understanding
				the latter, and as the solution of the problem of hunger has been the aim of man, so
				will the understanding and direction of the love impulse come under woman's realm.
				As the faster woman evolves in her emancipation, the higher and more spiritual will
				be her understanding of the beauty of life and of love.</p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<head type="sub">III.</head>
			<p>When I finished my medical training, I married <person reg="Sanger, William">William
					Sanger</person>, an artist. Mr. Sanger is an artist of the new day. He belongs
				to that school of the impressionists generation has passed away. He has the
				temperament of the idealist and is willing to sacrifice material gain in order to
				live up to his own ideal. He is considered to be temperamental and eccentric but is
				acknowledged by all who have looked on his work to be a genius.</p>
			<p>My marriage to Mr. Sanger came as a logical sequence to my life's work, for he helped
				me to realize love in all its pristine beauty. Three children were born to us.
					<person reg="Sanger, Stuart">Stewart</person> is now eighteen, <person
					reg="Sanger, Grant">Grant</person> is thirteen, and the little <person
					reg="Sanger, Peggy">daughter</person> who passed away five years ago, would have
				been nine. When I fist began my married life, I had a dream of a large family. We
				built a large house--an Italian villa--over looking the Hudson River in which we
				made provision and plans for at least ten children. By the time my third child was
				born, I gave up this plan and also the house and decided that it would be better for
				my three living children to have a mother who had health and to raise them, if
				possible, to full maturity, than it would be to risk my life to further maternity.
				My children were spaced far enough apart to permit me to continue my studies in
				economics and science and to develop literary clubs and to keep abreast of current
				topics. My husband and I evolved a plan of working together for six months and to
				spend the other six months in the country with our children for leisure to devote
				ourselves to their development and recreation. In this way we were both permitted to
				develop our tastes, he continued with his artistic career, while I spent my leisure
				time in the study of sex hygiene.</p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<head type="sub">IV.</head>
			<p>It is impossible to hide one's knowledge, and I could in no time when I was called
				upon to lecture in social hygiene before working girl's club and various women's
				organizations. These lectures I delivered in the evening after my day's work, for I
				continued nursing for six months each year continually though many years.</p>
			<p>In 1912 I became convinced that the necessary element in woman's freedom was not the
				vote but control over her own body. For no matter what ideals placed before the
				mother of the day, such ideals were cast aside to make place for the more urgent
				need of her life–-"<q who="UNK">How can I prevent having more children than I can
					feed, clothe and care for.</q>" This was the urgent cry of mothers in the poor
				districts everywhere.</p>
			<p>In 1912 I was confronted by a serious case of a <person reg="Sachs, Sadie"
					>mother</person> who had been brought to death's door though the ill-advised
				attempt to interrupt a pregnancy. She was poisoned as the result, and with the
				greatest difficulty we brought her out of the valley of death. She already had a
				small family of three children and felt she could afford no more. She asked me and
				the doctor to advise her how to prevent conception, but we both turned away and left
				her question unanswered. A few months later I was called again to this woman's
				bedside, but this time it was too late to rescue her, for she died before either of
				us could aid her.</p>
			<p>I was greatly agitated by this woman's death and I saw from it the whole panorama of
				social evils arise before me. I resolved that night to devote my life to help women
				avoid such experience and to rescue them from such untimely death. Since 1914 I have
				been publicly advocating the idea of Birth Control. I expect to continue in such
				work until every mother in the entire world may have such knowledge if she desires
				it.</p>
		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
