<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/05/23 CE</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/05/24 CE Corrections</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/06/21 CE Corrections</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/11/30 CH Correct typo</prepDate><prepDate>2011-11-30 CH typo</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1926-10-00">Oct 1926</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>The Function of Sterilization</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp304387</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>The Birth Control Review</title>Oct. 1926, p. 299.</bibl>
            <bibl><title>MSM</title><title>C16:282</title></bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>No complete version of Margaret Sanger's address
            survives; the following is a shortened treatment. For an expanded
            version drawn from newspaper coverage, see Vol. 1 of <title>Selected
                Papers of Margaret Sanger</title>, "Excerpt from Racial
            Betterment," Aug. 5, 1926, pp. 445-449.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"
            level3="negative consequences of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="sterilization"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="socio-economic benefits of"/>
        <index level1="England" level2="population policies of"/>
        <index level1="family planning"/>
        <index level1="feeble-minded persons"
            level2="fertility and birth rate of"/>
        <index level1="physically disabled and diseased"
            level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="mentally disabled and diseased"/>
        <index level1="mentally disabled and diseased"
            level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="overpopulation" level2="emigration and"/>
        <index level1="politicians" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="population" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="population growth" level2="regulation of"/>
        <index level1="population growth" level2="standard of living and"/>
        <index level1="reproduction"/>
        <index level1="sterilization" level2="candidates for"/>
        <index level1="sterilization" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="population policies of"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="population of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>The Function of Sterilization</head>
        <head type="sub">Part of an address delivered by Margaret Sanger before
            the <org>Institute of Euthenics</org> at <org>Vassar College</org>
            August 5th</head>
        <p>The Question of race betterment is one of immediate concern, and I am
            glad to say that the <place>United States</place>
            <org reg="United States Government">Government</org> has already
            taken certain steps to control th equality of our population through
            the drastic immigration laws.</p>
        <p>There is a quota restriction by which only so many people from each
            country are allowed to enter our shores each month. It is the latest
            method adopted by our government to solve the population problem.
            Most people are convinced that this policy is right, and agree that
            we should slow down on the number as well as the kind of immigrants
            coming here.</p>
        <p>But while we close our gates to the co-called “undesirables” from
            other countries, we make no attempt to discourage or cut down the
            rapid multiplication of the unfit and undesirable at home.</p>
        <p>In fact through our archaic and inhuman laws against Birth Control
            information the breeding of defectives and insane becomes a
            necessity.</p>
        <p>These types are being multiplied with break-neck rapidity and
            increasing far out of proportion to the normal and intelligent
            classes. In 1923 over nine billions of dollars were spent on state
            and federal charities fo the care and maintenance and perpetuation
            of these undesirables. Year by year their numbers are mounting. Year
            by year their cost is increasing. Huge sums- yes, vast fortunes- are
            expended on these, while the normal parents and their children are
            compelled to shift for themselves and compete with each other.</p>
        <p>The American public is taxed, heavily taxed, to maintain an
            increasing race of morons, which threatens the very foundations of
            our civilization.</p>
        <p>Over one-quarter of the total income of the state of <place>New
                York</place> is spent on the maintenance of asylums, prisons,
            and other institutions for the care of the defective and the
            diseased. It must not be assumed that all the undesirable breeders
            are segregated in institutions. There is only a very small
            proportion of the feebleminded given over to institutions, the vast
            majority are living their lives among us, propagating their kind and
            providing abundant opportunity for the continuation of charities and
            various pauperizing institutions for generations to come.</p>
        <p>When we view the political situation and realize that a moron’s vote
            is as good as an intelligent, educated, thinking citizen, we may
            well pause and ask ourselves: “Is America really safe for
            democracy?”</p>
        <p>In <place>England</place> a few weeks ago the <org>House of
                Lords</org> passed a resolution sanctioning the giving of
            contraceptive instruction in all the maternity centers supported by
            the government.</p>
        <p>It now remains for the United States government to set a sensible
            example to the world by offering a bonus or a yearly pension to all
            obviously unfit parents who allow themselves to be sterilized by
            harmless and scientific means. In this way the moron and the
            diseased would have no posterity to inherit their unhappy condition.
            The number of the feebleminded would decrease and a heavy burden
            would be lifted from the shoulders of the fit.</p>
        <p>Such a bonus would be a wise and profitable investment for the
            nation. It would be the salvation of American civilization. It would
            enable thousands of parents to get a firm footing on the path of
            life and enable them to give some care to those children they have
            already borne.</p>
        <p>It would mean facing our debts today, here and now, instead of
            passing them on and piling them up for future generations to
            pay.</p>
        <p>Our statistics tell us that the birth rate of the college men and
            women is lower than it should be. This applies to all the
            professional classes, doctors, clergymen, lawyers and skilled
            workers. There are some who deplore this condition and would remedy
            it by abusive epithets hurled at this conscientious group of decent
            and responsible citizens, who would rather have only the umber of
            children they can decently rear, than to enter a cradle competition
            with the less responsible.</p>
        <p>There is only one reply to a request for a higher birth rate among
            the intelligent, and that is to ask the government to <emph
                rend="italics">first</emph> take off the burdens of the insane
            and feebleminded from your backs. Sterilization for these is your
            remedy.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
