<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article ">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2003-12-01 ML</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2009-0602 CH linked draft version.</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-24 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1925-09-00">Sept1925</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Editorials</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp304414</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title>, Sept. 1925, 243-44.</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Papers Microfilm</title> C16:263</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="GANMo">Gandhi, Mohandas K.</name>
            <name id="MUSBE">Mussolini, Benito</name>
            <name id="SBOC">South Dakota State Board of Charities</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
            <name id="HIN">Hindu</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>For a draft of the portion of this editorial on India, see "Mahatma Gandhi and Birth
            Control," 1925 (<title>MSM</title> C16:275).</p>
        <index level1="England" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Italy" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="war" level2="overpopulation and"/>
        <index level1="public health" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="Italy" level2="birth rate in"/>
        <index level1="Gandhi, Mohandas K."/> 
        <index level1="birth control" level2="morality of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Editorials</head>
        <p>The fall opens with news of important developments in <place>England</place>,
                <place>India</place> and the <place reg="United States">United States</place>. In
            England the systematic work of the Malthusian League and the Labor women is bringing
            pressure of numbers to bear on the <org reg="United Kingdom, Ministry of Health"
                >Ministry of health</org>, and the time is not far off when the Ministry will have
            to yield to a bona fide public demand represented by hundreds of thousands of
            petitioners. In India the opposition expressed by <person reg="Gandhi, Mohandas K."
                >Mahatma Gandhi</person> in the India press to any method for preventing
            overpopulation except self-control has both revealed the strong and intelligent support
            which Birth Control has already won in that country and has brought the subject to the
            attention of many thousands who had never heard of it before.</p>
        <p>In America the statement of a representative of the Italian government at the conference
            at <place reg="Williamstown, MA">Williamstown</place>, together with Professor <person
                reg="East, Edward Murray">East</person>'s reply, which we publish in this number of
            the <title type="journal">REVIEW</title>, has circulated throughout the press of that
            country and has taught American doubters that there is a very real relation between war
            and overpopulation. Count <person reg="Cippico, Antonio">Cippico</person>'s statement is
            the more menacing taken in conjunction with the press interview with <person
                reg="Mussolini, Benito">Mussolini</person> last January, when he said that the
            Italian birth rate was pressing, that the Italians were "<q who="MUSBE">too
                intelligent</q>" to limit the numbers of their children and that the only answer to
            the problem was "<q who="MUSBE">to make war or to seek outlets for overpopulation</q>."
            When that war breaks out of whose approach two spokesmen of the Fascisti have now given
            us ample warning, it will show the world that the refusal of a government to tolerate
            and encourage the practice of Birth Control is not only a crime against the individual
            but a crime against international peace.</p>
        <p>Mahatma Gandhi, the great leader of India, has recently given public utterance, in the
            columns of <title type="journal">Young India</title>, to his opinion concerning
            "artificial" methods of Brith Control. "<q who="GANMO">There can be no two opinions
                about the necessity for Birth Control</q>," writes Mahatmaji, "<q who="GANMO">but he
                only method handed down from ages past is self control or '<foreign lang="HIN"
                    >Brahmacharya</foreign>.' It is an infallible sovereign remedy doing good to
                those who practice it. And medical men will earn the gratitude of mankind, if
                instead of advising artificial means of Birth Control they will find out the means
                of self-control. The union is not meant for pleasure but for bringing forth progeny.
                And union is a crime when the desire for progeny is absent</q>." Self-control,
            austere unrelenting asceticism, is in brief, in the ethics of Mahatma Gandhi, "<q
                who="GANMO">the only noble and straight method of Birth Control</q>."</p>
        <p>Coming as it does from the great spiritual leader of India, this expression of opinion is
            a welcome one. It as stimulated the liveliest discussion in the Indian press, and has
            brought forth a number of emphatic and clearly expressed refutations of the ascetic
            philosophy of life embodied in Gandhi's brief expression, as well as some spirited
            defenses of contraception. The most vigorous opponent of Gandhi's views has been
            Professor <person reg="Karve, R. D.">R. D. Karve</person>, whose protest is quoted by
            Mr. <person reg="Roy, Basanta Koomar">Roy</person>, together with the able replies of
            other friends of Birth Control, on another page of the <title type="journal"
                >REVIEW</title>.</p>
        <p>There is little to add to these comments by Gandhi's compatriots. They are marked by
            brilliant, lucid reasoning. They indicate the vitality of the idea of Birth Control in
            the <place reg="Asia">Orient</place> and presage the advent of a new era of
            enlightenment in that prostrate domain. We are happy indeed that, despite his hesitation
            and extreme reluctance, Mahatma Gandhi was induced to express publicly his disapproval
            of artificial methods of contraception. But we might not impertinently ask if any method
            is more artificial, more contrary to the laws of human nature than a self-imposed
            "self-control" which instead of leading one through the threshold of life onward toward
            an understanding of its meaning and beauty, would prevent the exponent of abstinence
            from ever understanding its deeper rhythm, and condemn him to endless torment, in
            discord with the cosmic rhythm and in eternal conflict with the surge of his deepest
            desires.</p>
        <p>This thoughtless utterance-profoundly thoughtless, we are sorry to say-of India's great
            leader places him in the category of those traditional dogmatists and reactionary
            moralists for whom this world is irremediably a vale of tears and whose irresponsible
            "idealism" has indeed made it one. To Western minds, the influence of such leaders must
            be forever dysgenic. We are happy that our friends in India are so vigorously combating
            it.</p>
        <p>Life, we challenge these opponents, is neither an evil, a malady, nor a disease to be
            avoided. Life is the supreme experience, into which we must unreservedly and joyfully
            plunge. Sexual expression is one of the most profoundly spiritual of all the avenues of
            human experience, and Birth Control the supreme <emph rend="italics">moral</emph>
            instrument by which, without injury to others nor to the future destinies of mankind on
            this earth, each individual is enabled to progress on the road of self-development and
            self-realization. Human salvation is not to be attained by a steady diet of the bitter
            fruit of renunciation. We are all seeking for "<q who="GANMO">life more
            abundant</q>."... Despite his world-wide renown, Gandhi's recent utterance seems to lack
            spiritual profundity or vision. Yet, we must express our thanks, since he has stimulated
            his young compatriots and ourselves as well, to a new crystallization of our spiritual
            values.</p>
        <p>The Medical Officer fo the town of <place>Hartlepool, England</place>, does not,
            according to recent press reports, believe in teaching Birth Control Yet his recent
            report on conditions in that town of 5,000 families, which has circulated widely, is
            nothing less than a sermon of which Birth Control ought to be the text. His report shows
            that 2,5000 families- half the total population by family- have at some time in the last
            two or three years been on the poor rates on account of unemployment. At the same time
            the birth rate during the past year was 28.4 or 51 per cent. higher than that for
            England as a whole, and infant mortality was 132 per thousand. In one month indeed it
            soared as high as 250 per 1000. The officer, Dr. <person reg="McKendrick, William"
                >William McKendrick</person>, lays the high death rate directly to poverty and bad
            housing and mentions the prevalence of rickets and scurvy. Under conditions like these,
            which cry aloud not for moralizing, but for a practical remedy, to reject Birth Control
            and recommend self-control is like reciting an Abracadabra.</p>
        <p>The application of the <org reg="South Dakota State Board of Charities">State Board of
                Charities</org> for increased appropriation for the <org><place>South Dakota</place>
                School and Home for the feeble-minded</org> shows to what extent our present methods
            are meeting the problem of the breeding of the unfit.</p>
        <p>"<q who="SBOC">If the estimate of the superintendent is correct</q>," says the
            application "<q who="SBOC">and only fifteen percent of the feeble-minded in South Dakota
                are now having institutional care and the other eighty-five percent are at large in
                the state breeding up a still larger crop of subnormal persons for the future to
                deal with, the situation is desperate enough</q>."</p>
        <p>The impracticability of either raising money on the scale or of actually rounding up all
            defectives for institutional care is not recognized by the South Dakota board. It is
            however, recognized in a thoughtful editorial from the <place>Summit, New Jersey</place>
            <title type="journal">Herald and Record</title> reprinted in this issue, on the Birth
            Control and Sterilization Bills which failed to pass the Legislature last winter. This
            foresighted editorial writer estimates that any attempt to care for all state charges in
            institutions "<q who="UNK">would take almost half the revenue on which we depend to run
                the state in all its branches</q>."</p>
        <p>From <place reg="Paris, France">Paris</place><person reg="Humbert, Eug&edot;ne">Eugene
                Humbert</person> and his <person reg="Humbert, Jeanne">wife</person> send grateful
            messages to the friends in America who contributed toward the payment of their fine of
            30,000 francs, imposed by the postal authorities for giving out contraceptive
            information. The fine is not completely paid and the government simply waives its right
            to imprison for the balance as long as the Humberts are "on their good behavior". This
            means that the hands of two of the most active of French propagandists are tied for an
            indefinite period, until the depopulation scare in <place>France</place> has run its
            course. Until that time this family of pioneers are under surveillance and for real or
            imagined activities in behalf of Birth Control the <person>Damocles</person> sword of
            the unpaid balance may descend on their heads. Should this happen we hope that their
            fellow workers for Birth Control throughout the world will hold themselves ready to be
            called on again. M. Humbert's letter is published on another page of the <title
                type="journal">REVIEW</title>.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
