<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2003/07/2 RK</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2003-07-28 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/27 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/08/09 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/08/13 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007/08/28 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2001/03/11 CH Entered corrections suggested by Andy Carloff.</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-18 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1919-07-00">Jul 1919</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Vanderlip's Speech -- A Warning Note</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp304523</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title>, July 1919, 3-4</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> C16:123</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="VANFR">Vanderlip, Frank A.</name>
            <name id="LLODA">Lloyd George, David</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="efforts to reduce"/>
        <index level1="population" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="population" level2="war and"/>
        <index level1="population" level2="food supply and"/>
        <index level1="Germany" level2="population policies"/>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="population policies"/>
        <index level1="Russia" level2="population policies"/>
        <index level1="England" level2="population policies"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="population policies"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="expansion of"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="population of"/>
        <index level1="Vanderlip, Frank A."/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Vanderlip's Speech -- A Warning Note</head>
        <byline>
            <emph rend="italics">An Editorial by <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret
                    Sanger</person></emph>
        </byline>
        <p>The birth control movement in <place reg="United States">America</place> has heretofore
            centered its interest upon two points. The first of these is woman's freedom. The other
            is relief for the economically oppressed workers through limitation of offspring.</p>
        <p>This has been the movement's development in most countries, except
            <place>England</place>. There it has been very definitely based upon the principle that
            failure to control the birth rate consciously and sufficiently has a constant tendency
            to permit the population to increase beyond the food supply. This is the first of what
            may be called the two principal tenets of the English movement. The second is that
            over-population is the first and most fruitful source of ignorance, pauperism, disease
            and crime. Around these two principal points the advocates of Birth Control in England
            have waged their battle.</p>
        <p>English statesmen and economists, however, are keenly conscious that Britain is
            over-populated. It is a matter which is discussed constantly by press, politician and
            publicist. America is a newly developed country. The overcrowding of population has not
            yet made itself so greatly felt. For this reason, perhaps, the advocates of Birth
            Control have had less direct interest in this phase of the matter than have the
            advocates of the same doctrine in the tightly packed <place>United Kingdom</place>.</p>
        <p>It required the World War to awaken us to this phase of the general problem. Conditions
            revealed by this struggle and its aftermath make it impossible for American believers in
            Birth Control to leave out of consideration, hereafter, the relation between population
            and its means of subsistence.</p>
        <p>Of all those who have written and spoken upon problems arising out of the war, none has
            called our attention so plainly and emphatically to the food question as <person
                reg="Vanderlip, Frank A.">Frank A. Vanderlip</person>, until recently head of the
                <org>City National Bank of New York</org>, one of the most powerful financial
            institutions in the country. In an address delivered May 26, which stirred the press of
            the country into a hysterical discussion that has not yet run its course, Mr. Vanderlip
            directed attention to some of the most significant facts in the European situation. In
            all the babble of discussion that has followed, no newspaper has yet commented upon the
            fundamentals pointed out by the financier. None of the editorial writers was able to
            discover that the vital points on the address were those which dealt with the European
            food situation, as it arises out of over-population.</p>
        <p>Here are some of the facts which Mr. Vanderlip brought out:</p>
        <p rend="blockquote">"<q who="VANFR"><place>Europe</place> has increased its population
                since the Napoleonic wars from 175,000,000 to 440,000,000. Now just think of those
                figures- 175,000,000 to 440,000,000! Now Europe did not become any more productive.
                She probably does not raise a very great amount more food than she did a hundred
                years ago. How has she fed those people?...</q>"</p>
        <p rend="blockquote">"<q who="VANFR"><emph rend="italics">The <org
                        reg="United Kingdom Goverment">British government</org> will have to get
                    five or six million Englishmen out of England and nearer to the source of the
                    food supply.</emph> It is that fact that we must grasp; that these industries
                must be kept going in these highly industrialized European countries if the people
                are to live. Take England -- the most thickly populated country in the world -- 700
                to the square mile. They have built up that whole island into an industrial
                community that can live only by selling abroad a great part of the product of the
                factories, and with the proceeds of that export buying more raw material and the
                foods for the population......</q>"</p>
        <p rend="blockquote">"<q who="VANFR">English industry has made a red ink overdraft on the
                future by underpaying labor so that it did not receive enough to live efficiently
                and you know that in the mill towns of England there grew up a secondary race of
                underfed, uneducated, undeveloped people. Well, England has got to pay the overdraft
                now. She found that a third of her men of military age were unfit for military
                service. One of Mr. <person reg="Lloyd George, David">Lloyd George</person>'s most
                famous utterances was that '<emph rend="italics">
                    <q who="LLODA">You could not make an A-1 nation out of a C-3 population</q>
                </emph>.' They all see it and that differential (low wages), which England has had
                in international trade is gone. That is not all of it.</q></p>
        <p rend="blockquote">"<q who="VANFR">England must maintain her markets if she is to maintain
                her population. Remember, she is an industrial community just like an industrial
                village. She has this vast population that her fields will not sustain. She must
                bring in raw material, pass it through her factories, sell it abroad, and have
                margin enough to get more raw material for the food she needs, and she is facing the
                demoralized markets of Europe</q>."</p>
        <p>Mr. Vanderlip speaks, of course, as a financier. But whether one is a financier, a
            reformer or a revolutionist, the facts that he points out are the facts that must be
            faced. No matter what our theories or our faiths, these facts stand, they grow
            increasingly ominous, and the necessity that they be dealt with grows more
            insistent.</p>
        <p>What do these facts mean to America -- to the people of America? They mean, first of all,
            that upon America will be made increasing demands for food for Europe. We have already
            been supplying England, <place>France</place> and a great part of <place>Italy</place>.
            Plans are already under way to "feed <place>Germany</place>" if a peace satisfactory to
            those in power, politically and commercially, is made. </p>
        <p>We know, too, that while supplying food to England and France, we went through a period
            of scarcity and unprecedented high prices. We know that this period was also marked by
            high mortality among the civilian population. Witness for instance, the influenza
            epidemic.</p>
        <p>It is also to be remembered that America, like England, as long as this nation depends
            upon present means of production and distribution, will be forced to seek more and more
            markets and sources of raw materials. What else is the meaning of the expansion of the
            United States within the last generation? Why have we taken over <place>Hawaii</place>,
            the <place>Philippines</place>, <place reg="Puerto Rico">Porto Rico</place>, and why
            have we virtually held a protectorate over <place>Cuba</place>? Why is American capital
            so interested in <place>Mexico</place>? Why is it that we go to <place>South
                America</place> for much of our meat supply -- and only within the past few years?
            Why do American packers control much of the cattle and most of the packing industry in
                <place>South America</place>? What is the meaning of our heavy importations of rice?
            Is our situation different from that of England, except in degree?</p>
        <p>A look at our populations statistics may shed some light upon the question. In 1880 our
            population was a little over 50,000,000. Ten years later it had increased to
            approximately 63,000,000. In 1900 it was approximately 76,000,000. In 1910 it lacked but
            a few thousand of 93,000,000. Now it is estimated at 106,000,000. It has more than
            doubled itself in thirty-eight years. The rate of increase for the twenty years between
            1890 and 1910 was approximately 21 per cent. At this rate, we will have 200,000,000
            people in 1950! While only a generation ago, we began reaching out for imports to add to
            the stock of foods produced at home.</p>
        <p>It is well understood that one of the causes of the World War was the rapid increase in
            the German and Russian populations. The German population grew from 41,000,000 in 1871
            to 67,000,000 in 1918. It increased 60 per cent in forty-seven years and made a world
            cataclysm inevitable because it did not produce sufficient food to sustain its
            tremendously increasing numbers.</p>
        <p>It took <place>Russia</place>, with the highest birth rate in Europe, forty years -- from
            1871 to 1911--to increase her population 77 per cent. In but 38 years, we have more than
            doubled our own population. It took Japan sixty-five years to double her population, and
            her government has been making a studied effort to increase the number of Japanese.</p>
        <p>In view of these facts. it is high time for people living in America to give careful
            attention to the population problem. It is especially important that those of us who
            advocate Birth Control should at once begin to make an intensive and exhaustive study of
            the subject. If England, with the most extensive colonial system in the world at her
            command, cannot take care of her few tightly packed millions, what will be the state of
            affairs when the United States, youngest, most powerful and most rapidly growing of the
            nations, with no more colonies to take except by force, shall have 200,000,000 or
            300,000,000 people?</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
