<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2001-11-08 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2002-08-27 KH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2003/07/01 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/07 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007-05-30 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-05 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1913-10-05">5 Oct 1913</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Review of the <title type="book">The Eugenic Mother and
                Baby</title></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp304930</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">New York Call</title>, Oct. 5, 1913, p. 5</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> C16:66</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="HAGW">Hague, W. Grant</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
        <index level1="eugenics"/>
        <index level1="motherhood" levle2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="sex education"/>
        <index level1="venereal disease"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="enslavement of"/>
       </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>
            <title>THE EUGENIC MOTHER AND BABY</title>
        </head>
        <byline>Reviewed by <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">MARGARET H. SANGER</person>.</byline>
        <p><title type="book">THE EUGENIC MOTHER AND BABY</title> By Dr. <person reg="Hague, W. Grant">W. Grant
                Hague</person>. Published by the <org>Hague Publishing Company, Inc.</org> Price
            $5.00.</p>
        <p>In "<title type="book">The Eugenic Mother and Baby</title>," Dr. W. Grant Hague has endeavored in a
            most comprehensive style to give to a young wife a complete insight, not only into the
            laws regarding her health, but into laws which he claims are essential to the right kind
            of home building.</p>
        <p>The book is written in a simple manner and its purpose is at once recognized: that of
            spreading the "<q who="HAGWG">eugenic idea</q>" among women--especially wives, young
            wives.</p>
        <p>He says, in part, that eugenics is the "<q who="HAGWG">art of being well born,</q>" and
            involves the consideration of every subject upon which the health of the people depends.
            These subjects are motherhood, marriage, heredity, environment, disease, hygiene,
            sanitation, vice, education and culture, and some phases of all these subjects are
            touched upon in the book. </p>
        <p>Dr. Hague realizes, as all physicians do, that the great mass of young girls enter the
            marriage relation without any real knowledge of its meaning or of its responsibilities,
            that they attempt to direct the upbuilding of a home without any training for such a
            task; and also that they take upon themselves the cares and duties of motherhood without
            the knowledge of the first principles of the care of the child. But Dr. Hague writes his
            book with this knowledge also; that the great majority of the mothers of the world are
            poor, that they are uneducated and that they are inexperienced, and with these important
            facts in mind, he enables all classes of readers to follow him into the realms of the
            eugenic ideas most clearly. </p>
        <p>He first tells the young wife of the conditions throughout the world which have brought
            eugenics about, and its relation to marriage, parenthood, motherhood and the husband. He
            tells her in a most simple and concise way the meaning of the eugenic principle, and
            then leads her gently to herself and shows her just how eugenics concerns her and all
            mothers of today. He tells her how to prepare for the coming baby, what articles to have
            at hand, how to calculate the date of confinement, and gives a calendar which enables
            one to estimate the probable date at a glance; he advises the young woman to the choice
            of a nurse and physician, as well as to her conduct through the entire period of
            pregnancy. </p>
        <p>The chapter on the Hygiene of Pregnancy is unusually complete, for he touches upon the
            most trivial disturbances (trivial to the physician, but most important to the young
            woman with her first child), explaining their causes and unimportance, but giving to her
            other ailments such tender consideration as is seldom met with in books of this
            character. </p>
        <p>He explains to her the different stages of her "labor," through
            which she must pass, the meaning of every stage up to the birth of the child, not
            forgetting what the mother should eat for the first breakfast, lunch and dinner after
            labor. He goes with her through the convalescent period, and explains why and how long
            she should remain in bed after a confinement, and why friends and relatives should not
            be allowed in the sick room; he discusses the care of a nursing mother, her diet,
            breasts, nipples, etc., and he gives thorough treatment to the development of the
            baby.</p>
        <p>The splendid understanding of the young mother's psychology is beautifully stated by Dr.
            Hague when he says:</p>
        <p>"<q who="HAGGW">As she rests from her weary labor during the first long days after
                getting out of bed, the loneliness of it all crushes her. She is weak, nervous and
                discouraged, and her white, <supplied resp="MSPP">wan</supplied> face, with its
                tired, appealing eyes, bespeaks her anemic and hopeless condition. She is only a
                child herself, yet fate has crowned her with the holy diadem of motherhood.</q>"</p>
        <p>How those words recall to all mothers that terrible first day when the nurse left her
            with the weight of the world crashing down upon her!</p>
        <p>If a woman had written "<title type="book">The Eugenic Mother and Baby</title>," she could not have
            touched the tender and hidden feelings of the young mother more truly and
            sympathetically than does Dr. Hague. Especially is this true of her psychic discomforts:
            seldom can one find such consolation as the young mother will find in its pages.</p>
        <p>The chapter on the Hygiene and Development of the Baby will be especially appreciated by
            mothers of children in the second year. For here are the essential facts, plainly given
            of what to feed the child at this difficult age, how often, and how much food is to be
            given. After a glance at the diet which an infant of this age is allowed, no mother
            would ever again be guilty of feeding her child the convulsive diet of fried potatoes
            and meat. </p>
        <p>He does not stop here, however, but goes straight to the vital spot in sex hygiene for
            the boy and girl, for he says, with 10,000,000 suffering with venereal diseases in
                the <place>United States</place>, it is not sufficient to tell the youth of their
            dangers, but why it is to his best interest to live a clean life and thereby avoid them.
            The symptoms of both gonorrhea and syphilis are given and the consequences of them to
            the boy and girl. The evils of masturbation and the treatment for same are
            sympathetically covered, as is the physical development of the girl and her preparation
            for motherhood. </p>
        <p>Indeed, this is but a small part of the information he gives us, compared to the last
            half of the book beginning with what mothers should know. Here he unstintingly opens his
            storehouse of knowledge and allows us a full helping, a gift seldom approved of by the
            medical profession. If the chapter on the Diseases of Children was well understood, the
            trained nurse would soon have a substantial rival in the mother, who, instead of
            fainting at the approach of a prominent symptom, would understand its meaning and be
            prepared for it.</p>
        <p>Here a mother is made acquainted with the symptoms of the common diseases of the nose,
            mouth, and chest, such as cold in the head, croup, tonsillitis, bronchitis, pneumonia,
            nose-bleeds, thrush and adenoids, and the care and treatment so necessary to the quick
            recovery of the little one. Then follow the symptoms and treatment of every ailment
            under the sun a child is subject to, such as colic, summer diarrhea, acute intestinal
            indigestion, appendicitis, jaundice, worms, rupture, earache, boils, eczema, anemia,
            bed-wetting, thumb-sucking and biting the fingernails--to say nothing of the contagious
            diseases, such as measles, whooping cough, diphtheria, etc., not forgetting the care of
            the mother in caring for the patient, so as to prevent the spread of the disease.</p>
        <p>It would seem there was no accident, or emergency, or disease common to either women or
            children about which Dr. Hague has not given his best effort to inform us, and as a
            nurse, I should delight in every mother, both young and old, possessing a copy and
            keeping it close beside her (on the parlor table if necessary, instead of the
                <title>Bible</title>). But, as a woman, I must protest against Parts V and VI, and I
            should like to remove these two parts from the book and add them to the rubbish heap, or
            tenderly place them upon the shelves of a museum, where all fossilized relics lie. </p>
        <p>Part V is: Advice to Young Wives. </p>
        <p>Part VI: The Home.</p>
        <p>In both parts the writer idealizes the slave woman, fresh from the cave, who lays her
            freedom, personality and individuality at her lord-and-master's feet in return for a
            home. The husband, says he, "<q who="HAGWG">will be a child in your hands if you only go
                about it right," and going about it right means that the woman must, of necessity,
                have</q>"<q who="HAGWG">tact</q>"; that she must help him attain success; keep him
            in good health by seeing that he has the proper food and does not overeat; that he is
            free from worry, has enough rest and sleep, and has sufficient exercise; she must not
            find fault or allow the first quarrel, "<q who="HAGWG">no matter how acute the sense of
                injustice may be--silence is the only way out!</q>" And again, "<q who="HAGWG">Take
                our advice, don't experiment with a man--deep down every man is a brute, there is a
                certain elemental devil in every male animal; don't rouse it. You are only a woman,
                don't invite a quarrel, you will get the worst of it. Keep on the peaceful side of
                the street. Stroke the hair of the animal the right direction, act as if you were
                afraid of him, don't obtrude, let him alone to think it over.</q>" Nor is that all:
                "<q who="HAGWG">Change the expression on your face, smile, even if it pains you, the
                moment your husband enters the house,</q>" says he, "<q>for her world is her husband
                and her home.</q>" A little further on he advises her to wash "<q who="HAGWG"
                >her</q>" dishes while the husband reads the evening paper.</p>
        <p>Keep cool, sisters of 1913, sit a little closer and let's talk a while. Evidently the
            doctor wants to sugar-coat our slavery by calling his own sex names. A doctor is, in
            many ways, a strange creature. This doctor has seen the unrest and dissatisfaction of
            the woman of today in the homes of the thousands. He thinks it is a disease crowding
            into every home in the country; he sees all the symptoms, but he's groping about in the
            past centuries for a cure, and hopes to find it by pushing the women of this century
            back to the ideals and customs of another age. But you and I know that just as we women
            object to being slaves ourselves, so do we refuse to make slaves of the men. We love. We
            despise the courtesan type, who wants the man "<q who="HAGWG">to eat out of her
            hand</q>" and wins his love and caresses through subtle tricky means. It is self-evident
            from these chapters that the doctor has not his fingers on the pulse of the women's
            movement throughout the world, or he would see that this dissatisfaction is a historical
            development. For we stand erect at last, and we shall look into the eyes of our husbands
            only as our lover, comrade, equal. And we shall proceed with out, development in
            politics, science, art, literature, in whatever field our desires lead us, husband and
            home notwithstanding.</p>
        <p>Aside from these two parts, the book is indeed a gem, and we hope it will find its way
            into many homes, where its excellent medical teachings are badly needed.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
