<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "file:/S:/TRANSCRIPTIONS/XML%20Drafts/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article ">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2007/09/05 EK</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007-09-11 EK - Corrections</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007-10-01 EK Corrections</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1924-02-00 ">Feb. 1924</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Birth Control and China and Japan</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp305275</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>The Thinker</title>, Feb 1924, 32-35</bibl>
            <bibl><title>MSM</title> C16:214</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id=" JT">Japan Times</name>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
        <p>This article was fifth in a six-part series. For the preceding articles see "<xref
                from="306641.xml">Highlights in the History of Birth Control</xref>," Oct. 1923;
                "<xref from="306638.xml">A Better Race Through Birth Control</xref>," Nov. 1923;
                "<xref from="306006.xml">Woman and Birth Control</xref>," Dec. 1924; the fourth and
            sixth articles have not been found</p>
        <index level1="poverty"/>
        <index level1="population" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="history of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Japan"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="opposition to"/>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="gender roles and"/>
        <index level1="physicians"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="instructions"/>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="women in"/>
        <index level1="labor movement," level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues"/>
        <index level1="China" level2="birth control in"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Birth Control and China and Japan</head>
        <byline>by Margaret Sanger</byline>
        <p><supplied resp="MSPP">It</supplied>is not only in the <place>United
                States</place><supplied resp="MSPP">that</supplied> there is need for Birth Control.
            On the contrary, there are countries which need it far more than we do, countries where
            overcrowding and poverty sweep millions of babies out of existence, and where life is a
            bare struggle for existence. Such countries are <place>Japan</place>, and especially
                <place>China</place>. In 1921 students from these countries in the <place>United
                States</place> came into touch with the movement here for Birth Control. Their
            attention was aroused and their interest awakened. Here was something that was
            desperately needed in their own countries. They determined to start a campaign for Birth
            Control among their own countrymen and country-women.</p>
        <p>Due to the arousing of this interest, invitations reached me, towards the close of 1921,
            to go to Japan and deliver lectures on Birth Control. The invitation came from a group
            of progressive thinkers, known as the <org>Kaizo group</org>, and in February, 1922, I
            left <place reg="New York, NY">New York</place> for <place reg="San Francisco, CA">San
                Francisco</place>, however, I found that there were difficulties in the way.
            Applying to the <person>Japanese Consul General</person> there for a vise to my passport
            I was surprised to learn that the <org>Japanese Government</org> had issued orders that
            my passport should not be vised, and that I could not lecture on Birth Control in Japan.</p>
        <p>It is not easy to surprise anyone who has worked for long in the Birth Control movement.
            We get accustomed to unexpected obstacles and difficulties. In this case, however, my
            surprise was real; because I was led to believe by Japanese in the United States that
            the interest in the subject of Birth Control was general among the younger members of
            the Government. Then, too, the Kaizo group, with whom I was under agreement to deliver
            five lectures on the subject, publishes a magazine which is highly respected in Japan,
            and as <person reg="Russell, Bertand">Bertrand Russell</person> had visited Japan under
            the same auspices, I had every reason to believe that the Kaizo group knew the laws of
            their country and were acquainted with the possibilities and limitations under those
            laws.</p>
        <p>In neither of these assumptions was I mistaken. There is a younger <org
                reg=" Kakushin Kurabu (Reform Club) ">group</org> in the Government, and a very
            large group, whose ideas and ideals are broader and higher than those represented by the
            minority, the military party. Many of these more progressive men came to the receptions
            and meetings where I was the guest of honor and expressed their disapproval of the
            government's action; their belief in the principle of Birth Control, and their desire to
            help forward the movement in Japan. While these sympathizers can be numbered int eh
            hundreds, in special departments they are powerless against the more conservative
            statesmen. </p>
        <p>I was desirous to get at the root of the objection to my presence in Japan; but it was
            not until I reached <place reg="Yokohama, Japan">Yokohama</place> Harbor that I knew
            whether I should be permitted to land or not. While the <ship>Taiyo Maru</ship> was at
            sea, a vigorous correspondence had gone between the Home Office and the Foreign Office
            of the Japanese Government. The Vice Minister of the Foreign Office, <person
                reg="Hanihara, Masanao">Masanao Hanihara,</person> who had attended the <org
                reg="Washington Naval Conference, 1922">Disarmament Conference</org> in <place
                reg="Washington, D.C.">Washington</place>, was a fellow traveler on the steamer. He
            interested himself greatly in my mission, and urged by wireless that all courtesy be
            shown me. The final outcome of the negotiations was described by the <title>Japan
            Times</title> of March 11, 1922. <q who="JT">“Mrs. Sanger,”</q> it stated, <q who="JT"
                >“was allowed to land in this country last night, after a series of negotiations
                that made the diplomacy at the Washington Conference look like child's play. She
                will remain here for some time and hopes to have an opportunity of discussing with
                doctors, at least, her theories on Birth Control. But she has promised the police
                that she will 'be good’ and make no attempt to deliver any public addresses on the
                subject</q></p>
        <p>The following day I called upon the <person reg="Yokahama Prefector of Police">Chief of
                Police</person>. It was amusing to find that everyone from the hall porter to the
            interpreter knew that I was coming. We were ushered into a pleasant room and tea was
            served, although it was only ten o’clock in the morning. One of the attendants spoke to
            me about my book “<title>Woman and the New Race,</title>” which he said he had read with
            great interest and much pleasure. He then presented me with a Japanese translation, much
            to my surprise, for until I saw it there at the <org reg="Yokahama Police">Police
            Office</org>, I had not known that it had been translated or published in Japan.</p>
        <p>The interview lasted about half an hour, and ended by my receiving permission to speak in
            private, or under private auspices on Birth Control. I was told that it was not possible
            to discuss the subject in public meetings, although I might speak publicly on any other
            subject. Before I left the room we were photographed and interviewed by reporters from a
            number of Japanese papers. I never saw anything like the passion of the Japanese press
            for photographs. Everywhere I went I was interviewed and photographed, and at the
            meetings where I spoke there were flashlights--sometimes as many as twenty being taken
            before the meeting started.</p>
        <p>From that day on, there was an address made every day, and some days there were two
            meetings. We found that it was a far better plan to speak to small groups of one or two
            hundred people, where we could discuss the subject freely and frankly, than it would
            have been to have attempted to address large public meetings. Among the groups which
            expressed the greatest interest was the <org>Peers’ Club</org>, organized by <person
                reg="Karamura, Sumiyoshi,">Count Cowamura</person>. At no time in my life have I
            given a more intimate address. I can say also that it was received with the finest
            spirit of respect and understanding and desire to know more. it was one of the most
            encouraging events of my stay in Japan. The fact that men of high station came eagerly
            to hear a woman speak is considered by the women here a victorious event in a land where
            the position of women is subordinate and where the men do not seem to take the woman's
            movement seriously. </p>
        <p>My lectures were given before the most intelligent people in Japan. The <org
                reg="Zaibatsu (Industrial and Commercial ombines)">Industrial Organization</org>
            consisted of men at the head of practically every industry in Japan. It gave a dinner in
            my honor, where we sat, Japanese fashion, on the floor, creating an atmosphere conducive
            to conversation. The questions asked by these men indicated much thought on the problem
            of population. </p>
        <p>Perhaps the most enthusiastic meeting that was held was that given in the Imperial Hotel
            at <place reg="Tokyo, Japan">Tokyo</place> on March 20, by a prominent <org>commercial
                organization</org>. Again it was a dinner but not
            Japanese--“<soCalled>foreign</soCalled>” as they term it here. Men from the <org
                reg="Japan Home Office">Home Office</org>, <org reg="Japan Foreign Office">Foreign
                Office</org> and various other <org reg="Japanese Government">Government</org>
            Departments attended. While many of them understood English, it was necessary to have my
            speech interpreted. This was done exceedingly well by Baron <person
                reg="Ishimoto, Keikichi">Ishimoto</person>, my host while in Japan, and I felt that
            this was the most important and successful meeting held while I was there. </p>
        <p>The doctors of Tokyo asked me to give an address on practical methods. The interpreter, a
            young doctor recently returned from United States, was not very good, and I felt at a
            great disadvantage. At Kyoto the <org>medical association</org> turned out four hundred
            strong at a few hours notice, and filled the <org>Congregational Church</org> to its
            fullest capacity. The <person reg="add name ">minister</person> of the church
            interpreted and did it remarkable well, making this meeting a full success. </p>
        <p>All the organizations which invited me to speak were represented by prominent and
            distinguished people. They were all, except the <org reg="Shinfujin Kyokai"> New Woman's Organization</org>,
            composed of the so-called well-to-do. This organization is the most advanced and
            intellectual group of women in Japan. Many of its members are working in various trades
            and industries.</p>
        <p>From Yokohama to <place reg="Kobe, Japan">Kobe,</place> and again across the inland sea
            to <place reg="Fuzan, Japan">Fuzan</place>, the interest was tremendous and the
            reception accorded me was beyond my hopes or dreams. The opposition of the government
            threw the sympathy of the people with me, and I believe I accomplished more, established
            more centers and aroused more discussion in one month than I could under ordinary
            circumstances have done in a year. Japan now has a <org>Birth Control League.</org> It
            has for its officers four most intelligent men representing four branches of
            civil life--Medicine, Science, Labor and Commerce. It is the general opinion that the
            agitation is most timely. While women were slowly advancing towards their emancipation
            and Labor was taking its first flights, neither had included Birth Control in its
            programme. Now they see their problems in a new light, and they see that by the adoption
            of Birth Control they can cut short their struggles and hasten their victories.</p>
        <p>From Japan I went to the <place>Korea</place>, where I found the people wonderfully alert
            and much interested in the idea of Birth Control. I was not able to stay long there, for
            I was due in <place>China</place>, and the time was short. We in the Western world have
            often asked ourselves how the idea of Birth Control would be accepted in the Orient. Our
            opponents have told us that Japan and China would never practise Birth Control, and that
            if we persisted in our work here the white race would be wiped out. I found, however, on
            the contrary, that the idea of Birth Control is readily accepted both in China and
            Japan, and that there were men and women in both countries ready to go to work to get
            the idea put into practice.</p>
        <p>In <place reg="Shanghai, China">Shanghai</place>, I met a number of men connected with
            the press--editors and influential writers in the Chinese world. They entertained me at
            tea, and made plans for the translation and publication of my pamphlet on
                "<title>“Family Limitation</title>," and for the establishment of a magazine devoted
            to the subject of population and Birth Control. In <place reg="Beijing, China"
            >Pekin</place> the <person reg="Cai, Yuanpei">Chancellor</person> of the <org
                reg="Peking University">National University</org> took a special interest in my
            mission, and before I left China a Birth Control League had been formed there and was
            ready for active work. </p>
        <p>We cannot go into China with our sympathies and our moral codes, saving her babies from
            infanticide, without increasing her problems. We find that after we have rescued 200
            infants from the river one year, 2000 additional “<soCalled>sing-song</soCalled>” girls are in the ranks of
            the prostitutes the next year. In China, we witness the last act in the national tragedy
            of over-population. China, the mysterious fountainhead of art, philosophy, and the
            deepest wisdom of the world, is brought down by the super-abundant breeding of its worst
            elements. Here there are masses of human beings who live below the level of animals.
            They eat, sleep and breed in the crowded streets and sunless alleys. Thousands have not
            even a foothold on the land. They are compelled to live in makeshift boats on the
            crowded banks of the rivers. The flame of Chinese civilization is flickering. It is
            threatened with extinction. There is a rising tide of famine, of wretchedness, of
            disease--a flood which, because of the incessant fertility of those millions, spreads
            like a plague. To contribute to famine funds and to the support of missions in China is
            like trying to sweep back the sea with a broom. But as long as the American public
            prefers sentimentality to science this waste of money, thrown into the bottomless pit of
            charities, with continue. China does not need our missions. The Chinese need our
            sanitation, our hygiene, our Birth Control. (To Be Continued) </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
