<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2003/10/29 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/01 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/11/28 CH correct typos</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011-11-30 CH typos</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-01 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1925-08-15">15 Aug 1925</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Is Race Suicide Probable?</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp305433</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Colliers</title>, Aug. 15, 1925, p. 25</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> C16:260</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="BIB">Bible</name>
            <name id="BURLU">Burbank, Luther</name>
            <name id="FRE">French</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>This article is prefaced by an editorial note mentioning that Dr. <person
                reg="Dublin, Louis I.">Louis I. Dublin</person> argued the negative side of the
            issue in the April 25, 1925 issue of <title type="journal">Colliers</title>.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="socio-economic benefits of"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="decline in"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="Burbank, Luther"/>
        <index level1="eugenics"/>
        <index level1="race suicide"/>
        <index level1="&quot;unfit&quot; to reproduce" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="&quot;unfit&quot; to reproduce" level2="social burdens, as"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="population of"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="socio-economic conditions in"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head rend="italics">Is Race Suicide Probable?</head>
        <byline>BY <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">MARGARET SANGER</person></byline>
        <p>The people of the <place reg="United States">United States</place> have been warned
            against the menace of birth control. If they exercise intelligent self-discipline, it is
            said, Americans may bring this country to destruction through depopulation. The fear
            that the present rate of increase in the population of the United States may be
            decreased and that our population may indeed be brought to a standstill through the
            practice of birth control is hardly substantiated by the last estimate of the <org
                reg="United States Census Bureau">Bureau of the Census</org>. Within the last five
            years there has been an increase in our native population of approximately 6,000,000, or
            1,200,000 a year.</p>
        <p>We are a nation of business men and women. We believe in efficiency, accuracy, and sound
            economic policy. If this is so, it strikes me that it is high time that not only
            American science but American business as well should begin to analyze the cost to the
            community of the haphazard, traditional, happy-go-lucky methods in producing the
            Americans of to-morrow--the <foreign lang="FRE">laissez-faire</foreign> policy approved
            by those who forget that the Biblical injunction "<q who="BIB">be fruitful and
                multiply</q>" was given to <person>Noah</person> immediately after the Flood, when
            according to the Biblical narrative, the entire population of the globe was eight.</p>
        <p>It has been conservatively estimated that no less than one quarter of the gross incomes
            of our states is expended upon the upkeep of asylums for the feeble-minded and insane,
            the mentally defective, the criminal, the congenitally defective, the delinquent and the
            dependent. We are spending billions, literally billions, keeping alive thousands who
            never, in all human compassion, should have been brought into this world. We are
            spending more in maintaining morons than in developing the inherent talents of gifted
            children. We are coddling the incurably defective and neglecting potential geniuses.</p>
        <p>We have not chosen this Sisyphean task; it has been forced on us because we have left the
            production of American children to <emph rend="italics">chance</emph>, instead of
            bringing this most important of all human functions within the sphere of <emph
                rend="italics">choice</emph>.</p>
        <p>Until the leaders of American business decide to cooperate in this analysis of our
            biological and racial problems we shall be at a loss to answer such critics as
                <person reg="Burbank, Luther">Luther Burbank</person>, to whom American civilization is deeply indebted.
            In a recent interview he is quoted as asserting:</p>
        <p>"<q who="BURLU">America . . . is like a garden in which the gardener pays no attention to
                the weeds. Our criminals are our weeds, and weeds breed fast and are intensely
                hardy. They must be eliminated. Stop permitting criminals and weaklings to
                reproduce. All over the country to-day we have enormous insane asylums and similar
                institutions where we nourish the unfit and criminal instead of exterminating them.
                Nature eliminates the weeds, but we turn them into parasites and allow them to
                reproduce.</q>"</p>
        <p>Could any business maintain itself with the burden of such an
                "overhead"? Could any breeder of live stock conduct his
            enterprise on such a basis? I do not think so.</p>
        <p>It is one of the bad habits of us Americans to estimate everything by magnitude, in terms
            of millions and billions. But in the matter of increasing population we must hesitate
            before throwing bouquets at ourselves. I am not a calamity howler, and I think my vision
            of the future of America is as cheerful as anyone's. But let me conclude with the
            emphatic statement of my conviction that mere increase in population has nothing to do
            with progress, nor can a decreasing birth rate by any stretch of the imagination be
            interpreted as an omen of national calamity.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
