<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/06/21 CE</prepDate><prepDate>2011-11-30 CH typos</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1923-12-00">Dec 1923</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Woman and Birth Control</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp306006</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>The Thinker</title> (Dec. 1923), pp. 69-72.</bibl>
            <bibl><title>MSM</title> C16:206</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>This is the third of a six-article series. For other articles in the
            series, see <xref from="306641.xml"><title>Highlights in the History of Birth
                    Control</title> Oct. 1923</xref>; <xref from="306638.xml"><title>A Better Race
                    Through Birth Control</title> Nov.1923</xref>; <xref from="305275.xml"
                    ><title>"Birth Control in China and Japan"</title> Feb. 1924</xref> and<xref
                from="300368.xml"><title>The Birth Control Movement in 1923</title> April
                1924</xref></p>
        <index level1="abortion" level2="health risks of"/>
        <index level1="American Birth Control League"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="class-based"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits and risks"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="in marriages"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="opposition to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="socio-economic benefits of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="suppression of"/>
        <index level1="children" level2="unwanted"/>
        <index level1="Europe" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="family size" level2="class-based"/>
        <index level1="France" level2="birth rate in"/>
        <index level1="Germany" level2="birth rate in"/>
        <index level1="labor movement," level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="mentally disabled and diseased" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="motherhood" level2="consripted"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="infant"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="maternal"/>
        <index level1="physicians" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="poverty" level2="family size and"/>
        <index level1="pregnancy" level2="fears of"/>
        <index level1="quackery"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="biography"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="nursing and"/>
        <index level1="Spain" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="upper classes" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="enslavement of"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="freedom and rights of"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="health of"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
        <index level1="working classes" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="working classes" level2="children"/>
        <index level1="working classes" level2="fertility of"/>
        <index level1="working classes" level2="living conditions of"/>
        <index level1="working classes" level2="women and girls"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Woman and Birth Control</head>
        <byline>By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>, 104 5th Ave., <place
                reg="New York City, NY">New York City</place></byline>
        <p>The Birth Control movement has its roots in the history of subjection. In the past women
            have been brood animals to the state, to industry, to the church. Whenever they have
            raised their heads and tried to loosen the chains that bound them, they have met with
            opposition--opposition often cloaked in apparent solicitude for their moral and
            spiritual well-being, and efforts have been made to keep them in servitude in the sphere
            that men marked out for them. Today, however, women are rising, even though slowly, in
            fundamental revolt. Their efforts at superficial reforms are steps in that direction.
            but more essential is their demand for the right to voluntary motherhood. They are
            determined to decide for themselves whether they shall become mothers, under what
            conditions, and when. They are beginning to ask the purposes for which their children
            will be used; whether as slaves or freemen. This is a fundamental question. This is a
            fundamental revolt. It is for women the key to the temple of liberty.</p>
        <p>For centuries, woman has gone forth with man to till the fields, to feed and clothe the
            nations. She has sacrificed her life to populate the earth. She has overdone her labors.
            She now steps forward and declares that she will cease producing in ignorance. To do
            this she must have the power to control birth. To secure this power--to obtain the
            knowledge that will give it to her--this is the first immediate step she must take
            towards the goal of her freedom.</p>
        <p>Those who are opposed to giving this power to women are simply those who do not know.
            Anyone who, like myself, has worked among the people and who has found on the one hand
            an increasing proletarian class with its ever deepening misery, poverty and ignorance,
            and on the other hand a stationary or decreasing section of the population with
            increasing wealth and higher standards of living, greater freedom, greater possibilities
            of joy and happiness, cannot doubt that Birth Control is the livest issue of the day and
            one on which depends the future welfare of the race.</p>
        <p>Before I turn to the arguments against Birth Control, I should like to tell something of
            the conditions I met with in my work as a trained nurse, and a little of the experiences
            that convinced me of the necessity of Birth Control, and led me to jeopardize my liberty
            in order to place this information in the hands of the women who most need it.</p>
        <p>My first clear impression of life was that large families and poverty went hand in hand.
            I was born and brought up in a glass factory town in the western part of <place>New York
                State</place>. I was one of eleven children--so I had some personal experience of
            the struggles and hardships that a large family endures. When I was seventeen years old
            my <person reg="Higgins, Anne Purcell">mother</person> died form overwork and the strain
            of too-frequent child-bearing. I was left to care for the younger children and share the
            burdens of all. When I was old enough I entered a hospital to take up the profession of
            nursing.</p>
        <p>In the hospital I found that seventy-five per cent of the diseases of men and women are
            the result of ignorance of their sex functions. I found that every department of life
            was open to investigation and discussion except that shaded valley of sex. The explorer,
            scientist, inventor may go forth in their various fields of investigation and return to
            lay their discoveries at the feet of mankind. But woe to him who dares explore that
            forbidden realm of sex. No matter how pure the motive, no matter what miseries he seeks
            to remove, slanders, persecution, jail await him who dares bear the light of knowledge
            into that cave of darkness.</p>
        <p>So great was the ignorance of the women and girls whom I met concerning their own bodies,
            that I decided to specialize in women’s diseases, and took up gynecological and
            obstetrical nursing.</p>
        <p>A few years of this work brought me to a shocking discovery--that knowledge of methods of
            controlling birth was accessible to women of wealth, while the working women were
            deliberately kept in ignorance!</p>
        <p>I found that the women of the working class were as anxious to obtain this knowledge as
            their sisters of wealth, but that they were told that there were laws on the statute
            books against imparting it to them. And the medical profession was most religious in
            obeying these laws when the patient was a poor woman.</p>
        <p>I found that women of the working class had emphatic views on the crime of bringing
            children into the world to die of hunger. They would rather risk their lives through
            abortion than give birth to little ones they could not feed or care for.</p>
        <p>I found that the laws against imparting this knowledge force thousands of poor women into
            the hands of the filthiest midwives and quack abortionists, with the consequence that,
            while abortion is practised among all classes of women, the deaths from abortion are
            almost entirely among the poor.</p>
        <p>No other country in the world has so large a number of abortions, nor so large a number
            of women dying therefrom as the <place reg="United States">United States of
                America</place>. Our law-makers close their virtuous eyes, while they refuse access
            to safe scientific contraceptive knowledge, and drive these unfortunate women to this
            abominable crime. A most conservative estimate is that there are 500,000 abortions
            performed in this country every year.</p>
        <p>For millions of babies whose mothers have not resorted to abortion there is no welcome
            when they arrive. How often have I stood at the bedside of a woman in childbirth and
            seen the tears flow in gladness and heard the sigh of “<q who="UNK">Thank God</q>!” when
            told that her baby was born dead! What can men know of the fear and dread of unwanted
            pregnancy? What can men know of the agony of carrying beneath one’s heart a little life
            that tells the mother every instant that there is no room and no chance for it on earth?
            Even if it should be born alive, the probabilities are that it would perish within a
            year, after costing its mother untold anguish and suffering.</p>
        <p>Do you know that 200,000 babies under one year of age die in the United States every
            year, chiefly from poverty, neglect and bad antenatal conditions; while four hundred
            thousand parents are kept in ignorance of how to prevent two hundred thousand more
            babies from coming into the world next year, again to die because they ought never to
            have been born?</p>
        <p>I found from records concerning women of the under-world that eighty-five per cent of
            them come from parents averaging nine living children. And that fifty per cent of them
            are mentally defective.</p>
        <p>We know that the birth rate of mentally defective parents is about four times as great as
            that of normal parents. Is not this a cause for alarm? And yet there are people who
            raise the objection to Birth Control that it may cause women to be immoral! Solicitude
            for woman’s morals has ever been the cloak that Authority has worn in its age-long
            conspiracy to keep woman in bondage.</p>
        <p>When I was in <place>Spain</place> some years ago I found that the Spanish women were far
            behind their European sisters in readiness or even in desire for modern freedom. Upon
            investigation into the causes of this, I found that there were over five thousand
            villages and towns in Spain with no facilities for travel, transportation or
            intercommunication except donkeys, over bridle paths. I was told that all attempts to
            build roads and railroads in Spain had met with the strongest opposition from the clergy
            and the government on the ground that roads and railroads would make it easier for the
            women to leave the country for the cities, and that in the cities they would meet their
            downfall.</p>
        <p>Do we, who have roads and railroads, think that our women are less moral than the Spanish
            women? Certainly not. But, after all, we in this country are only just emerging from the
            fight for higher education for women which met with the same kind of opposition only a
            few years ago.</p>
        <p>We now know that education has not done the dreadful things to women and women’s morals
            that were predicted as certain to result from it. and so we shall find that knowledge to
            control birth, which has been in the hands of the more fortunate women of wealth for the
            past twenty-five years, will not tend to lower woman’s standard of morals, but rather to
            make a woman a more responsible human being.</p>
        <p>Statistics show us that the birth rate of any give quarter is in inverse ratio to its
            wealth, and direct ratio to over-crowdedness and poverty. The figures show that in large
            cities the birth rate of the rich districts is a third of that of the poor districts. In
                <place reg="Paris, France">Paris</place> for every 1,000 women between the ages of
            15 and 50, the poor districts yield 116 births and the rich districts 34 births. In
                <place reg="Berlin, Germany">Berlin</place>, conditions before the war were
            approximately the same. For every 1,000 women between the ages of 15 and 50, the poor
            districts yielded 157 births, while the rich yielded 47. The same proportion is found in
            practically all the large cities of the Western world.</p>
        <p>It may be inferred form these figures that women of wealth use means to prevent
            conception which it is not permitted to teach to the poor. But the menace of our
            civilization, which constitutes the population problem of today, is not so much the
            stationary birth rate among the upper classes as the tremendous increase among the poor,
            the diseased and the defective members of the community.</p>
        <p>Can it be openly denied that woman has a right to consider her health? Is woman to remain
            a producing machine? Is she to have no time to think, to study, to care for herself and
            her own development? Man cannot travel to his goal alone. And until woman has knowledge
            to control birth she cannot get the time to think and to develop. Until she has the time
            to think, neither the labor question nor any other social question will interest her.
            she cannot learn to use aright the vote which woman suffrage has put into her hands. She
            will merely use it to strengthen the forces of reaction and ignorance; while she herself
            will remain the drudge she is, and her husband the slave he is, putting their whole
            strength and energy into continuing to supply the market with cheap labor.</p>
        <p>Let me ask you: “Has the State any more right to ravish a woman against her will by
            keeping her in ignorance than a man has through brute force? Has the State a right to
            decide when a woman shall bear a child and to refuse to her the right to decline to
            bear?</p>
        <p>Picture a woman with five or six little ones living on the average working man’s wage.
            The mother is broken in health and spirit, the wornout shadow of the woman she once was.
            Where is the man or woman who would reproach us for trying to put into this woman’s
            hands knowledge that will save her from giving birth to any more babies doomed to
            certain poverty and misery and perhaps to disease and death?</p>
        <p>It is to make such knowledge legally and medically accessible to the oppressed mothers of
            our land that in November 1921 we formed the <org>American Birth Control League</org>--a
            League that is growing and extending itself across this continent and even reaching into
                <place>Mexico</place>, <place>Canada</place>, <place>Japan</place>,
                <place>China</place> and <place>India</place>.</p>
        <trailer>(To Be Continued.)</trailer>
    </docBody>
</doc>
