<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/06/22 CE</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011-11-14 CH corrections entered</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-26 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1923-10-00">Oct 1923</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>High Lights in the History of Birth Control</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp306641</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">The Thinker</title> Oct. 1923, pp. 59-61.</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microflm</title> C16:0201</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>This is the first of a six part series. Only five articles have been
            located. For the second article, see <xref from="306638.xml"><title type="article">A
                    Better Race Through Birth Control</title></xref>, Nov. 1923; for the third
            article see <xref from="306006.xml"><title type="article">Woman and Birth
                    Control</title></xref>, Dec. 1923; and for following articles see <xref
                from="305275.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control in China and
                Japan</title></xref>, Feb. 1924 and <xref from="300368.xml"><title type="article"
                    >The Birth Control Movement in 1923</title></xref>, Apr. 1924.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="arrests and imprisionment"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="class-based"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Federal"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="State"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="American"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="history of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="international"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="rights associated with"/>
        <index level1="England" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="eugenics" level2="positive"/>
        <index level1="Europe" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="family size" level2="class-based"/>
        <index level1="France" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Holland" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="New York City" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="population" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="Woman Rebel"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="enslavement of"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="freedom and rights of"/>
        <index level1="working classes" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="working classes" level2="fertility of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>HIGH LIGHTS IN THE HISTORY OF BIRTH CONTROL</head>
        <byline>By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>, 104 5th Ave., <place
                reg="New York, NY">New York City</place></byline>
        <p><emph rend="italics">(Complete in Six Articles)</emph></p>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">ARTICLE I.</head>
            <p>No great problem affecting the welfare of nations and races has been so
                misinterpreted and misunderstood, even by men who consider themselves well informed,
                as that of population and Birth Control. Advocates of Birth Control do not ask
                merely for assent and approval. They demand investigation and understanding as the
                initial steps toward support of and adherence to their doctrine.</p>
            <p>Much of the opposition to Birth Control has had its source among clergymen and other
                professional moralists. This ecclesiastic opposition is the more surprising in view
                of the fact that the “<q who="UNK">only true begetter</q>” of the whole Birth
                Control movement was <person reg="Malthus, Thomas Robert">Robert Malthus</person>,
                himself a clergyman of the <org>Church of England</org>. He advocated prudential
                checks which called for the most austere morality. Our clergical opponents also
                ignore the fact that many of the most noted champions of Birth Control today are
                clergymen. The most distinguished example is the Dean of <org>St. Paul’s
                    Cathedral</org>, <place reg="London, England">London</place>, the Very Reverend
                    <person reg="Inge, William Ralph">William Ralph Inge</person>.</p>
            <p>The backbone of the Birth Control movement, from the time that Malthus first
                published his epoch-making “<title>Essay on Population</title>,” has been
                essentially Anglo-Saxon. <person reg="Mill, John Stuart">John Stuart Mill</person>,
                    <person reg="Place, Francis">Francis Place</person>, <person
                    reg="Arnold, Matthew">Matthew Arnold</person>, <person
                    reg="Huxley, Thomas Henry">Thomas Huxley</person> and our own great men--<person
                    reg="Jefferson, Thomas">Thomas Jefferson</person>, <person reg="Madison, James"
                    >James Madison</person>, <person reg="Emerson, Ralph Waldo">Ralph Waldo
                    Emerson</person> and <person reg="Ingersoll, Robert Green">Robert G.
                    Ingersoll</person>, all spoke openly in favor of the control of population.
                Today such thinkers and writers as <person reg="Wells, H. G.">H. G. Wells</person>,
                    <person reg="Cox, Harold">Harold Cox</person> (Editor of the <title>Edinburgh
                    Review</title>) <person reg="Bennett, Arnold">Arnold Bennett</person>, Dean
                Inge, <person reg="Archer, William">William Archer</person>, <person
                    reg="Ellis, Havelock">Havelock Ellis</person>, <person reg="Murray, George"
                    >Gilbert Murray</person>, <person reg="Russell, Bertrand">Bertrand
                    Russell</person>, <person reg="Keynes, John Maynard">John Maynard
                    Keynes</person> (Editor of the <title type="journal">London Nation</title>),
                    <person reg="Macbride, Ernest William">E. W. McBride</person>, and <person
                    reg="Dawson, Bertrand">Lord Dawson</person> (the <person
                    reg="George V (England)">King</person>’s Physician) and innumerable others in
                    <place>Great Britain</place> speak openly and valiantly for Birth Control.</p>
            <p>The present movement in this country must not be confused with the Neo-Malthusian
                movement in Great Britain and on the Continent of <place>Europe</place>. In England
                the Neo-Malthusian League was the direct outcome of the celebrated trial of <person
                    reg="Bradlaugh, Charles">Charles Bradlaugh</person> and Mrs. <person
                    reg="Besant, Annie">Annie Besant</person>, who had openly and in the face of the
                authorities distributed among the English poor thousands upon thousands of copies of
                pamphlet by a Boston physician, <person reg="Knowlton, Charles">Dr.
                    Knowlton</person>, entitled “<title>The Fruits of Philosophy</title>”--a
                pamphlet originally published in 1833 in this country. The <org
                    reg="Malthusian League">Neo-Malthusian League</org>, sponsored by those valiant
                pioneers, <person reg="Drysdale, Charles Robert">Charles</person> and <person
                    reg="Drysdale, George Robert">George Drysdale</person> and Dr. <person
                    reg="Vickery, Alice">Alice Vickery</person>, soon spread its influence to all
                parts of the <place>Continent</place>. In <place reg="Netherlands"
                    >Holland</place> its doctrines were openly put into practice, and fifty-three
                Birth Control clinics, approved by the <org>Dutch Government</org>, have been
                conducted there with great success for forty years.</p>
            <p>The Birth Control movement, which has now absorbed the earlier Neo-Malthusian
                movement, originated in New York, just a decade ago. While the Neo-Malthusians based
                their propaganda on Malthus’s theory of Population and earnestly discussed the
                scientific aspects of the question, the slogan “Birth Control” was put forward in my
                little paper of advanced feminism, <title type="journal">Woman Rebel</title>, and was used as the
                battle cry of fundamental rights in the fight for the emancipation of the working
                woman. The response was so immediate and overwhelming that a league was formed--the
                first <org reg="American Birth Control League">Birth Control League</org> in the
                world.</p>
            <p>With the flame-like ardor of pioneers we did not at first realize the full scope of
                our campaign. At that time I knew nothing of Malthus, nothing of the courageous and
                desperate battle waged by the Drysdales in England, <person reg="Rutgers, Johannes"
                    >Rutgers</person> in Holland, <person reg="Giroud, Gabriel">G. Hardy</person>
                and <person reg="Robin, Paul">Paul Robin</person> in <place>France</place>, for this
                century-old doctrine. I was merely thinking of the poor mothers of the <place
                    reg="New York, NY">East side</place> who had so poignantly begged me for
                relief, in order that the children they already had brought into the world might
                have a chance to grow into strong and stalwart Americans. It was almost impossible
                to believe that the dissemination of knowledge easily available to intelligent and
                thoughtful parents of the well-to-do classes was actually a criminal act, proscribed
                not only by State laws but by Federal laws as well.</p>
            <p>My paper was suppressed. I was arrested and indicted in the Federal court. But, owing
                to the vigorous protests of the public and to an appeal sent by a number of
                distinguished English writers and thinkers, the case against me was finally
                dismissed.</p>
            <p>Meanwhile Birth Control, as the slogan of the movement, not only spread through the
                American press from coast to coast, but immediately gained currency in Great
                Britain. Succinctly and with telling brevity these two words sum up our whole
                philosophy. Birth Control does not mean contraception indiscriminately practised. It
                means the release and cultivation of the better elements in our society, and the
                gradual suppression, elimination and eventual extinction, of defective stocks--those
                human weeds which threaten the blooming of the finest flowers of American
                civilization.</p>
            <p>Birth Control aims to introduce into the creation of the next generation of American
                citizens the sound and scientific principles observed by the gardener and the
                agriculturist. We must cultivate the human garden by proper spacing, by improving
                the quality of our precious crop of children by methods of intensive cultivation and
                not by the production of mere numbers. As long as we wilfully, as a nation, waste
                the most precious resources we have--our child life-- let us hold our tongues about
                the dangers of Birth Control. The advocates of Birth Control place a higher value on
                the life of a child than do its opponents. We want every child born in this country
                to bring with it the heritage of health and fine vitality. This is the true wealth
                of our <place>United States</place>.</p>
            <p>The first Birth Control clinic in this country was established in Brownsville, <place
                    reg="Brooklyn, NY">Brooklyn</place>, in 1916. It had but a brief existence. It
                was raided by the police and its founders sentenced to jail as petty miscreants but
                it is not without significance that , since then, there has been an immense
                recrudescence of interest in the persistent problem of population, and that a number
                of new efforts have been made--notably by <person
                    reg="Carr-Saunders, Alexander Morris">A. M. Carr-Sanders</person>, to
                reinterpret the thesis for which so massive a foundation was laid by that obscure
                clergyman, Thomas Malthus. The whole current of opinion in regard to the question
                has advanced, not merely in this country and in England, but all over the world. The
                results of the intelligence tests, the menace of indiscriminate immigration, the
                fertility of the unfit, and the increasing burden upon the healthful and vigorous
                members of American society of the delinquent and dependent classes, together with
                the growing danger of the abnormal fecundity of the feeble-minded, all emphasize the
                necessity of clear-sightedness and courage in facing the problem, and throw new
                light on the possibilities of Birth Control as a practical and powerful weapon
                against national and racial decadence.</p>
            <p>We are not, I must repeat, trying to force this doctrine upon the American public.
                Every day thousands of poor mothers are begging us for help, fully conscious that
                their sacred duty to the children they have already brought into the world demands
                that they shall not assume further parental responsibilities which they cannot
                fulfil. It is in answer to those unfortunate and conscripted mothers that we have
                banded ourselves together in the American Birth Control League.</p>
            <trailer>(To be continued)</trailer>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
