<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/06/21 CE</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/11/14 CH entered corrections on headnote</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1923-11-00">Nov 1923</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>A Better Race Through Birth Control</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp306638</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>The Thinker</title> (Nov. 1923), pp. 60-62.</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> C16:205</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>This is the second of a six part series. Only five
            articles have been located. For the first, see <xref
                from="306641.xml"><title>Highlights in the History of Birth
                    Control</title></xref>, Oct. 1923; for the third article see
                <xref from="306006.xml"><title>Woman and Birth
                Control</title></xref>, Dec. 1923; for articles that followed
            see <xref from="305275.xml">Birth Control in China and Japan</xref>,
            Feb. 1924 and <xref from="300368.xml"><title>The Birth Control
                    Movement in 1923</title></xref>, Apr. 1924.</p>
        <index level1="abortion"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="economic benefits and risks of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits and risks"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="in marriages"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="and marriage"/>
        <index level1="child labor"/>
        <index level1="child welfare"/>
        <index level1="children" level2="rights of"/>
        <index level1="children" level2="unwanted"/>
        <index level1="conjugal intimacy" level2="the right of"/>
        <index level1="eugenics" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="family planning"/>
        <index level1="family size"/>
        <index level1="family size" level2="class-based"/>
        <index level1="marriage age" level2="men"/>
        <index level1="marriage age" level2="women"/>
        <index level1="men" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="men" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
        <index level1="motherhood" level2="consripted"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="infant"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="maternal"/>
        <index level1="poverty" level2="family size and"/>
        <index level1="pregnancy" level2="fears of"/>
        <index level1="prostitution" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="&quot;unfit&quot; to reproduce" level2="descriptions of"/>
        <index level1="&quot;unfit&quot; to reproduce" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="venereal disease" level2="syphilis"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="health of"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
        <index level1="working classes" level2="fertility of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>A Better Race Through Birth Control</head>
        <byline>By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>, 104
            5th Ave., <place reg="New York City, NY">New York
            City</place></byline>
        <p>The most important problem, barring none, that confronts humanity
            today is that of race culture. It has often been said, and never
            with more truth than at the present time, that man breeds his cattle
            with more intelligence and care than he breeds his own kind. The
            draft figures alone should be sufficient to galvanize the human race
            to action, for the intelligence tests made on our soldiers during
            the recent war indicated that approximately 25 per cent of our
            population never attains a mentality superior to that of a
            twelve-year-old child. When we consider that the mentally deficient
            reproduce more rapidly than those of normal intelligence, we may
            well look into the future with dismay. Unless a halt is called, and
            that speedily, our race is doomed to inevitable deterioration.</p>
        <p>The object of civilization is to obtain the highest and most splendid
            culture of which humanity is capable. But such attainment is
            unthinkable if we continue to breed from the present race stock that
            yields us our largest amount of progeny. Some method must be devised
            to eliminate the degenerate and the defective; for these act
            constantly to impede progress and ever increasingly drag down the
            human race. This is especially the case in the nations which have
            reached the highest degree of civilization, for it is just in these
            nations that the degenerate and defective are enabled to produce the
            largest number of progeny.</p>
        <p>It is impossible to conceive of eugenic legislation that would be
            acceptable and that would cover the present need. Our knowledge is
            insufficient to insure intelligent race culture through statute law.
            Fortunately, however, Birth Control offers an avenue of escape. It
            is reasonable to assume that women of subnormal mentality, however
            lacking they may be in vision and altruism, would prefer to avoid
            the pain and responsibilities of procreation, if the satisfaction of
            sex could be divorced from reproduction. Given Birth Control, the
            unfit will voluntarily eliminate their kind. On the other hand Birth
            Control will permit large numbers of intelligent women, such as our
            teachers and nurses, to enter upon marriage, in the knowledge that
            they can limit their families to their economic conditions. While
            these women would probably not have large families of children,
            nevertheless those that they give to the world will be of rare value
            and will assist materially in the improvement of the race stock.</p>
        <p>In addition to its salutary effect on the future germ plasm of the
            human race, Birth Control will be an effective force in the solution
            of the problem of the social evil, and in the control of venereal
            diseases. Syphilis is the most destructive racial poison known to
            man; gonorrhea is unmatched in its operation as a sterilizing
            agency. Any factor which tends to diminish the demand for illicit
            sex relationship tends equally to repress venereal disease.
            Unmarried men and men who are married but are debarred from their
            wives constitute the principal patronage of prostitutes. Upon the
            money which these men are willing and able to pay for illicit sexual
            gratification depends the whole business of prostitution. At the
            present time the choice for most young unmarried men lies between
            celibacy and vice. They cannot marry, because they cannot afford to
            support a wife and children, and therefore their minds turn to
            illicit relationships. With adequate knowledge of Birth Control,
            these young men would very generally choose marriage instead of
            prostitution, and the solution of the problem of the social evil
            might be achieved.</p>
        <p>As a background to monogamous marriage, Birth Control is essential,
            for it is clearly an economic impossibility for the average young
            man and woman to support as many children as human fertility would
            presuppose. Almost any rational person is willing to admit that the
            earning power of an average husband and the physical health of an
            average wife are unequal to the demands of an excessively large
            family, and that earning power and health should be considered in
            determining the number of children in a family. Self control,
            instead of Birth Control, is however advocated by some as the method
            to be favored. The utter fallacy of this position is made clear by a
            consideration of what marriage means. Marriage in the absence of
            love, even for the purpose of reproduction, is recognized as an
            unethical relationship by almost all high-minded individuals. For
            humanity, love is the only right basis for sex relations; in other
            words these relations are the language of love. To demand that a man
            and woman in wedlock restrain their affectional expression toward
            one another is to require that they repudiate the very fundaments of
            marriage. Marriage itself is reduced to prostitution when the child
            is regarded as a necessary justification for sex relations.</p>
        <p>It is pitiful and it is very evil that man should so far have
            degraded his concept of love as to require any ulterior
            justification for its expression between man and wife.</p>
        <p>The home is the backbone of the state, and upon it depends the whole
            social structure, and the future of the race. But the home is built
            upon monogamous marriage and this institution is feasible only with
            Birth Control. Let humanity but rid itself of false and impure
            mental associations with the idea of sex, and the truth will appear
            that love is the greatest of all forces for good in the world and
            that its full expression through marriage is ethically sound. Such
            expression, however, is only possible through Birth Control which
            will, when we have learned its lessons, be the best bulwark of
            marriage and the most efficient guardian of happiness within the
            family that mankind has yet known.</p>
        <p>Birth Control means liberation for women and for men. It means
            freedom and happiness. It means gifts and blessing for the family
            and the nation.</p>
        <p>It will give the mother the right and power to have children only
            when she feels that her health and strength will allow her to give
            them the care and attention that they need and ought to have.</p>
        <p>It will give the young wife the possibility of recovering her
            strength before she embarks on the great adventure of motherhood, if
            she has worked hard and long hours before her marriage. No woman
            should become pregnant when exhausted by fatiguing or unwholesome
            labor.</p>
        <p>It will give the mother time to know her children and to devote
            herself to the needs of each one as she brings them up. It will give
            the woman a chance to develop mother-love, instead of being an
            irritable drudge, overwhelmed by the demands of too many children, a
            broken-spirited, harassed slave of excessive motherhood.</p>
        <p>Birth Control will give the husband courage. He will no longer be
            intolerably harassed and driven to desperation by the claims of a
            family too large for his wages or salary to support. It will
            preserve and develop his domestic life, his love for his wife and
            children, and his pride in the home.</p>
        <p>Birth Control will prevent abortion. It will do away with the
            practice of taking drugs and poisonous nostrums to end undesired
            pregnancies. It will put an end to the tens of thousands of illegal
            operations to which women resort in despair. Mothers will not submit
            to the murder of unborn children when they can control
            conception.</p>
        <p>It will wipe out the disgrace of our high rate of maternal mortality.
            Many mothers die because they are not in a fit state of health to
            stand the strain of pregnancy and childbirth.</p>
        <p>It will reduce enormously our infant mortality rate. Thirty-five
            thousand babies die every day on the day that they are born, and
            nearly seventy thousand more within the first month of their lives.
            The passing out of most of these babies is due to the physical
            condition of their mothers. Had the mothers known how to control
            conception a very large proportion of them would never come into
            existence. During their short lives, they have drained the mother of
            her remaining strength, aggravated the physical conditions which
            made their survival impossible, exhausted the narrow financial
            resources of the family into which they have come, and probably
            caused privation and distress to other children, probably little
            more than babies themselves.</p>
        <p>Birth Control will also check the mortality rate of the 100,000
            babies who survive the first month but die within the first year of
            their lives. The death of many of these babies is caused by poverty,
            over-crowding and lack of proper care from mothers too burdened with
            many children to attend fully to any one of them.</p>
        <p>Birth Control will prevent child labor. Child laborers come largely
            from overcrowded homes with more children than can be fed and
            clothed out of the father’s wages.</p>
        <p>Birth Control will prevent prostitution. Young people will be able to
            marry early, knowing that they can wait to have children until they
            are in a position to stand the expense. Married men will not be
            driven to prostitution because they are denied their wives, whose
            love for their husbands has been destroyed by the haunting fear of
            pregnancy. When a woman is set free from this fear, she will not
            hesitate to give full expression to her love for her husband, an
            expression which is necessary if love is to be kept alive and in
            bloom. Thus husband and wife will be held together, and many a
            marriage which under present conditions would be a failure, will be
            made permanently happy and successful.</p>
        <p>Birth Control will thus make of the home a place of peace, harmony
            and love. Then man will return to it from his work with contentment
            and rejoicing. The woman will find in it her happiness and
            development; the children, well nourished and carefully educated,
            will grow up in it to be the greatest assets of the nation.</p>
        <p>Constant exhortations from writers and preachers to the men and women
            of the better educated classes are being made to urge them to
            increase their small and carefully controlled families. This is a
            very definite testimony to the general conviction that in these
            families are to be found the finest children, the best Americans of
            the future. Give the women of the poorer classes a chance also to
            limit and control their families, and it will be found that in very
            many cases the material is equally good. The difference is that,
            like plants crowded too close together on poor soil, there is no
            chance to develop and the whole families are left impoverished in
            mind and body. Give room for each <supplied resp="MSPP"
                >to</supplied> grow and all may become fine and healthy American
            citizens.</p>
        <trailer>(To Be Continued)</trailer>
    </docBody>
</doc>
