<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Review">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2003/10/13 NS</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-04-10 CH clean regs</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-20 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1925-02-00"> Feb 1925</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>Book Review: Impressions and Comments</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp306920</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title>, Feb 1925, 48-49 </bibl>
			<bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> C16:239</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="ELLHA">Ellis, Havelock</name>
			<name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<index level1="birth control" level2="as a term"/>
		<index level1="Book Review"/>
		<index level1="Ellis, Havelock"/>
		<index level1="overpopulation"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Book Reviews</head>
		<head type="sub" rend="italics"><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">MARGARET SANGER</person> on
				<title type="book">IMPRESSIONS AND COMMENTS</title></head>
		<div type="section">
			<p><title type="book">IMPRESSIONS AND COMMENTS: Third (and Final) Series,
					1920-1923</title>. By <person reg="Ellis, Havelock">Havelock Ellis</person>.
					<place reg="Boston, MA">Boston</place> and <place reg="New York, NY">New
					York</place>: <org>Houghton Mifflin Company</org>, 1924. ($3.00.)</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<p>I have an irresistible temptation to quote from this latest book of Havelock Ellis.
				But to quote all that I would like to call to your attention would be to republish
				the whole book. It is all quotable, all arresting, all stimulating. One closes it
				regretting only one thing that is printed in the book. The thing that never should
				been printed are two words on the title page. I mean those two words "<q who="ELLHA"
					>And Final</q>!" Let us hope, let us pray, that Havelock Ellis may be persuaded
				to change his mind on this point--that there may be more impressions and comments.
				How we need them in this muddled world--one clear serene voice expressing eternal
				values and verities, one voice above the shouting and the tumult of little men and
				little women!</p>
			<p>But that temptation to quote persists. And so, since you readers of these pages must
				be asking what he says about the problem close to our hearts, about Birth Control
				and over-population, let me call your attention to these comments:</p>
			<p>". . . <q who="ELLHA">There are people among us, and not a few, who view with
					complacency the vast increase of the world's population everywhere taking place,
					people who would even urge the human procreative impulse to still wilder
					excesses. Until every square yard of the earth is intensively cultivated by Man,
					until the virulent air is soaked with the noxious fumes of human machinery,
					until the sea is poisonous with human effluvia, until all earth's shore are
					piled high with the sordid refuse of human maleficence, it seems to these people
					that the world will never feel happy</q>." This, Havelock Ellis asserts, is an
				immediate problem, confronting every so-called "civilized" country, here and now.
				There is he claims, but one solution, one way of escape. "<q who="ELLHA">If, even
					yet, Man should gain conscious and deliberate control of his own fatal power of
					reproduction, if he could learn to bring his own kind back again into better
					adjusted perspective with Nature, by decreasing his reproductive exuberance to
					increase the possibilities of free and exalted living, he would be making what
					seems to many foolish people the Great Renunciation of life which would yet be
					in reality the Great Triumph of Life</q>." His ideal, in brief, is of a finer
				human race that shall become the "<q who="ELLHA">reasonable artists</q>" of its own
				size and shape. Today, he concludes this note, a choice is still offered--"<q
					who="ELLHA">brief yet endless.</q>"</p>
			<p>There is another brief yet superlatively eloquent note in which he answers a remark
				casually made to the effect that "<q who="UNK">Mr. Havelock Ellis invests Birth
					Control with the guardianship of Civilization</q>." Here is the reply: "<q
					who="ELLHA">The <org reg="United Kingdom House of Commons"><org
							reg="United Kingdom House of Lords">Houses of Parliament</org></org> on
					the banks of the Thames are, I believe, built of magnesian limestone, a stone on
					which the poisonous <place reg="London, England">London</place> atmosphere
					exerts its ever-corrosive action, so that a continual effort of repair is
					required. If at the time when the Houses of Parliament were built, some
					intelligent critic had insisted in pointing out to the builders the
					desirability, the absolute necessity, if a strong and resistant building were to
					be set up, of choosing a better material, he would not have been usurping the
					place of the architect, he would merely have been asserting a reasonable
					condition of good architecture</q>.</p>
			<p>"<q who="ELLHA">Anyone who insists on the desirability, the absolute necessity, if a
					sound future race is to arise, in care and choice in the control and breeding of
					men is not investing anything with 'the guardianship of civilization,' or
					assuming the function of architect of society. He is merely asserting an
					elementary condition which must without fail be fulfilled if any worthy
					civilization, any sound society, is ultimately to arise</q>."</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<p>Humanity and the War</p>
			<p>This, practically, is all that is specifically said on Birth Control. Yet more truth,
				more courage, more conviction, it seems to me, are concentrated in these brief
				passages than are to be found in whole volumes by less daring thinkers. There are
				other passages I would quote, passages concerning humanity in general and on the war
				in particular. With the passage of years Havelock Ellis seems to have shed his last
				illusion about Mankind. The savage stupidity of the human breed embitters him, with
				a bitterness that reminds you at times of <person reg="Swift, Jonathan">Dean
					Swift</person>; yet this bitterness is without malice, and is illuminated by
				profound spirituality.</p>
			<p>How he hits those who once furiously patriotic and bellicose, are now talking and
				writing against the war--the "<q who="ELLHA">now it can be sold</q>" school of
				erstwhile war workers which is busy producing novels and plays showing up "warfare"
				in its true light! Where were these people in 1914? asks Havelock Ellis. Where were
				they during the war? "<q who="ELLHA">One cannot avoid the conclusion that they were
					themselves fighting, or kicking other people into the fighting line, or wildly
					rushing to the rear in search of 'war work,' and shouting patriotic songs and
					wagging national flags and writing to the papers--for I speak of writers, be it
					noted--to stimulate all the force of hate, to extol--no doubt often in innocent
					simple-minded credulity--the men on their own side, whichever that may have
					been, as heroes, and the men on the other as dealers in 'atrocities.'</q>" And
				further, of these same men who are now so eloquent against war--yes, there are a few
				in this country also: "<q who="ELLHA">Why need the generation of 1914 proclaim to
					the world that their minds are moulded of such soft pap? It would be better to
					continue the march to hell like men. It is enough to have been traitors to all
					that is great and noble in Man. There is no occasion to be renegades also from
					their own miserable selves</q>."</p>
			<p>I stop quoting not because I wish to, nor because I think these passages are more
				significant than others in this great life-giving book, so full of suggestions for
				reading and thought. Havelock Ellis truly possesses the secret of eternal youth--not
				the solemn, conservative, dull, thoughtless and selfish youth as we too often find
				it in those young in years. His is the eternal youth and fiery freshness of the
				spirit, of Nature and of the ocean--how beautifully he paints the restless sea in
				these pages!--of eternity itself. There is a divine light in these comments and
				notes, the divine autumn light in which the sky becomes blue and clear and
				measurable. It is the silent evening light, and we find ourselves listening to no
				mere human voce, but to that of a god on some ancient hillside. We forget the
				pettiness, the meannesses of men.</p>
			<p>The voice of Havelock Ellis almost by itself confutes his disillusion with Man. To us
				he incarnates Man. That more men and more women are every year pausing to listen to
				this serene voice is a most encouraging sign. They cannot turn back unchanged to
				their daily tasks. After the high privilege of associating with this man and his
				quiet courageous assertion of eternal and basic truths, life must be changed for all
				of us. And to bring this inadequate review to a close, I shall permit myself one
				more quotation, one thought that all of us should read and re-read and ponder over
				each day of our lives. This is it: "<q who="ELLHA">The really essential things in
					life, if one looks strictly at it, are simple and few. So simple and so few that
					we are inclined to hide them from sight, to forget them; we may even attempt to
					neglect them altogether</q>."</p>
		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
