<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2003/07/04 SR</prepDate>
        <prepDate>5/09/2012 AW</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-09 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1924-06-00">Jun 1924</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>The War Against Birth Control</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp307894</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">The American Mercury</title> June 1924, 231-236.</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> C16:222.</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="BLAWI">Blake, William</name>
            <name id="HUXAL">Huxley, Aldous</name>
            <name id="HAYPA">Hayes, Patrick J.</name>
            <name id="GER">German</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>For typed drafts, see Library of Congress Microfilm 129: 637, 647 and 695. Excerpts of
            the article were published in the Sept. 1924 <title type="journal">Birth Control
                Review</title> as "<title type="article">The Fight Against Birth Control</title>,"
            245-248, 269. </p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="opposition to"/>
        <index level1="Comstock, Anthony"/>
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Federal"/>
        <index level1="Catholic Church" level2="birth control and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>THE FIGHT AGAINST BIRTH CONTROL</head>
        <byline>BY <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">MARGARET SANGER</person></byline>
        <epigraph>
            <p><q who="BLAWI"> ...and priests in black gowns were walking their rounds, and binding
                    with briars my joys and desires.</q> --<person reg="Blake, William">William
                    Blake</person>.</p>
        </epigraph>
        <p>"<q who="HUXAL">Strange</q>," exclaims a character in <person reg="Huxley, Aldous">Aldous
                Huxley's</person> "<title type="book">Antic Hay</title>," "<q>how long it has taken
                the ideas of love and procreation to dissociate themselves in the human mind. Even
                in this so-called Twentieth Century they are, in the majority of minds, indivisibly
                wedded.</q>"</p>
        <p>For ten years I have challenged this union of ideas, and in that turbulent period I have
            discovered that in this great commonwealth it is still considered "lewd, lascivious and
            obscene" to suggest their dissolution. When the diabolic words, Birth Control, first
            made their appearance in print, my obscure little journal was forbidden the mails, seven
            Federal indictments were lodged against me, and I was denounced, condemned and hounded
            out of the country. Since that time books on Birth Control have been suppressed,
            meetings called to discuss the underlying problem have been illegally broken up, and
            police officials, city councils, mayors, priests, archbishops, and other self-appointed
            meddlers have joined in obstructing and overriding all the constitutional guarantees of
            free speech. Their methods have been of infinite variety, their purposes audacious, and
            their organization and cohesion admirable.</p>
        <p>These ten years of suppression and persecution have taught me many things. Despite the
            personal inconvenience I have undergone, I can now look with amusement and at times even
            with tolerance upon the incessant activities of this new caste of thought controllers.
            Perhaps I really owe them a debt of gratitude, for I have come to see that they
            discharge a useful function in our great national pageant, enact a picturesque and
            perhaps even necessary role in our human-all-too-human comedy. Without the aid of their
            frenzied opposition the idea of Birth Control might never have been broadcasted to the
            remotest outposts of civilization.</p>
        <p>It is not my purpose here to argue the cause of Birth Control. I wish merely to touch
            upon certain aspects of the psychology of these thought suppressors--aspects perhaps
            unfamiliar to many who have never incurred their enmity.</p>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">II</head>
            <p>In the first place, let us recognize that in the ordinary acceptance of the term,
                morality is nothing but the sum total, the net residuum, of social habits, the
                codification of customs. Decent, conservative and altogether respectable cannibals
                find nothing immoral in anthropophagy. The only "immoral" person, in any country, is
                he who fails to observe the current folkways. Thus nothing can be so absolutely
                "moral," as <person reg="Butler, Samuel">Samuel Butler</person> suggested, as
                complete mental stagnation. To think about something new is as painful to the true
                conservative as to exercise an atrophied muscle. To doubt the wisdom of tradition is
                frowned upon. To introduce a new idea is to awaken a violent protest. More than once
                new inventions and discoveries of great value have been punished as crimes against
                the public good.</p>
            <p>Contrary to a widespread illusion, no sort of conduct among primitive and barbaric
                tribes is more rigidly regulated than the sexual. Custom controls the sexual impulse
                as it controls no other, and infraction of the traditional rules is punished by the
                severest penalties. In contrast with this tyranny of the primitive <emph
                    rend="italics">mores</emph>, civilization has brought about the gradual
                extension of the sphere of individual liberty and of personal choice. It has
                substituted heterogeneity in behavior and thought for rigid and routine servility to
                custom.</p>
            <p>But during the past half century in the <place>United States</place> we have been the
                witnesses of a counter movement. Manifestly, it has been impossible to enforce upon
                the ebullient and inchoate groups which make up our population any hard and fast set
                of rules for sexual behavior. It has been perfectly possible, however, to enforce a
                strict silence concerning sex, and to forbid, under the threat of severe punishment,
                any frank or open discussion of its problems. This counter movement, therefore, has
                been not so much an attempt to codify and ritualize sexual conduct among the
                population at large as an effort to control thought and speech upon the subject.</p>
            <p>Fifty-one years have passed since <person reg="Comstock, Anthony">Anthony
                    Comstock</person>, patron saint of our morality mongers, succeeded in having his
                psychosexual hyperaesthesia codified into State and Federal statutes. <name
                    type="law" reg="United States Penal Code, Section 211">Section 2II</name> of the
                Penal code, which legally links contraception with obscenity, is based on his
                curiously morbid conception of human functions. The only lawful justification of
                love, he believed, was the procreation of children. Except for this avowed purpose,
                all intercourse should be made punishable by fine and imprisonment. Unless men and
                women could prove the virtuous motive of their cohabitation, they should be--and
                indeed I am informed that in certain sections of the United States they often
                are--thrown into jail. The Comstockian legislation against contraception was thus
                aimed at those who held that, independent of prospective parenthood, sexual
                relations had a legitimate excuse and value of their own.</p>
            <p>Comstock, though he is dead, remains the archetype of the successful moral censor.
                His fanaticism generated a terrific energy. Galvanized into incessant and frenzied
                activity by the intensity of his obsession, he discovered obscenity everywhere. He
                came to be a national pontiff of prurience. Congress quailed before his passion. He
                convinced sheep-like legislators that unless his last-minute measures were enacted
                into law, American society would be hurled over the cliff into the abyss of eternal
                damnation. He gained greater and greater authority. He swayed Congress and the state
                legislatures, he became the moral censor of the Postoffice, and finally he
                controlled even the port of <place reg="New York, NY">New York</place>.</p>
            <p><person reg="Ellis, Havelock">Havelock Ellis</person> has told us that anything that
                sexually excites a prurient mind is obscene to that mind. Obscenity dominated
                Comstock's mind. "<q who="UNK">Men think they know</q>," some one has written, "<q
                    who="UNK">because they feel, and are firmly convinced because they are strongly
                    agitated.</q>" There was never any doubt in Anthony's breast and his certainty
                was always translated into action. He hounded men and women, regardless of their
                dignity and good intentions. Because, at the age of 75, <person reg="Harmon, Moses"
                    >Moses Harmon</person> published an article discussing matrimonial relations
                without evasion, he was sentenced to hard labor at <place reg="Leavenworth, KS"
                    >Leavenworth</place>. Through the force of his fanatical zeal and the
                inexhaustible resources of his energy Comstock was able for years to terrorize and
                anaesthetize the American mind. Armed with his newly legal forged weapons, his
                tyranny became complete. Always he was able to work "within the law."</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">III</head>
            <p>In one respect the self-appointed guardians of American morality differ today from
                their heroic ancestor. Speaking on the basis of my own experience and observation, I
                cannot escape the conclusion that those who have made the Birth Control movement the
                object of their particular enmity are totally ignorant of what may be termed the
                classical tactics of suppression. They are like schoolboys playing with chemicals.
                Where they have hoped to enforce silence, they have been surprised and shocked by
                the force and repercussive effect of unexpected detonations. They themselves are
                often compelled to run to cover. Instead of silencing an idea or a book, they merely
                dramatize it. Over and over again they have worked miracles of publicity that would
                have been impossible to a regiment of press-agents.</p>
            <p>The Birth Control movement in America has had the good luck to incur the wrath of two
                distinct schools of censors. At first the Comstockians focused their attention on
                us. But with te passing of that patriarch any experienced observer must have noted
                the rapid decline of the Comstockian school. It has now become almost senile. No
                longer is it actuated by the stupendous frenzy of its founder. The grandiose
                gestures of the Golden Age are now things of the past. The neo-Comstocks are making,
                it is true, occasional spurts of activity, successful mainly because of te
                feebleness of the literary challenges to Mr. <person reg="Sumner, John S.">John S.
                    Sumner</person>. But I venture to predict that, in a future not too distant,
                there will be a gradual disintegration of the whole school. Times are changing. We
                are no longer in the Victorian era. Despite itself, American society cannot again
                bring to fruit so perfect a specimen of dynamic psychosexual hyperaesthesia as
                Anthony Comstock presented. And without the impelling force of an overwhelming
                pathological prurience, no virtuoso of his caliber can arise among us.</p>
            <p>Today the chief warfare against Birth Control is waged by the Roman Catholic clergy
                and their allies. From the psychological point of view the fact is not without its
                significance. For at least fifteen hundred years the church has occupied itself with
                the problem of imposing abstinence upon its priesthood--an intelligent and trained
                body of men who have been taught to look upon complete asceticism as the highest
                ideal--and it is not surprising that such a class of professional celibates should
                be psychically sensitive to the implications of the idea of contraception. Taught to
                look upon all expressions of physical love as sinful, it is but natural that these
                men should combat a school of thought so diametrically opposed to their own. Thus
                the opposition of the <org>Roman Catholic Church</org> and its representatives, high
                and low, is logical and to be expected. The philosophy of Birth Control insists upon
                the maximum of personal liberty in every sphere of human behavior that is compatible
                with the maximum of personal responsibility. Rightly or wrongly, it throws back upon
                the individual full responsibility for his behavior. It requires him to act upon the
                basis of reason, experience and prudence. True morality, we claim, is the outgrowth
                of experience and of the exercise of rational intelligence upon that experience.</p>
            <p>The Catholic scheme of ethics, on the contrary, demands strict obedience to the laws
                and prohibitions that have been codified by authority. That authority declares in no
                uncertain terms that "<q who="UNK">all positive methods of this nature
                    [contraception] are immoral and forbidden.</q>" In a Christmas pastoral
                Archbishop (now Cardinal) <person reg="Hayes, Patrick J.">Patrick J. Hayes</person>
                ventured so far as to assert that</p>
            <p rend="blockquote"><q who="HAYPA">even though some little angels in the flesh, through
                    the moral or physical deformities of their parents, may appear to human eyes
                    hideous, misshapen, a blot on civilized society, we must no lose sight of this
                    Christian thought: that under and within such visible malformations lives an
                    immortal soul to be saved and glorified for all eternity among the blessed in
                    Heaven</q>.</p>
            <p>From exponents of the philosophy represented by this utterance the early advocates of
                Birth Control were prepared for the bitterest opposition. As a matter of fact, we
                welcomed such opposition, hoping only that the battle might be carried on according
                to the rules of decency and honesty. Neither the theory nor the practice of Birth
                Control has ever been thrust upon women unwilling to accept it, least of all upon
                Catholics. We have conceded to Catholic and all other clergymen the full right to
                preach their own doctrines, both of theology and of morals. When, however, the
                Catholic clergy attempt to force their ideas upon non-Catholic sections of the
                American public and transform them into legislative acts, we believe we are well
                within our rights as American citizens when we voice our protest. The
                unsportsmanlike tactics and strategy of these opponents to Birth Control may be
                illustrated by two examples of attempted suppression.</p>
            <p>Three years ago, as a fitting conclusion to the <org
                    reg="American Birth Control Conference, 1st">First American Birth Control
                    Conference</org>, a public meeting was arranged at the Town Hall in New York
                City. The subject chosen for discussion was the ethics of Birth Control. It was our
                aim to use this occasion, not for agitation, but to determine the opinions of
                representative men and women of all professions. Opponents of the doctrine were to
                be given a fair opportunity to state their objections. But the meeting was summarily
                closed by the police, acting, as subsequent investigation proved, on the
                instructions of Monsignor <person reg="Dineen, Joseph P.">Dineen</person>, secretary
                to Archbishop Hayes! When I attempted to speak, I was dragged off to a police
                station, and with me went those who protested against this illegal and unwarranted
                abuse of authority. The case was promptly dismissed by the magistrate the following
                morning. The ecclesiastical instigators of the suppression did not appear against
                me. But the investigation which followed indicated that the police who broke up the
                meeting had received their orders, not from police headquarters, but from the
                clergy!</p>
            <p>The boomerang effect of this performance was indicated by the reverberations in the
                press. The idea of Birth Control was advertised, dramatized, made the recipient of
                column upon column of publicity. Only an infinitesimal section of the public had
                been aware of the first <title>American Birth Control Conference</title>; even fewer
                persons knew of the proposed meeting in the Town Hall. The clumsy and illegal
                tactics of our opponents made the whole country aware of what we were doing. Even
                the most conservative of American newspapers were placed in the position of
                defending our doctrine. Letters showered in upon us. Many new members joined the
                    <org reg="American Birth Control League">League</org>. At a later date, in a
                much larger auditorium, crowded to the doors, the meeting was held. Thus our first
                national conference was crowned with triumph. Indeed, the momentum of the publicity
                we obtained by this unlawful interference carried us over many months. Instead of
                cutting off the public discussion of Birth Control, the episode made the whole
                country talk about Birth Control. There were symposiums, editorials, letters from
                "constant readers"--all of which had the effect deliberately sought by us, of
                keeping our idea interesting to the public at large.</p>
            <p>Other tactics were invoked by the avowed enemies of Birth Control in a more recent
                attempt at censorship. When a state conference was arranged in <place
                    reg="Syracuse, NY">Syracuse</place> our clerical opponents brought pressure to
                bear upon the Common Council of that city--the members of which, unless I am
                mistaken, had all taken an oath to uphold the Constitution of the United States and
                that of the State of <place>New York</place>. An ordinance was introduced
                making it a misdemeanor to discuss the subject of Birth Control in the city of
                Syracuse, and with but a single dissenting voice it was passed. To become a law it
                needed only the signature of the mayor. A violent protest now arose. Many who had
                not hitherto shown any interest in Birth Control sprang to the defense of the
                constitutional guarantees of free speech and peaceable assembly. The mayor, finally,
                vetoed the ordinance and the state conference was successfully held. By this episode
                the inhabitants of Syracuse were not merely introduced to our idea; they were in
                addition taught something about the Constitution.</p>
            <p>I might recount almost innumerable other instances of crude and usually unsuccessful
                attempts at illegal suppression. Hotels have been boycotted by such organizations as
                the <org>Knights of Columbus</org> because the managers have purveyed luncheons to
                advocates of Birth Control. Halls contracted and paid for have been withdrawn at the
                last minute on account of pressure brought to bear upon their owners. Permits to
                hold meetings have been refused by mayors or other city officials in cities in which
                there was a powerful Catholic constituency. Few politicians, though they have sworn
                to uphold the Constitution, dare jeopardize their future as office holders by
                incurring the displeasure of clerical authorities who control the thoughts of their
                adherents.</p>
            <p>It is hardly necessary, I hope, to reiterate here that we concede to Catholics and to
                all other churchmen full freedom to preach their own doctrines, whether theological
                or moral. But when they attempt, through illegal tactics, to force their opinions
                and codes upon non-Catholics they should be and will be challenged.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">IV</head>
            <p>I do not wish to convey the impression that my ten years of experience have driven me
                to the conclusion that suppression is an unmixed blessing. It is true that the idea
                of Birth Control has been made thrive by these ill-advised attempts to extirpate it
                from the American mind. But its vitality is not merely the chance result of such
                clumsy, clownish antics. If we had not been determined, with all the courage and
                stamina at our command, constantly, promptly and unflinchingly to challenge the
                assumed authority of these self-appointed censors, our movement never would have
                profited nor advanced.</p>
            <p>Looked at from a broad point of view, the disadvantages of opposition have probably
                outweighed the benefits. If a powerful ecclesiastical organization, armed with the
                vast authority of tradition, can countenance and even encourage an impudent
                disregard of the Constitution of the United States, the document which insures to
                that organization itself the freedom to perpetuate itself and extend its influence,
                does the fact not set an evil example to any lesser organization or group which sets
                up shop to interfere in other people's affairs? Public opinion in America, I fear,
                is too willing to condone in the officials of the Roman Catholic Church what it
                condemns in the <org>Ku Klux Klan</org>. Today American "purity" is protected by an
                interlocking directorate of professional meddlers, a bloodless but bloodthirsty
                tribe, scanning the horizon for any and every outbreak of human passion, galloping
                post haste to the scene of every such <foreign lang="GER">verboten</foreign>
                manifestation like a tribe of Indians descending upon a pioneer's wagon. Any
                    <person>Dogberry</person> clothed in brief authority, any psychopathic person
                with an "obscenity" complex may inaugurate the hunt. I have run the gauntlet in this
                new American sport and I know how well the new Inquisition is organized.</p>
            <p>Sporadic protests against the program of organized encroachment upon the citizen's
                constitutional rights; indignation meetings called by radicals, Liberals and
                intellectuals when some book is banned; anaemic, half-hearted denunciations of all
                censorship; campaigns for free speech, so often inaugurated and so rapidly
                dropped--such phenomena as these appear to me as one who has been more or less in
                the trenches for ten years, as not unsuggestive of an awkward squad of school boys
                armed with bean-shooters, advancing against the machine guns and poison gases of a
                trained army. Nevertheless, as I have tried to show, a little group of women under
                the direction of one who may be a fanatic have been able to wrest victory form this
                army. The secret of our success, if I may be permitted for the moment to call it a
                success, is to be found in the fact that we have never wasted our time and energy
                whining about our constitutional right to free speech. We have simply spoken out. We
                have asserted the truth as we have found it. We have spoken openly, honestly,
                aboveboard, and without equivocation or hypocrisy. We have repeated ourselves, we
                have reiterated our truisms, we have been, perhaps, at times tiresome and boring,
                but by following that program--by saying something and standing by what we have
                said--we have recaptured, for ourselves at least, the right to be heard. In this, I
                am convinced, we have set an example to others who have ideas to propagate--some of
                them, perhaps, of infinitely more importance to the American public than Birth
                Control. But so far they do not seem to be courageous enough to challenge an
                authority that invades every field of thought. We have, as a nation, not yet
                awakened to the realization that eternal vigilance is the price of liberty.</p>
            <p>Vituperation of the purity brigade may be an amusing substitute for mah jong and
                radio concerts for the intellectually detached, and indignant libertarians may
                derive some satisfaction from making loudmouthed protests after somebody or
                something has been suppressed, but such activities contribute exactly nothing toward
                a cure for our national disease. If the American public is ever to be brought safely
                out of the mental coma into which it has fallen, something more than persistent
                criticism of the professional meddler is imperative. an ounce of courage is worth a
                ton of criticism.</p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
