<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2012-03-23 AW</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-02 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1957-00-00">1957</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>A Summing Up</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp307902</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Humanist</title></bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> C16:0495</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="WHIST">White, Stewart Edward</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>This award was given by the <org>American Humanist Association</org>.</p>
        <p>The article is an excerpt from Sanger's full acceptance speech, which has not been found.</p>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="biography"/>
        <index level1="humanism" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="awards"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>A Summing Up</head>
        <byline><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></byline>
        <p>Somewhere I have read that there are two types of human beings -- those who, like the
            fox, know many things, and those who, like the hedgehog, know <emph rend="italics">one
                big thing</emph>. I do not need to remind you that I belong to the second class! But
            I have discovered -- indeed, I have always known -- that it is not enough just to know
            one great truth. Truth must be <emph rend="italics">lived</emph> -- not merely passively
            accepted. Trust must be <emph rend="italics">lived</emph>, even though your truth makes
            you a minority of one. Still water stagnates. Unless a tree puts forth its branches into
            the sun and winds, it will wither away and perish. So inaction saps the vigor of the
            human mind. Passive acceptance, even of a great truth, is an evil -- the evil resides
            not so much in the acceptance, as in slothful inaction.</p>
        <p>So, I have discovered, human beings must test their truths on the battlefield of this
            world, must fight for them through the derision of the press, the prejudices of the
            courts, even through the ordeal of prison. Truth cannot be ladled out by the spoonful,
            ready made, like instant coffee, into an agreeable beverage.</p>
        <p>For me, it has not been difficult -- never was -- to decide upon my one great truth. From
            the time of <person reg="Malthus, Thomas Robert">Malthus</person> the idea that children must
            be brought into this strange little planet of ours <emph rend="italics">by choice</emph>
            and not <emph rend="italics">by chance</emph> has been stated time after time,
            generation after generation. But until this truth has been put into action -- dramatized
            -- it could not increase and grow strong enough to bear fruit in combating popular
            prejudice and entrenched bigotry. </p>
        <p>No one has expressed better what I have learned by experience -- sometimes bitter,
            sometimes rewarding -- than the late <person reg="White, Stewart Edward">Stewart Edward
                White</person> who wrote:</p>
        <p><q who="WHIST">One acquires a truth as one believes in it, and tries to stick to it.
                Until that truth has become in you an unfailing motive power; until you have
                established yourself in it without intermission; until you cannot help acting any
                other way but in it; until you are one of its supporting elements, as it were, you
                do not gain the full benefit of its possession.</q></p>
        <p>Some doubter may rise to question the <emph rend="italics">Great Truth</emph> which has
            animated my life. Is not <emph rend="italics">Birth Control</emph>, he might ask, merely
            a negative concept? To this I promptly reply that, on the contrary, the philosophy of
            birth control envisages humanity redeemed, regenerated, nay -- even reborn by this new
            instrument of intelligence and liberation. It has awakened and stimulated thought in all
            countries of the world today, especially in Asia. It should be the humanist spearhead in
            the endless battle against entrenched complacency, against mass conformity, against the
            glacierlike menace of prejudice. My reward has been to see seemingly insurmountable
            prejudices melting away like icebergs under the sunlight of challenging truth.</p>
        <p>In the beginning I was confronted by contempt, derision, and persecution for my
            convictions. I was literally run out of the country. To papaphrase <person
                reg="Thoreau, Henry David">Thoreau</person>, I could not keep pace with that
            conformity imposed upon American women in that dim, distant, pre-World War I era. My
            mind and soul were attuned to a different truth. But I had the courage to keep step to
            the music of that inner truth, however far away or strange its measures seemed to my
            fellow women. <emph rend="italics">--From Margaret Sanger’s little known response when
                she was named 1957 Humanist of the Year.</emph></p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
