<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "file:/S:/TRANSCRIPTIONS/XML%20Drafts/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2010/03/10 AC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2010/03/18 CH proof</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1934-00-00">1934</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Foreword to For Legalized Birth Control</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp308022</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>For Legalized Birth Control</title>(New York:
                1934)</bibl>
            <bibl><title>National Republic</title> Records, Hoover Institution
                of War, Revolution and Peace.</bibl>
            <bibl><title>MSM</title>C16:0347</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="SMIHE"> Smith, Helena Huntington</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>Margaret Sanger wrote the foreword to the pamphlet, pbublished by the
                <title>New Republic</title>, which compiled two articles,
                "<title type="article">Wasting Women's Lives</title>," by Helena
            Huntington Smith and "<title type="article">Birth Control's Business
                Baby</title>," by Elizabeth H. Garrett.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="effectiveness of"/>
        <index level1="New York City" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Free Speech League"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation"
            level3="New York "/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Foreword</head>
        <byline>by Margaret Sanger</byline>
        <p>So convincingly do these essays expose two different aspects of a
            heartbreaking national tragedy that it has become imperative to
            reprint them in the pamphlet herewith presented for the
            consideration of serious-minded Americans.</p>
        <p>
            <person reg="Smith, Helena Huntington">Helena Huntington
                Smith</person> summarizes “<q who="SMIHE">the long-standing
                horror</q>” of <place reg="United States of America"
                >America</place>’s maternal death rate. Behind this picture of
            the appalling waste of women’s lives we can sense the desperate need
            and utter frustration which preceded the fatal effort for
            relief.</p>
        <p> In contrast--and in what vividly dramatic contrast-- <person
                reg="Garrett, Elizabeth H.">Elizabeth H. Garrett</person>
            exposes the new generation of profiteers and quacks which has arisen
            to batten upon human misery, credulity and despair, and amass greedy
            profits from the traffic in pseudo-contraceptives.</p>
        <p> This situation, which all sane-minded people must deplore, has
            arisen as a result of the confusion and indifference of public
            opinion. The intelligent citizen cannot absolve himself wholly from
            blame so long as he stands aside, while the battle to supplant
            confusion and ignorance by an honest, long-range program for racial
            health is being fought.</p>
        <p> In a test of more than one hundred of these so-called
                “<soCalled>contraceptives</soCalled>,” undertaken by our
                <org>Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau</org> in <place
                reg="New York, NY">New York City</place>, forty-five were
            discovered to be utterly unreliable. This fact will not, of course,
            come as a surprise to most people. On the contrary, it would be a
            revelation if they had been found to have value. The phenomenon is
            part and parcel of the whole fabric of “<soCalled>big
                business</soCalled>”. A high-pressure salesman unloads his wares
            upon indifferent pharmacists, along with highly-colored and
            deceptive window displays and suggestive advertising material.
            Concerning the efficacy, the harmlessness or the potency of these
            products, the guarantee is implied rather than explicit, evasive
            rather than assured.</p>
        <p> During the last five years this business has grown by leaps and
            bounds, not always because it seeks honestly to minister to human
            needs but because, with diabolic insight, it has supplied the
            demands of desperation.</p>
        <p> It was precisely this lamentable possibility that I foresaw some
            eighteen years ago. That premonition compelled me to attempt to
            divert the current of opinion within the ranks of the Birth Control
            movement away from the so-called Free Speech aspects of the campaign
            to the necessity of a scientific approach. Cooperation of the
            medical profession was imperative if the women of America were to
            receive the best information available-- for even then the
            adulteration of drugs and the traffic in quack nostrums was a
            scandal smelling to the heavens.</p>
        <p> We called upon the leaders of the medical profession to inaugurate
            modern research into the whole problem of contraception from the
            physiological point of view, and to develop from the resources of
            science a technique that would be harmless and unfailing. Concerning
            the moral and ethical aspects of the problem, we insisted that they
            could not be delegated to any external group but that parents must
            decide these issues for themselves. And on this we still insist.</p>
        <p> The medical profession was, unfortunately, less responsive than
            women themselves in recognizing the crucial importance of the
            technique of contraception. More recently an aroused section of
            public opinion has stirred the doctors out of their lethargy. As
            individuals, many are rallying to the cause of Birth Control. But
            even today, as an organized national body, this profession withholds
            its support from legislative measures that are organically related
            to their liberty and the most pressing problems confronting
            them.</p>
        <p> Confusion concerning State and Federal legislation is evident. One
            of the clearest of judicial opinions and I think one of the earliest
            was that of the <org>New York State Court of Appeals</org>, handed
            down by <person reg="Crane, Frederick E.">Justice Crane </person>in
            my own case in 1918. This specified that contraceptives might be
            prescribed to safeguard the patient against “<soCalled>disease or
                the prevention of disease</soCalled>.” Woefully inadequate this
            decision stands in an era like the present. What is imperative today
            is the removal of the whole problem from the realm of secrecy and
            commercialism into the daylight of intelligent control and
            supervision. The objectives sought by the Birth Control movement
            must become part of a clear-sighted and long-range program of
            national and racial health. </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
