<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011-08-04 NC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2012-04-04 CH Proofed Tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-08 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1954-00-00"><supplied resp="MSPP">1954</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Infertility Services at the Margaret Sanger Research
                    Bureau</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp308111</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Abraham Stone Papers, Countway Library of Medicine, Harvard University</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> C16:1045</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="infertility"/>
        <index level1="Margaret Sanger Research Bureau"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <p>For forty years I have been advocating responsible parenthood--the idea that every child
            shall be a wanted child. This is the meaning of “control”. “Control” does not
            necessarily mean limitation; it implies the ability to regulate in accordance with one’s
            needs and desires. A woman who either for health, eugenic, or social reasons should bear
            no more children, should be given the best available medical advice for the prevention
            of conception. At the same time, however, the woman who wants a child but cannot bear
            one for physical reasons should be given the best available medical advice and care to
            help her have a baby.</p>
        <p>At our Bureau in <place reg="New York, NY">New York</place>, now known as the
                    <org><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person> Research
                Bureau</org>, we have a large service for women who for medical reasons require
            advice on family planning and child spacing; but we also have an extensive service for
            the care and treatment of the childless couple. This service was organized in 1935 by
            Dr. <person reg="Stone, Abraham">Abraham Stone</person> and Dr. <person
                reg="Shields, Frances A.">Frances A. Shields</person>, and is now one of the most
            active centers of its kind in this country. Only patients referred by physicians are
            accepted at the <org reg="Margaret Sanger Research Bureau, Infertility Services"
                >Infertility Service</org> of the Bureau, but already more than 2500 couples have
            received medical care for their childlessness at the Bureau.</p>
        <p>At our Service we regard barrenness as a problem not of the wife or of the husband, but
            as a problem of the family. In every instance both the husband and the wife are
            thoroughly studied. The examination of the husband is usually simpler and may sometimes
            obviate extensive investigations of the wife.</p>
        <p>As a first step, every couple is asked to come to a medical orientation lecture at a
            designated time. These lectures are given to groups of ten or fifteen newly registered
            couples. At this lecture the physician explains to the patients the anatomical and
            physiological factors of human reproduction, the various conditions that may lead to
            infertility, the tests required to determine the particular cause in individual cases,
            and the nature of the treatment employed. We have found that this orientation lecture is
            very helpful, not only in providing the necessary information, but also in relieving
            many tensions and anxieties.</p>
        <p>What generally happens at an infertility service? Recently I had the privilege of
            observing one of the oldest centers in this field, the one conducted by Dr. <person
                reg="Rock, John">John Rock</person> at the <org>Free Hospital for Women</org> in
                <place reg="Brookline, MA">Brookline, Massachusetts</place>. The following story
            tells of the work being carried on in that particular service, and is more or less
            representative of well-equipped centers for childless couples throughout the
            country.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
