<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2012-03-23 AW</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2012-03-27 AW</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-04 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1957-03-02">2 March 1957</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Message of Thanks for Humanist of the Year
                    Award</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp309258</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Ellen Watumull Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> C18:380</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="WHIST">White, Stewart Edward</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>This award was given by the <org>American Humanist Association</org>. The title was added
            by Sanger by hand.</p>
        <p>For an excerpt of the speech see "A Summing Up," <emph rend="underline">Humanist</emph>
            38 [July 1978], p. 62. Margaret Sanger Microfilm C16:0495.</p>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="biography"/>
        <index level1="humanism" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="awards"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head><add>Humanist award to MS. Woman of the year--</add></head>
        <byline><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">MARGARET SANGER</person></byline>
        <p> I am sending this message of thanks from <org>The Reef</org>. No -- I have not been
            shipwrecked on a desert island. I am resting at The Reef, which is a hotel overlooking
            the beach at <place reg="Waikiki, HI">Waikiki</place>. Much as I regret being absent for
            the high honor you are conferring upon me, the great distance from the Mid-Pacific to
            the Middle West has prevented me from being present this evening.</p>
        <p> Lying here within the pounding of the ceaseless breakers of this vast <place
                reg="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</place>, I have been able to look upon the great events
            of the past forty years, and to get a new and true perspective upon my own activities
            during those tumultuous years.</p>
        <p>Somewhere I have read that there are two types of human beings –- those who, like the
            fox, know <emph rend="underline">many</emph> things; and those who, like the hedgehog,
            know <emph rend="underline">one big thing</emph>. I do not need to remind you that I
            belong to the second class! But I have discovered –- indeed I have always known– that it
            is not enough just to know one great truth. Truth must be <emph rend="underline"
                >lived</emph> –- not merely passively accepted. Truth must be <emph rend="underline"
                >lived</emph>, even though your truth make you a minority of one. A wise man has
            told us that unused iron soon rusts. Still water stagnates. Unless a tree put forth its
            branches into the sun and winds, it must wither away and perish. So, inaction saps the
            vigor of the human mind. Passive acceptance, even of a great truth, is an evil – the
            evil residing not so much in the acceptance as in slothful inaction.</p>
        <p> So, I have discovered, human beings must test their truths on the battlefield of this
            world, must fight for them through the derision of the press, the prejudices of the
            courts, even through the ordeal of prison. Truth cannot be ladled out by the spoonful,
            ready made like “instant coffee”, into an agreeable beverage.</p>
        <p> For me, it has not been difficult –- never was -– to decide upon my one great truth.
            From the time of <person reg="Malthus, Thomas Robert">Malthus</person> the idea that children
            must be brought into this strange little planet of ours by <emph rend="underline"
                >choice</emph> and <emph rend="underline">not by chance</emph> has been stated time
            after time, generation after generation. But until this truth had been put into action
            -- dramatised -- it could not increase and grow strong enough to bear fruit in
            combatting popular prejudice and entrenched bigotry.</p>
        <p> No one has expressed what I have learned by experience– sometimes bitter, sometimes
            rewarding– than the late <person reg="White, Stewart Edward">Stewart Edward
                White</person>; who wrote somewhere:</p>
        <p><q who="WHIST">“One acquires a truth as one believes in it, and tries to stick to it.
                Until that truth has become in you an unfailing motive power; until you have
                established yourself in it without intermission; until you cannot help acting any
                other way but in it; until you cannot help supporting elements, as it were, you do
                not gain the full benefit of its possession.”</q></p>
        <p>Some doubter may rise to question the Great Truth that has animated my life. Is not Birth
            Control, he might ask, merely a negative concept? To this I promptly reply that, on the
            contrary, the philosophy of Birth Control envisages humanity redeemed, regenerated, may
            even reborn by this new instrument of intelligence and liberation. It is based not
            merely upon the keen prophetic foresight of Thomas Malthus, but the inspiring vision of
            a <person reg="Galton, Francis">Francis Galton</person> -- that long-neglected genius,
            by the evidence of the latest findings of those patient young researchers, the new
            generation of demographers. It has awakened and stimulated thought in all countries of
            the world today, especially in Asia. It should be the Humanist spearhead in the endless
            battle against entrenched complacency, against mass conformity, against the glacier-like
            menace of prejudice. My reward has been to see seemingly insurmountable prejudices
            melting away like icebergs under the sunlight of challenging truth.</p>
        <p>In the beginning I was confronted by contempt, derision, and persecution for my
            convictions. I was literally run out of the country. To paraphrase <person
                reg="Thoreau, Henry David">Thoreau</person>, I could not keep pace with that
            conformity imposed upon American women in that dim, distant pre-World I period. My mind
            and soul were attuned to a different truth. But I had the courage to keep step to the
            music of that inner truth, however faraway or strange its measures seemed to my
            fellow-women.</p>
        <p>Tonight, in spirit, if not in body, I am present with my fellow-Humanists, and the honor
            you confer upon me will always be remembered as one of the proudest moments of my
            life!</p>

    </docBody>
</doc>
