<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2001-10-23 MH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2003-10-14 NS</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2003/11/25 CH cleaned up tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007/05/30 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-05 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1911-09-10">10 Sept 1911</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Impressions of the East Side</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp320122</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">New York Call</title>, Sept. 10, 1911, 15</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
        <p>For Part I see "<xref from="320121.xml">Impressions of the East Side</xref>, Sept. 3,
            1911.</p>
        <index level1="socialism"/>
        <index level1="working classes" level2="children"/>
        <index level1="capitalism"/>
        <index level1="poverty"/>
        <index level1="physicians" level2="MS on"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Impressions of the East Side</head>
        <head type="sub">PART II--</head>
        <byline>BY <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">MARGARET H. SANGER</person>.</byline>
        <p>The <place reg="New York, NY">East Side</place> is full of superstition. Superstitious
            fear prompts them in many of their acts. If they can give a penny to a blind man, they
            feel sure it will bring them "luck;" they fear to mix meat and milk, not so much because
            of religious scruples as because it brings them bad "luck." One of the desires of their
            life is to move up town, to cleaner quarters, but even when they are able to, the fear
            that "luck" will leave them, keeps them down town. A physician of some repute, living
            down town, when asked why he lives down there when his practice is mostly up town, said,
                "<q who="UNK"> "Luck" came to him there and he will stay with it.</q>" Almost
            everything depends on "luck," to them it seems almost a part of their religion, and is
            difficult to overcome. </p>
        <p>Their great desire is to get "rich" and employ men and women. The capitalistic instinct
            to be your own "boss" and make off the labor of others is everywhere. It is ridiculous
            to think for a moment that the class struggle is on the East Side only and every one who
            understands the meaning of the words, knows only too well that it is everywhere. But
            certainly it is at its height on the East Side, for there it is the aim and ambition of
            everybody to bleed everybody else. The doctors, druggists and lawyers all take a share
            in this. The druggists charge from 10 to 15 cents more on every article than is paid
            elsewhere.</p>
        <p>An example of the doctor's bleeding is shown by the story which follows: During the very
            hot weather a rash broke out on an infant whose parents had had a little "luck" in
            accumulating this world's goods. The ever kind neighbors and friends of the parents
            advised them to go to a baby specialist, just for a change of "luck," they said, as the
            baby had not been well since birth. These were easily persuaded, and the first visit
            cost them $5. The specialist then sent the mother to another physician to have her milk
            tested, which cost five more. Then both parents had to have their blood tested, which
            cost five each, and go back again to the first specialist to tell him there was nothing
            the matter with either the milk or the blood, which cost five more, or $25 in all. And
            the first day it grew a little cooler the baby's rash disappeared!</p>
        <p>It is surprising to see the large number of push carts, and one wonders how they can
            exist there, when it is impossible for some people to buy only the bare necessities of
            life. But the fact is that over half of the people there do not patronize the push
            carts, and the other half who do are compelled to buy the same articles over and over
            again, so cheap are the wares. A pair of stockings cost 15 cents, but after one day's
            moderate wear they are unfit for darning, so badly and of such wretched material are
            they made.</p>
        <p>The fruit peddlers too astonish you at the thriving business they seem to do. But when
            you have eaten with these people for a few days the same erratic appetite takes hold of
            you, and meat, fish and bread no longer satisfy you, and if there is a cent to be had
            you find yourself on your way to the fruit carts too, eagerly longing to quench the
            terrible hunger which has taken possession of you. The people are always eating, for
            they are always hungry. </p>
        <p>The parents' love of the little ones is almost animal like in its emotions, especially to
            those under four, after that--well--it's just like waiting for the years to pass
            till they can bring in some return for their earthly existence.</p>
        <p>The shouting, screaming and swearing at the children and even at the infants, is
            impossible to conceive of, having had no childhood themselves it is difficult for them
            to realize the evolution or state of the child mind, and a child of four or five is
            expected to think and act like the parents, which accounts for the many slaps the little
            tots get all around. They are proud to call their children Americans, and when they are
            able, or brave enough to try their "luck," in a new section, they emerge to the upper
            East Side. There they rapidly develop, and improve in manners, language and habits. In a
            few years they have outgrown that neighborhood and the West Side becomes their <place
                reg="Mecca, Saudia Arabia">Mecca</place>.</p>
        <p>The word Socialism is almost a household word among them. They have neither the fear, nor
            have they the disgust which our friends up town have of the word. Yet the deep, and
            abject pity with which they regard you when they discover that you are a Socialist is a
            hundred times more maddening and much more difficult to meet. If you had escaped from an
            asylum with a placard of "harmless" on you they could not treat you with more
            tenderness. They will even listen to you while you expound your Socialism to them, but
            when you have finished they will smilingly shake their heads, and tell you that it is a
            beautiful dream, but as long as the world lasts, "Brains" will be the only thing that
            can count. On their explaining just what "Brains" mean, you find that the principle the
            druggist used when he charged them 10 cents more than the article could be purchased for
            elsewhere is the brilliant example. </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
