<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2004/08/01 MPL</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/08/06 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/08/09 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007/06/25 CH Oxygen Update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/03/11 CH Entered corrections suggested by Andy Carloff.</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-12 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1916-08-09">9 Aug 1916</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>A "Birth Control" Lecture Tour</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp320118</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Malthusian</title>, Sept. 1916, 83-84</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>Sanger's letter to Charles and Bessie Drysdale was published as an article, with a brief
            introduction by the <person reg="Kerr, R. B.">editor</person> of the <title
                type="journal">Malthusian</title>.</p>
        <index level1="Family Limitation" level2="censorship of"/>
        <index level1="Allison, Van Kleeck"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues" level3="formation of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movememt"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="opposition to"/>
        <index level1="censorship"/>
        <index level1="Michigan" level2="birth control in"/> equi <index level1="middle classes"
            level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="Missouri" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Ohio" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Oregon" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret " level2="speaking tours" level3="1916 (U.S.)"/>
        <index level1="Wisconsin" level2="birth control in"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>A "Birth Control" Lecture Tour.</head>
        <byline>(EXTRACTS FROM A LETTER FROM MRS. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">MARGARET
                SANGER</person>.)</byline>
        <p>I have been promising myself each day since my return from the West that I would write to
            tell you of the wonderful trip I had, and also of the great enthusiasm shown everywhere
            in this country on the subject of Birth Control.</p>
        <p>I left New York on April 16th and delivered a trial lecture in <place
                reg="New Rochelle, NY">New Rochelle</place> before starting. I spoke in <place
                reg="Washington, DC">Washington</place>, <place reg="Pittsburgh, PA"
                >Pittsburgh</place>, <place reg="Cleveland, OH">Cleveland</place>, <place
                reg="Chicago, IL">Chicago</place>, <place reg="Detroit, MI">Detroit</place>, <place
                reg="Racine, WI">Racine</place>, <place>Milwaukee, Wisconsin</place>, <place
                reg="MN">St. Paul</place> and <place reg="Minneapolis, MN">Minneapolis</place>. Then
            I turned back a little and went down to <place reg="Indianapolis, IN"
                >Indianapolis</place> to speak at the <org>National Convention of Charities</org>. I
            will tell you of it later. The next stop was in <place reg="St. Louis, MO">St.
                Louis</place>, then <place reg="Denver, CO">Denver</place>, <place
                reg="Los Angeles, CA">Los Angeles</place> and <place reg="San Francisco, CA">San
                Francisco</place>. After two weeks in that glorious State, I went up to <place
                reg="Portland, OR">Portland (Oregon)</place>, by boat; spoke also in <place
                reg="Seattle, WA">Seattle</place> and <place reg="Spokane, WA">Spokane
                (Washington)</place>, and thus ended my first and maiden tour in <place
                reg="United States">U.S.A.</place></p>
        <p>The first two meetings in Pittsburgh and Washington were mild in numbers and enthusiasm
            compared with all the other meetings I had. In Cleveland I spoke in the <org>Unitarian
                Church</org> in the afternoon, under the auspices of some social workers, while in
            the evening there was an overflow meeting arranged by a radical group. Both meetings
            were splendid. Since then a strong <org reg="Birth Control League of Ohio">Birth Control
                League</org> has been formed in Cleveland of over four hundred members, and I
            enclose the little paper they have just issued--the first wee voice of Birth Control in
            the U.S.A.</p>
        <p>In <place reg="Akron, OH">Akron</place>, near Cleveland, I was not permitted by the
            authorities to speak at all. In Chicago, a <person reg="Mindell, Fania">young Jewish
                girl</person> who has been for the last two years spreading the information to the
            women of the stock-yards in her own language, got up three large public meetings for me
            there. There were also several private meetings. There is the promise of a debate there
            this fall between a prominent woman physician and myself, which promises a good piece of
            propaganda if it can be arranged.</p>
        <p>In Racine, the organizer of my meeting was the <person reg="Unknown">wife of a working
                man</person> and the mother of seven children; nevertheless she was socially
            ostracized for having anything to do with "that woman" as I was called.</p>
        <p>In Milwaukee I had an amusing experience. The women who arranged the meeting for me were
            very "respectable," and were allied with other lines of social work which they did not
            want to compromise by coming out too strong for anything which might be "obscene." They
            whispered to me that it was a most conservative city, and they hoped I'd put the soft
            pedal on too radical ideas, etc. (Milwaukee is the one city in the States which has had
            a <person reg="Hoan, Daniel Webster">Socialist Mayor</person>!) At any rate I had no
            choice, for before the meeting the city physician with four detectives came up to me and
            demanded to be given a synopsis of the lecture before I was allowed to proceed. I would
            have made a fight for free speech then and there, but the friends interested preferred
            to let it go that way.</p>
        <p>In Detroit over nine hundred pledges to form a <org reg="Detroit Birth Control League"
                >League</org> were given, and a very enthusiastic meeting was held. Several women
            doctors there expressed a wish for clinics to be formed, and it is to be looked for
            soon. The nurses in St. Paul were greatly interested. I addressed one of the nurses'
            societies, and a clinic is on its way there also. Minneapolis, as well as St. Paul, have
            two strong Leagues carrying on educational work on Birth Control.</p>
        <p><org>The Ramsey County Medical Society</org> of <place reg="St. Paul, MN">St.
                Paul</place> refused to allow me to speak before them, though several members of the
            Society had requested me to do so; but in Indianapolis the interest was tremendous--all
            social workers--and all had been feeling the terrible need for this work for years.
            Nevertheless, the Catholic element was strong in the meeting, and when one woman rose to
            ask me "<q who="UNK">What about the order from the Divine book?--'suffer the little
                children to come unto Me</q>,'" the house went into a rage with her. They--the
            social workers, always on the fence in any really vital issue--actually hissed the woman
            down, and also every other opponent who dared to raise his head against birth control
            that day. It was thrilling. Then after the conference the women living in the city
            formed a <org reg="Minnesota Birth Control League">League</org> there, and a very
            representative group was interested.</p>
        <p>St. Louis was the best of all. Another <person reg="Taylor, Clara">Russian girl</person>,
            a social settlement worker, arranged the meeting for me and engaged a <org
                reg="Victoria Theater">theatre</org>. When we arrived, however, the doors of the
            theatre were closed, and the <person reg="Markham, W. C.">manager</person> said he was
            compelled to do it, as the Catholics in St. Louis had threatened to boycott him if he
            allowed me to speak there. They had offered to pay any loss he might be put to if I sued
            him for breach of contract. They also issued the same orders to all other managers of
            theatres and halls, and for two days friends hunted all over that city for a place to
            speak in. Two private meetings had been arranged, however, one at the <org
                reg="St. Louis Men's City Club">City Club</org>, where the business men dine each
            week, the other at a <org reg="St. Louis Women's Town Club">Women's Dinner Club</org>.
            Both were filled to their utmost capacity, and it was said that neither Taft nor
            Roosevelt had had such a big attendance. Forty Catholic members of the men's club
            resigned that day. I am going back this winter to fight it out with St. Louis.</p>
        <p>At Denver I had the pleasure of having Judge <person reg="Lindsay, Benjamin Barr"
                >Lindsey</person> act as chairman of the meeting. The women there were splendid, and
            took a very active interest in establishing a clinic at once.</p>
        <p>At Los Angeles a <org reg="Los Angeles Birth Control League">league</org> had been formed
            at the time of my trial. It was doing fairly good work, but needed a bit of a push. Five
            hundred women signed their willingness to join the league at one meeting. We had two
            public meetings, both overcrowded, and two private meetings at women's clubs. They are
            getting "<title type="book">Family Limitation</title>" translated into Japanese and
            Mexican.</p>
        <p>In San Francisco I had a collapse, and was three days in bed under medical care, but
            recovered sufficiently to hold six meetings. Two prominent medical men are at the head
            of the league there, and it is hoped there will soon be a clinic formed.</p>
        <p>In Portland a Birth Control League has been established since the publication of "<title
                type="book">Family Limitation</title>," and has been doing very splendid work. They
            reprinted the pamphlet, and have given away thousands of them. They have also held
            educational meetings each month, at which Mr. <person reg="Uthoff, H. C."
                >Uthoff</person> and <person reg="Dekker, Meta M.">his wife</person> conducted. They
            asked very specially about <person reg="Drysdale, Charles Vickery"><person
                    reg="Drysdale, Bessie Ingham">you</person></person>, and are deeply interested
            in the subject from the theoretical point of view, and, I think, would like to carry on
            that side of the work rather than the actual giving of information. When I arrived there
            one of the men in the labor movement asked me if he could sell the revised pamphlet at
            my meeting. I said I had no objection, providing it did not interfere with the rules of
            the league. To make a long story short, it was sold, and <person reg="Chervin, Ralph"
                    ><person reg="Jenkins, E. L."><person reg="Rave, Carl">three of the
                    men</person></person></person> were arrested. They were allowed out on bail, and
            a postponement of the trial was permitted so that I could deliver my lectures in Seattle
            and Spokane and return to be called as a special witness for them. On my return, I found
            that the <org reg="Portland City Council">City Council</org> (the <person
                reg="Albee, H. Russell">Mayor</person> a Puritan) had met in secret and passed an
            ordinance against that special pamphlet. This action on the part of five men enraged all
            the women in Portland, and they issued leaflets, saying: "<q who="UNK">Shall five men
                legislate in secret against ten thousand women?</q>" Then one of the women doctors
            revised the pamphlet on "<title type="book">Family Limitation</title>," and at the
            protest meeting on the night before the men's trial, I asked for women volunteers to
            sell the pamphlet. Ten women came forward, and four of us were arrested -- the <person
                reg="Equi, Marie">doctor</person>, myself, and two English women living there. We
            spent the night in jail, all of us refusing to accept bail, saying: "Let those who put
            us in take us out."</p>
        <p>The next day the trial of the seven of us took place, and I want to say that it was
            simply magnificent. <person reg="Swett, Isaac"><person reg="Wood, Charles Erskine Scott"
                    >Two lawyers</person></person> came and offered their services, and took the
            case without anyone's consent. They were both men of the old democratic type, trying to
            keep a few of the old principles of democracy alive. We had nothing to say about
            consulting a lawyer: they just went ahead and were splendid. It would be impossible for
            me to give you the details of that trial, but one of the significant things was that no
            one took an oath. We all refused to swear, and by the afternoon session the officers in
            charge did not even ask us to. Both pamphlets were on trial, the first and the second. I
            enclose them both. Both were considered "obscene." We were all found "guilty" and the
            men fined ten dollars, which the <person reg="Langguth, Arthur">judge</person> said they
            need not pay, and the women were not fined at all. The interest was intense, the room
            packed. On the day before we had fifteen men with ten transparencies walking up and down
            the streets with such sentences as "<q who="UNK">Poverty and large families go hand in
                hand</q>," "<q who="UNK">Poor women are denied what the rich possess</q>." I don't
            remember them all, but each was good and to the point. It took the judge a week to
            decide the case, and in the meantime letters were pouring into the press, and thousands
            of requests for the pamphlets came to all of us.</p>
        <p>In Seattle also a <org reg="Seattle Birth Control League">league</org> had been formed
            since a year ago, and had been doing educational as well as practical work. The two
            lectures there were good in every way. In Spokane the lecture was given in the Unitarian
            Church, which was crowded, and a league was formed the next day.</p>
        <p>I distributed over twenty thousand pamphlets on my trip, and had over one thousand
            letters from St. Louis alone. Women came to me in the hotels with babies in their arms;
            men ready for work, carrying their lunch baskets, came early to get a little private
            advice before I left. The farm women way down in <place>Texas</place> and
                <place>Arizona</place> who never got out to a lecture or meeting of any kind were
            the ones whom I cared most to reach; their letters were most touching and tragic.</p>
        <p>On my way back, the Cleveland League gave a banquet for me, and the interest in the work
            was very earnest.</p>
        <p>On my arrival in New York I found to my dismay another meeting before me. A young man
            named <person reg="Allison, Van Kleeck">Van Kleick Allison</person>, of <place
                reg="Boston, MA">Boston</place> Mass., had been arrested and just received a three
            year sentence in the House of Correction for giving a detective a leaflet on Birth
            Control. I wired him to have the case appealed. He did so. Then they had a protest
            meeting in one of the theatres there, and I went to offer up my wee voice in that. It
            was one of the greatest meetings I ever attended. They now have a good <org
                reg="Allison Defense League">Defence League</org>, and I trust they will make things
            hum there in Boston. The <person reg="Murray, Michael J.">Judge</person> who sentenced
            Allison was a Roman Catholic, as was also the District Attorney and all those who were
            on the prosecution!</p>
        <p>So this is a brief summary of the trip and the meetings. I consider we have a big
            movement started from coast to coast, and I hope to open a free clinic here in New York
            City in September, and also get out a regular monthly paper dealing with Birth Control
            from all points of view. I trust you are all well. There is a great interest in you both
            here, and when I mentioned to several Leaguers that we might get you both here this
            winter, or early in the spring, there was great enthusiasm. I am certain splendid
            meetings could be arranged for you as soon as the Leagues get into shape. I am anxious
            for the people here to get your ideas of population straight from you. There are three
            arrests here in New York pending trial in the fall. So it looks as though we should have
            another winter of fighting the ignorance which keeps every great movement backward.</p>
        <p>The pamphlet "<title type="book">Family Limitation</title>" has been pirated by many, and
            is being sold from house to house, as well as from shop to shop in the small towns, in
            factory and mill. Heaven only knows what the Churches will do in another generation if
            this keeps up!</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
