<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger"  "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published interview">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2012-02-07 EK</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2012-02-08 CH proof and correct</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Earl Conrad</docAuthor>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1945-09-22">22 Sept 1945</docDate>
        <docTitle>
           <titlePart>On U.S. Birth and Bias Control</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp320145</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Chicago Defender</title>, Sep 22, 1945, p. 11</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp><name id="CONEA">Conrad, Earl</name><name id="UNK"
                    >Unknown</name></resp>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
        <index level1="African-Americans" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="African-Americans"
            level2="maternal mortality rates among"/>
        <index level1="African-Americans" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/>
        <index level1="African-Americans" level2="discrimination"/>
        <index level1="child spacing"/>
        <index level1="racial/ethnic references" level2="to African-Americans"/>
        <index level1="Southern States"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>AMERICAN VIEWPOINT<lb/> On U.S. Birth and Bias Control</head>
        <byline>by <person reg="Conrad, Earl">Earl Conrad</person></byline>
        <byline>Defender, <place reg="New York, NY">New York</place>
            Bureau</byline>
        <div>
            <p><q who="CONEA"><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret
                        Sanger</person>, the elderly battle-axe of planned
                    parenthood--better known as birth control--has sound and
                    emancipated views of the Negro-white situation.</q></p>
            <p><q who="CONEA">I interviewed the 58-year-old, gray-haired, lively
                    woman, with the lined face and eager interest in things, in
                    the offices of the <org>Planned Parenthood Federation of
                        America</org> here.</q></p>
            <p><q who="CONEA">In recent years Miss Sanger has let down from the
                    great energies she gave to her idea in an earlier period.
                    She estimates that she has made about 67,000 speeches for
                    birth control--addresses all over <place>America</place>, in
                        <place>Europe</place> and the <place>Orient</place>. It
                    was nothing to speak five or ten times a day.</q></p>
            <p><q who="CONEA">Her home is in <place reg="Tucson, Arizona"
                        >Tucson, Ariz</place>., now, where she is more or less
                    in retirement, and where she awaits the return from the
                    armed service of her two doctor <person reg="Sanger, Stuart">
                        <person reg="Sanger, Grant">sons</person></person>. But
                    she was in New York long enough to see <person
                        reg="Buck, Pearl">Pearl Buck</person>, Mrs. <person
                        reg="Roosevelt, Eleanor">Eleanor Roosevelt</person> and
                    other women who have supported her in her fight for planned
                    home life, and I managed to get an hour with her.</q></p>
        </div>

        <div>
            <head type="sub">Called “Fanatic”</head>
            <p><q who="CONEA">“Say, Miss Sanger,” I asked “what was the magazine
                    that once referred to you as a fanatic? Was it the <title
                        type="journal">Nation</title> or the <title
                        type="journal">New Republic</title>?”</q></p>
            <p>“I am afraid it was every magazine in the country,” she replied
                with a smile.</p>
            <p><q who="CONEA">Seated opposite me, in a small office of the
                    federation, Miss Sanger seemed like the most unprepossessing
                    of individuals. She wore a plain, blue cotton dress, a
                    simple blue hat, and a wrist watch that she looked at once
                    or twice.</q></p>
            <p>"<q who="CONEA">How many times did you go to jail, Mrs.
                    Sanger?</q>"</p>
            <p>“Eight times,” <q who="CONEA">she answered</q> “Never for long.
                It always gave me a much-needed rest, however.”</p>
            <p><q who="CONEA">Like <person reg="Anthony, Susan B.">Susan
                        Anthony</person> who fought for woman suffrage, <person
                        reg="Tubman, Harriet">Harriet Tubman</person> who
                    battled for the abolition of chattel slavery, and <person
                        reg="Nation, Carrie">Carrie Nation</person> who carried
                    the torch for prohibition, Miss Sanger belongs to a small
                    and unique line of American women pioneers.</q></p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Views on Negro</head>
            <p><q who="CONEA">When, before World War I, Miss Sanger launched her
                    famous idea of curtailing the size of families in order to
                    safeguard mothers and children against poverty, disease,
                    crime and miserable home life, she was attacked by
                    “respectable” society. She was insulted, stoned, jailed--but
                    she went on with her work until her idea is a
                    widely-accepted institution in America and in other parts of
                    the world.</q></p>
            <p><q who="CONEA">Miss Sanger views the problems of the American
                    Negro as part of a world problem.</q></p>
            <p>“They are not separate problems,” <q who="CONEA">she says.</q>
                “It is not just a Negro problem. Like the problems of the people
                of <place>India</place>, of minorities everywhere, it is a
                democratic problem. We have got to work all together on these
                issues.”</p>
            <p><q who="CONEA">She likened the attitude of most of the white
                    North toward the Negro to that of the British attitude
                    toward the Indian peoples. “I like to think of it that way;
                    as a concept of superiority over others.</q>”</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">White Man’s Power</head>
            <p>“I’ve traveled in India and <place>China</place>,” <q
                    who="CONEA">she said.</q> “Knowing our own problem, it gave
                me greater sympathy with the others, with what I saw in the
                Orient. I can recall many horrible things I saw in India. I once
                saw a white man come out of a train; there were five or six
                Indians in his way; he just kicked them away--literally, with
                his foot. There were a hundred people around, who were powerless
                to strike him. The white man’s power and the Indian’s
                defenselessness were so unjust.</p>
            <p>“In <place>China</place>, the Chinese could not go on ‘our’
                property. A Chinese doctor was not allowed to see me, couldn’t
                come into the American area. Discrimination is a world-wide
                thing. It has to be opposed everywhere. That is why I feel the
                Negro’s plight here is linked with that of the oppressed around
                the globe.</p>
            <p>“The big answer, as I see it, is the education of the white man.
                The white man is the problem. It is the same as with the Nazis.
                We must change the white attitudes. That is where it lies.”</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Change for Better</head>
            <p><q who="CONEA">I asked Miss Sanger how she had encountered the
                    Negro question in her own special sphere.</q></p>
            <p>“From the very beginning of birth control, there was the problem
                of approaching the Negro. Soon after I launched the campaign, a
                    <place>Harlem</place>
                <person reg="Unknown">Methodist leader</person>, who was most
                intelligent, questioned me about birth control. He was a
                brilliant speaker, and he had been thinking about it. Later a
                man named <person reg="Harrison, Hubert">Harrison</person> of
                the <org reg="Urban League, New York City">Urban League</org>
                took up our idea.”</p>
            <p>“<q who="CONEA">Have you seen any change in the Negro-white
                    situation generally since the times of your pioneer days?” I
                    wanted to know.</q></p>
            <p>“I think things have changed for the better. There is a changed
                attitude among employers, I believe.”</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Offered Bribe</head>
            <p>“The Negro has made great progress. Harlem is an example. When we
                started out in Harlem with birth control, we couldn’t get a
                colored physician. Now there is much less of a problem in
                reaching Harlem physicians with planned parenthood. I think this
                shows how things have advanced.</p>
            <p>“Here is another example of how attitudes have changed. When we
                first started out an <person reg="Unknown">anti-Negro white
                    man</person> offered me $10,000 if I started in Harlem
                first. His idea was simply to cut down the number of Negroes.
                    ‘<q who="UNK">Spread it as far as you can among them,</q>’
                he said. That is, of course, not our idea. I turned him down.
                But that is an example of how vicious some people can be about
                this thing.</p>
            <p>“It is our experience, as it was our aim, that as a result of
                child-spacing and adequate care of mothers, death rates would be
                reduced. It is now a fact that as a result of birth control, the
                survival rate among mothers and children is higher. There is
                less sufferings for all groups.”</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Tells of Tucson</head>
            <p><q who="CONEA">Miss Sanger based her views of the general
                    situation on her own broad experience and travel. She spoke
                    of Tucson, Ariz.</q></p>
            <p>“It is not so bad there,”<q who="CONEA"> she said. </q>“There is
                no Jim Crow in the theatres, and the restaurants serve Negroes
                equally with whites. But there is some overflow of southern idea
                into the state and supremacist feeling can be found there.”</p>
            <p><q who="CONEA">I asked her to recall some experience from her own
                    travel in the South.</q></p>
            <p>“Yes,” <q who="CONEA">she said, </q>“I remember addressing a
                colored church group once. I was staying with a <person
                    reg="Unknown">white doctor</person> at the time. They didn’t
                let a Negro doctor introduce me to the people. The white doctor
                had to do it. That was in <place reg="Memphis, TN"
                    >Memphis</place>.”</p>
            <p>“What hangs over the South is that the Negro has been in
                servitude. The white southerner is slow to forget this. His
                attitude is the archaic in this age. Supremacist thinking
                belongs in the museum.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Breaking Barriers</head>
            <p>“One thing that is most helpful is to have people working
                together. When you have Negroes working with whites you have the
                breakdown of barriers, the beginning of progress. Negro groups
                must take the initiative, and not wait around for integration to
                come to them. They must get it themselves. The struggle for it
                will bring it.”</p>
            <p><q who="CONEA">I thought that she had spoken well enough and
                    broadly enough on the general situation and then asked her
                    about planned parenthood--for Miss Sanger has more to give
                    the Negro than ideas; she has the gift of her own famous
                    plan.</q></p>
            <p><q who="CONEA">“What can the Negro group do in connection with
                    planned parenthood?” I asked.</q></p>
            <p>“In the first place, the Negro leaders should understand it. It
                is a basic principle for a sound healthy race. Leaders should
                have the courage in their respective communities to stand for
                the idea. Planned parenthood is not aimed at any one people. It
                is for all, and the objective is to do away with the waste of
                life</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Cites Death Rate</head>
            <p>“A sickly race is a weak race. As long as Negro mothers die in
                childbirth at two and one-half times the rate of white mothers,
                as long as Negro babies are dying at twice the rate of white
                babies, colored homes will be unhappy.</p>
            <p>“Greater understanding and practice of planned parenthood,
                through the use of contraceptive methods prescribed by doctors
                and clinics, will mean that there will be more strong and
                healthy children and fewer defective and handicapped babies
                unable to find a useful or happy place in life.</p>
            <p>“Planned parenthood does not mean using contraceptives not to
                have babies. It means using medically prescribed methods so that
                each member of the family will come into life in good health and
                wanted by its parents.</p>
            <p>“Years ago the first emphasis of birth control was on family
                limitation and it still is in advising those parents to whom
                another child might mean death of the mother or added misery.
                Since then, however, planned parenthood has shifted its emphasis
                to child-spacing--allowing each mother needed rest and
                recuperation between each birth.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Aid Childless Couples</head>
            <p>“More recently planned parenthood has come to include treatment
                of infertility for childless couples who want children but have
                been unable to have them.”</p>
            <p><q who="CONEA">Miss Sanger said that planned parenthood is not
                    “quack medicine,” but a widely-approved measure.</q> “Most
                doctors now believe in it and it has been approved by both the
                    <org>American Medical Association</org> and the
                    <org>National Medical Association</org>,” she pointed
                out.</p>
            <p><q who="CONEA">In conclusion she said: </q>“The extension of
                planned parenthood to reach millions of colored families now
                handicapped for lack of this knowledge is not a panacea for all
                the ills of the race.</p>
            <p>“But planned parenthood, together with x-rays for tuberculosis,
                penicillin for other maladies, venereal disease control and
                other health measures can help the Negro family to attain a
                position of greater strength and security in America.</p>
            <p>“Negro participation in planned parenthood means democratic
                participation in a democratic idea. Like other democratic ideas,
                planned parenthood places greater value on human life and the
                dignity of each person. Without planning at birth, the life of
                Negroes as a whole in a democratic world cannot be planned.”</p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
