<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2001-10-26 MH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2002-08-20 KH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2003/12/08 CH fix codes</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007-05-30 CH Oxygen cleanup</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-05 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1911-12-24">24 Dec 1911</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Dirt, Smell and Sweat</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp320124</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">New York Call</title>, Dec. 24, 1911, 15</bibl>
            <bibl></bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="WEEAN">Weeks, Anna Ross</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
        <index level1="woman suffrage" level2="working women and"/>
        <index level1="Woman's Suffrage Party"/>
        <index level1="woman suffrage" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="working classes" level2="women and girls"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="freedom and rights of"/>
        <index level1="socialism"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>DIRT, SMELL AND SWEAT</head>
        <p>Editor Woman's Sphere:</p>
        <p>At a meeting of the <org reg="New York City Woman's Suffrage Party ">Woman's Suffrage
                party</org> of the 27th Assembly District a few days ago a tall, beautiful and
            charming woman named <person reg="Weeks, Anna Ross">Mrs. Weeks</person>, acted as
            chairman of the meeting. In what was called her maiden speech, she mentioned among other
            things that the men who objected to woman's voting because she would be obliged to bump
            against the dirty, smelly and sweaty men at the polls, evidently did not object to her
            bumping against them at other times; they objected only on Election Day and at the
            ballot box. Then she offered the following suggestion as a cure for this objection. "<q
                who="WEEAN">to remove the dirty, smelling, sweaty men from the polls," so that she
                and her class could vote undisturbed.</q></p>
        <p>But what about the women who are liable to be just as dirty, smelly and sweaty as their
            working brothers? Are they, too, to be removed? Dirt is dirt, smell is smell, and sweat
            is sweat, no matter on whom these unfortunate afflictions happen to be. And if the
            chairman and her class object to the smell of the workingman, so will they object to the
            smell of the working woman.</p>
        <p>Throughout the meeting the atmosphere was laden with class arguments. Such nice and
            polite and kind arguments in favor of the women in the home, who need the ballot to get
            CLEAN milk, clean streets and fresh air. Not one word about the millions of women driven
            out of the home into the factories and shops. Never a word about the women who cannot
            give any kind of milk to their children, but give them black tea and coffee and sell the
            milk and cream to her own class. These women and these conditions have not been
            considered by the Woman's Suffrage party, and it is doubtful if they will consider them
            until the working woman stands shoulder to shoulder with her working brother for the
            emancipation of her class.</p>
        <p>The only thing which seems to concern this chairman and her followers is POLITICAL
            FREEDOM. No other kind of freedom enters into their arguments. For instance, she spoke
            of the men who say the women who are suffragists smoke cigarettes. This she hotly denied
            by saying it is the anti-suffragist who smokes! Did she stop to ask why any woman,
            suffragist or anti-suffragist, should not smoke as well as a man if she cared to? Not
            she. The idea of emancipating woman from any of the narrow conventionalities of the dark
            ages has not yet dawned upon the minds of these women. </p>
        <p>The idea of making woman's sphere "<q who="UNK">unlimited, unbounded</q>," as the
            Socialist women are striving for, has so far scarcely entered their craniums. </p>
        <p>The working women evidently are not aware that POLITICAL FREEDOM does not mean INDUSTRIAL
            FREEDOM and it is the object and desire of Socialist women to show the working woman
            that Socialism stands not only for her political freedom, but for her industrial freedom
            and her intellectual freedom. All three with one stroke of the pen can be gained and
            given to her by the <org reg="Socialist Party of America">Socialist party</org>. </p>
        <p>When the workingman shall be paid the full value of his labor he can then emancipate
            himself from dirt, smell and sweat. If he had the full product of his labor he would
            have the time and place to get and keep clean. If he were not robbed of the product of
            his toil by the master class, to which the chairman of that meeting belongs, he could
            have a clean coat, instead of wearing one either already bought second-hand, or given
            him by the charity organizations. No wonder it is smelly.</p>
        <p>Let any woman who labors for her bread enter any of these meetings and see what there is
            in this movement for her benefit, and she will be made to realize that there is no more
            for her in political freedom alone than there has been for her brother who has had his
            political rights for some time.</p>
        <p>Unless the women will use their political rights in the interest of their class, they
            will be no more free from dirt, smell and sweat than their brothers in the working
            class, and will find themselves liable to the same treatment at the hands of their
            "sisters" of the upper class.</p>
        <byline>Margaret H. Sanger.</byline>
    </docBody>
</doc>
