<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2001-10-29 MH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2002-08-27 KH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/07 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007-05-30 CH Oxygen cleanup</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-05 CH clean up regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1913-04-15">15 Apr 1913</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Hazleton Strikers Repudiate A.F. of L.</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp320120</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Solidarity</title>, Apr. 19, 1913</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="CONSA">Conboy, Sarah</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
        <index level1="labor movement" level2="Hazleton, PA Strike, 1913"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="arrests and imprisonment"/> 
        <index level1="Industrial Workers of the World"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head><place reg="Hazleton, PA">HAZLETON</place> STRIKERS REPUDIATE <org
                reg="American Federation of Labor">A.F. OF L.</org></head>
        <head type="sub">(Special to <title type="journal">Solidarity</title>.)</head>
        <dateline>Hazleton, Pa., <date value="1913-04-15">April 15.</date></dateline>
        <p>The strike of the Duplan Silk Workers, at Hazleton, Pa., is still on, in spite of the
            fact that Mrs. <person reg="Conboy, Sarah">Sarah Conboy</person>, general organizer for
            the <org>United Textile Workers of America</org>, tried to break the strike by drawing
            up a contract in which the mill bosses agreed to give the strikers a raise of from 5 to
            10 cents a week.</p>
        <p>Evidently their generosity became painful to them, and they injected a clause whereby
            even this "slap in the face" raise could be taken from them at the discretion of the
            bosses. Most of the workers are little boys and girls who range in age from 14 to 18
            years. This is their first strike, and they all claim that they have learned more in
            seven weeks on strike, than their fathers or mothers learned in ten years.</p>
        <p>When running full force there are about 1,200 workers in the mill, and to date there are
            about 300 back to work.</p>
        <p>The papers, as usual, lie and slander the <org reg="Industrial Workers of the World "
                >I.W.W.</org> The church, with all its influence, preaches in the pulpit against the
            organization, using its influence to send the boys and girls who have stood out for nine
            weeks firmly against the boss, back to work for a few cents' raise a week. The contract
            signed by Mrs. Conboy and her A. F. of L. organization speaks for itself as a cowardly,
            dastardly, sell out.</p>
        <p>Everything was going to be in readiness last Monday to resume work. The boys and girls
            requested <person reg="Flynn, Elizabeth Gurley">Elizabeth Gurley Flynn</person> to come
            and explain the signed contract to those who live so far away that they cannot attend
            the daily meetings. The <org>Family Theatre</org> was packed to the doors and a lively
            and enthusiastic meeting resulted.</p>
        <p>When some of the opposition pushed their way into the hall and asked to be heard, it was
            all that <person reg="Gergotz, Louis">Louis Gergotz</person>, the chairman, could do to
            get the floor for them. He plead with the boys and girls to give them a hearing. That
            they were there only to break up the meeting was evident, for insult after insult was
            thrown at the I. W. W. speakers, which only incited the wrath of the audience. The trick
            was to break up the meeting, arrest the speakers and intimidate the workers so that they
            would all return to work Monday, the following day. The trick failed.</p>
        <p>Another meeting was held that night for the parents, many of whom are miners; and the
            Italians, where E. G. Flynn and <person reg="Tresca, Carlo">Carlo Tresca</person> again
            spoke.</p>
        <p>On Monday morning there were almost 5,000 pickets and sympathizers around the <org
                reg="Duplan Silk Works">mill</org>. The whole force of mill bosses, political
            bosses, and heelers joined forces with Mrs. Conboy at the mill gates, begging the
            workers to return "<q who="CONSA">where you belong</q>" as Mrs. Conboy said.</p>
        <p>The youngsters snapped their fingers in their faces and proceeded to another big meeting
            in which they declared the strike was still on, and they would remain out until their
            demands were granted.</p>
        <p>The next day the police began their dirty work of arresting crowds of pickets for
            "loitering," which means when the police tell you to "stop" you are arrested for
            "loitering." Twenty-six of us altogether were arrested in one day. Very few fines were
            paid; all agreed we would pay not a cent in fines.</p>
        <p>The political boss, <person reg="McKelvey, Daniel">McKelvey</person>, holds several
            positions in Hazleton. At 7 A.M. he's at the mill gate in the capacity of a county
            detective, who may arrest anyone. At 9 o'clock you may be confronted with Mr. McKelvey
            in the capacity of alderman, acting as judge to sentence the one previously
            arrested.</p>
        <p>The last card is being played Monday next, when <person reg="Golden, John">John
                Golden</person> has been invited to explain the contract to those I.W.W. and A. F.
            of L. silk workers, not allowing I.W.W. organizers within the hall. The boys and girls
            wired <person reg="Haywood, William D.">Big Bill Haywood</person> to come and hold a
            meeting the same night and explain the contract, and invite everyone--including John
            Golden. </p>
        <p>The little town is all excitement. The strike has been a wonderful eyeopener to all
            workers, including the miners. Some of the mine locals have promised to stop work and go
            on picket duty with the boys and girls next Monday.</p>
        <p>Keep your eye on Hazleton, fellow workers, and watch results.</p>
        <byline><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret H. Sanger</person>.</byline>
    </docBody>
</doc>
