<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
<mepHeader>
<prepDate>2003-12-17</prepDate>
<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
<docDate value="1926-02-00">Feb. 1926</docDate>
<docTitle>
<titlePart>Passports for Babies </titlePart>
</docTitle>
<idno>msp320229</idno>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title type="journal">Holland's Magazine</title>
</bibl>
<bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Papers Microfilm</title>C16:278</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
<respStmt>
<resp/>
<name id="PUSWI">William Allen Pusey</name>
<name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
<name id="INGWI">William Inge</name>
<name id="BIB">Bible</name>
</respStmt>
</mepHeader>
<headNote resp="MSPP">For typed draft version see LCM 130:461. <index level1="eugenics"
level2="MS on"/>
<index level1="eugenics" level2="negative"/>
<index level1="eugenics" level2="positive"/>
<index level1="&quot;unfit&quot; to reproduce" level2="descriptions of"/>
<index level1="&quot;unfit&quot; to reproduce" level2="MS on"/>
<index level1="birth control" level2="medical community and"/>
<index level1="working classes" level2="birth control and"/>
</headNote>
<docBody>
<head>Passports for Babies.</head>
<byline>By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></byline>
<p>"<q who="UNK">Of course</q>," said the distinguished professor, "<q who="UNK">we all believe in
Birth Control. There is no need to talk about it. The trouble in this country is that those who can
afford to have large families limit the number of their children, while the unfit keep steadily on
recklessly populating our lunatic asylums with imbeciles, idiots, and morons, and providing our
prisons with inmates</q>.</p>
<p>"<q who="UNK">The trouble with you people</q>," continued the professor, "<q who="UNK">is that
you do not reach those who should be taught the hygiene and technique of contraception. The only way
to strike a balance is for the normal, healthy, fit elements of American society to have large
families, so that our country won't be swamped by the unfit</q>." The professor, by the way, seemed
to have forgotten that he himself was "fit," healthy, wealthy--the father of only two children.</p>
<p>"I see what you mean," I answered. "A sort of cradle competition between the fit and the
unfit."</p>
<p>"<q who="UNK">Call it what you will</q>," he retorted.</p>
<p>"How long would the fit remain fit," I asked, "if they entered this race, full speed ahead,
bringing children into the world without any thought of spacing their offspring or providing them
with food, shelter, and education? Did you ever stop to think, my dear doctor, that perhaps the
'fit,' as you call them--the better classes, the mental and physical aristocrats--may have risen
from the ranks of poverty precisely because they have limited their families?</p>
<p>"They remain 'fit' because they exercise foresight, respect good breeding, insist that their own
children have an even better chance in life than they had. What is such discipline and sacrifice but
Birth Control? Now you advocate the very opposite policy in family ethics. Would you encourage the
best families to spawn children with reckless and irresponsible rapidity? Are you not holding the
worst elements in our society up to them as examples? But no sane or thoughtful parents would follow
your advice."</p>
<p>"<q who="UNK">Perhaps not</q>," he admitted reluctantly. "<q who="UNK">But how do you expect to
get your message of Birth Control to the people who need it? To the ignorant, the irresponsible, the
poverty-stricken</q>?"</p>
<p>"It can and must be done," I answered. "All that we need is the cooperation of intelligent
serious-minded American citizens."</p>
<p>In the dozen years I have been battling for the liberation of motherhood through Birth Control,
the professor's question has arisen almost daily.</p>
<p>In this paper I shall try to explain how this is possible, to show how the various obstacles that
stand in the way of the widespread dissemination of this new education in hygiene and sanitation may
ultimately be overcome.</p>
<p>The foremost duty of every American is to aid in the creation of a healthy, vigorous race of
Americans. If the American citizen remains passively indifferent to the obstacles which are now
obstructing the road to the fulfillment of our racial destiny, he cannot be called a good
citizen.</p>
<p>The chief obstacles at present are various state and federal laws forbidding the dissemination of
contraceptive information, even by physicians. Yet in many states, including <place>Texas</place>,
<place>Colorado</place>, <place>Utah</place>, <place>New Mexico</place>, <place>Illinois</place>,
and others, there is no such prohibition for physicians. These states are indeed fortunate in having
escaped the blight of this near-sighted, hypocritical type of legislation fundamentally in conflict
with constitutional rights of life, liberty, and the pursuit of happiness. Such ill-advised
enactments implicitly deny the right of every American child to be well-born, the right of every
child to be born with an equal opportunity of development, or to be born under conditions
guaranteeing to each a fair chance of education and growth into a sturdy American citizen, instead
of being foredoomed from birth to become a burden upon and a menace to our national development.</p>
<p>In such fortunate states as Texas, for instance, there is only the obstacle of public
indifference and inertia, and the opposition of reactionaries and perhaps certain religious
organizations. Granted that it would be possible to inaugurate a maternity school or clinic of the
type already successful in such countries as <place reg="the Netherlands">Holland</place> and
<place>Great Britain</place>, what is the next step?</p>
<p>At this point it is necessary to revise our ideas of the place of the physician in any American
community. It is said that in <place>China</place> you pay the doctor to keep you well. In our
country, the family physician is, as a rule, called only in cases of illness or emergency. To-day we
are beginning to change our whole attitude about doctors. It is not a very rash prediction to assert
that more and more we shall appeal to the doctor as a counselor of health rather than to seek
remedies for petty maladies.</p>
<p>To a certain extent this is the actual present situation of the relation of physician and
patient. Nowadays most young wives who are approaching the threshold of maternity go to the doctor
for advice concerning the problems of gestation. He counsels her concerning diet, exercise, rest,
and all such problems. These frequent consultations between the mother-to-be and her physician are
hygienic precautions in the interest of the mother's well-being and the baby's health.</p>
<p>Surely there is nothing shocking in the idea that parents should extend the period of these
consultations still further back. In other words, that they should ask the doctor's advice even
before the conception of the child, and even before marriage, so that before this hazardous task is
undertaken, the health of the parents, as well as their economic, physical, and spiritual health may
be assured.</p>
<p>In other words, I believe that the day is not far distant when the physician shall be as
intimately concerned in the matter of marriage-making and the task of parenthood as is the
clergyman, the county, or the lawyer to-day.</p>
<p>The more one thinks of this possibility, the more inevitable it seems as the next necessary step
of American civilization. For what does civilization mean if not the increasing command of and
control over all the factors of human life? And control of reproduction, mastery of the quantity and
the quality of the very stuff of life, the raw material of civilization, is the very first of these
factors. Animals are not permitted by breeders to bear young when they are unfit. Surely American
babies--not some of them, but every last one of them--should be assured the birthright of being as
well born and as well cared for as calves and pigs!</p>
<p>As long as they do not involve the future of the race, and therefore the future of our great
country, it may be admitted that the intimate relationships of married life are no one's business
but the participants. But when a new life is concerned, when it is a question of brining no just a
baby, but a new citizen into this county, all should be willing to accept the best biological advice
concerning the proper time, place, and environment for this all-important event.</p>
<p>Our federal government is now beginning to take precautions about immigration, permitting only
properly qualified foreigners to enter our gates, and those only in restricted numbers. And yet
within our gates, our chaotic laws and traditional prejudices encourage the entrance into these
<place>United States</place> of ill-born, unfit, undesirable citizens. Poor little victims who have
neither pedigree nor passport!</p>
<p>This situation has suggested to my mind that it should be a point of honor with all American
parents that babies should be provided with health passports!</p>
<p>Passports for babies, beginning their perilous, adventurous voyage into this stormy old world of
ours would insure at least a happy arrival, for such passports would mean that the baby had been
conceived in love, born of a health mother's conscious desire, and bringing with it the heritage of
health.</p>
<p>The duty of the physician would be to represent the unborn child, to stand as the representative
of public health and racial purity, and to offer his benevolent advice as spokesman for the
child-to-be.</p>
<p>Sometimes, in moments of idle revery, I have wondered what would happen if there were some sort
of a baby bureau, to which all prospective parents would have to apply and answer the questions of
the unborn. You would have to apply at these bureaus for a baby, just as you apply at an employment
bureau for a cook, and there the wise baby-to-be would ask for references, and make certain, before
it undertook the hazards of Life's voyage, that these parents were desirable, the possessors of a
happy home, and really desirous of a new baby. Think of the question an intelligent baby might ask.
For instance:</p>
<p>"Have you paid for your last baby yet?"</p>
<p>"How many children have you already? Are you sure your hands are not already too full, and your
pocketbook empty? What are your plans for bringing me up?</p>
<p>"Can you furnish a happy home for me? Proper food? A sunny nursery? Love and affection and
understanding?</p>
<p>"Can you furnish a certificate of health?</p>
<p>"Do you look upon children as a reward or a penalty?</p>
<p>"What's that you say? Five children already? Two dark rooms in the slums? No! Thank you! I don't
care to be born at all if I cannot choose to be well-born. Good-bye!"</p>
<p>So the interview might be abruptly terminated if all parents had to apply for babies at a sort of
bureau of the unborn. Since such a bureau is nothing but a fantastic impossibility, the best
substitute we can suggest is that the family physician act as attorney for the new generations to
come.</p>
<p>If the physician, the woman doctor as well as the man, could be a true counselor of racial as
well as individual health for every husband and wife, not only from the beginning of marriage, but
even before, there would be no need of enacting new laws of a compulsory or prohibitive nature.
Instead, there would be a frank, honest relationship, not only between this counselor and his
clients, but a finer, more unselfish, and therefore more enduring, love between husband and
wife.</p>
<p>For instead of merely concerning himself with the petty ailments of his patients, the physician
would become more of a true creative educator in the difficult science of marriage and
parenthood.</p>
<p>But, the reader may object, you are not telling us how to reach those parents who cannot afford
the counsels of such a physician and are so sunk in the mire of poverty that they would not know
such advice could be obtained?</p>
<p>In the first place, the objection that one cannot reach the parents who most need to be
instructed in Birth Control is without foundation in fact. As I pointed out in my first article
published in these pages, thousands of poor conscript mothers throughout the country are clamoring
for emancipation from their endless slavery of involuntary maternity. Not only do they appeal
directly to me by the thousands every year, they appeal to doctors, to hospitals, to clinics, to
maternity centers, to the directors of settlement houses. Everywhere they are seeking reliable
knowledge--from neighbors, friends, as well as druggists, midwives, clergymen, nurses, social
workers, any one, every one, yet they are consistently refused.</p>
<p>Even though these mothers realize the tragedy of brining helpless children into this world by
chance, they are forced to go through the tragedy of enslaved maternity.</p>
<p>What can we do to help them?</p>
<p>In the first place, education in the control of conception must be accepted as an integral part
of medical and hygienic education, so that every hospital, every free clinic, every dispensary,
every licensed physician, and every visiting registered nurse may become of real help to the mothers
of America. It is the public duty of each specialist to uphold our racial strength and purity.</p>
<p>This is an essential part of true patriotism, a more profound patriotism than taking an oath to
uphold the laws of our country or to protect the flag. The future of our country depends upon the
men and women we produce.</p>
<p>That this new education in parenthood can be made universal is not wild theory. It has been
tested successfully in other countries.</p>
<p>This system of marital and parental education is being carried on among the poorer classes in a
number of countries, notably in Holland, and more recently in Great Britain, under the name of
"Birth Control Clinics."</p>
<p>These maternity education centers--or, as we call them to-day, Birth Control Clinics--were
inaugurated no less than forty years ago in Holland, under the pioneering leadership of two
<place>Amsterdam</place> physicians, Dr. <person reg="Jacobs, Aletta">Aletta Jacobs</person> and her
colleague, <person reg="Rutgers, Johannes">J. Rutgers</person>. Their success in establishing a
beneficial balance between the birth rate and the death rate in Holland, in diminishing the evils of
poverty and overcrowding, led to the rapid spread of maternity education centers. Finally, in the
compressed little kingdom of Holland, there were no less than fifty-two such clinics, recognized by
the Dutch government as achieving social service of national importance.</p>
<p>Since the war, a large number of these clinics have been opened in <place reg="London, England"
>London</place> and other important cities of <place>England</place>. Some of them are known as
Birth Control Clinics and others as Welfare Centers. They are supported in the belief that the
welfare of the nation demands that married couples suffering from diseases which are likely to be
transmitted to or to damage the offspring should be advised against parenthood and instructed how to
avoid it "<q who="UNK">without having recourse to the unnatural method of prolonged sexual
abstinence which strikes at the very roots of marriage itself</q>." </p>
<p>At such clinics women would be advised against childbearing:</p>
<p>First: When either parent has an inheritable disease, such as insanity, feeble-mindedness,
epilepsy, or syphilis.</p>
<p>Second: When the mother is suffering from tuberculosis, kidney disease, heart disease, or pelvic
deformity.</p>
<p>Third: When either parent has gonorrhea. This disease in the mother is the cause of ninety per
cent of blindness in newborn babies.</p>
<p>Fourth: When children already born are not normal, even though both parents are in good physical
and mental condition.</p>
<p>Fifth: Not until the woman is twenty-three years old and the man twenty-five.</p>
<p>Sixth: Not until the previous baby is at least three years old. This gives a year to recover form
the physical ordeal of the birth of the baby, a year to rest, be normal and enjoy her motherhood,
and another year to prepare for the coming of the next.</p>
<p>Seventh: Children should not be born to parents whose economic circumstances do not guarantee
enough to provide the children with the necessities of life.</p>
<p>Eighth: A woman should not bear children when exhausted form labor. This especially applies to
women who marry after spending several years in industrial or commercial life. Conception should not
take place until she is in good health and has overcome her fatigue.</p>
<p>Ninth: Not for two years after marriage should a couple undertake the responsibility of becoming
parents.</p>
<p>When children are conceived in love and born into an atmosphere of happiness, then will
parenthood be a glorious privilege, and the children will grow to resemble gods. This can be
obtained only through the knowledge and practice of Birth Control.</p>
<p>"<q who="UNK">Even when parents are healthy</q>," it is further pointed out, "<q who="UNK">too
frequent childbearing weakens the health of both mothers and babies, especially if their life is one
of poverty and squalor</q>." Therefore, at these clinics both antenatal and postnatal care is given.
In addition, competent medical men and women advise and instruct parents in safe and hygienic
methods of family limitation whenever for reason of public and private health they are convinced
that disease or extreme poverty renders childbearing prejudicial to the health of either mother or
child. In such cases temporary or permanent avoidance of pregnancy is advised.</p>
<p>The best scientific thought, not only on the continent and <place>Great Britain</place>, but in
this country as well, now recognizes medicine's responsibilities in forwarding the Birth Control
movement as an essential factor in the maintenance of public and racial health. In the words of Dr.
<person reg="Pusey, William Allen">William Allen Pusey</person>, formerly president of the
<org>American Medical Association</org>: "<q who="PUSWI">The relation of medicine to this problem is
obvious. Methods of birth control have to do with the human body: and that is our province. . .
Medicine has not give to this problem the attention that it deserves--not because medicine is not
confronted with it every day, but because the subject is taboo and the adequate exchange of
scientific knowledge concerning it is illegal. It is a problem that requires the technical skill fo
medicine. . . .</q></p>
<p>"<q who="PUSWI">This is peculiarly woman's problem. Of course it is man's problem also, but men
are not concerned in it in the way that women are. It is women who bear the penalties in injury,
disease, death, and mental torture that are involved in it. They have a right to know how they can
intelligently--not crudely and dangerously--Control their sexual lives, and they are justified by
the highest considerations in fighting vociferously and persistently until they have this right
granted to them</q>."</p>
<p>In recent years there has likewise been a great awakening among liberal churchmen and religious
teachers as to the ethical and moral justification of the theory and practice of Birth Control.
Leading churchmen of all Protestant sects are not practically unanimous in urging this scientific
and hygienic education as necessary to the foundations of contented marital life, to strong, happy
family bonds and the welfare of posterity.</p>
<p>The <person reg="Barnes, E. W.">Bishop of <place reg="Birmingham, England"
>Birmingham</place></person> has preached vigorous sermons urging the adoption of Birth Control as a
national policy. <org>The Society of Friends</org> (the Quakers) have issued a report approving of
the small-family system. The only religious organization bitterly and violently inimical to Birth
Control is the Roman Catholic Church.</p>
<p>But this does not mean that Birth Control is contrary to the teaching of Christ. This point has
been effectively presented by Dean <person reg="Inge, William Ralph">Inge</person> of <org>St.
Paul's Cathedral</org>, London, whose recent visit to this country attracted so much attention. Dean
Inge claims that Birth Control is an essential part of Christian morality. On this point he has
written:</p>
<p>"<q who="INGWI">We wish to remind our orthodox and conservative friends that the Sermon on the
Mount contains some admirably clear and unmistakable eugenic precepts. '<q who="BIB">Do men gather
grapes of thorns, or figs of thistles? A corrupt tree cannot bring forth good fruit, neither can a
good tree bring forth evil fruit. Every tree which bringeth not forth good fruit is hewn down, and
cast into the fire</q>.' We wish to apply these words not only to the action of individuals, which
spring from their inherited qualities. This extension of the cope of the maxim seems to me quite
legitimate. Men do not grapes of thorns. As our proverb says, 'You cannot make a silk purse out of a
sow's ear.' If we believe this and do not act upon it by trying to move public opinion, we are
sinning against the light, and not doing our best to bring in the kingdom of God upon
earth</q>."</p>
<p>Elsewhere this courageous churchman has written: "<q who="INGWI">Either rational selection must
take the place of the natural selection which the modern state will not allow to act, or we must go
on deteriorating. When we can convince the public of this, the opposition of organized religion will
soon collapse or become ineffective. . . . The Christian conception of a kingdom of God on earth
teaches us to turn our eyes to the future and to think of the welfare of posterity as a thing which
concerns us as much as that of our new generation</q>."</p>
<p>The enemies of contraceptive methods declare them to be unnatural and, therefore, immoral. The
<org>American Birth Control League</org>, of which I have the honor to be president, effectively
answers the objection that Birth Control is unnatural.</p>
<p>We admit the accusation.</p>
<p>Yes. Emphatically yes. Of course it is!</p>
<p>As unnatural as the hat on your head. As unnatural as the shoes on your feet. As unnatural as the
house you live in. The natural man shivered in a dark cave, and lived on raw roots and uncooked
flesh.</p>
<p>Contraception is as unnatural as the radio you listen in on. It is unnatural, like talking over
the telephone, or riding in a motor car, or a flight in an aeroplane.</p>
<p>All inventions are unnatural. Civilization had advanced by conquering and controlling the forces
of nature. Man has in the past century worked miracles in controlling the great forces of nature
outside of himself. He has harnessed great water power. He has enslaved electricity for his uses and
comforts. He has discovered radio activity, and he is busy upon his conquest of the air, and with
fine bravery and illimitable courage is going forth on his greatest voyage of exploration--the
exploration of the atom.</p>
<p>He has still to learn to conquer and control these mysterious forces of nature, forces the great
power of which has never yet been adequately measured, which well up to his own consciousness from
the dark uncharted depths of his own procreative instincts.</p>
<p>Sanitation is unnatural. Hygiene is unnatural. And so is contraceptive foresight, which is, none
the less, the safest, surest, and only effective instrument by which men and women may become the
masters of instinct and desire, instead of their slaves.</p>
<p>We are held back by silence, by inertia, by prejudice. But all of us--every American
citizen--must join in this campaign sooner or later. Because the life happiness and opportunity of
every man, woman, and child among us is bound up with the success or failure of the movement for
Birth Control. Upon the shoulders of the normal, the healthy, the independent, and the
self-supporting falls the ever-increasing burden of the reckless and the improvident. Every state of
the Union is carrying thousands of wards, criminals, and delinquents. Subnormal and mentally
defective children are cluttering up the public schools and impeding the progress of gifted and
talented children.</p>
<p>We advocates of Birth Control are not aiming, as our enemies assert, upon the destruction of the
morals of the country. On the contrary, we are fighting for the realization of all the latent
possibilities of development now hidden. We claim that the true wealth of the United States can be
measured only by its strength in real men and real women. And we refuse to remain indifferent to
truths that are crying aloud for general recognition.</p>
<p>Therefore, we insist on passports for babies. We insist on the recognition and the rigid
observance of necessary racial traffic regulations.</p>
<p>Without going out of their way, every wife, every mother, every thoughtful husband can influence
public opinion to a new understanding of our problem.</p>
<p>You are being continually asked to contribute to charities. Find out what the particular
organization is doing to prevent the repetition of the distress it is seeking to alleviate.</p>
<p>Find out the laws of your state concerning the liberty it affords physicians to act as counselors
in parenthood.</p>
<p>Break through the conspiracy of silence on parenthood and Birth Control, and help those less
fortunate than yourself toward independence, self-support, and parental prudence.</p>
<p>We crusaders for Birth Control invite opposition; we invite discussion; we invite questions and
cross-examination. Lethargy and indifference are the only true enemies of human progress.</p>
</docBody>
</doc>
