<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article ">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2003/06/10 RK</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2003/08/07 CH Index</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/08/23 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007/06/25 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2001/03/11 CH Entered corrections suggested by Andy Carloff.</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011-11-30 CH correct typo</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-01 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1916-06-10">10 June 1916</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Prolific Child-Breeding Scored By Mrs. Sanger</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp320266</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">San Francisco Call &amp; Post</title> June 10, 1916</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="MILJO ">John Stuart Mill</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>Second article in a two-part series. The first article was <xref from="320267.xml">"<title type="article">Tell
                Girls Things They Should Know: Mrs. Sanger</title></xref>," June 9, 1916.</p>
        <index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="morality and"/>
        <index level1="family size"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="socio-economic benefits of"/>
        <index level1="morality" level2="infant"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>PROLIFIC CHILD-BREEDING SCORED BY MRS. SANGER</head>
        <byline>By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></byline>
        <div>
            <p>Woman throughout the ages has been forced to take the role of child bearer. She has
                had almost no other function in our civilization. This action of passive maternity
                on her part has been of great injury, not only to herself as regards her health,
                strength and intellectual development, but an equal, if not greater, injury to her
                child and to the community.</p>
            <p>The first and most important question which every man and woman should ask themselves
                as they start out upon life's journey together should be:</p>
            <p>"How many children are we able to bring into the world?"</p>
            <p>The first consideration should be that of the woman's health, and the next that of
                its environment.</p>
            <p>There are thousand of women in this country today whose health has been broken
                because of too frequent child bearing. There are thousands whose health has been
                broken because of illegal operations, the tortures of which they prefer rather than
                unwanted children. There are thousands who go to early graves because of both.</p>
            <p>It may seem at first that this feeling on the part of womankind who prefers to face
                this torture, and yes, even death, is unnatural and criminal on her part.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub " rend="bold">WHO IS THE REAL CRIMINAL?</head>
            <p>But let us look upon the question more closely and decide for ourselves who is the
                real criminal in this case, the woman or the makers of the laws which make it
                necessary for her to commit such crimes.</p>
            <p>Let us take a woman and a man starting out with an average man's wage of $12 a week.
                She is fresh and young, he buoyant and strong; life lies before them, and their
                desires are the best and their motives the purest. In a few years time nature has
                provided them, according to her laws, with a child every year, and they find
                themselves, in five years' time, with four little ones, living on the same wage that
                at first was only sufficient to keep two. Already her health is beginning to fail,
                although she may be only 23 years old. His strength is overtaxed by long hours of
                labor and the worry of extra mouths to feed.</p>
            <p>Can your imagination picture the conditions which await not only the parents, but
                also the unborn children which shall inevitably come into this home in the remaining
                years of her child-bearing period?</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub " rend="bold">LIMIT TO ENDURANCE</head>
            <p>Would it not be better, not only for these already born, for the parents themselves,
                and for the future of the race, if no more children were allowed to come for these
                parents to feed, clothe and care for?</p>
            <p>The answer seems so simple that any child could answer it, and yet millions of men
                and women seem unable to decide this question for themselves today.</p>
            <p>One of the earliest pioneers of the woman's movement, <person reg="Mill, John Stuart">John Stuart
                    Mill</person>, considered the production of large families the most serious
                difficulty which confronted humanity, and said:</p>
            <p>"<q who="MILJO">Little advance can be expected in morality until the production of
                    large families is considered in the same light as drunkenness and any other
                    physical excess</q>."</p>
            <p>We have in the <place reg="United States">United States</place> 300,000
                babies under one year of age which died last year from poverty and neglect, while
                600,000 parents remain in ignorance of how to prevent 300,000 more babies from
                coming into the world this year to die of poverty and neglect.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub " rend="bold">IS WASTE MORAL?</head>
            <p>Is this waste of human energy and little lives to be called moral? </p>
            <p>Can we pride ourselves upon our morality while this condition exists?</p>
            <p>Certainly not. So long as present conditions exist, the mother of a large family can
                not give her children the proper advantages for their development.</p>
            <p>Mere prolific breeding is not a sign of intelligence or strength. What we need for
                the race is quality, not quantity. Our problem is for mothers to give to the race
                the best human quality, and to help its development.</p>
            <p>It goes without saying that the first thing a mother should know is to care for her
                child physically. She should also have some knowledge of its intellectual and moral
                development.</p>
            <p>Needless to say, this involves a great deal of care and study on the part of the
                mother, and we further know that the advantages gained while she has two children
                she will be unable to give to eight or ten.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub " rend="weight(bold)">BAR WEAKNESS, DISEASE</head>
            <p>We want women to demand their rights, as mothers of the race to regulate their
                families in accordance with their advantages of giving their children the best
                physical, mental and moral inheritance and environment. We want them to refuse
                altogether to bring weakly and diseased children into unwholesome surroundings.</p>
            <p>What a magnificent future lies before humanity when woman shall demand these!</p>
            <p>Millions of women go into the battle of forced maternity every year. Thousands of
                them die upon this battlefield.</p>
            <p>There is no sadder sight in our modern life than the silence of society toward these
                casualties. Any reflecting woman should realize from this how low the value of
                motherhood has fallen, and convince her that the only hope of making motherhood
                truly respected is to make its function less prolific.</p>
            <p>It is only through the fact that women have been freed from the burden of large
                families that the present powerful women's movement throughout the world has risen.
                It is this mainly which has enabled them to devote themselves to this work and other
                intellectual pursuits.</p>
            <p>The voluntary and conscious regulation of the number of children by the mother is
                that which shall secure her social and domestic individuality. It is her fundamental
                and primitive right.</p>
            <p>There is no mother living today who wishes to see her child toiling in factories and
                mills. Schools and playgrounds and fields are the dreams she has for them. We know
                from the figures where child labor exists that children are compelled to toil in
                these places because they are members of large families, and little brothers' and
                sisters' lives depend upon their pitiful earnings.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub " rend="bold">NO PROPER TRAINING</head>
            <p>The most barbaric nations would not allow their children to toil and pass away their
                child lives under such conditions that we of civilization allow. Motherhood is
                supposed to be the prime and principal function of woman, yet it is the one vocation
                for which she receives no instruction or training.</p>
            <p>We want strong, healthy mothers to produce a strong, healthy race. Woman must reject
                with indignation the old rule of blind chance and irresponsible motherhood.</p>
            <p>Birth control will give her the power to break the chains which have kept her in
                bondage. It is unnecessary that she should be made a child-bearing machine. She will
                use this knowledge and control her maternity for the glory and uplift of herself and
                the human race.</p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
