<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2003/06/09 SB</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2003/07/01 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/23 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007/06/25 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2001/03/11 CH Entered corrections suggested by Andy Carloff.</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-18 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1916-08-00">Aug 1916</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Schools and Education in Spain</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp320327</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Modern School</title>, August 1916, 88-90</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="anarchism and anarchists" level2="in Spain"/>
        <index level1="education" level2="in Spain"/>
        <index level1="Ferrer, Francisco"/>
        <index level1="radicals" level2="in Spain"/>
        <index level1="Spain" level2="political conditions in"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>SCHOOLS AND EDUCATION IN SPAIN.</head>
        <p>THE term "free-thinker" applied to one in <place>Spain </place>is considered a mark of
            advanced ideas. Other terms such as "liberal", "republican", are used to classify
            certain stages of one's development, which to an American seem like relics of a past
            age. The free-thinker who is accepted by all respectables as <emph rend="italics"
                >the</emph> most progressive is in reality usually a generation behind in general
            phases of thought. </p>
        <p>It is the Anarchist in Spain who is alive to the broader interests of life, and it is and
            has been the anarchists who have done more in proportion to their number to educate and
            to promote a desire for education amongst the working people, than any other
            organization. They are the only educators who offer to the Spanish people a program of
            life and society which naturally applies to the Spanish temperament as well as being
            consistent with their conduct.</p>
        <p>If we can realize what it means to attempt to educate a people where in a population of
            17,667,256 there are 11,945,971 out of that number who are illiterate, who can neither
            read nor write, then one may be able to understand the importance of the work of the
            Anarchist propaganda and the difficulties which confronted <person
                reg="Ferrer, Francisco">Francisco Ferrer</person>. It is impossible to separate
            Anarchism from Spanish education or from anything which is important in Spain, for it is
            the only spark of life there today. It will be left to the Anarchist to drive out the
            priests and the robbers, before Spain can step freely in any direction.</p>
        <p>Organized anarchy in Spain dates back to the year 1868, when the <org>International
                Association of Workers</org> was formed, the result of which was the First National
            Congress held in <place reg="Barcelona, Spain">Barcelona</place> in 1870. So great was
            the interest in these ideals and so rapidly did they spread, that the following year the
            Government declared the International to be an illegal organization and the executive
            left Spanish soil and fled to <place>Portugal</place>. A <org
                reg="AIT-Sec&ccedil;&atilde;o Portuguesa">Portugese organization</org> was soon
            established and the ideas flourished on both soils. </p>
        <p>In spite of the law declaring the International Association of Workers illegal, several
            conferences were held throughout Spain. The movement became so strong and general that
            the Republicans attempted to capture it by swinging it into a political groove, but
            failed. The Spaniard has little faith in government, no matter what its brand, so they
            kept to one straight issue-- Revolution through economic action. They supported <person
                reg="Bakunin, Mikhail ">Bakunin</person> at the famous Conference at <place
                reg="Geneva, Switzerland">Geneva</place> in 1873 in this. </p>
        <p>The Government realized the importance of the movement when it saw it could not be
            side-tracked into a political camp. The issue was too straight to be tolerated, at all
            costs it must be crushed; it accordingly took steps to disolve it and smash the
            organization by arresting and banishing the prominent members to penal settlements in
            the <place reg="Marianne Islands, Micronesia">Marianne Islands</place>. This had the
            desired effect and many members abandoned the movement entirely, while others simple
            withdrew their activities. For several years it remained at a standstill until in 1889,
            when a new programme was drawn up upon which was based Modern Anarchism in Spain.</p>
        <p>I will not attempt to tell of the hardships, strifes and struggles of these who were able
            to keep the propaganda current and the ideals alive in the face of persecutions,
            tortures and executions. There was no conceivable plot which the criminal tactics of the
            police and the priests did not resort to in order to incriminate sympathizers and to
            extinguish anarchist ideals. Whole issues of both daily and weekly papers were
            confiscated by the government day after day and week after week.</p>
        <p>One anarchist four-page daily, "<title type="journal">Tierra Y'Libertad</title>", (<title
                type="journal">Land and Liberty</title>), which in 1905 had a circulation of 10,000
            copies, had to be converted into a weekly with 8,000 copies. This is only one instance
            -- there are many others -- but it is estimated very roughly and conservatively that at
            the present time there are more than 70,000 copies of current anarchist papers, weekly,
            daily, etc., and we know there are always two or three readers to every purchase, which
            goes to prove that suppression and confiscation may delay or hold back for a time, but
            ideals cannot be killed and often take root while they stand.</p>
        <p>Anarchists attribute the poverty, ignorance and misery to present day society. They
            believe a society can be established in which Law, authority, government or church shall
            not dictate or regulate human conduct, but that mutual help through natural desires will
            give individual freedom.</p>
        <p>Spanish Anarchism embraces the philosophy of Bakunin, <person reg="Reclus, Elise E. "
                >Reclus</person> and <person reg="Kropotkin, Peter">Kropotkin</person>. They
            consistently advocate the general strike to bring about the social revolution.</p>
        <byline><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">MARGARET H. SANGER</person>.</byline>
    </docBody>
</doc>
