<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
<mepHeader>
<prepDate>2003/07/15 SR</prepDate>
<prepDate>2003/07/23 SR</prepDate>
<prepDate>2014-03-04 CH correcting regs</prepDate>
<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
<docDate value="1923-04-08"> 8 Apr 1923</docDate>
<docTitle>
<titlePart>Apostle of Birth control Sees Cause Gaining Here: </titlePart>
</docTitle>
<idno>msp320595</idno>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl><title type="journal">New York Times</title>, Apr. 8, 1923, XII.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
<respStmt>
<resp/>
<name id="MALTH"> Thomas Malthus</name>
<name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
<name id="SANTZ"> Tzi Sang</name>
<name id="LUSE"> Set Lu</name>
</respStmt>
</mepHeader>
<headNote resp="MSPP">
<p>This article was reprinted by the <org>American Birth Control League</org> in a flyer with two
other newspaper articles as "<title type="article">Real Facts About Birth Control</title>," ca.
April 1923.(LCM 129:580)</p>
<index level1="birth control" level2="in New York"/>
<index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="New York "/>
<index level1="birth control" level2="morality of"/>
<index level1="birth control" level2="neo-Malthusian arguments for"/>
<index level1="censorship" level2="in United States"/>
</headNote>
<docBody>
<head>APOSTLE OF BIRTH CONTROL SEES CAUSE GAINING HERE</head>
<p>After ten years of incessant agitation and activity the much-discussed question of Birth Control
has invaded the legislative halls of <place reg="Albany, NY"> Albany</place>. A bill intended to
amend existing laws so that <place>New York</place> physicians may be authorized to disseminate
contraceptive advice has been introduced. There will be a hearing on the matter in the Assembly
Chamber on April 10. If enacted, we may hope for the beginning of a new era of social welfare and
racial hygiene. But whatever the outcome, this bill means that Birth Control is no longer looked
upon, even in the judicial and legislative field, as a topic "obscene and indecent," worthy only of
ribald jest and suggestive leer.</p>
<p>No other great problem affecting the welfare of nation and race has been more misinterpreted and
misunderstood, even by Americans who consider themselves well informed. Advocates of this doctrine
do not beg for mere assent or approval. They ask for investigation and understanding, as the initial
step toward support and adherence to their doctrines.</p>
<p>Much of the opposition to Birth Control has had its source among clergymen and other professional
moralists. This ecclesiastic opposition is amazing in view of the fact that the "onlie true
begetter" of the whole Birth Control movement, <person reg="Malthus, Thomas Robert"> Robert
Malthus</person>, was himself a clergyman of the <org>Church of England</org>. He advocated "<q
who="MALTH"> prudential checks</q>" on the grounds of austere morality. Our clerical opponents also
ignore the fact that many of the most noted champions of Birth Control today are clergymen. The most
noteworthy example is that of the distinguished Dean of <org reg="St. Paul's Cathedral">St. Paul's,
<place reg="London, England"> London</place></org>, <person reg="Inge, William Ralph">William Ralph
Inge</person>.</p>
<p>There is a confusion in the public mind concerning the origin of the present movement, which must
be distinguished from the so-called Neo-Malthusian movement of <place>Great Britain</place> and the
Continent. The <org>Neo-Malthusian League</org> was the direct outcome of the celebrated trial in
London in 1877 of <person reg="Bradlaugh, Charles">Charles Bradlaugh</person> and Mrs. <person
reg="Besant, Annie">Annie Besant</person>, who had frankly admitted distributing among the English
poor thousands upon thousands of copies of the pamphlet of a <place reg="Boston, MA"> Boston</place>
physician, Dr. <person reg="Knowlton, Charles"> Knowlton</person>, entitled "<title type="book"
>Fruits of Philosophy</title>," originally published in this country in 1833. The Neo-Malthusian
League, sponsored by those valiant pioneers, <person reg="Drysdale, Charles Robert">
Charles</person> and <person reg="Drysdale, George">George Drysdale</person> and Dr. <person
reg="Vickery, Alice">Alice Vickery</person>, soon spread to all countries of the <place reg="Europe"
>Continent</place>, and its doctrines were put into practice in <place reg="The Netherlands">
Holland</place>, where fifty-three Birth Control clinics, approved by the Dutch Government, have
been conducted with great success for forty years.</p>
<p>The Birth Control movement, which has now absorbed the earlier Neo-Malthusian movement,
originated right here in <place reg="New York, NY"> New York</place> just a decade ago. While the
Neo-Malthusians based their propaganda on the broad general basis of Malthus's theory of population,
the expression "Birth Control" was devised in my little paper of advance feminism, <title
type="journal">The Woman Rebel</title>, as one of the fundamental rights of the emancipation of
working women. The response to this idea of Birth Control was so immediate and so overwhelming that
a league was formed--the first Birth Control league in the world.</p>
<div>
<head type="sub">Why She Took Up Task.</head>
<p>With all the flame-like ardor of pioneers we did not at first realize the full scope of this
fundamental discovery. At that time I knew nothing of Malthus, nothing of the courageous and
desperate battle waged by the Drysdales in England, <person reg="Rutgers, Johannes">
Rutgers</person> in Holland, of <person reg="Giroud, Gabriel">G. Hardy</person> and <person
reg="Robin, Paul">Paul Robin</person> in <place>France</place>, for this century-old doctrine. I was
merely thinking of the poor mothers of congested districts of the East Side who had so poignantly
begged me for relief, in order that the children they had already brought into the world might have
a chance to grow into strong and stalwart Americans. It was almost impossible to believe that the
dissemination of knowledge easily available to the intelligent and thoughtful parents of the
well-to-do classes was actually a criminal act, proscribed not only by State laws but by Federal as
well.</p>
<p>My paper was suppressed. I was arrested and indicted by the Federal authorities. But owing to the
vigorous protests of the public and an appeal sent by a number of distinguished English writers and
thinkers, the case against me was finally abandoned. Meanwhile "Birth Control" became the slogan of
the idea and not only spread through the American press from coast to coast, but immediately gained
currency in <place>Great Britain</place>. Succinctly and with telling brevity and precision "Birth
Control" summed up our whole philosophy. Birth Control is not contraception indiscriminately and
thoughtlessly practiced. It means the release and cultivation of the better racial elements in our
society, and the gradual suppression, elimination and eventual extirpation of defective
stocks--those human weeds which threaten the blooming of the finest flowers of American
civilization.</p>
<p>In our efforts to effect the repeal of the existing laws which declare the use of contraceptive
methods indecent and obscene, Birth Control advocates have been forced to battle every inch of the
way. To get the matter before the Legislature of New York my path has led completely around the
earth. Our effort has been to enlist the support of the best minds of every country, an object we
have achieved even beyond our fondest expectations.</p>
<p> The backbone of the Birth Control movement has been from the time Malthus first published his
epoch-making "<title type="book">Principles of Population</title>" essentially Anglo-Saxon. <person
reg="Mill, John Stuart">John Stuart Mill</person>, <person reg="Place, Francis">Francis
Place</person>, <person reg="Arnold, Matthew">Matthew Arnold</person>, <person reg="Huxley, Thomas"
>Thomas Huxley</person> and our own <person reg="Jefferson, Thomas">Thomas Jefferson</person>,
<person reg="Madison, James">James Madison</person>, <person reg="Emerson, Ralph Waldo">Ralph Waldo
Emerson</person> and <person reg="Ingersoll, Robert G.">Robert G. Ingersoll</person> spoke openly in
favor of control of the population. Today such thinkers and writers as <person reg="Wells, H. G.">H.
G. Wells</person>, <person reg="Cox, Harold">Harold Cox</person> (editor of The <title
type="journal">Edinburgh Review</title>), <person reg="Bennett, Arnold">Arnold Bennett</person>,
Dean Inge, <person reg="Archer, William">William Archer</person>, <person reg="Ellis, Havelock"
>Havelock Ellis</person>, <person reg="Murray, Gilbert">Gilbert Murray</person>, <person
reg="Russell, Bertrand">Bertrand Russell</person>, <person reg="Keynes, John Maynard">John Maynard
Keynes</person> (editor of <title type="journal">Nation and Athenaeum The Nation</title>), and
<person reg="Dawson, Bertrand Edward">Lord Dawson</person>, one of the <person
reg="George V (England)">King</person>'s physicians, and innumerable others in Great Britain speak
openly and valiantly for Birth Control.</p>
<p>It is not without significance that since the inauguration of our agitation in 1913 there has
been an immense recrudescence of interest in the persistent problem of population; and a number of
new efforts, notably that of <person reg="Carr-Saunders, Alexander Murray">A. M.
Carr-Saunders</person>, to reinterpret the thesis so brilliantly advanced by that obscure clergyman,
Malthus.</p>
<p>Most gratifying to the battle-scarred propagandist for Birth Control has been the awakening of
the Orient. <place>China</place> and <place>Japan</place> for ages have been the notoriously
overpopulated countries of the earth, the high birth rate, as always, accompanied by a high death
rate, a high infant mortality rate and even acceptance of the widespread practice of infanticide.
Famine, pestilence and flood have been the only checks to overpopulation in China, and these have
been regarded even as a blessing by the yellow races. "<foreign>Yang to meng ping</foreign>" is a
well-known exclamation in China--"<q who="UNK">Many men, life cheap!</q>"</p>
<p>Following my sojourn in China last year, the <title type="journal">Ladies' Journal of
China</title>, the most influential women's publication there, devoted a special edition of more
than one hundred pages to the problem of Birth Control. In this paper <person reg="Sang, Tzi">Tzi
Sang</person> wrote: "<q who="SANTZ"> Since Mrs. Sanger's visit, public opinion has been greatly
influenced, and I understand that some educators are planning to propagate the doctrine in the
interior so that our women will no longer be mere machines for breeding children. When the majority
of our people know the benefits of Birth Control and believe that it is the remedy for plague,
famine and war in China, then we can adopt the method of asking doctors to pass on their knowledge
to women poor in health</q>."</p>
<p><person reg="Lu, Set">Set Lu</person>, another writer in the same paper, points out that "<q
who="LUSE"> If we study the actual situation in China we find that unconsciously the Chinese have
attempted to practice Birth Control in a different way. Do we not throw away our babies?</q>"
frankly asks this writer of his compatriots. His answer is interesting: "<q who="LUSE"> Savages
practice infanticide, but civilized people use scientific methods of prevention. Herein lies the
difference between a barbarous and a civilized people. No wonder that our civilization fails to make
any noticeable advance</q>."</p>
<p>Both in Japan and China, as a result of my visit, and especially as the effect of the attempt
upon the part of the <org>Imperial Japanese Government</org> to suppress Birth Control and to shut
its door in my face, the subject of birth control has aroused the deepest and most widespread
interest among all classes. In both these great Oriental empires the roots of a permanent Birth
Control movement have struck deep in popular interest, and undoubtedly will exert a great influence
toward bringing down the alarmingly high birth rates to the level of those of Western civilization.
The importance, the immediate necessity of an autonomous control of the birth rate by the races of
the Orient is by no one more emphatically stated than by that eloquent and picturesque writer and
traveler, <person reg="Bland, John Otway Percy">J. O. P. Bland</person>.</p>
<p>Since the first Birth Control clinic established in this country was raided by the New York
police in <place reg="Brownsville, NY"> Brownsville</place> some years ago, and its founders
sentenced to jail as petty miscreants, the whole current of opinion has advanced, not merely in this
country but throughout the world. The results of the intelligence tests, the menace of
indiscriminate immigration, the fertility of the unfit and the increasing burden upon the healthful
and vigorous members of American society of the delinquent and dependent classes, together with the
growing danger of the abnormal fecundity of the feeble-minded, all emphasize the necessity of
clear-sightedness and courageously facing the problem and the possibilities of Birth Control as a
practical and feasible weapon against national and racial decadence.</p>
<p>With the invasion of the New York Legislature exponents of this challenging doctrine may well
congratulate themselves that they have won another victory against their opponents. Whatever the
outcome of the hearing on April 10, Birth Control in any event will have compelled serious attention
from our legislators. If we can convince the Assemblymen and State Senators that this is a matter
which concerns not merely a group of "well-meaning" feminists, but is organically bound up with the
biological welfare of the whole community, we shall consider that our efforts have not been entirely
in vain.</p>
</div>
</docBody>
</doc>
