<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011-06-29 CH initial tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-21 CH clean reg</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1939-01-19">19 Jan 1939</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Doors to a New World</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp320520</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title>, March 1939, pp. 165-68</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="MILJO">Mill, John Stuart</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Sanger gave this address at the <org>Birth Control Federation of
                America</org> annual luncheon at the <org>Biltmore Hotel</org> in <place
                reg="New York, NY">New York City</place>. For draft versions see Library of Congress
            Microfilm 129:582 and Margaret Sanger Microfilm S72:14, 16, 24, 27, 38, 47, and 54.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="American"/>
        <index level1="Birth Control Federation of America"/>
        <index level1="immigration" level2="birth control and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Doors to a New World</head>
        <byline>By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person> Honorary Chairman Birth
            Control Federation of America.</byline>
        <p>It is needless for me to attempt to express the happiness I feel today. Words are not
            sufficient to express how much I rejoice that at last this miracle has happened which
            has brought the activities of both national groups into one national federation. Many of
            us have tried time and time again to do this, but we were not successful and each
            failure seemed only to strengthen our opinion that it could never be done. It took the
            high faith of <person reg="Suarez, Evelyn">Mrs. Suarez</person>, the keen enthusiasm of
                <person reg="Potter, Grace">Mrs. Potter</person>, the experience and guidance of
            both <person reg="Dickinson, Robert Latou">Dr. Dickinson</person> and <person
                reg="Wile, Ira S.">Dr. Wile</person>, and last but not least, the fairness, the
            justness and the impartial attitude of our chairman, <person reg="Pierson, Richard N."
                >Dr. Pierson</person>, to bring this about. These are the qualities of the spirit
            which guided us into the harmony of today.</p>
        <p>I wish also to thank all members of the <org
                reg="Joint Committee of the American Birth Control League and the Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau"
                >Joint Committee</org> as well as those associated with both groups who made many
            concessions to their loyalties. For it was the loyalties that kept us apart. Now let us
            transfer these splendid qualities, these loyalties, from persons to principles and
            together, today, let us lay the cornerstone of the soundest, finest, most constructive
            organization on this continent. As I look around this crowded room I see many faces of
            friends, old and new. Some of you, perhaps only a few who are here, came into the
            movement in those early pioneering days of 1915, almost 25 years ago. But as the idea of
            birth control has grown and expanded, you have seen the others come to take their stand
            beside us and it is thanks to the vision, devotion and fearless activity of both groups
            that the idea has grown and taken root until the principles of birth control have become
            accepted almost universally.</p>
        <p> The great task now before us is to put those principles into practice. While the
            separation of the two national groups has caused some confusion in the public mind, the
            work of each has succeeded in stimulating and challenging the other to do its best. I
            have never looked upon the separation as anything but a healthy stimulus, like the
            splitting of a live cell which grows through a process of evolution. The parent cell
            splits and each part does its special function and eventually in the end all parts come
            together in a stronger form than ever.</p>
        <p>The <org>American Birth Control League</org> has done a splendid piece of work in
            organizing state groups, in establishing clinics, and interesting the doctors.</p>
        <p>The <org>National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control</org> did a
            concentrated piece of work of mass education through clubs, churches, conventions and
            conferences and secured the endorsement of nearly 1,000 important organizations whose
            total membership represented close to 20,000,000 citizens. Through the legislative bills
            introduced, national attention was focused on the principle that the giving of
            contraceptive information should be in the hands of the medical profession, and,
            secondly, that the physician should be free to advise a patient in his public as well as
            private practice.</p>
        <p>The <org>Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau</org> during the years has carried on
            far-reaching and significant work. It has not only provided clinic service for nearly
            70,000 women, but has pioneered as a research, demonstration, and teaching center.</p>
        <p>While each organization tried to outdo the other in results, fotunately we were at one on
            principles and medical policies, and that is why we can now unite our forces, save our
            energies, and pool our labors, interests and finances. Such a unified effort has now
            become a necessity to further our cause.</p>
        <p> In looking over the history of the English movement, which began in 1879 and from which
            the present birth control movement stems, it is interesting to find approximately the
            same social and economic problems existing at that time as we are facing today. I ran
            across an editorial criticizing the relief work of 1846. It pointed out that in November
            of that year, 115,000 heads of families were on relief work and that from November to
            March -- within four months -- that army increased to 750,000 and it was estimated that,
            as these represented heads of large families, the number of persons who were being
            supported was between 4,000,000 and 5,000,000 people “living on the tax-paying people,
            money got for idling away their time at work that is not necessary to be done at
            all.”</p>
        <p> It all has a familiar sound to us in 1938 and 1939. The records revealed that finally
            the cost became so heavy that the project collapsed. <place>England</place> sent her
            surplus unemployed population to <place>Australia</place>, <place>New Zealand</place>
            and <place>Canada</place>, thereby increasing her colonial population, while
                <place>Ireland</place> increased ours. The rationalists of <place>Europe</place> and
            the “birth-controllers,” like voices in the wilderness, shouted that immigration was
            only a temporary way out, that the workers would only impede their cause in other
            countries, unless they kept their birth rate down to their earning power, and that they
            were not solving the problems of poverty or misery, but pushing their problems over to
            the next generation to solve. <person reg="Mill, John Stuart">John Stuart Mill</person>
            was quoted as saying: “<q who="MILJO">It is questionable if mechanical inventions have
                done more than to enable a greater population to live the same life of
            drudgery.</q>”</p>
        <p> Then in 1881 the Marxian philosophy began to cross swords with the Malthusian and called
            upon the workers to swell their ranks. Discussion issued forth in papers and magazines
            as to whether a large population constituted the wealth of a nation. It was pointed out
            that if that were so, <place>India</place> and <place>China</place> should be ruling the
            world and islands like <place>Puerto Rico</place> should be among the happiest, most
            powerful and prosperous nations in the world. This was the situation in 1881.</p>
        <p> Today we see <place>Germany</place>, <place>Italy</place> and <place>Japan</place>
            clutching at the throats of democracies and demanding more land, more colonies for the
            expansion of territory and markets with which to feed their surplus populations. How any
            of us who desire peace in the world and the advancement of civilization can clamor for a
            larger population is beyond me, as we survey the European scene.</p>
        <p>The peace of Europe is not going to be permanently established by handing over a bit of
            territory or colonies to any nation with a high birth rate. This simply postpones the
            crisis. With some nations spawning to the utmost, the cry of “land and colonies” is not
            a permanent answer.</p>
        <p> The discovery of <place reg="United States">America</place> was the solution of the
            surplus population of Europe for some time. Now we shall have to see the discovery of
            another continent or the miracle of a new one rising out of the ocean to absorb the
            surplus population of Europe, unless the statesmen of the world will face population
            problems squarely and reckon with the facts. But there is no use in asking one nation to
            slow down its birth rate or its armaments while other nations speed up on their own.
            There must be an adjusted distribution of the birth rate of each country to its
            resources. This, of course, will be a touchy subject for some nations to grapple with,
            but a selective birth rate similar to our selective immigration quota will soon be in
            order nationally and internationally. Here is an exciting and controversial subject for
            the scientific mind to solve: “Who shall inherit the earth?”</p>
        <p> The birth control movement in this country, during the past 25 years, was largely given
            over to efforts to demolish ghosts and fears -- fears of the law, of nature, of
            immorality, and dozens of other fears with which you are all familiar. All of these
            fears of yesterday have been largely dispelled through education. But on the horizon of
            today loom the fears of tomorrow and we will soon meet the argument of the need for a
            larger population, for a higher birth rate, and fears of a declining or stationary
            population.</p>
        <p> It has recently been estimated that in 1980 there may be ten million fewer people in
            this country. The picture is presented that there will be a nation of old men and women
            over 65 years of age, using spectacles, ear trumpets, crutches, and wheel chairs and
            these old people will dominate our health resorts and increase the call upon the
            services not of obstetricians but of neurologists.</p>
        <p>To some this may seem a sad prediction, but I agree with <person reg="Ellis, Havelock"
                >Havelock Ellis</person>, who says that perhaps a million more old people may make
            for more peaceful and happy conditions. That is the countries dominated by the
            racketeering young, with their black-jacks, their machine guns, their military drills,
            uniforms and the adventurous and exciting activities of arrogant youth, that have made
            for chaos in the world.</p>
        <p>At a recent conference on public welfare, an outstanding <person reg="Haber, William"
                >professor of economics</person> stated that 10 per cent of our population will
            continue to remain on relief at a cost of $2,500,000,000 a year and that it will be a
            long time before this number will level itself out. Must we wait until 1980 as the time
            when with fewer people there will be a smaller army of unemployed?</p>
        <p>We hear a great deal about preserving our institutions of democracy and the traditions of
            liberty, free speech, free press and all of these ideals for future generations. Rather
            should we be concerned as to the quality of life that we are passing on today. What type
            of people are we breeding to form future generations? These institutions and traditions
            will take care of themselves if the people of future generations will have the
            intelligence to use and appreciate them. We have got to revalue our own human values. We
            have got to change the inference that the quality of our population depends upon the
            birth rate of college graduates. To me this is tinsel thinking. There are just as sound
            qualities to be found in the <place>Arizona</place> cowboys, in the artisans, the
            mechanics, and artists -- the qualities of initiative and capacity for clear thinking as
            a result of sound minds and sound bodies -- which must form the cornerstone of any
            enduring civilization.</p>
        <p> To attain the objectives of this new Federation will demand concentrated effort on a
            national scale. We must take birth control up and down to every level of society. We
            must make is possible for every mother to use this knowledge to avoid unwanted and
            unwarranted pregnancies and to help parents plan for really wanted children. That will
            open the doors of a new world for us all.</p>
        <p> Birth control can be used as a means to raise the level of the intelligence of our
            population; to lower infant and maternal mortality. It can be used to improve our
            general health and well-being and it can curb the pressure of population which explodes
            into war. We have a powerful instrument for good in our hands, and now that we have a
            unified, strengthened organization in the Birth Control Federation of America, let us
            see that this instrument for good is used intelligently and creatively for the best
            interests of all the people of this land.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
