<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2003/06/26 JA</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/02 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/08/09 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007/08/28 CH Oxygen update; this has a table</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/11/28 CH correct typos</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-01 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1919-03-00">Mar 1919</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Why Not Birth Control Clinics in America?</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp320522</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">American Medicine</title>, Mar. 1919, 164-167</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="WILJW">Williams, J. Whitridge</name>
            <name id="EDETH">Eden, Thomas Watts</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>This article was reprinted in the May 1919 <title type="journal">Birth Control
                Review</title> under the same title., (<title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title>
            S70:821.)</p>
        <index level1="abortion" level2="birth control vs."/>
        <index level1="abortion" level2="frequency of"/>
        <index level1="abortion" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits and risks"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="economic benefits and risks of"/>
        <index level1="eugenics" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="Netherlands" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="physicians" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="&quot;unfit&quot; to reproduce" level2="descriptions of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>WHY NOT BIRTH CONTROL CLINICS IN AMERICA?</head>
        <byline>BY <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">MARGARET SANGER</person></byline>
        <dateline><place reg="New York, NY">New York City</place>.</dateline>
        <p>The absurd cruelty of permitting thousands of women each year to go thru abortions to
            prevent the aggravation of diseases, for which they are under treatment, assuredly
            cannot be much longer ignored by the medical profession. Responsibility for the
            inestimable damage done by the practice of permitting patients suffering from certain
            ailments to become pregnant, because of their ignorance of contraceptives, when the
            physician knows that if pregnancy goes to its full term it will hasten the disease and
            lead to the patient's death, must in all fairness be laid at his door.</p>
        <p>What these diseases are and what dangers are involved in pregnancy are known to every
            practitioner of standing. Specialists have not been negligent in pointing out the
            situation. Eager to enhance or protect their reputations in the profession, they
            continually call out to each other: "<q who="UNK">Don't let the patient bear a
                child--don't let pregnancy continue.</q>"</p>
        <p>The warning has been sounded most often, perhaps, in the cases of tubercular women. "<q
                who="WILJW">In view of the fact that the tubercular process becomes exacerbated
                either during pregnancy or after childbirth, most authorities recommend that
                abortion be induced as a matter of routine in all tubercular women</q>," says Dr.
                <person reg="Williams, J. Whitridge">J. Whitridge Williams</person>,
            obstetrician-in-chief to the <org>Johns Hopkins Hospital</org>, in his treatise on
                "<title type="book">Obstetrics</title>." Dr. <person reg="Eden, Thomas Watts">Thomas
                Watts Eden</person>, obstetrician and gynecologist to <org>Charing Cross
                Hospital</org> and member of the staffs of other notable British hospitals, extends
            but does not complete the list in a paragraph on page 652 of his <title type="book"
                >Practical Obstetrics</title>. "<q who="EDETH">Certain of the conditions enumerated
                form absolute indications for the induction to abortions</q>," he says. "<q
                who="EDETH">These are nephritis, uncompensated valvular lesions of the heart,
                advanced tuberculosis, insanity, irremediable malignant tumors, hydatidiform mole,
                uncontrollable uterine hemorrhage, and acute hydramnios.</q>"</p>
        <p>We know that abortion, when performed by skilled hands, under right conditions, brings
            almost no danger to the life of the patient, and we also know that particular diseases
            can be more easily combated after such an abortion than during a pregnancy allowed to
            come to full term. But why not adopt the easier, safer, less repulsive course and
            prevent conception altogether? Why put these thousands of women who each year undergo
            such abortions to the pain they entail and in whatever danger attends them?</p>
        <p>Why continue to send home women to whom pregnancy is a grave danger with the futile
            advice: "<q who="UNK">Now don't get this way again!</q>" They <emph rend="italics"
                >are</emph> sent back to husbands who have generations of passion and passion's
            claim to outlet. They <emph rend="italics">are</emph> sent back without being given
            information as to how to prevent the dangerous pregnancy and are expected, presumably,
            to depend for their safety upon the husband's continence. Back comes the patient again
            in a few months to be aborted and told not to do it again.</p>
        <p>Does any physician believe that the picture is overdrawn? I have known of many such
            cases: A recent one that came under my observation was that of a woman who suffered from
            a disease of the kidneys. Five times she was taken to a maternity hospital in an
            ambulance after falling in offices or in the street. One of the foremost gynecologists
            of <place reg="United States">America</place> sent her out three times without giving
            her information as to the contraceptive means which would have prevented a repetition of
            this experience.</p>
        <p>Why does this situation exist? One does not question the intent or the high purposes of
            these physicians, or that they are working for the improvement of the race. But here is
            a situation that is absurd -- hideously absurd. What is the matter?</p>
        <p>Several factors contribute to this state of affairs. First, the subject of contraception
            has been kept in the dark, even in medical colleges and in hospitals. Abortion has been
            openly discussed as a necessity under certain conditions, but the subject of
            contraception, as any physician will admit, has only recently been brought to the
            front.</p>
        <p>It has been permitted to lie latent; it has escaped specialized attention in the
            laboratories and the research departments. Thus there has been no professional stamp of
            approval by great bodies of experimenters.</p>
        <p>The result is that the average physician has felt that contraceptive methods are not yet
            established as certainties and has, for that reason, refused to direct their use.</p>
        <p>Specialists are so busy with their own particular subjects and general practitioners are
            so taken up with their daily routine that they cannot give to the problem of
            contraception the attention it must have. Consultation rooms in charge of reputable
            physicians who have specialized in contraception, assisted by registered nurses -- in a
            word, clinics designed for this specialty -- would meet this crying need. Such clinics
            should deal with each woman individually, taking into account her particular disease,
            her temperament, her mentality and her condition, both physical and economic. Its sole
            function should be to prevent pregnancy. In the accomplishment of this, a higher
            standard of hygiene is attained. The result would be not only the removal of a burden
            from the physician who sends her to the clinic, but an improvement in the woman's
            general condition that would reflect itself in a number of ways to the benefit of her
            family.</p>
        <p>All this for the diseased woman. But every argument that can be made for preventive
            medicine can be made for birth control clinics for the use of woman who has not yet lost
            her health. Sound and vigorous at the time of her marriage, she could remain so if given
            advice as to by what means she could space her children and limit their number. When she
            is not given such information, she is plunged blindly into married life and a few years
            is likely to find her with a large family, herself diseased, damaged, an unfit breeder
            of the unfit, and still ignorant. What are the fruits of this woeful ignorance in which
            women have been kept? First, a tremendous infant mortality -- hundreds of thousands of
            them dying annually of diseases which flourish in poverty and neglect. Next, the rapid
            increase of the feebleminded, of criminal types and of the pathetic victims of toil in
            the child labor factories. Another result is the familiar overcrowding of tenements, the
            forcing of the children into the street, the ensuing prostitution, alcoholism and almost
            universal physical and moral unfitness.</p>
        <p>These abhorrent conditions point to a blunder upon the part of those to whom we entrust
            the care of the health of the individual, the family and the race. The medical
            profession, neglecting the principle involved in preventive medicine, has permitted
            these conditions to come about. If they were unavoidable, we would have to bear with
            them, but they are not unavoidable, as shown by facts and figures from other countries
            where contraceptive information is available.</p>
        <p>In <place reg="Netherlands">Holland</place>, for instance, where the information
            concerning contraceptives has been accessible to the people, thru clinics and pamphlets
            since 1881, the general death rate and the infant mortality rate have fallen until they
            are the lowest in Europe. <place reg="Amsterdam, Netherlands">Amsterdam</place> and
                <place reg="The Hague, Netherlands">The Hague</place> have the lowest infant
            mortality rates of any cities in the world.</p>
        <p>It is good to know that the first of the birth control clinics of Holland followed
            shortly after a thoro and enthusiastic discussion of the subject at an international
            medical congress in Amsterdam in 1878. The first birth control clinic in the world was
            opened in 1881 by Dr. <person reg="Jacobs, Aletta">Aletta Jacobs</person> in Amsterdam.
            So great were the results obtained that there has been a gradual increase in the number
            of clinics, until today there are fifty-two in operation in that country of some
            6,000,000 people. Physicians have found that nurses trained for this work by specialists
            are highly competent to take care of it and it is the almost invariable rule that Birth
            Control clinics are conducted by such nurses. Dr.<person reg="Rutgers, Johannes"> J.
                Rutgers</person> of The Hague, secretary of the <org
                reg="Nieuw-Malthusiaansche Bond">Neo-Malthusian League</org>, is the specialist who
            trains and instructs the nurses. The general results of the work are best judged by
            tables, appended to this article, taken from <title type="book">The Annual Summary of Marriages,
                Births and Deaths in <place>England</place>, <place>Wales</place>, etc.</title>, for
            1912*</p>
        <p>In conclusion, I am going to make a statement which may at first seem exaggerated, but
            which is nevertheless carefully considered. The effort toward racial progress that is
            being made to-day by the medical profession, by social workers, by the various
            charitable and philanthropic organizations and by state institutions for the physically
            and mentally unfit is practically wasted. All these forces are in a very emphatic sense
            marking time. They will continue to mark time until the medical profession recognizes
            the fact that the ever-increasing tide of the unfit is overwhelming all these agencies
            are doing for society. They will continue to mark time until they get at the source of
            these destructive conditions and apply a fundamental remedy. That remedy is birth
            control.</p>
        <p>*Amsterdam (Malthusian {Birth Control } League started 1881; Dr. Aletta Jacobs gave
            advice to poor women, 1885.)<lb/> 1881-85 1906-10 1912<lb/>Birth Rate 37.1 24.7 23.3 per
            1,000 of population<lb/>Death Rate 25.1 13.1 11.2 per 1,000 of population<lb/>Infantile
            Mortality: Deaths in first year 203 90 64 per thousand living births</p>
        <p>The Hague (now headquarters of the Neo-Malthusian {Birth Control} League)<lb/>1881-851
            906-10 1912<lb/>Birth Rate 38.7 27.5 23.6 per 1,000 of population<lb/>Death Rate 23.3
            13.2 10.9 per 1,000 of population<lb/>Infantile Mortality: Deaths in first year 214 99
            66 per thousand living births<lb/></p>
        <p><place reg="Rotterdam, the Netherlands">Rotterdam</place>.<lb/>1881-85 1906-10
            1912<lb/>Birth Rate--37.4 32.0 29.0 per 1,000 of population<lb/>Death Rate 24.2 13.4
            11.3 per 1,000 of population<lb/>Infantile Mortality: Deaths in first year 209 105 79
            per thousand living births<lb/></p>
        <p>Fertility and Illegitimacy Rates: <lb/>1880-2 1890-2 1900-2<lb/>Legitimate fertility
            306.4 296.5 252.7} Legitimate birth per 1,000 married women aged 15 to
            45<lb/>Illegitimate fertility 16.1 16.3 11.3 }Illegitimate birth per 1,000 unmarried
            women, aged 15 to 45<lb/>The Hague. 1880-2 1890-2 1900-2 <lb/>Legitimate fertility 346.5
            303.9 255.0 <lb/>Illegitimate fertility 13.4 13.6 7.7<lb/>Rotterdam. 1880-2 1890-2
            1900-2 <lb/>Legitimate fertility 331.4 312.0 299.0 <lb/>Illegitimate fertility 17.4 16.5
            13.1</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
