<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/05/31 CE</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/06/28 CE Corrections</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/08/18 EK</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1936-08-00">Aug 1936</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Birth Control Crusade Marches On</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp320557</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>The Clubwoman</title> (August 1936), pp. 6, 15</bibl>
            <bibl><title>MSMC</title>??:??</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="USCB">United States Children's Bureau</name>
            <name id="COMAC">Comstock Act, 1873</name>
            <name id="CRA">Crane Decision</name>
            <name id="NMCFSCL">National Medical Committee on Federal and State Contraceptive Legislation</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>For a draft version, see LCM 128:477; for a reprint issued by the
            National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control, see LCM 128:473.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues" level3="in US"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="economic benefits and risks of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits and risks"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Comstock act"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="New York "/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="legal cases" level3="Crane Decision'"/>
        <index level1="Brownsville Clinic" level2="arrests and trial"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="medical community and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="MS on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="MS on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="legal cases" level3="Crane Decision'"/>
        <index level1="family planning"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="infant"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="maternal"/>
        <index level1="physicians" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="government" level3="public health programs"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>THE BIRTH CONTROL CRUSADE MARCHES ON</head>
        <byline>BY <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">MARGARET SANGER</person>, President of the
                <org>National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control</org></byline>
        <p>Readers of <title>The Clubwoman <org reg="General Federation of Women's Clubs"
                >GFWC</org></title> will recall that a year ago the <org>General Federation of
                Women's Clubs</org> passed a resolution <q who="GFWC"> “endorsing the principles of
                birth control legislation.”</q> By so doing, it took a stand which will affect for
            good the welfare and lives of thousands upon thousands of women, the happiness of
            millions of American families. It will especially help mothers in families on relief who
            are denied information in public hospitals.</p>
        <p>The general concept of birth control--conscious parenthood, planned families, wanted
            children--is simple. Children should be born as a result of thoughtful choice on the
            part of the parents, and that choice should be made in accordance with the health of the
            mother, the earning power of the father, and an adequate period between births, to
            enable the mother to regain her strength and properly care for the family she already
            has.</p>
        <p>These items seem to me--and to you--common sense and obvious. And a goodly company of men
            and women in all parts of the country and in all walks of life agree with us. The
            National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control, of which I have the honor
            of being President, recently issued a list of organizations which have passed
            resolutions similar to that passed by the General Foundation. It covers, in small print,
            a sheet two feet long and a yard wide, and lists over 800 organizations, medical,
            religious, social, educational, and political, representing every State in the Union and
            almost every kind of group.</p>
        <p>What, then, is the problem, if the need for legal and scientific birth control is so well
            recognized? Seventy years ago, the so-called Comstock laws were passed, classing “<q
                who="COMAC">the prevention of conception</q>” with obscenity and making it a serious
            crime, carrying a penalty of $5,000 fine or five years in prison, or both, for anyone to
            send through the mails or common carriers any information or article “<q who="COMAC"
                >designed, adapted, or intended</q>” to prevent conception. The result has been that
            the entire matter has been pushed underground, has become confused and relegated to the
            class of back-fence gossip instead of being recognized as an important health
            service.</p>
        <p>Progress, wonderful and inspiring in the face of opposition, has been made. In 1916,
            convinced that birth control instruction was a basic factor in social work, I opened a
                <org reg="Brownsville Clinic">clinic</org> in one of the poorest sections of <place
                reg="Brooklyn, New York City, NY">Brooklyn, New York</place>. It was immediately
            closed by the police as a “public nuisance” and my co-workers and I were carted off to
            jail. But seven years later, on the basis of a test <title rend="Crane Decision">case
                decision</title> which permitted a doctor to give birth control instruction for <q
                who="CRA">“the cure and prevention of disease”</q> in New York, we opened the
                <org>Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau</org> in <place reg="New York City, NY"
                >New York City</place>. It is today the oldest birth control clinic in America and
            the largest in the world, and has taken care of over 50,000 patients. There are now some
            250 clinics in thirty-nine states, the <place>District of Columbia</place>, and
                <place>Hawaii</place>, but large areas of the country, particularly rural districts,
            are still without clinical service. No exact figures as to the number of women cared for
            per year are available, though it is known that 100 clinics (or “centers” as they are
            generally called) gave advice to 20,772 patients in 1935. Fine. . . splendid. . . we
            have gone a far way, and not an easy way, in a score of years.</p>
        <p><emph>But</emph>. . . alas, the “but” is large and tragic.</p>
        <p>According to the most recent figures issued by the <org>United States Children's
                Bureau</org>, 16,000 women die each year from “<q who="USCB">causes associated with
                pregnancy and childbirth</q>,” and our maternal mortality rate is higher than any
            other country boasting vital statistics, with the exception of <place>Scotland</place>,
                <place>Lithuania</place>, and <place>Northern Ireland</place>. It is higher than
                <place>Australia</place>, <place>Belgium</place>, <place>Canada</place>,
                <place>England</place>, <place>Germany</place>, <place>Japan</place>,
                <place>Sweden</place>, <place>Switzerland</place>. . . truly this becomes a roll
            call of shame for the <place>United States</place>, for we are told that two deaths out
            of three are preventable.</p>
        <p>Too frequent and too many pregnancies, and abortion, that tragic substitute for reliable
            birth control, are responsible for a large number of these preventable deaths. No lists
            of figures and complicated statistics are needed to show that nation-wide provision for
            scientific birth control advice would go far towards remedying this situation.</p>
        <p>There are in America twenty-six million women of child-bearing age, and as mothers and
            potential mothers they should have access to birth control advice. Existing clinics,
            though their number gives cause for rejoicing, can do little more than point the way.
            The devoted service of all the clinic workers--doctors, social workers, nurses, finance
            committees, and so on--can care for only a fractional part of all the women who need
            this advice.</p>
        <p>Whether we like it or not, we must accept the fact that present methods, if they are to
            be reliable and safe, demand medical supervision. We need, then, some action which will
            at one stroke enable hospitals, public health, and other governmental agencies
            throughout the country to establish birth control service, which will place the matter
            where it belongs, in the hands of the medical profession. We need to recognize birth
            control as a public health measure.</p>
        <p>Cut through the Gordian knot which forces our legislators to wait for the doctors and our
            doctors wait for the legislators. The <org>American Medical Association</org> a year ago
            appointed a <org
                rend="National Medical Committee on Federal and State Contraceptive Legislation"
                >Committee</org> to study the subject of birth control and report its findings. The
            report has just been issued, and, unfortunately, as it was summarized in the press, it
            seems to be a sweeping condemnation of birth control and the activities of the lay
            organizations which have not only educated the public but brought to the medical
            profession the methods which it uses in its practice today. A careful study of the
            report, however, shows that the doctors, as one would expect, recognize the need for
            reliable birth control. The report strengthens my conviction that a law exempting the
            medical profession from the restrictions of the present Comstock statutes would rectify
            the conditions which the doctors deplore.</p>
        <p><q who="NMCFSCL">“Voluntary limitation of conception may be necessary to safeguard the health of some
            women,</q>” the doctors state. They also point out the inadequacy of present methods and
            suggest that more complete education in this field be given to medical students.</p>
        <p>With a change in the law, with the removal of the confusion and taboos now existing,
            research will be stimulated and better methods, which we cannot at the present time even
            envisage, will undoubtedly be developed. Medical schools, freed from the restrictions
            (actual and psychological) imposed by the present law, will recognize the need for
            teaching future doctors about contraception, fertility, and all the medical problems of
            marriage, and hospitals will provide adequate clinical service.</p>
        <p>Lastly, maternal and infant mortality will be reduced.</p>
        <p>Women, who bear the children, have a right to knowledge of their own bodies, they have a
            right to conscious decision in undertaking the most important, and inspiring career in
            the world--motherhood. Freed from fear of unwanted pregnancies, freed from the dread of
            bringing into the world children whom they cannot adequately rear, the women of America
            will build ever happier families and better homes and create a new race.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
