<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2003/07/29 SR</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-03-04 CH correct regs</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-09 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1923-04-15"> 15 Apr 1923</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>Highlights in the History of Birth Control</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp320597</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="journal">New York Tribune</title>, Apr. 15, 1923, p. 6.</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="HOOHE"> Hoover, Herbert</name>
			<name id="EMERA"> Emerson, Ralph Waldo</name>
			<name id="MALTH"> Malthus, Thomas Robert</name>
			<name id="NOYJO"> Noyes, John Humphrey</name>
			<name id="INGRO"> Ingersoll, Robert G. </name>
			<name id="ARNMA"> Arnold, Matthew</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>This article was reprinted in an <org>American Birth Control League</org> flyer, long
			with other articles as "<title type="article">Real Facts about Birth Control</title>,"
			Apr. 1923 (LCM 129:579). This article included a photo of <person reg="Besant, Annie"
				>Annie Besant</person> and the caption "Annie Besant was to England in 1877 what
				<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person> is now to America."</p>
		<index level1="England" level2="birth control in"/>
		<index level1="birth control movement" level2="history of"/> 
		<index level1="United States" level2="birth control in"/>
		<index level1="United States" level2="overpopulation in"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Highlights in the History of Birth Control</head>
		<byline>By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">MARGARET SANGER</person></byline>
		<p>The history of Birth control propaganda in this country, as in <place>England</place>, is
			full of excitement, certain phases of it being more like a novel of adventure than a
			record of fact. Ten years ago the very words "Birth Control" were considered daring.
			Today the expression is taken for granted and has, indeed, circled the globe. Birth
			Control is discussed in <place reg="Shanghai, China">Shanghai</place>, <place
				reg="Tokyo, Japan">Tokio</place>, <place reg="Calcutta, India">Calcutta</place>,
				<place reg="Cairo, Egypt">Cairo</place>, <place reg="Columbo, Sri Lanka"
				>Colombo</place>, no less than in <place reg="London, England">London</place>,
				<place reg="New York, NY">New York</place>, <place reg="Chicago, IL">Chicago</place>
			and <place reg="Albany, NY">Albany</place>. Most of those who hold up their hands in
			holy horror at this doctrine, who condemn it as illegal and un-American, do so in
			ignorance of its history.</p>

		<p>The theory of birth Control was first formulated by the Rev. <person
				reg="Malthus, Thomas Robert">Robert Malthus</person>, an obscure clergyman in the
				<org>Church of England</org>. Malthus advocated "<q who="MALTH">prudential
				checks</q>" and late marriages to limit the birth rate. This was one hundred and
			twenty years ago. Two of the earliest Presidents of the <place reg="United States"
				>United States</place>--<person reg="Jefferson, Thomas">Thomas Jefferson</person>
			and <person reg="Madison, James">James Madison</person>--were ardent champions of
			Malthus.</p>

		<p><person reg="Owen, Robert Dale">Robert Dale Owen</person>, a <place>United States</place>
			Senator and later Ambassador to <place>France</place>, wrote a book entitled, "<title
				type="book">Moral Physiology</title>," which gave Birth Control information and led
			to the arrest and conviction of a London bookseller. Owen's book was published in 1830.
				<person reg="Emerson, Ralph Waldo">Ralph Waldo Emerson</person>, <place>New
				England</place>'s greatest philosopher, advocated Birth Control. He wrote: "<q
				who="EMERA">If government know how, I would like to see it check, not multiply, the
				population.</q>"</p>

		<p>Ninety years ago Dr. <person reg="Knowlton, Charles">Knowlton</person>, a <place
				reg="Boston, MA">Boston</place> physician, published his "<title type="book">Fruits
				of Philosophy</title>, " based on Birth Control. In 1876 <person
				reg="Bradlaugh, Charles">Charles Bradlaugh</person> and Mrs. <person
				reg="Besant, Annie">Annie Besant</person> distributed 125,000 copies of this book in
			England. They were arrested there for distributing "indecent literature." But the birth
			rate of England began to drop and it has never ceased decreasing.</p>

		<p>In 1841 the <org>Oneida Community</org> was founded by <person reg="Noyes,John Humphreys"
				>John Humphreys Noyes</person> at <place reg="Putney, VT">Putney, Vt.</place> Later
			this colony moved to <place reg="Oneida, NY">Oneida, N. Y</place>. In his first annual
			report Noyes wrote: "<q who="NOYJO">We are opposed to excessive and, of course,
				oppressive procreation. We are opposed to random procreation. We are in favor of
				intelligent, well-ordered procreation.</q>"</p>

		<p><person reg="Ingersoll, Robert G.">Robert G. Ingersoll</person> advocated Birth Control.
			He said: "<q who="INGRO">Science, the only possible savior of mankind, must put it in
				the power of woman to decide for herself whether she will or will not become a
				mother.</q>"</p>

		<p>The first statute prohibiting the passage of Birth Control information through the mails
			was enacted through the efforts of the late <person reg="Comstock, Anthony">Anthony
				Comstock</person> in 1873. In 1906 <person reg="Harman, Moses">Moses
			Harman</person>, a man seventy-five, was sentenced to hard labor, breaking stone, in
				<org reg="Leavenworth Penitentiary"><place reg="Leavenworth, KS">Leavenworth</place>
				prison</org>, because he published a serious discussion of marital relations. In
			1912 Dr. <person reg="Jacobs, Abraham">Abraham Jacobi</person>, is his presidential
			address before the <org>American Medical Association</org>, indorsed Birth Control as a
			hygienic program. Birth Control clinics, with government approval, have been in
			operation in <place reg="Netherlands">Holland</place> since 1878.</p>

		<p>The morality of Birth control is upheld by many distinguished clergymen of the
				<org>Church of England</org> and other denominations. Dean <person
				reg="Inge, William Ralph">Inge</person>, of <org reg="St. Paul's Cathedral">St.
				Paul</org>'s, London, believes this doctrine is an essential part of Christian
			ethics.</p>

		<p><person reg="Arnold, Matthew">Matthew Arnold</person>, the greatest critic of English
			literature of the Victorian era, championed the doctrine of Birth Control. He wrote: "<q
				who="ARNMA">A man's children are not really 'sent,' any more than the pictures on
				his walls or the horses in his stable are sent, and that to bring people into the
				world when one cannot afford to keep them and one's self decently and not too
				precariously is by no means an accomplishment of the divine will or a fulfillment of
				nature's simplest laws, but is contrary to reason and the will of <name type="deity"
					>God</name>.</q>"</p>

		<p>Such facts as these should, I think, demonstrate at least that Birth Control is not
			merely an expression of the fringe of feminism, that it cannot be dismissed as a subject
			too indecent and obscene to merit serious consideration. We can no longer ostrich-like
			bury our heads in the sands of sentimentality. Not merely in New York but in every
			metropolis of the United States and the world we must face the problems of population. </p>

		<p>What are these problems?</p>

		<p>Go out into the streets. Our cities are overcrowded. We make desperate attempts to cope
			with the traffic problem. Everywhere there are congested districts. The higher the
			rents, the more paradoxically do people flock t the cities. All efforts to relieve
			congestion, seemingly, increase it. Despite all the efforts of city planners and
			engineers, modern civilization seems unable to keep even one step ahead of the growth of
			the populations.</p>

		<p>We have become a nation of crowds--crowds in the theaters, crowds in the subways, crowds
			in motor cars waiting hours to cross in ferryboats or seeking to escape, for at least
			one day in the country, the eternal gregariousness of city life. And yet the ceaseless
			drift to the cities continues.</p>

		<p>At first glance this problem might seem to be one of city planning alone. But if we
			investigate it more closely, if we summon the courage to look ahead for two or three
			generations and try to envisage the results of this continuous and uncontrolled growth
			of population in our urban centers, we shall see that if, as a nation, we are merely
			interested in an endless multiplication of numbers we are doomed to sacrifice the finer
			interests of American civilization.</p>

		<p>We cannot deny, for instance, that the schools of New York City are lamentably
			overcrowded; our school buildings are inadequate to the needs of the thousands of
			children who crowd into them. Individual attention is impossible. Little children are
			forced to play in city streets. Small wonder, then, that juvenile delinquency is always
			increasing and precocious lawbreakers are sent away to reform schools and such
			institutions--an added expense to the community.</p>

		<p>Until we are prepared to give each and every child a fair start in life we have only
			ourselves to blame for the evils of juvenile crime and delinquency and the shame of
			child labor. As <person reg="Hoover, Herbert">Herbert Hoover</person> pointed out not
			long ago: "<q who="HOOHE">The nation as a whole has the obligation of such measures
				toward its children as will yield to them an equal opportunity at their start in
				life. If we could grapple with the whole child situation for one generation our
				public health, our economic efficiency, the moral character, sanity and stability or
				our people would advance three generations in one.</q>"</p>

		<p>The bill introduced in the <org reg="New York State Assembly">Assembly at Albany</org>
			did not aim to force the practice of Birth Control upon unwilling parents. It did not
			aim to destroy the teaching of any one's church or religion. It aimed at the alleviation
			of what we may legitimately term the conscription of motherhood.</p>

		<p>Birth Control aims to introduce into the creation of the next generation of American
			citizens those sound and scientific principles observed by the gardener and the
			agriculturist. We must cultivate the human garden by proper spacing, by improving the
				<emph rend="italics">quality</emph> of our precious crop of children by methods of
			intensive cultivation and not by the production of mere number.</p>

		<p>We are not, I must repeat, trying to force this doctrine upon the American public. Every
			day thousands of poor mothers are begging us for help, fully conscious that their sacred
			duty to the children they have already brought into the world demands that they shall
			not assume further parental responsibilities which they cannot fulfill. It has been in
			answer to these unfortunate and conscripted mothers that legislation authorizing duly
			registered physicians to administer the necessary hygienic and scientific advice has
			been asked.</p>

		<p>Its enactment would make possible the establishment of bureaus and clinics where the
			women of the poor might receive the first lesson in racial responsibilities and hygienic
			education. It is our conviction that such instruction would do far more toward the
			creation of a fine, sturdy race of vigorous and representative Americans in twenty-five
			to fifty years than any other political or legislative measure.</p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
