<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011-07-22 NC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/08/18 EK</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-26 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1949-10-00">Oct 1949</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>A Question of Privilege</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp320519</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Women United</title>, Oct. 1949, pp. 6-8.</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>For a draft version see MSM S72:585.</p>
        <index level1="family planning"/>
        <index level1="population growth" level2="natural resources and"/>
        <index level1="parenthood"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="MS on"/>
        <index level1="Brownsville Clinic"/>
        <index level1="African-Americans" level2="maternal mortality rates among"/>
        <index level1="African-Americans" level2="infant mortality rates among"/>
        <index level1="Puerto Rico" level2="maternal mortality rates in"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/>
        <index level1="public health" level2="birth control and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>A Question of Privilege</head>
        <byline>By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></byline>
        <p>Philosophers have often commented on the fact that mankind seems to be so constituted
            that we destroy those things which we most cherish. Certainly it is true of the ideal of
            parenthood. Hardly anyone would deny that the bringing of new life into the world and
            rearing it to maturity is one of the most satisfying and uplifting of human experiences.
            Yet innumerable tragedies, incalculable misery have been inflicted upon men, women and
            the children themselves in the name of parenthood.</p>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Attitudes and the Family</head>
            <p>Much of the unhappiness stems from two attitudes toward the family. One is that
                children are a right and a duty. The other is that they are sent by a fate against
                which it is useless to struggle. Actually, of course, children are a privilege and a
                responsibility.</p>
            <p>It is only when we appreciate this fact that the basis of sound, healthy family life
                can be paid. It is the basis on which the <org
                    reg="Planned Parenthood Federation of America">Planned Parenthood</org> movement
                is founded. When it first began more than a generation ago as a crusade for birth
                control, it was because we who were in the forefront of that early fighting realized
                that parenthood was a privilege that should be granted with complete equality.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head rend="subhead">A Plan for All</head>
            <p>In those days--and still today, although perhaps on a somewhat lesser scale--it was a
                privilege for the well-to-do and the well educated. For the privilege of having
                children carries with it the meaning that the children are wanted by their parents,
                planned for and cared for. Wives and mothers with access to the best medical help
                were able to exercise this privilege. But this was not true of their poorer and less
                fortunate sisters.</p>
            <p>The birth control movement was an effort to extend this privilege to all. Since my
                    <person reg="Byrne, Ethel Higgins">sister</person> and I founded our <org
                    reg="Brownsville Clinic">first clinic</org> in a <place reg="Brooklyn, NY"
                    >Brooklyn</place> slum in 1916, the idea has spread until now there are more
                than 500 clinics, and many of them are maintained by public health services.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Tragic Statistics</head>
            <p>But we are far from having achieved real equality. It remains true that information
                about and access to birth control methods is denied to whole segments of our society
                to whom it is more important. We have only to look at the maternal and infant death
                rates of Negro mothers and babies in this country to see that this is true.</p>
            <p>The death rate of Negro mothers is three times as high as that of whites. The
                stillbirth ratio is twice as high among Negroes. Nor are Negroes the only
                underprivileged people in our society. In <place>Puerto Rico</place>, the maternal
                death rate is nearly twice that of the continental <place>United States</place>, the
                infant death rate more than double.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Not Birth Control Alone...</head>
            <p>Birth control, of course, is not the sole reason. The fact that on the average
                Negroes have less access to hospitalization and medical care in childbirth plays its
                part. But countless studies have shown that mothers die in childbirth because they
                have a pregnancy when their health is undermined, and would not die if they had been
                able to practice birth control until their health is restored. The studies show that
                the stillbirth rate rises with fantastic speed after a fourth child so that it is in
                these large families that we so often hear: “Eleven babies, but four of them born
                dead.”</p>
            <p>The knowledge and privilege of voluntary parenthood is denied these mothers, along
                with a great many other privileges that command more attention publicly but are of
                far less real importance to the families themselves. But it is not enough to deplore
                the situation and condemn the blindness, folly and downright evil that has brought
                it about. The real answer to the problem is to do something about it.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head rend="subhead">What To Do About It</head>
            <p>Everyone, especially through organizations, churches, clubs, can help. Here, for
                example, is the kind of a program that should be established in every community:</p>
            <p>1. <emph rend="italics">Control of conception</emph> as an essential feature of
                maternal and child health should be part of every public health clinic and every
                hospital that has a delivery room. Such services will be established only when the
                public, the mothers and the fathers, the organizations and the people generally
                demand it. The basic battles have been won; the <org>United States Public Health
                    Service</org> now gives State requests for funds to establish conception control
                programs the same consideration as any other health need.</p>
            <p>2. <emph rend="italics">Civic minded groups</emph> of every community should include
                in their programs the education of their members and the public in the importance of
                birth control to the family, to the nation and to the world. Through them we would
                win not only education for those who need it now but the next generation would grow
                up better prepared for the responsibilities and the joys of marriage and parenthood.
                Preparation for family life begins in the cradle. The home, the school and the
                church all have a share in developing the individual’s attitude toward marriage.
                When the preparation is well done, we have young couples who are keenly aware of
                their duties as well as their privileges.</p>
            <p>3. <emph rend="italics">Medical and nursing professions</emph>, social workers,
                welfare departments should give their workers training in the basic facts of Planned
                Parenthood. Through the doctors, the public health workers and the others, we can
                achieve a far better service to the married couples of the community and a better
                understanding of parenthood.</p>
            <p>4. <emph rend="italics">Intelligent and generous support</emph> of research of this
                field is needed. Unfortunately, the physiology and the psychology of human
                procreation are almost unexplored territory. We know a great deal more about the
                facts of reproduction in race horses and white mice, hybrid corn and orchids than we
                do about ourselves. <person reg="Vogt, William">William Vogt</person>, in this
                brilliant book “<title type="book">The Road to Survival</title>” says that the discovery of a
                completely reliable, simple and inexpensive contraceptive is as important as atomic
                energy and would be well wroth the two billion dollars spent to develop the atom
                bomb. This is almost as true within our own country as it is of the world at large.
                The international problem of population is more acute than that of the United
                States. But it is a question of degree. Furthermore, our own country can hardly be
                either safe or prosperous for very long in a world where population in most places
                has outstripped the resources to support that population. Yet, while there are
                peoples who need this ideal contraceptive more than we do, that does not minimize
                the importance of it to those millions of our own who are in the same family
                predicament as the Chinese or the Indians.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Experience and Observations</head>
            <p>In seeking to put such a program into effect, the individual and the group can do
                more than they think, when they first measure their own puny strength against the
                magnitude of the problem. Furthermore, there is no civic progress to which women’s
                organizations can contribute with more satisfaction to themselves or benefit to
                their fellows. From my own experience and observations of the long fight for birth
                control and family happiness, I have reached these conclusions:</p>
            <p>Parents should avoid having children if either parent has a transmissible disease
                because no mother or father wants to see their children helpless, devoid of physical
                or mental development.</p>
            <p>Every child should be spaced from two to three years to insure the living child
                nourishment, care, love and a place in the affection of its parents, before another
                comes to take from it, its natural inheritance.</p>
            <p>Young people should marry early but postpone parenthood for two years after marriage
                to secure a firm foundation of love and companionship in marriage before they usher
                a new life into being to share that environment.</p>
            <p>Fewer children, better healthier children in any family helps to establish higher
                standards and bring peace on earth, good will to men over the entire face of the
                globe.</p>
        </div>


    </docBody>
</doc>
