<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/06/22 CE</prepDate><prepDate>2011-11-21 CH correct typo</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1937-06-00">Summer 1937</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Morality and Bigotry</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp320523</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Champion of Youth</title> (Summer 1937), Vol. II, no. 11, p.114.</bibl>
            <bibl>Not filmed.</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="NITFR">Nietzsche, Frederick</name>
            <name id="BIB">The Bible</name>
            <name id="HAM">The Tragedy of Hamlet, Prince of Denmark</name>
            <name id="MACHE">MacCracken, Henry Noble</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>For an earlier, typewritten draft see LC128:0652.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="in marriages"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"
            level3="negative consequences of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="legal cases" level3="U.S. v. One Package of Japanese contraceptives"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="legalization of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="and marriage"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="instructions"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="rights associated with"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="youth and"/>
        <index level1="family planning"/>
        <index level1="marriage" level2="reforms"/>
        <index level1="pregnancy" level2="fears of"/>
        <index level1="sex education" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="sex education" level2="need for"/>
        <index level1="sexual desire"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Morality and Bigotry</head>
        <byline>By <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></byline>
        <p>As I write, thousands upon thousands of young people throughout the country are urging
            the passage of the <name type="bill">American Youth Act</name>. This modern Crusade is
            asking that youth be given a chance, that it be granted at least the same opportunity
            for success as existed for the older generations.</p>
        <p>With the closing of the Western frontier, with the overcrowding of industries and the
            professions, young people (it is pointed out) must be helped to gain a foothold if they
            are to find their place in the sun.</p>
        <p>Youth asks for training, for education, for work. Beneath these demands is the wish to
            exercise the most fundamental of human rights. Youth wants some measure of security, it
            wants the right to marry, to establish homes, to rear children.</p>
        <p>In one respect American youth is starting with a far greater chance for happiness than
            did its parents and grandparents. It is less hemmed in by ancient taboos, by fear and
            reticence, by false modesty and all the tragedy that comes from refusing to face
            facts.</p>
        <p>Love in the finest meaning of the term is the foundation stone of successful marriage. It
            should not be thought of as synonymous with the sexual impulse, though that is a
            necessary part of love. There must be sexual attraction, but it must be firmly rooted in
            mutual understanding. Upon this are built respect, self control, sympathy, unity of
            purpose, many common tastes and desires, a building up and up, until love in its fullest
            expression has flowered to unite two individual personalities. Marriage thus developed
            becomes the strongest, purest, most valuable and unique relationship which we human
            beings are capable of building.</p>
        <p>I believe that a couple entering marriage should start with the idea of taking at least
            two years to get acquainted, to foster a cultural, physical and spiritual understanding,
            a joint way of life. Nothing so certainly dooms marriage--the greatest of adventures--to
            failure as to undertake the trials and complications of parenthood too soon. It is
            unfair to the young bride, because she never knows herself as a wife, a joyful
            companion, but only as a mother. And the young husband cannot learn to know his wife as
            a comrade and helpmate if her whole physical and psychic being is too soon turned
            towards maternity.</p>
        <p>And so, despite the increasing complexity of our present day world, despite its ever
            present threat of war, its economic upheavals, I believe youth has a greater chance for
            happiness than those who entered upon marriage in what may seem to have been a time of
            more ample opportunity.</p>
        <p>Young people today can plan their lives. They can decide when and how often to undertake
            parenthood. Modern methods of birth control permit them to consciously plan their
            future. No longer need they start out on their honeymoon, outwardly rejoicing, but
            inwardly filled with fear of the unknown.</p>
        <p>The young couple about to be married should go for advice to some sympathetic and fully
            informed physician. (Doctors young in years but with a mature outlook and themselves
            married are preferable for this advice.) They should understand the wonderful and
            beautiful facts about sex and their own bodies. The truth about sex, as about all other
            things in life, when frankly and clearly taught, cannot injure healthy, normal young
            minds. Concealment and suppression are what do harm. I have full confidence in the clean
            mindedness, the courage and promise of young people, and to them I say, as has been said
            of old: “<q who="BIB">Know the truth and the truth shall make you free</q>.” Let them
            remember the command: “<q who="NIEFR">Build thou beyond thyself, but first be sure that
                thou thyself art strong and wholesome in body and mind</q>.”</p>
        <p>Dr. <person reg="MacCracken, Henry Noble">Henry Noble MacCracken</person>, president of
                <org>Vassar College</org>, said recently: “<q who="MACHE">Of all hated things, youth
                hates most to be betrayed. <name type="character">Hamlet</name>'s question to <name
                    type="character">Ophelia</name> is the question which youth is ever asking
                education: ‘<q who="HAM">Art thou honest?</q>’ In this whole question of social
                hygiene, of which birth control is a part, youth wants to trust and to be
                trusted</q>.”</p>
        <p>That the president of one of our leading colleges for women can come out in public and
            thus fearlessly advocate giving birth control instruction to youth, is in itself a sign
            of progress. This wise and experienced educator closed his address by saying that he
            believed that, above all, American youth is democratic and demands equality of
            privilege. “<q who="MACHE">When youth learns</q>,” he said, “<q who="MACHE">that those
                who are privileged have access to the facts, while the underprivileged have not, it
                is first angered and then cynical</q>.”</p>
        <p>All honor to American youth, say I, that it has so deep rooted a sense of justice.</p>
        <p>It is doubtless hard for young people who read about birth control in magazines and
            newspapers, who hear it discussed from lecture platforms and pulpits, to realize the
            bigotry which blocked the movement in its early days. The first birth control clinic in
                <place reg="United States">America</place>, which I opened in the crowded slums of
                <place reg="Brooklyn, New York City, NY">Brooklyn</place> twenty-one years ago, was
            closed by the police as a “public nuisance,” and I and my co-workers were arrested. As
            the patrol wagon carried us away to the police station, one young women, who had come
            too late to get advice, ran after us crying and sobbing: “<q who="UNK">Save me, save me,
                come back and save me</q>.”</p>
        <p>She wanted to be saved from the fear of unwanted pregnancies, from the torture and black
            despair of bringing into the world children which she could not feed or care for, from
            the hell of having her life ruled by blind chance.</p>
        <p>How splendid if I could write that no such fear exists today that everyone wh wants birth
            control information can get it. But this is still far from the case. Birth control
            clinics are no longer closed as public nuisances. More and more are being established
            with the help of doctors and social workers and public spirited citizens, and with the
            blessings of the liberal clergy. Birth Control methods are safe, easy to use, and
            reasonably cheap and reliable. Women who happen to live near one of the 350 clinics now
            functioning throughout the country, and women who can afford to go to private
            physicians, can get information. A <name type="case"
                reg="United States vs. One Package of Japanese Contraceptives">recent Court
                decision</name> has removed the legal barriers which have retarded birth control
            work, and has established the right of American physicians in this field of medicine.
                <emph rend="italics">But thousands upon thousands of people are still in
                ignorance</emph>, and the women who most need this advice are still vainly crying
            “save me, save me.”</p>
        <p>But I do not despair, for youth will take a hand, and as Dr. MacCracken says, youth will
            not tolerate hypocrisy. What is the privilege of the comparative few, is the right of
            the many.</p>
        <p>I believe young people should look forward to marriage and parenthood. To this end, I
            acclaim their struggle for education and economic security. I believe they should enter
            marriage with full knowledge of how to postpone parenthood for at least two years, so
            that they may work and play and learn to know each other, and strengthen the bonds which
            have brought them together. Then and then only should they undertake parenthood. I also
            believe that young people should be better prepared and trained for a full, useful life.
            Girls in particular, before going into shops and factories, should be given training in
            hospitals. They should learn about diet, hygiene, care of the body and the home. I
            should like to see every girl enrolled for such training before she is allowed to enter
            the world of business, or before she is given a license to marry. For homemaking in the
            fullest meaning of the term is an exacting career and needs the best preparation that
            can be secured.</p>
        <p>With such a program, we would have more permanent marriages, happier homes, greater love
            and respect, and in the end, more children.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
