<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/06/01 CE</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1936-11-00">Nov 1936</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Gandhi and Mrs. Sanger Debate Birth Control</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp320521</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Asia</title>Vol. 26, no. 11, November 1936, pp.
                698-702</bibl>
            <bibl><title>LCM</title>C19</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="GANMO">Gandhi, Mohandas K.</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>For typed and handwritten drafts, see LCM 129:535
            and LCM 129:525.</p><p>The editor's introduction draws heavily from
            Sanger's diary entry. For the full entry, see LCM 1:209.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to" level3="international"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits and risks"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="in marriages"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="international"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="continence"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="opposition to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="religion and"/>
        <index level1="children" level2="unwanted"/>
        <index level1="conjugal intimacy" level2="the right of"/>
        <index level1="family planning"/>
        <index level1="family size" level2="class-based"/>
        <index level1="Gandhi, Mahatma"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="love" level2="concept of"/>
        <index level1="men" level2="sexual fulfillment of"/>
        <index level1="population" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="population" level2="food supply and"/>
        <index level1="poverty" level2="family size and"/>
        <index level1="pregnancy" level2="fears of"/>
        <index level1="sexuality" level2="women's"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Gandhi and Mrs. Sanger Debate Birth Control</head>
        <div type="section">
            <p><head type="sub">Editor's Introduction</head>.--Last winter
                    <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
                spent ten weeks in <place>India</place>, speaking on birth
                control to large audiences throughout the country. During her
                visit she held more than forty public meetings, established
                about fifty centers of birth control information and secured the
                endorsements of the <org>All-India Women's Conference</org>, the
                    <org>All-India Medical Conference</org> and <org
                    reg="Bombay Municipal Corporation">Bombay
                municipality</org>.</p>
            <p>Mrs. Sanger stayed two days with <person
                    reg="Gandhi, Mohandas K.">Gandhi</person> at his
                    <emph>ashrama</emph> in <place reg="Wardha, India"
                    >Wardha</place> and engaged him in a friendly argument on
                birth control. We quote what Mrs. Sanger says in her own diary
                of their meeting:</p>
            <p>“We went directly to his place and met, although this is his day
                of silence. He rose to greet me, smiling from ear to ear. I put
                down my bag and gloves and flowers and magazines inorder to take
                both his hands. He has an unusual light that shines in his face;
                that shines through the flesh; that circles around his head and
                neck like a mist with white sails of a ship coming through. It
                lasted only a few seconds, but it is there. When I looked again
                it was only the shiny appearance of his flesh that I saw but
                always the smile and a hospitable welcome.”</p>
            <p>Since Mrs. Sanger arrived on Gandhi's day <supplied>of</supplied>
                silence, she spent her first day inspecting the industries
                connected with the ashrama.</p>
            <p>In the evening there was “supper on the veranda at Gandhiji's
                residence. They are building another story to the old house for
                his study. Now he has no privacy and needs it. We all sat on the
                floor. Shoes removed first, food is placed on trays by
                attendants. No one may eat until prayers are said which are said
                only when the tray has considerable food. It was a chant by all
                in a ‘lullaby’ tune. Gandhiji gave me a spoonful of very bitter
                green puree. They were all amused at its reception and my face
                in getting it down. Then there were raw onions cut up in cream.
                One hot vegetable soup, one hot milk, dry flap-jacks, a fresh
                orange and other vegetables and rice. Really a lot of food.
                Gandhi is experimenting with foods, trying tofind out the most
                economical for the village people and the most nourishing. The
                great majority are living a life of starvation. When you ask a
                villager how things are going, he points to his stomach and
                says, ‘<q who="UNK">Sahib, stomach too long empty</q>.’</p>
            <p>“We went on the roof to see the sun set, then in the tonga to the
                temple and now to evening prayers. At seven P.M. all twenty
                persons were seated with legs crossed under them onthe roof.
                They were all dressed in white, with the moon shining down and
                the stars overhead. Gandhiji and both woman guests were seated
                at the head of the circle. Since we came in a little late we sat
                in the circle near the poor ‘depressed’ woman workers who were
                not in white. <person reg="Gandhi, Devdas">Mr. Gandhi's
                    son</person>, his youngest, is here. His <person
                    reg="Gandhi, Kanti Harilal">grandson</person> led the
                prayers in the moonlight. <person reg="Gandhi, Kasturba Nakanji"
                    >Mrs. Gandhi</person> served our food and spices. She is a
                short, stoutish, unimpressive woman, but very kind and tender.
                After prayers, which were chanted, I went down to Gandhiji's
                office; he wrote a few notes tome inviting me to walk in the
                morning, also saying that at seven thirty A.M. he will have a
                talk with me and it can be absolutely exclusive.”</p>
            <p>The next morning Mrs. Sanger rose at six and went to meet Gandhi
                and the two other woman guests. They “all went with him to the
                village, San, which is his regular morning walk. He is trying t
                clean up the village by erecting ‘privies,’ portable on stilts
                to be moved from pit to pit to save the fertilizer and use it
                quickly. Gandhiji walks quickly and has his customary white
                robes, sandals and staff. We talked of food and diet. He has
                studied this question for forty years and disapproves of
                uncooked starches. After the walk I had a bath and dashed over
                to keep the seven thirty appointment on the roof in the morning
                sun. There were four of his people present and <person
                    reg="Phillips, Anna Jane">Anna Jane</person> [Anna Jane
                Philips, Mrs. Sanger's secretary] and myself. I am to return at
                three o’clock.”</p>
            <p>Mrs. Sanger goes on: “At three o’clock promptly, we went to the
                Mahatma's house and had our talk on the roof. He sat in the
                burning sunshine with a white cloth over his head. We sat inthe
                shade. the arguments were along the same line as inthe morning,
                but I am convinced his personal experience at the time of his
                father's death was so shocking and self-blamed that he can never
                accept sex as anything good, clean or wholesome.”</p>
            <p>When a western woman of such international prominence as Mrs.
                Sanger has a serious talk with the greatest Indian of our time
                on a subject so important and controversial as birth control, we
                believe that what they had to say to each othr on this occasion
                has historical as well as immediate value and should be offered
                verbatim to our readers. Fortunately Mrs. Sanger's secretary was
                present at both the morning and afternoon interviews and took
                them down in shorthand. We are therefore presenting this unusual
                interview, which has never before been published. A few extracts
                from it were quoted in an article which Mrs. Sanger wrote while
                she was in India for <title>The Illustrated Weekly of
                    India</title> and in the reply to Mrs. Sanger by <person
                    reg="Desai, Mahadev">Mahadev Desai</person> in Mr. Gandhi's
                paper <title>Harijan</title>--reprinted in part by <title>The
                    Illustrated Weekly of India</title>. We are presenting the
                interview exactly as it took place between Mrs. Sanger and
                Gandhi, except to strike out a few statements that duplicated
                what had gone before and to eliminate a few unessential passages
                to save space.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">Morning</head>
            <p><emph>Mrs. Sanger</emph>: Mr. Gandhi, you and I have the interest
                of humanity at heart, but while both of us have that in common,
                you have greater influence with the masses of humanity. I
                believe no nation can be free until its women have control over
                the power that is peculiarly theirs, I mean the power of
                procreation.... Women's lack of control over fecundity results
                in overpopulation, in poverty, misery and war. Should women
                control this force which has made so much trouble in their
                lives? Do you see any practical solution for this problem, which
                in my humble opinion is the direct cause of much of the chaos in
                the world today?</p>
            <p><emph>Mr Gandhi</emph>: <q who="GANMO">I suppose you know that
                    all my life I have been dinning into the ears of women the
                    fact that they are their own mistresses, not only in this
                    but in all matters. I began my work with my own wife. While
                    I have abused my wife in many respects, I have tried to be
                    her teacher also. If today she is somewhat literate it is
                    because I became her teacher. I was not the ideal teacher
                    because I was a brute. The animal passion in me was too
                    strong and I could not become the ideal teacher. My wife I
                    made the orbit of al women. In her I studied all women. I
                    came into contact with many European women in <place>South
                        Africa</place>, but I knew practically every Indian
                    woman there. I worked with them. I tried to show them they
                    were not slaves either of their husbands or parents, that
                    they had as much right to resist their husbands as their
                    parents, not only in the political field but in the domestic
                    as well. But the trouble was that some could not resist
                    their husbands. I feel that I speak with some confidence and
                    knowledge because I have worked with and talked with and
                    studied many women. But the remedy is in the hands of the
                    women themselves. The struggle is difficult for them but I
                    do not blame them. I blame the men. Men have legislated
                    against them. Man has regarded woman as his tool. She has
                    learned to be his tool and in the end found it easy and
                    pleasurable to be such, because when one drags another in
                    his fall the descent is easy. I have come in contact with
                    some women of the West but not many, so that my deductions
                    about them may be faulty, but I have known tens of thousands
                    of women in India, their experiences and their aspirations.
                    I have discussed it with some of my educated sisters but I
                    have questioned their authority to speak on behalf of their
                    unsophisticated sisters, because they have never mixed with
                    them. The educated ones have never felt one with them. But I
                    have. they regarded me as half a woman because I have
                    completely identified myself with them. I have identified
                    myself with my wife to the same extent, but she observes
                    certain decencies with me, which I have not done with her. I
                    intimately know her. I have made use of her. But I do not
                    suppose there are many women who can claim to have followed
                    their husbands so slavishly as she has. She has followed,
                    sometimes reluctantly, but her reluctance has had a tinge of
                    obedience in it, for she is a good Hindu wife. I have often
                    challenged her and asked her to lead her own independent
                    life but she will not do so. She is too much a Hindu wife
                    for that. I have felt that during the years still left to me
                    if I can drive home to women's minds the truth that they are
                    free, we will have no birth control problem in India. If
                    they will only earn to say “no” to their husbands when they
                    approach them carnally! ... The real problem is that they do
                    not want to resist them. I have been reading about this
                    cause which you advocate so eloquently. I know some of the
                    greatest people in the world agree with you. In India I
                    would mention only two great representative names, <person
                        reg="Tagore, Rabindranath">Tagore</person> and <person
                        reg="Naidu, Sarojini">Mrs. Naidu</person>. I know I have
                    them all arrayed against me. I have tried to think with
                    them.... My fudamental position is that so far as the women
                    of India are concerned, even if the method you advocate were
                    a solution, it is a long way off, for the women of India
                    have so many things to think of now. Don't tell me of the
                    educated girl of India. She will be your slave, much to her
                    damage, I’m afraid.</q></p>
            <p><emph>Mrs. Sanger</emph>: You mean for instance that the women of
                the chawls will be against me, the women in the tenements of
                    <place reg="Bombay, India">Bombay</place>?</p>
            <p><emph>Mr. Gandhi</emph>: <q who="GANMO">Yes</q>.</p>
            <p><emph>Mrs. Sanger</emph>: I disagree with you. When I was in
                Bombay one of th first places I went was to these women of the
                tenements. I saw them sitting around, each with three, four or
                more children. We asked them how many children they had had, how
                many were dead. There were always some dead. Then we asked how
                many more they were going to have, and every woman but one held
                out her hands in supplication as though saying: “<q who="UNK">No
                    more. Pray God, no more!</q>” It showed that they were
                already awakened to this idea. Again and again they ask what to
                do to prevent more children from coming into the world. I want
                to go to the villages and see whether this desire to have fewer
                children is not there. Let us not worry about the methods. Let
                us first discover whether they want more children or not. that
                will be the beginning.</p>
            <p><emph>Mr Gandhi</emph>: <q who="GANMO">I don't want to say that
                    women want children but that they will not do the thing that
                    will keep them from having more children. They will not
                    resist their husbands. Then I suppose you will say, if
                    neither party resists, why should they not adopt artificial
                    methods?</q></p>
            <p><emph>Mrs. Sanger</emph>: You have been a great advocate of civil
                disobedience, Mr. Gandhi. Do you also recommend that the women
                of India adopt legal and marital disobedience?</p>
            <p><emph>Mr. Gandhi</emph>: <q who="GANMO">Yes, I do. But no
                    resistance bordering upon bitterness will be necessary in
                    ninety-nine out of a hundred cases. If a wife says to her
                    husband, “No, I don't want it,” he will make no trouble. But
                    she hasn't been taught</q>....</p>
            <p><emph>Mrs. Sanger</emph>: But that advice is not practical. It
                means a revolution in the home. It leads to divorce. The average
                marriage contract assumes that the married relationship will be
                harmonious.</p>
            <p><emph>Mr. Gandhi</emph>: <q who="GANMO">There should be mutual
                    consent. Without it the thing will be wholly wrong</q>.</p>
            <p><emph>Mrs. Sanger</emph>: that is right, but the problem is not
                often discussed by young people before marriage, although our
                young of today are beginning to discuss it more and more, which
                is a very good thing. But consider the turmoil, the unhappiness
                it means for the woman if she resists her husband! What if he
                puts her out of her home? In some states in the <place>United
                    States</place> a wife has no rights if she resists her
                husband. What can she do? I do not know the law in India, but
                custom compels her to submit to the sexual needs of her
                husband.</p>
            <p><emph>Mr. Gandhi</emph>: <q who="GANMO">There are no such laws
                    here</q>.</p>
            <p><emph>Mrs. Sanger</emph>: Yes, but the custom is here. Customs
                are harder to change than laws.</p>
            <p><emph>Mr. Gandhi</emph>: <q who="GANMO">Yes</q>.</p>
            <p><emph>Mrs. Sanger</emph>: You are giving them advice which they
                cannot accept. Would it not make their condition worse?</p>
            <p><emph>Mr Gandhi</emph>: <q who="GANMO">Not if they learn the art
                    of resistance. It boils down to education. I want woman to
                    learn the primary right of resistance. She thinks now that
                    she has not got it. Among the women of India it is most
                    difficult to drive home this truth. If I were to devote
                    myself to birth control I would miss this primary
                    education</q>.</p>
            <p><emph>Mrs. Sanger</emph>: But cannot education go with birth
                control? In <place>England</place> many social workers claim
                that if they can instruct the poorer women in birth control
                before their fifth child is born, before the women have fallen
                into poverty and drink and degradation, these women can be
                helped. In <place>America</place> in the clinics it has been
                found in a number of cased where women have been given birth
                control information and freed from undesired pregnancies for a
                period of from eighteen months to two years that the woman and
                her husband have become self-reliant and self-supporting and the
                case has been closed on the welfare books. The woman has more
                hope. She is not haunted by the fear of more and more and still
                more pregnancies. Every case shows a better condition of the
                woman's mind, more patience, love, education in the woman's life
                and home after she has been freed of the worry of having too
                many children. Mr. Gandhi, do you not see a great difference
                between sex love and sex lust? Isn't it sex lust and not sex
                love which you oppose?</p>
            <p><emph>Mr. Gandhi</emph>: <q who="GANMO">Yes, it is. But when both
                    want to satisfy animal passion without having to suffer the
                    consequences of their act, it is not love. It is lust. But
                    if love is pure it will transcend animal passion and will
                    regulate itself. We have not had enough education of the
                    passions. When a husband says, “Let us not have children but
                    have relations,” what is that but animal passion? If they do
                    not want to have any more children they should simply refuse
                    to unite</q>.</p>
            <p><emph>Mrs. Sanger</emph>: Then you hold that all sex union is
                lust except that for the specific purpose of having
                children?</p>
            <p><emph>Mr. Gandhi</emph>: <q who="GANMO">Yes</q>.</p>
            <p><emph>Mrs. Sanger</emph>: I think that is a weak position, Mr.
                Gandhi. The act is the same. The force that brings two people
                together is sex attraction, a biological urge, which finds
                expression in sex union. There are two kinds of passion. One is
                a force around which centers respect, consideration and
                reverence known as love. The latter kind may be the stepladder
                to God. I do not call that kink of love lust, even when it finds
                expression in sex union, with or without children.</p>
            <p><emph>Mr. Gandhi</emph>: <q who="GANMO">I think there is a flaw
                    in that position and the world will not have to wait long
                    before it discovers it. I have found the same thing in old
                    Sanskrit volumes, found lust clothed in the dress of love.
                    But I know from my own experience that, as long as I looked
                    upon my wife carnally, we had no real understanding. Our
                    love did not reach a high plane. There was affection, of
                    course, between us. Affection there has been between us
                    always but we came closer and closer the more we, or rather
                    I, became restrained. There never was want of restraint on
                    the part of my wife. Very often she would show restraint,
                    but she rarely resisted me although she shower
                    disinclination very often. All the time I wanted carnal
                    pleasure I could not serve her. She would be a fairly
                    learned woman today if I had not let this lust interfere
                    with her education. She is not dull-witted, but it takes all
                    one's resources to drive home a lesson. I had plenty of time
                    at my disposal to teach her before I became involved in
                    public affairs but I didn't take advantage of it. When I had
                    outlived animal passion and found a better mission in life,
                    I had no time</q>.</p>
            <p><emph>Mrs. Sanger</emph>: I think lust is a very different thing
                from love. I believe in sex love. Perhaps love in sex is a new
                thing in our evolution, and develops in the human race as we
                evolve toward a higher consciousness. But it is usually
                acknowledged to be a very real thing, a force that cannot be
                denied....</p>
            <p><emph>Mr. Gandhi</emph>: <q who="GANMO">May one man have pure sex
                    lust with more than one woman or a woman with more that one
                    man? Your literature is full of that</q>.</p>
            <p><emph>Mrs. Sanger</emph>: Love, no. Lust, yes. But I think pure
                love comes of itself.</p>
            <p><emph>Mr. Gandhi</emph>: <q who="GANMO">No, it does not come of
                    itself. If you have a love for more than one woman, how do
                    you know which is which?</q></p>
            <p><emph>Mrs. Sanger</emph>: If we can have a choice in our mates
                there is a natural sex attraction between two people. You then
                have a different experience and in the experience an expression
                of love which makes you a finer human being. Sex lust is spent
                in prostitution, the sort of relationship which makes for
                oneness, for completeness between the husband and wife and
                contributes to a finer understanding and a greater spiritual
                harmony.</p>
            <p><emph>Mr. Gandhi</emph>: <q who="GANMO">You are talking in this
                    strain because social custom has restricted marriage to one
                    at a time in the West, but in the East it is not so. Many
                    believe it lawful to have more than one wife. Or you may
                    have a wife and concubines. I have thought this question
                    through. In the East this practice has been going on a long
                    time. Now I don't ask this question to put you in a corner.
                    This is the argument I had with a woman with whom I almost
                    fell. It is so personal that I did not put it in my
                    autobiography. We had considered if there can be this
                    spiritual companionship. the marriage relationship is a
                    matter of contract. Your parents arrange it in your
                    childhood and you have nothing to do with it. I come in
                    contact with an illiterate woman. Then I meet a woman with a
                    broad, cultural education. Could we not develop a close
                    contact, I said to myself? This was a plausible argument,
                    and I nearly slipped. But I was saved, I awoke from my
                    trance. I don't know how. For a time it seemed I had lost my
                    anchor. I was saved by youngsters who warned me. I saw that
                    if I was doomed, they also were doomed. I decided I was not
                    right in my argument</q>.</p>
            <p><emph>Mrs. Sanger</emph>: I wonder if this is a rationalization
                or a personal feeling. Even with those men who have concubines,
                don't you think there is one person among the concubines to whom
                they are most devoted? When a man finds the one woman for him,
                their personalities tune in. There is harmony and growth in
                their union.</p>
            <p><emph>Mr. Gandhi</emph>: <q who="GANMO">Have you read of the
                        <title>Mahabharata</title> legend where
                        <person>Draupadi</person>, the heroine, has five
                    husbands? In its place this union has been glorified as the
                    ideal union. Each husband has his own complete right in the
                    wife. Now in Islam, in contrast, they let a man marry up to
                    five wives on condition that all be treated as upon the same
                    level. The <person reg="Mohammed">Prophet</person> does not
                    call it lust and several philosophers in Islam defend the
                    thing. I have talked to many of these men. They think what
                    is happening in the West is debasing and that if all
                    recognized polygamy the world would be better. The followers
                    of Islam can advance good arguments for it</q>.</p>
            <p><emph>Mrs. Sanger</emph>: We cannot speak for all nations. The
                human race is evolving like a class in school.... But I agree
                with you that we have to start with the individual. You feel
                that the beginning is with the individual's control of sex.
                There is no argument there. But do you realize that from the
                time of marriage until the end of woman's child-bearing period,
                if she has sex relations with her husband only once each year,
                she will have ten or twelve children? So that, even with the
                most continent life, she will be the victim of a large family
                which she cannot take care of. Must husbands and wives sacrifice
                their lives for this? Must this relationship, based on a finer
                quality of love, take place only three or four times in their
                entire lifetime?</p>
            <p><emph>Mr. Gandhi</emph>: <q who="GANMO">Why should people not be
                    taught that it is immoral to have more than three or four
                    children and that after they have had that number they
                    should live separately? If they are taught this it would
                    harden into custom. And if social reformers cannot impress
                    this idea upon the people, why not a law?</q> ...</p>
            <p><emph>Mrs. Sanger</emph>: The education that goes with birth
                control gives men and women a higher physical, mental and moral
                control. Isn't there something you can approve that they can put
                into practice? Can't you advise something practical, something
                that can be applied to solve the problem of too frequent child
                bearing for the mothers of India?</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">Afternoon</head>
            <p><emph>Mrs. Sanger</emph>: Let us go back to your first point,
                continence. Do you accept the decision of most modern
                neurologists and physicians of the world that continence cannot
                be generally advised and except for particular cases its
                practice makes for great nervous and mental disturbances?</p>
            <p><emph>Mr. Gandhi</emph>: <q who="GANMO">I have read much on the
                    subject. the evidence is all based on examination of
                    imbeciles. The conclusions are not drawn from the practice
                    of healthy minded people. The people they take for examples
                    have not lived a life of even tolerable continence. These
                    neurologists assume that people will be able to exercise
                    self-restraint while they continue to lead the same
                    ill-regulated life. The consequence is that they do not
                    exercise self-restraint but become lunatics. I carry on a
                    correspondence which many of these people and they describe
                    their own ailments tome. I simply say that if I were to
                    present them with this method of birth control, they would
                    lead far worse lives</q>.</p>
            <p><emph>Mrs. Sanger</emph>: I just wondered because as you know
                there are many men who encounter this problem, who are not
                abnormal men but good fathers, hard workers, men who want to do
                right. I just want to give you two cases in particular.... These
                men are not vicious men. They are not brutes. They love their
                wives. They are trying to control a powerful force planted in
                their beings at birth. If that force is wrong and evil, why was
                it placed in their bodies by the Creator of all good?</p>
            <p><emph>Mr. Gandhi</emph>: <q who="GANMO">If bother are not ready
                    it becomes degradation for one to ask. If you eliminate
                    birth control there will be other methods. The case for
                    birth control is not hopelessly weak, otherwise these
                    brilliant men would not be aligned with it. As in law, hard
                    cases make bad law and because you can cite hard cases does
                    not prove your method right. We must devise other means. As
                    soon as you agree to eliminate certain methods as harmful,
                    you are bound to find others. In the cases you tell of, as
                    soon as I made the discovery I would have seen to it that
                    the men and women were separated</q>.</p>
            <p><emph>Mrs. Sanger</emph>: But what about the woman's economic
                condition? She has had no preparation to support herself,
                especially in India. She has depended upon marriage and her
                husband for maintenance and her bread and butter. Who is to take
                care of the children? You must think of these things when you
                suggest separation.</p>
            <p><emph>Mr. Gandhi</emph>: <q who="GANMO">You must devise means. I
                    might suggest that the state take care of them. Or the law
                    might be called in to give a divorce. At present divorce is
                    granted on grounds of infidelity. In the future it may be
                    granted on grounds of health. Even then some hard cases will
                    occur</q>....</p>
            <p><emph>Mrs. Sanger</emph>: But, Mr. Gandhi, the advanced women of
                the western world have for the past decade or two refused to
                submit their bodies as receptacles for a man's passion. Women
                have feelings as deep and as amorous as men. There are times
                when wives desire physical union as much as their husbands.
                Doesn't that change the character of the relationship? Doesn't
                that make a difference? In such cases where there is a
                fifty-fifty proposition regarding sex or marital expression,
                both feel this is a necessary part of the happiness of their
                lives. What have you to say in regard to this?</p>
            <p><emph>Mr. Gandhi</emph>: <q who="GANMO">I would devise other
                    methods. I would not say all methods have universal
                    application. There would be ways of regulating or curbing
                    that passion. If artificial methods are to be avoided,
                    other, natural methods will have to be devised. Supposing
                    that you and I as social reformers said, “If this remedy is
                    not open, we’ll have to fall back on others.” But the
                    difficulty of mutual approach stares us in the face, because
                    I belong to a generation that believes that life is made for
                    self-restraint in every way of life. Your generation
                    believes in a multiplication of wants, freedom of all human
                    passions.... When you make up your mind to follow a code of
                    ethics you must determine to sacrifice health and ease.
                    there are things more important than health; things more
                    precious that life and well-being</q>.</p>
            <p><emph>Mrs. Sanger</emph>: Yes, I agree that such things should
                not be imposed upon people. I am not attempting to force birth
                control upon any one. I am just offering the knowledge to help
                solve some difficult problems.</p>
            <p><emph>Mr. Gandhi</emph>: <q who="GANMO">Ah yes, Mrs. Sanger, I
                    know you are not trying to impose birth control but there
                    are some birth controllers who would compel men and women to
                    follow them</q>....</p>
            <p><emph>Mrs. Sanger</emph>: In the United States our birth rate is
                lowering. We have many older people now because people live
                longer. Then we have raised the age of marriage, which shortens
                a woman's childbearing period. You think that your poorer people
                are not fertile? Where does your population increase come from
                then? Who has the large families?</p>
            <p><emph>Mr. Gandhi</emph>: <q who="GANMO">The burden of large
                    families falls on the middle class; as far as mere fertility
                    is concerned, the fertility is greater among the middle than
                    the lower classes. If that was not true you would not have
                    the low average of five children per family for India. We do
                    not have such a terrible problem as you face in America or
                        <place>Europe</place>. The problem is with the middle
                    class where indulgence is running riot. They use their wives
                    as playthings. I am sorry to have to say this, but it is
                    true. I don't say there is no illicit intercourse among the
                    poor in India but there is not the fertility.... Take the
                    lot of the millions--starvation. I have lived in it for
                    twenty-one days, but I had no passion. I do not mean to tell
                    you that at sixty-seven I have no passion, but I can
                    regulate it</q>.</p>
            <p><emph>Mrs. Sanger</emph>: But, Mr. Gandhi, there are thousands,
                millions, who regard your word as that of a saint. How can you
                ask them who are so humble, so weak, to follow, when you are so
                much stronger and wiser, have taken years to bring about that
                self-control in your life?</p>
            <p>(Mr. Gandhi just smiled.)</p>
            <p><emph>Mrs. Sanger</emph>: But to come back to this point. Is the
                reason you object to artificial means of birth control because
                of the means or the act? ...</p>
            <p><emph>Mr. Gandhi</emph>: <q who="GANMO">Yes, I object for the
                    latter reason</q>....</p>
            <p><emph>Mrs. Sanger</emph>: Have you from your experience in life
                seen that the people who have had no love in their lives, who
                have practised continence and restraint, are higher evolved
                persons than those who have lived normally?</p>
            <p><emph>Mr. Gandhi</emph>: <q who="GANMO">I can not lay down an
                    absolute rule. I know many fine people who have practised
                    continence and restraint and many who have not</q>....</p>
            <p><emph>Mrs. Sanger</emph>: Haven't you some message of
                encouragement that I can take away with me to help in this work
                which we are doing for humanity?</p>
            <p><emph>Mr. Gandhi</emph>: <q who="GANMO">I can only say may <name
                        type="deity">God</name> guide you right as you would say
                    to me. We are only human beings. I think highly of your
                    purpose; otherwise I would not have given time to this
                    subject. With me God is truth. I would sacrifice everything,
                    even India, for the sake of truth. But if someone wanted to
                    open my mind and tried to prove I was living in a fool's
                    paradise, I would not close my ears to him. Of course, I
                    should have little part with a man arguing a case for
                    untruth, but I would let him argue it and say, "Let untruth
                    be as much God as truth and have as much effect of me if it
                    should.”</q></p>
            <p><emph>Mrs. Sanger</emph>: The good of humanity is in both our
                hearts, and I ma the last person to say that the end justifies
                the means. But in birth control as in everything else the proper
                use of knowledge is very important. Everything good can be
                misused or used without control, and thus becomes harmful. When
                we give birth control information it goes hand in hand with
                education for the betterment of the children, the family and the
                race.</p>
            <p><emph>Mr. Gandhi</emph>: <q who="GANMO">Don't go away with the
                    idea that this has been wasted effort. We have certainly
                    come nearer together</q>.</p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
