<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/06/07 CE</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/06/20 CE</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1959-00-00">1959</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Birth Control, 1958</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp320988</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Britannica Book of the Year</title>(1959), p.
                108</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="LCBAC">Lambeth Conference of the Bishops of the Anglican
                Communion</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>For other articles in the <title>Britannica Book of
                the Year</title> series, see <xref from="320976.xml"
                    ><title>Birth Control, 1944</title></xref>; <xref
                from="320980.xml"><title>Birth Control, 1946</title></xref>;
                <xref from="320979.xml"><title>Birth Control,
                1947</title></xref>; <xref from="321981.xml"><title>Birth
                    Control, 1948</title>, 1949</xref>;<xref from="320981.xml"
                    ><title>Birth Control, 1949</title></xref>; <xref
                from="321981.xml"><title>Birth Control, 1950</title></xref>;
                <xref from="320983.xml"><title>Birth Control,
                1951</title></xref>; <xref from="320984.xml"><title>Birth
                    Control, 1952</title></xref>; <xref from="321984.xml"
                    ><title>Birth Control, 1953</title></xref>; <xref
                from="320985.xml"><title>Birth Control, 1954</title></xref>;
                <xref from="320986.xml"><title>Birth Control,
                1955</title></xref>; <xref from="none.xml"><title>Birth Control,
                    1956</title></xref>; <xref from="320987.xml"><title>Birth
                    Control, 1957</title></xref></p>
        <index level1="Asia" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to" level3="international"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues"
            level3="in US"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"
            level3="morality of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="international"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="international conferences on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation"
            level3="New York "/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="legalization of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="American"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="international"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="Soviet Union"/>
        <index level1="Catholic Church"/>
        <index level1="England" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="family planning"/>
        <index level1="New York City" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="physicians" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="Planned Parenthood Federation of America"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="freedom and rights of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Birth Control.</head>
        <p>Two events–one in the <place>United States</place> and one in
                <place>England</place>–highlighted the year 1958 for the family
            planning movement. In <place reg="New York City, NY">New York
                city</place>, a longstanding prohibition on birth control
            services in municipal hospitals was reversed. And in England, the
                <org>Lambeth conference of the bishops</org> of the
                <org>Anglican (Protestant Episcopal) Communion</org> adopted a
            new statement vigorously endorsing family planning.</p>
        <p>In July the <person reg="Jacobs, Morris A.">hospital
                commissioner</person> of New York city ordered a doctor at a
            city hospital not to prescribe a contraceptive for a Protestant
            patient whose life, the doctor believed, would be endangered by
            another pregnancy. This action drew widespread protests from the
            city’s Protestant and Jewish groups, as well as many civic and
            medical organizations; it was supported by the <org
                reg="Roman Catholic Archdiocese of New York City">Roman Catholic
                Archdiocese</org>. After two months in which the issue was
            discussed prominently in the press, the <org
                reg="New York City Board of Hospitals">Board of Hospitals</org>,
            by an 8-2 vote, reversed the ban. The board, noting that the medical
            profession recognizes contraception as the proper therapeutic
            procedure when pregnancy is contraindicated, authorized municipal
            hospital staffs to provide this service in such situations. It also
            exempted from participation personnel who had religious objections
            to birth control. The new policy was subsequently extended to cover
            the medical services of the city’s welfare department.</p>
        <p>At the Lambeth conference the Episcopal bishops, representing 46
            countries, characterized birth control as “<q who="LCBAC">a right
                and important factor in Christian family life</q>.”
            Responsibility “<q who="LCBAC">for deciding upon the number and
                frequency of children has been laid by God upon the consciences
                of parents everywhere</q>,” the bishops stated. “<q who="LCBAC"
                >The procreation of children is not the sole purpose of
                Christian marriage. Implicit within the bond between husband and
                wife is the relationship of love with its sacramental expression
                in physical union</q>.”</p>
        <p>Further progress was made in the world-wide effort to discover
            simpler, more effective means of controlling fertility. Clinical
            tests continued in <place>Puerto Rico</place>, the U.S. and
            elsewhere of a new oral contraceptive pill–a steroid device–while
            basic research was initiated into other aspects of the reproductive
            system.</p>
        <p>Interest in family planning in the <place
                reg="Union of Soviet Socialist Republics">Soviet Union</place>
            was indicated by an official invitation to <person
                reg="Stone, Abraham">Abraham Stone</person>, vice-president of
            the <org>Planned Parenthood Federation of America</org>, to address
            the <org>10th National Conference of Gynecologists and
                Obstetricians</org> in <place reg="Moscow, Soviet Union"
                >Moscow</place>. Stone reported that physicians from all parts
            of the Soviet Union were eager to obtain specific information on
            modern birth control techniques, products and research activities in
            western countries.</p>
        <p>In its annual report, the Planned Parenthood Federation of America
            noted that during 1957 more than 250,000 visits were made to centres
            operated by the federation’s 103 state and local affiliates by women
            seeking contraceptive service, infertility treatment and marriage
            education. At the federation’s annual meeting in November, the
            Albert and Mary Lasker Award in Planned Parenthood was given to
                <person reg="Brown, Harrison">Harrison Brown</person> of the
                <org>California Institute of Technology</org> for his pioneering
            work on the relationship between population growth and future needs
            for resources <supplied resp="MSPP">...</supplied> his educational
            activity among scientists and laymen on <supplied resp="MSPP"
                >the</supplied> need for world-wide family planning to achieve
            and maintain global resource population balance. The
                <org>International Planned Parenthood federation</org> held a
            western hemisphere regional conference in <place>Jamaica</place>,
                <place reg="British West Indies">B.W.I.</place>, in <gap
                reason="faulty reproduction" extent="one word"/> and heard a
            forthright statement of the need for birth control <supplied
                resp="MSPP">from</supplied> Sir <person
                reg="Adams, Grantley Herbert">Grantley Adams</person>, who had
            just been elected premier of <supplied resp="MSPP">the</supplied>
            newly formed <place>West Indian federation</place>. Similar emphasis
            on <supplied resp="MSPP">the</supplied> need for birth control was
            contained in many addresses at <supplied resp="MSPP">the</supplied>
            <org>Afro-Asian Conference of Women</org> in <place
                reg="Colombo, Ceylon">Colombo</place> in February <gap
                reason="faulty reproduction" extent="one word">...</gap>
            <supplied resp="MSPP">at</supplied>tended by 119 delegates from 18
            countries.</p>
        <p>The <org reg="Roman Catholic Church">Roman Catholic hierarchy</org>
            is opposed to mechanical <supplied resp="MSPP">and</supplied>
            chemical methods of contraception. Under ecclesiastical <supplied
                resp="MSPP">approbation</supplied> it permits, however,
            distribution of informational <supplied resp="MSPP"
                >literature</supplied> about the so-called “safe” period.</p>
        <byline>(<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">M.SR</person>.)</byline>
    </docBody>
</doc>
