<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/06/06 CE</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/06/20 CE</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1950-00-00">1950</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Birth Control, 1949</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp320981</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Britannica Book of the Year</title>(1950), p.
                113</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="JWM">Ministry of Health and Welfare, Japan</name>
            <name id="PPFA">Planned Parenthood Federation of America</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>For other articles in the <title>Britannica Book of
                the Year</title> series, see <xref from="320976.xml"
                    ><title>Birth Control, 1949</title></xref>; <xref
                from="320980.xml"><title>Birth Control, 1946</title></xref>;
                <xref from="320979.xml"><title>Birth Control,
                1947</title></xref>; <xref from="321981.xml"><title>Birth
                    Control, 1948</title>, 1949</xref>; <xref from="321981.xml"
                    ><title>Birth Control, 1950</title></xref>; <xref
                from="320983.xml"><title>Birth Control, 1951</title></xref>;
                <xref from="320984.xml"><title>Birth Control,
                1952</title></xref>; <xref from="321984.xml"><title>Birth
                    Control, 1953</title></xref>; <xref from="320985.xml"
                    ><title>Birth Control, 1954</title></xref>; <xref
                from="320986.xml"><title>Birth Control, 1955</title></xref>;
                <xref from="none.xml"><title>Birth Control, 1956</title></xref>;
                <xref from="320987.xml"><title>Birth Control,
                1957</title></xref>; <xref from="320988.xml"><title>Birth
                    Control, 1958</title></xref></p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues"
            level3="in US"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="international"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="international conferences on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation"
            level3="Japan"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="American"/>
        <index level1="Family Limitation"/>
        <index level1="North Carolina" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="government"
            level3="public health programs"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Birth Control.</head>
        <div type="section">
            <p>At a national conference in <place reg="New York City, New York"
                    >New York</place> sponsored by the <org>National Research
                    council</org>'s <org>Committee on Human Reproduction</org>,
                two major problems were considered: (1) the urgent need to
                develop through research a simple, inexpensive and universally
                acceptable contraceptive and (2) the equally urgent need to
                build world-wide public acceptance of the necessity for family
                limitation and for use of contraceptive measures to reach this
                objective. Scientists themselves needed to be alerted to the
                need for research in the field of human reproduction; few of
                them in 1949 were qualified to carry on such research. The
                conference also discussed the problems of infertility; increased
                knowledge in this area might lead to discovery of new factors
                involved in fertility control.</p>
            <p>Birth control was officially adopted by <place>Japan</place>
                during the year. The new law was passed unanimously in the house
                of representatives and backed by a large <org
                    reg="Japan, House of Councillors">house of councillors</org>
                majority. According to a statement issued by the <org
                    reg="Japan, Ministry of Health and Welfare">Japanese Welfare
                    ministry</org> “<q who="JWM">an overwhelming majority of the
                    Japanese people favour birth control as a solution of health
                    and population</q>.”</p>
            <p>The first meeting of the committee established by the 1948
                    <org>International Congress on Population and World
                    Resources in Relation to the Family</org> was held in <place
                    reg="London, England">London</place>. It was attended by
                delegates from the Planned Parenthood organizations from the
                    <place>United States</place>, <place>Great Britain</place>,
                    <place>Sweden</place> and the <place>Netherlands</place>.
                They adopted as their name the <org>International Committee on
                    Planned Parenthood</org>.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">Awards.–</head>
            <p>The fifth annual <org>Albert D. and Mary Lasker Foundation</org>
                Awards in Planned Parenthood went to <person
                    reg="Cooper, George M.">George M. Cooper</person>, head of
                the <org
                    reg="North Carolina State Board of Health, Division of Preventative Medicine"
                    >Division of Preventative Medicine</org>, North Carolina
                State Board of Health, and to <person
                    reg="Hartman, Carl Gottfried">Carl G. Hartman</person>,
                zoologist formerly with The <org>Johns Hopkins Medical
                    school</org>. Cooper was honoured for his leadership in
                establishing birth control in 1937 in the public health service
                of <place reg="North Carolina, United States">North
                    Carolina</place>, the first state to give this service
                through its public health departments. By 1949 the example had
                been followed by six other states. Hartman received his award
                for scientific research in the physiology and time of ovulation
                in women and the survival time of egg and sperm which brought
                nearer the solution of basic problems in the field of fertility
                and infertility.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">U.S. Goals.–</head>
            <p>The Planned Parenthood federation's annual meeting devoted a
                major part of its discussion to program goals. The membership
                expressed its aim “<q who="PPFA">to further universal acceptance
                    of family planning as an essential element of responsible
                    parenthood and stable family life</q>,” this program to be
                accomplished through three main lines of activity–service,
                education and research. The inclusion of birth control services
                in public health clinics, hospitals and as an integral part of
                national health planning was considered a service goal with
                continued maintenance of the federation's own services until
                availability of complete coverage for U.S. families. The
                provision of general an dprogessional education by the
                federation was recognized as the method for achieving this
                end.</p>
            <p>The Planned Parenthoood federation was in 1949 the national
                agency and clearinghouse for 15 state leagues and 131 local
                committees. Birth control clinics numbered 537. These services
                were in 229 public health departments, 48 hospitals, 227
                extramural clinics and there were 33 referral services. Of the
                92 infertility clinics reported to the federation, 25 were under
                Planned Parenthood auspices.</p>
            <byline><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">(M.SR.)</person></byline>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
