<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/05/23 CE</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/05/24 CE</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/06/20 CE</prepDate><prepDate>2011-11-21 CH correct typo</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1942-00-00">1942</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Birth Control, <supplied>1941</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp320973</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Britannica Book of the Year</title> (1942), pp.
                100-101.</bibl>
            <bibl>Not filmed.</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="SPA">Spanish</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>For other articles in the <title>Britannica Book of
        the Year</title> series, see <xref from="320974.xml"
            ><title>Birth Control, 1942</title></xref>; <xref from="320976.xml"
            ><title>Birth Control, 1944</title></xref>; <xref
                from="320980.xml"><title>Birth Control, 1946</title></xref>;
        <xref from="320979.xml"><title>Birth Control,
            1947</title></xref>; <xref from="320981.xml"><title>Birth
                Control, 1949</title></xref>; <xref from="321981.xml"
                    ><title>Birth Control, 1950</title></xref>; <xref
                        from="320983.xml"><title>Birth Control, 1951</title></xref>;
        <xref from="320984.xml"><title>Birth Control,
            1952</title></xref>; <xref from="321984.xml"><title>Birth
                Control, 1953</title></xref>; <xref from="320985.xml"
                    ><title>Birth Control, 1954</title></xref>; <xref
                        from="320986.xml"><title>Birth Control, 1955</title></xref>;
        <xref from="none.xml"><title>Birth Control, 1956</title></xref>;
        <xref from="320987.xml"><title>Birth Control,
            1957</title></xref>; <xref from="320988.xml"><title>Birth
            Control, 1958</title></xref></p>
        <p>For page proof, see LCM 129:137-38.</p>
        <index level1="Asia" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Australia" level2="birth rates in"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to" level3="international"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues"
            level3="in US"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation"
            level3="Japan"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="international"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="opposition to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="suppression of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="war and"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="efforts to increase"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="population growth and"/>
        <index level1="Connecticut" level2="birth control"
            level3="laws and legislation"/>
        <index level1="England" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Europe" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="France" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="France" level2="birth rate in"/>
        <index level1="Germany" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Germany" level2="birth rate in"/>
        <index level1="Germany" level2="population policies of"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="population policies of"/>
        <index level1="New York City" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="New Zealand" level2="conditions in"/>
        <index level1="North Carolina" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="politicians" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="population growth" level2="regulation of"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="government"
            level3="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="population policies of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Birth Control.</head>
        <div type="section">
            <p>The world picture abroad was dark and confused during 1941.
                Except for <place>Sweden</place>, information on clinical
                service on the birth control movement in other countries in
                    <place>Europe</place> could not be obtained. Constant and
                relentless pressure on the conquered nations, food rationing and
                requisition by <place>Germany</place> of supplies from every
                country overrun resulted in lowered birth rates.</p>
            <p>This form of birth control is dysgenic in the extreme; but no
                sane population policy could be adopted as long as Germany
                dominated Europe, and until world reconstruction programs
                included, as one essential for enduring peace, a consideration
                of the need for solving problems of overpopulation in relation
                to national resources.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub"><place>Australia</place>.--</head>
            <p>Vital statistics for Australia showed a slight rise in the birth
                rate of 1941 over that of 1940, and a sharp increase in the
                number of marriages, with their rate, 11.8 per 1,000 population,
                the highest on record. Established birth control clinics
                continued their work.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub"><place>Cuba</place>.--</head>
            <p>Efforts to establish birth control centres in the island were
                stimulated by lectures before the <org>Gynecological
                    association</org> of the island, and publication of a new
                illustrated pamphlet on contraceptive technique, by a <person
                    reg="Unknown">leading gynaecologist</person>, received wide
                circulation among the medical profession.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub"><place>England</place>.--</head>
            <p>Branch clinics of the <org>Family Planning association</org> in
                the worst bombed areas of the provinces had extraordinary
                escapes from serious damage and were carrying on at the close of
                1941. Some of the centres in or near <place
                    reg="London, England">London</place> and the southeastern
                districts were temporarily suspended. Headquarters of the
                association were evacuated to <place reg="Bournemouth, England"
                    >Bournemouth</place> late in 1940, with a small staff at the
                London office.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub"><place>France</place>.--</head>
            <p>Adoption of more drastic regulations against birth control and
                abortion failed to stem the fall in France's birth rate, nor has
                increase in family allowances had any such result. Food
                rationing resulted in a drop in the average weight of infants
                born and Germany's failure to release the 1,500,000 French
                prisoners held outside France tended to further reduce the birth
                rate.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub"><place>Germany</place>.--</head>
            <p>Germany endeavoured to raise its marriage rate by allowing
                soldiers at the front in any country to marry by proxy.
                Illegitimate births were officially stimulated and encouraged.
                In spite of all regulations against the sale of contraceptives,
                sales continued. Live births in the reich were reported
                increasing, but figures were contrasted with those of 1939.
                Civil statistics for the first quarter of 1941 showed them to be
                24.5% less than in the corresponding quarter of 1940,
                however.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub"><place>India</place>.--</head>
            <p>Progress in organization of birth control work was reported to
                the <org reg="Family Planning Association of India">Family
                    Planning association</org> by its organizer in that country.
                The last census in 1940 credited India with a population of
                400,000,000, an increase of 18% in 10 years.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub"><place>Japan</place>.--</head>
            <p>By official decree a higher birth rate was ordered in Japan in
                1941. The objectives are a perpetual population increase, so
                that other nations can be outrivalled in quantity and rate of
                increase, and industry and military manpower maintained. Birth
                control was rigorously suppressed, but in spite of this and of
                threats and inducements, the birth rate did not go up as fast as
                expected. Infant mortality rates, however, increased, and
                malnutrition was prevalent.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub"><place>New Zealand</place>.--</head>
            <p>The <org reg="Family Planning Association of New Zealand">Family
                    Planning association</org> stimulated the passage at many
                meetings of a resolution asking the <person
                    reg="Ferguson, Lindo">dean of the medical school</person> of
                    <org>Otago university</org>, the only medical school in New
                Zealand, to include a course in contraceptive technique in
                training the students there.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub"><place>Norway</place>.--</head>
            <p>All Norwegian birth control centres were closed by the police,
                following German occupation of the country.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub"><place>Sweden</place>.--</head>
            <p>The <org reg="Riksforbundet fur Sexuell Upplysning">Swedish
                    Society for Sexual Enlightenment</org> continued work during
                the year and its <org>Stockholm Birth Control</org> clinic
                advised many women. The society collected funds to open a home
                for deserted mothers and provide relief for them.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub"><place>Puerto Rico</place>.--</head>
            <p>There was a steady increase in the number of clinic services
                under the direction of the <org><foreign lang="SPA">Association
                        Pro Salud Maternal e Infantil de Puerto
                    Rico</foreign></org>. These services were medically
                directed, and research studies on them were being undertaken to
                determine rates of effectiveness and acceptability of the
                methods advised. An interdepartmental committee appointed by
                    <person reg="Roosevelt, Franklin Delano">President
                    Roosevelt</person> to survey Puerto Rico reported that
                overpopulation was the greatest problem of the island and that
                “birth control should be made a major function of the Insular
                    <org reg="Puerto Rico, Department of Health">Department of
                    Health</org>, as the key to the entire health situation in
                Puerto Rico.”</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub"><place>United States</place>.--</head>
            <p><emph>Population</emph>. Final figures of the 1940 census showed
                an increase of almost 9,000,000 during the decade, in spite of
                ten years of depression and the lowest marriage rates in many
                years. Both marriage and birth rates rose in 1941 and forecast
                was for a birth rate of 18.5 for the year. Number of family
                units in the country increased 16.6% during the decade, though
                the average number of persons declined slightly.</p>
            <p><emph><org>Birth Control Federation of America</org>,
                    Inc.--</emph>Thirty-four state organizations were affiliated
                with the federation in 1941. The year was one of marked progress
                and increased public support.</p>
            <p>On Oct. 16, simultaneous anniversary observances were held in 32
                cities throughout the U.S., commemorating the 25th anniversary
                of the founding of America's first birth control clinic by
                    <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person> in
                    <place reg="Brooklyn, New York">Brooklyn</place> in 1916,
                which was closed as a “public nuisance.” Numerous articles in
                the lay and medical press commented on the growth of clinic
                services and the increasing recognition by public health
                agencies of the importance of contraceptive service in their own
                programs.</p>
            <p><place>Alabama</place> followed North and <place>South
                    Carolina</place> as the third state to include birth control
                officially in its public health program, and reports on the
                programs in these states were requested by many public health
                officials in other states.</p>
            <p>Field work of the federation was concentrated in the south where
                population studies indicated the greatest need for a program of
                family spacing, where infant and maternal mortality rates are
                highest, and where high fertility and poverty make living
                conditions most difficult. Prominent citizens of the south held
                a <org>Third Southern Conference on Tomorrow's Children</org>
                and formulated a practical program of action.</p>
            <p><emph>Clinical Service</emph>.--Birth control centres in the
                United States totalled 637 in Nov. 1941. Of these 118 were in
                hospitals, 206 in health departments and 313 in other quarters,
                while 283 were supported wholly or in part by public funds. More
                than 90% of public health officers answering a questionnaire
                stated they were in favour of using federal funds for such
                service.</p>
            <p><emph>Legislation</emph>.--<place>Connecticut</place>: A bill to
                amend the law and give doctors the right to advise patients on
                contraception, when medically indicated, passed the house but
                was defeated in the senate.</p>
            <p><place>Massachusetts</place>: An initiative petition signed by
                more than 44,000 voters was presented to the legislature in the
                form of a bill. After a hearing, the bill was referred by the
                legislature to the state supreme court, for an opinion on its
                constitutionality, the opposition claiming that a religious
                issue was involved. The court ruled that the bill was purely
                permissive and that no religious issue was a factor in the bill.
                The bill was later defeated by both houses. The necessary
                thousands of additional signatures were secured to put the
                question on the ballot in 1942. The opposition, led by <person
                    reg="O'Connell, William Henry">Cardinal O’Connell</person>
                of <place reg="Boston, Massachusetts">Boston</place>, attempted
                to challenge the legality of the petition and prevent inclusion
                of the question on the ballot.</p>
            <p><emph>Legal.--</emph>The <org reg="U.S. Federal Trade Commission"
                    >federal trade commission</org>'s action against falsely
                advertised or dangerous contraceptives continued, but trade in
                bootleg materials went on in spite of “cease and desist” orders
                and suit.</p>
            <p><emph>Medical Education</emph> was fostered by the distribution
                of more than 50,000 copies of a new pamphlet, “<title>Techniques
                    of Conception Control</title>,” by <person
                    reg="Dickinson, Robert Latou">Robert L. Dickinson</person>,
                M.D., and <person reg="Woodbridge, Morris E.">Woodbridge E.
                    Morris</person>, M..D., among medical schools, state and
                county medical societies, public health departments, hospitals,
                medical libraries and individual physicians. More than
                one-fourth of the leading medical schools of the U.S. were
                visited by a medical representative of the federation, resulting
                in the inclusion of contraception in some programs, and in
                others an increase in the time allotted to the subject of
                contraception. (<emph>See</emph> also CIVIL LIBERTY.)</p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
