<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/06/01 CE</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-18 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1948-00-00">1948</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Birth Control, 1947</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp320979</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="book">Britannica Book of the Year</title>(1947), pp.122-123</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>For a typed draft, see <title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title>
            S72:550.</p>
        <p>For other articles in the <title type="book">Britannica Book of the Year</title> series,
            see <xref from="320980.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control, 1946</title></xref>;
                <xref from="321981.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control, 1948</title>,
                1949</xref>;<xref from="320981.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control,
                    1949</title></xref>; <xref from="321981.xml"><title type="article">Birth
                    Control, 1950</title></xref>; <xref from="320983.xml"><title type="article"
                    >Birth Control, 1951</title></xref>; <xref from="320984.xml"><title
                    type="article">Birth Control, 1952</title></xref>; <xref from="321984.xml"
                    ><title type="article">Birth Control, 1953</title></xref>; <xref
                from="320985.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control, 1954</title></xref>; <xref
                from="320986.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control, 1955</title></xref>; <xref
                from="none.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control, 1956</title></xref>; <xref
                from="320987.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control, 1957</title></xref>; <xref
                from="320988.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control, 1958</title></xref></p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues" level3="in US"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="international conferences on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Connecticut"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Massachusetts"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="medical community and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="American"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="international"/>
        <index level1="conferences" level2="World Conference on the Family and Population"
            level3="1947"/>
        <index level1="physicians" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="Planned Parenthood Federation of America"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="government" level3="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="government" level3="public health programs"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">Birth Control.</head>
            <p>Planned Parenthood programs throughout the <place>United States</place> were expanded
                in 1947, a direct result of the first nation-wide campaign of the <org>Planned
                    Parenthood Federation of America</org>, Inc. A major campaign by-product was the
                vast increase in public understanding and acceptance of Planned Parenthood services.
                The coverage given by the nation’s press, wire services, radio and other media,
                especially magazines, was instrumental in breaking down some of the resistance to
                publicized discussion of birth control.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">Research.–-</head>
            <p>The first comprehensive program for research in the field of human reproduction was
                instituted during 1947. It was under the direction of the <org>National Research
                    council</org> in <place reg="Washington, D.C.">Washington</place>. The <org
                    reg="National Research Council Committee on Human Reproduction">Committee on
                    Human Reproduction</org> established by the council was to study need and
                recommend grants for specific research to qualified institutions and investigators.
                The council by contact with the <org>National Committee on Maternal Health</org> and
                in collaboration with the Planned Parenthood federation established this committee
                to plan the program of research. Research panels were to operate in accordance with
                policies to be defined by the newly reorganized board of the Committee on Maternal
                Health, under the chairmanship of <person reg="Emerson, John Haven">Dr. Haven
                    Emerson</person>, professor emeritus of public health service at <org>Columbia
                    University</org>, and a member of the <org><place reg="New York City, NY">New
                        York city</place> board of health</org>.</p>
            <p>The Committee on Human Reproduction of the National Research council was headed by
                    <person reg="Taylor, Howard Canning, Jr.">Dr. Howard C. Taylor, Jr</person>.,
                professor of obstetrics and gynaecology at <org>Columbia university</org>’s college
                of physicians and surgeons.</p>
            <p>More than the purely medical aspects of reproduction was envisaged by the Committee
                on Human Reproduction as vital to its program. The medical aspects are so closely
                bound to the socio-economic environmental problems of the individual, family,
                community, nation, and the whole world that a sound research program can ignore none
                of them. The main areas of the study would include: (1) the physiology of and the
                factors controlling conception; (2) the causes of sterility and treatment for
                infertility; (3) maternal and foetal physiology and clinical disorders developing
                during pregnancy; (4) the psychological problems of marriage and family
                relationships; (5) the population aspects of these problems, social and economic as
                well as medical.</p>
            <p>The Planned Parenthood federation would seek to contribute a substantial part of the
                funds for the research program. The clinics and records of its affiliates would also
                constitute a valuable field for certain research projects. While not a party to the
                contract between the National Research council and the National Committee on
                Maternal Health, the federation was collaborating as a full partner in the whole
                program.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">Medical Survey of U.S. Physicians on Birth Control.–-</head>
            <p><person reg="Guttmacher, Alan Frank">Dr. Alan F. Guttmacher</person>, associate
                director of obstetrics and gynaecology at <org reg="Johns Hopkins University">Johns
                    Hopkins</org>, conducted a nation-wide survey to tabulate medical opinion on
                conception control. According to his poll, 96% of the physicians in the U.S.
                approved birth control. Teaching of conception control methods in medical schools
                was found inadequate. Three-quarters of the respondents had not received training in
                this area. Only 7% said they had received both lectures and clinical instruction in
                contraception.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">Lasker Awards in Planned Parenthood.–-</head>
            <p>Dr. Guttmacher and <person reg="Stone, Abraham">Dr. Abraham Stone</person> received
                the third annual Lasker Awards in Planned Parenthood for their distinguished
                contribution in the fields of marriage counseling and education. The award
                recognized Dr. Stone’s 30 years of clinical work, teaching and marriage
                counseling.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">Development of Services.–-</head>
            <p><person reg="Kling, Llewellyn E.">Dr. L. E. Kling</person>, formerly with the <org
                    reg="United States Public Health Service">U.S. public health service</org>,
                became acting medical director of the federation. During his public health services,
                Dr. Kling developed the first mass X-ray programs and had wide experience in
                tuberculosis and cancer control public health programs.</p>
            <p>Nearly two-thirds of the people of the U.S. believed government health clinics should
                furnish birth control information, it was found in a Gallup poll conducted during
                the year. Figure showed that 64% approved, 23% disapproved and 13% had no
                opinion.</p>
            <p>A bill to permit physicians in <place>Connecticut</place> to prescribe contraceptives
                to their patients was defeated in May when the state senate voted two to one against
                the bill. It had passed the lower house 180 to 40.</p>
            <p><place>Massachusetts</place> officially opened a campaign for repeal of the state law
                forbidding medical prescription of contraception on Sept. 2. An initiative petition
                for a new law was approved by the state attorney general after it had been filed by
                ten voters headed by <person reg="Compton, Karl Taylor">Dr. Karl T.
                Compton</person>, president of the <org>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</org>.
                Many more than the 20,000 registered voters required by law signed the petition.</p>
            <p>Four fertility clinics were opened during the year. Two of them were in
                    <place>Delaware</place> and Connecticut where these services had hitherto been
                unavailable. Of these four new clinics, two were under Planned Parenthood
                auspices.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">International Developments.–-</head>
            <p>An <org>International Union of Family Organizations</org> was established by 27
                nations meeting in <place reg="Paris, France">Paris</place> June 22-29 at a
                    <org>World Conference on the Family and Population</org>. It was called by the
                    <org>French Union of Family Associations</org>. U.S. representatives included
                Dr. Abraham Stone, who was delegated by the <org>National Research Council</org>,
                the Planned Parenthood federation and the National Council for Family Relations;
                    <person reg="Stebbins, Ernest Lyman">Dr. Ernest Stebbins</person>, professor of
                hygiene and public health, Johns Hopkins; Miss <person reg="Hoey, Jane M.">Jane
                    Hoey</person>, director of the social welfare bureau, <org
                    reg="United States Federal Security Agency, Social Welfare Bureau">Federal
                    Security Agency</org>; Mrs. <person reg="Nyswander, Rachel">Rachel
                    Nyswander</person>, director of the <org
                    reg="United States Department of Labor, Women's Bureau">women’s bureau of the
                    labor department</org>; and <person reg="Himes, Norman E">Dr. Norman
                    Himes</person> from the educational department of the U.S. military government
                in <place>Germany</place>. Representatives from the cultural department of the <org
                    reg="United States Embassy of Paris">U.S. embassy in Paris</org> and of the <org
                    reg="United Nations Organization for Education, Science and Culture">United
                    Nations Educational, Scientific, and Cultural organization</org> also
                participated. Dr. Stone was elected a vice-president of the new <org>International
                    Union of Family Organizations</org>.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">Organization.–-</head>
            <p>The Planned Parenthood federation was in 1947 the national agency and clearinghouse
                for 38 state leagues and 206 local committees. The total number of birth control
                centres stood at 550. These services were in 231 public health clinics, 60 hospital
                clinics and 214 extramural clinics. Of the 55 fertility clinics in the U.S., 12 were
                under Planned Parenthood direction. (See also BIRTH STATISTICS.)</p>
            <byline>(<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">M.SR.</person>)</byline>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
