<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/06/06 CE</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/06/20 CE</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1952-00-00">1952</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Birth Control, 1951</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp320983</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Britannica Book of the Year</title>(1952), pp.
                105-106</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="LFA">Albert D. and Mary Lasker Foundation Award in Planned
                Parenthood</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>For other articles in the <title>Britannica Book of
                the Year</title> series, see <xref from="320976.xml"
                    ><title>Birth Control, 1944</title></xref>; <xref
                from="320980.xml"><title>Birth Control, 1946</title></xref>;
                <xref from="320979.xml"><title>Birth Control,
                1947</title></xref>; <xref from="321981.xml"><title>Birth
                    Control, 1948</title>, 1949</xref>;<xref from="320981.xml"
                    ><title>Birth Control, 1949</title></xref>; <xref
                from="321981.xml"><title>Birth Control, 1950</title></xref>;
                <xref from="320984.xml"><title>Birth Control,
                1952</title></xref>; <xref from="321984.xml"><title>Birth
                    Control, 1953</title></xref>; <xref from="320985.xml"
                    ><title>Birth Control, 1954</title></xref>; <xref
                from="320986.xml"><title>Birth Control, 1955</title></xref>;
                <xref from="none.xml"><title>Birth Control, 1956</title></xref>;
                <xref from="320987.xml"><title>Birth Control,
                1957</title></xref>; <xref from="320988.xml"><title>Birth
                    Control, 1958</title></xref></p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues"
            level3="in US"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="international conferences on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="American"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="international"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Planned Parenthood Federation of America"/>
        <index level1="population" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="population growth" level2="standard of living and"/>
        <index level1="poverty"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="government"
            level3="public health programs"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Birth Control.</head>
        <div type="section">
            <p>During 1951 the <org>Planned Parenthood Federation of
                    America</org> appointed <person reg="Vogt, William">William
                    Vogt</person>, conservationist and ecologist, as its
                national director. Prime Minister <person
                    reg="Nehru, Jawaharlal">Jawaharlal Nehru</person> of
                    <place>India</place> during the year declared that birth
                control was essential to the national well-being of his country.
                His government implemented this policy by requesting assistance
                from the <org>World Health organization</org> of the <org>United
                    Nations</org> in initiating a population control program.
                    <person reg="Stone, Abraham">Abraham Stone</person>,
                federation vice-president, was designated to make a pilot
                project in India under W.H.O. auspices and Indian government
                sponsorship. He worked through local health centres, with
                control groups of illiterates as well as educated Indians who
                were taught family control methods requiring no artificial
                appliances.</p>
            <p>The third meeting of the <org>International Committee on Planned
                    Parenthood</org> took place in <place reg="London, England"
                    >London</place>, Eng., to plan a world conference on planned
                parenthood. Lady <person reg="Rama Rau, Dhanvanthi Handoo">Rama
                    Rau</person>, founder and president of the <org
                    reg="Family Planning Association of India">Indian Family
                    Planning Association</org>, invited the committee to hold
                its meeting in India in 1952 under the association's
                sponsorship, to facilitate the attendance of far easterners
                concerned with their countries' pressing population
                problems.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">Awards.–</head>
            <p>The seventh annual <org>Albert D. and Mary Lasker
                    Foundation</org> Awards in Planned Parenthood went to two
                authorities on world population problems. They were William Vogt
                and <person reg="Burch, Guy Irving">Guy Irving Burch</person>.
                Vogt was cited for “<q who="LFA">his investigations in the field
                    of conservation and his achievement in bringing world
                    population problems home to a vast number of people</q>.”
                Burch, founder and director of the <org>Population Reference
                    bureau</org>, <place reg="Washington, D.C.">Washington,
                    D.C.</place>, and coathor of <title>Human Breeding and
                    Survival</title>, was recognized posthumously because “<q
                    who="LFA">perhaps more than any other individual he was
                    responsible for today's awareness of the population problem
                    and the need for positive action to resolve it</q>.”</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">Research.–</head>
            <p>One of the serious gaps in the effort of make planned parenthood
                availale to families everywhere had been the lack of a simple,
                low-cost contraceptive that could be safely used by illiterate,
                poverty-stricken mothers in overcrowded parts of the world. In
                an effort to co-ordinate and promote the research required to
                discover such a contraceptive, the federation established the
                    <org>Robert L. Dickinson Research memorial</org> in 1951.
                The memorial, which was sponsoring basic research in the almost
                unexplored field of human reproduction, was established as the
                federation's tribute to Dickinson, distinguished medical birth
                control pioneer. Four research projects were sponsored during
                the year by Dickinson memorial grants, as approved by the
                federation's medical committee and the advisory committee of the
                memorial.</p>
            <p>Clinical and laboratory research in contraception and other
                phases of human fertility were also carried on during the year
                at the <org>Margaret Sanger Research bureau</org> in <place
                    reg="New York City, NY">New York
                city</place>.</p>
            <p>The Planned Parenthood federation was in 1951 the national agency
                and clearinghouse for 12 state leagues and 100 local committees.
                Birth control clinics numbered 517. These services were in 274
                public health departments, 48 hospitals, and 173 extramural
                clinics, and there were 22 referral services. The seven states
                which included birth control in their public health programs
                were: <place>Alabama</place>, <place>Florida</place>,
                    <place>Georgia</place>, <place>Mississippi</place>,
                    <place>North Carolina</place>, <place>South
                Carolina</place>, and <place>Virginia</place>. The known
                infertility clinics in the country were 66 of which 13 were
                under Planned Parenthood federation auspices.</p>
        </div>
        <byline>(<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">M.SR.</person>)</byline>
    </docBody>
</doc>
