<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/06/06 CE</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/06/20 CE</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1953-00-00">1953</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Birth Control, 1952</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp320984</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Britannica Book of the Year</title>(1953), p.
                106</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>For other articles in the <title>Britannica Book of the Year</title>
            series, see <xref from="320976.xml"><title>Birth Control,
                1944</title></xref>; <xref from="320980.xml"><title>Birth Control,
                    1946</title></xref>; <xref from="320979.xml"><title>Birth
                    Control, 1947</title></xref>; <xref from="321981.xml"
                    ><title>Birth Control, 1948</title>, 1949</xref>;<xref
                from="320981.xml"><title>Birth Control, 1949</title></xref>;
                <xref from="321981.xml"><title>Birth Control,
                1950</title></xref>; <xref from="320983.xml"><title>Birth
                    Control, 1951</title></xref>; <xref from="320984.xml"
                    ><title>Birth Control, 1952</title></xref>; <xref
                from="321984.xml"><title>Birth Control, 1953</title></xref>;
                <xref from="320985.xml"><title>Birth Control,
                1954</title></xref>; <xref from="320986.xml"><title>Birth
                    Control, 1955</title></xref>; <xref from="none.xml"
                    ><title>Birth Control, 1956</title></xref>; <xref
                from="320987.xml"><title>Birth Control, 1957</title></xref>;
                <xref from="320988.xml"><title>Birth Control,
                1958</title></xref></p>
        <p>For typed draft of the article, see MSM S72:733</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues"
            level3="in US"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="international"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="international conferences on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="research"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="American"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="international"/>
        <index level1="New York City" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="population" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="population" level2="food supply and"/>
        <index level1="population growth" level2="natural resources and"/>
        <index level1="Southern States"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="government"
            level3="public health programs"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Birth Control.</head>
        <div type="section">
            <p>Population increases, the result of marked and widespread
                lowering of death rates since 1932, were reported by the
                    <org>United Nations</org> in a population summary during
                1952. The year also marked increasing acceptance on an
                international level of the need to plan human birth in relation
                to available supplies of food and other vital resources.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">International.–</head>
            <p><person reg="Stone, Abraham">Abraham Stone</person>,
                vice-president of the <org>Planned Parenthood Federation of
                    America</org>, returned during the year from
                    <place>India</place> where he had established a pilot
                project in the rhythm method of birth control under auspices of
                the Indian government and <org>World Health organization</org>.
                The clinical studies that Stone initiated in <place
                    reg="New Delhi, India">New Delhi</place> and the states of
                    <place reg="Mysore, India">Mysore</place>, <place
                    reg="Madras, India">Madras</place> and <place
                    reg="West Bengal, India">West Bengal</place> continued under
                the supervision of two family-planning specialists, recommended
                by the federation at the request of W.H.O.</p>
            <p>The first <org
                    reg="Third International Conference on Planned Parenthood"
                    >World Conference on Planned Parenthood</org> to be held in
                the far east took place in <place reg="Bombay, India"
                    >Bombay</place>, India, Nov. 24-Dec. 1, 1952, initiated by
                the <org>International Committee on Planned Parenthood</org>
                whose headquarters were in <place reg="London, England"
                    >London</place>. Physicians, demographers and scientists
                from <place>Asia</place>, <place>Europe</place> and the <place
                    reg="United States">U.S.</place> met to study social,
                economic and cultural factors in relation to population
                problems; to exchange information and views on planned
                parenthood programs in different countries; to stimulate social
                and biological research in human reproduction and to encourage
                the formation of national planned parenthood organizations. The
                conference, which was held under the auspices of the <org
                    reg="Family Planning Association of India">Indian Family
                    Planning Association</org>, had <person
                    reg="Rama Rau, Dhanvanthi Handoo">Lady Rama Rau</person>,
                association president, as its chairman. Mrs. <person
                    reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>, founder of
                the birth control movement, who spearheaded the establishment of
                the International committee in 1948, was director of the
                American division of the conference.</p>
            <p>The first international birth control publication, <title>News of
                    Population and Birth Control</title>, was issued in January.
                Published monthly in <place reg="New York City, NY">New
                    York</place>, N.Y., at the request of the International
                committee, its 9,000 readers included government officials and
                key lay and professional leaders in 65 countries.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">Research.–</head>
            <p>The urgent need for simpler and less expensive methods of
                fertility control led to the federation's establishment of the
                position of research director, and the appointment of <person
                    reg="Henshaw, Paul Stewart">Paul Henshaw</person>, an
                experimental biologist, to the post, in order to expedite,
                co-ordinate, conduct and promote research in the field of
                fertility and sterility. Henshaw carried out a survey on the
                potentialities of the physiologic control of fertility, which
                revealed that the principle of such control could be regarded as
                established, based on the large amount of published literature
                in the field. The study also showed that two types of further
                research were needed: (1) practical studies to establish minimal
                doses, the most effective methods of treatment and the
                standardization of treatment materials at low cost; and (2)
                basic studies to develop still more suitable methods.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">U.S. Services.–</head>
            <p>The Planned Parenthood Federation of America was, in 1952, the
                national agency and clearing house for 11 state leagues and 91
                local committees. Birth control clinics numbered 519. These
                services were in 274 public health departments, 48 hospitals and
                175 extramural clinics, and there were 22 referral services. Of
                the 196,604 yearly total of patients visiting birth control
                clinics in 1951, the majority, or 189,658, were served in
                extramural clinics sponsored by federation affiliates. The seven
                states which included birth control in their public health
                programs were <place>Alabama</place>, <place>Florida</place>,
                    <place>Georgia</place>, <place>Mississippi</place>,
                    <place>North Carolina</place>, <place>South Carolina</place>
                and <place>Virginia</place>. The known infertility clinics in
                the country providing diagnosis and treatment of childless
                couples were 66, of which 13 were under the auspices of the
                Planned Parenthood federation.</p>
            <byline>(<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">M.SR</person>.)</byline>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
