<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/06/08 CE</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/06/20 CE</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-18 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1947-00-00">1947</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Birth Control, 1946</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp320978</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="book">Britannica Book of the Year</title>(1947), p. 128</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>For other articles in the <title type="book">Britannica Book of the
                Year</title> series, see <xref from="320976.xml"><title type="article">Birth
                    Control, 1944</title></xref>; <xref from="320979.xml"><title type="article"
                    >Birth Control, 1947</title></xref>; <xref from="321981.xml"><title
                    type="article">Birth Control, 1948</title>, 1949</xref>;<xref from="320981.xml"
                    ><title type="article">Birth Control, 1949</title></xref>; <xref
                from="321981.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control, 1950</title></xref>; <xref
                from="320983.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control, 1951</title></xref>; <xref
                from="320984.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control, 1952</title></xref>; <xref
                from="321984.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control, 1953</title></xref>; <xref
                from="320985.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control, 1954</title></xref>; <xref
                from="320986.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control, 1955</title></xref>; <xref
                from="none.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control, 1956</title></xref>; <xref
                from="320987.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control, 1957</title></xref>; <xref
                from="320988.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control, 1958</title></xref></p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="American opinion on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues" level3="in US"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="international"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="international conferences on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="American"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="propaganda and publicity"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="religion and"/>
        <index level1="child spacing"/>
        <index level1="family planning"/>
        <index level1="New York City" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Planned Parenthood Federation of America"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="government" level3="public health programs"/>
        <index level1="venereal disease"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Birth Control.</head>
        <div type="section">
            <p>The year 1946 marked the 25th anniversary of the <org>Planned Parenthood Federation
                    of America</org>, Inc. (formerly the <org>Birth Control Federation of
                    America</org>). The year was distinguished by advances in the field of religious
                acceptance and by international recognition of family planning as an aid in solving
                population problems related to world peace.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">International.–</head>
            <p>Speaking before the <org reg="United Nations International Health Conference"
                    >International Health conference</org> of the United Nations, Dr. <person
                    reg="Tutunji, Djamil Pasha">Djamil Pasha Tutunji</person>, health director of
                    <place>Trans-Jordan</place>, declared that birth control is as important to
                world peace as the control of the atom bomb.</p>
            <p>The first postwar international sex conference, attended by representatives of eight
                countries, was held in <place>Stockholm, Sweden</place>. Delegates from the
                unoccupied countries, where planned parenthood programs had been curtailed but not
                abolished, reported development of a three-fold program of child-spacing, treatment
                of infertility and education for marriage, in line with work of the <place
                    reg="United States">U.S.</place> group. Visiting physicians from
                    <place>India</place>, <place>China</place>, <place>Japan</place>, <place>New
                    Zealand</place>, <place>Spain</place>, <place>Brazil</place>,
                    <place>Argentina</place>, <place>South Africa</place> and <place>Italy</place>
                all reported growing awareness of the importance of planned parenthood in an
                over-all health program.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">Religion.–</head>
            <p>Recognizing that planned parenthood is one way to combat the country’s growing
                divorce, abortion and juvenile delinquency rates, the <org
                    reg="Planned Parenthood Federation of America, National Clergymen's Advisory Committee"
                    >National Clergymen’s Advisory committee</org> of the Planned Parenthood
                federation passed a resolution seeking the establishment of planned parenthood
                services in hospitals, public health clinics and other agencies where the service
                should be given. The resolution, signed by 3,200 Protestant and Jewish religious
                leaders, was given nation-wide publicity by the press. The united action of
                clergymen in favour of planned parenthood completed the year’s program which opened
                with an address by Bishop <person reg="Oxnam, Garfield Bromley">G. Bromley
                    Oxnam</person>, president of the <org>Federal Council of the Churches of Christ
                    in America</org>, before the 25th annual dinner.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">Medical and Public Health.–</head>
            <p>The <org>New York Academy of Medicine</org> conducted a survey of contraceptive
                services in <place reg="New York, NY">New York city</place> hospitals and found that
                only 5 of the city’s 89 hospitals had contraceptive clinics. The mistaken belief
                that birth control is illegal was believed to keep many patients from seeking
                medical advice on child-spacing from out-patient departments which they attended for
                other medical help. The New York academy report recommended that contraceptive
                information be made available when it was medically indicated. The addition of
                    <place>Virginia</place> and <place>Mississippi</place> to the states which
                include planned parenthood in their public health services brought the total number
                of such states to eight.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">Press and Radio.–</head>
            <p>Fifty-six articles making favourable mentions of planned parenthood appeared during
                the year in popular and technical magazines. Both the <org>United Press</org> and
                the <org>Associated Press</org> wire services carried the story of the clergymen’s
                resolution, and in many communities newspaper editors augmented the original story
                with statements from local clergymen whose names appeared among the 3,200
                signers.</p>
            <p>Radio’s attitude toward planned parenthood underwent a noticeable change during 1946.
                Bishop Oxnam’s address broadcast over the network of the <org>Columbia Broadcasting
                    system</org> was the most frank discussion of the religious significance of
                birth control ever heard on a network. The <org>National Broadcasting Company</org>
                gave the federation network time for a roundtable discussion of “Birth–By Choice or
                Chance.” Participants, who discussed the religious, medical and social aspects of
                planned parenthood were: Dr. <person reg="Shipler, Guy Emery">Guy Emery
                    Shipler</person>, editor of <title type="journal">The Churchman</title>; Dr.
                    <person reg="Nelson, Janet Fowler">Janet Fowler Nelson</person>, newly appointed
                consultant on education for marriage and family living, for the federation; and Dr.
                    <person reg="Guttmacher, Alan F.">Alan F. Guttmacher</person>, associate
                professor of obstetrics, <org reg="Johns Hopkins University Medical School">Johns
                    Hopkins medical school</org>. The program was transcribed and copies made
                available to planned parenthood groups for rebroadcast.</p>
            <p>The first series of planned parenthood programs was broadcast in the spring over
                    <org>WFAS</org>, <place reg="White Plains, NY">White Plains</place>, <place
                    reg="New York">N.Y.</place> Scheduled originally as a 13-week series, it was
                extended to 20 weeks, and the entire series was repeated over the same station in
                the fall. Scripts of this series were made available to all planned-parenthood
                leagues and committees.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">Education.–</head>
            <p>In addition to its extensive literature on child spacing, infertility, marriage
                counselling and population, the federation published two new pamphlets dealing with
                venereal disease and juvenile delinquency. <title type="book">The Story of Two Families</title>,
                produced in co-operation with the <title>Institute for Venereal Disease Education of
                        <place>North Carolina</place></title>, pointed out in popular cartoon style
                the relationship between venereal disease and parenthood. <title type="book">The Roots of
                    Delinquency</title> stressed the fact that most juvenile delinquency began at
                home and was traceable in a large measure to irresponsible parents.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">Fund Raising.–</head>
            <p>Preparations were made for the first nationwide campaign for $2,000,000 to open in
                Feb. 1947. A portion of the money was to be used for research which it was hoped
                would lead to the development of a simple, inexpensive contraceptive and add to
                current knowledge of the treatment of infertility. The federation also hoped to
                expand its current program and establish new clinics which would place medically
                reliable methods of contraception within the reach of all married women regardless
                of geographical location or economic status.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">Organization.–</head>
            <p>The Planned Parenthood federation was the national agency and local clearinghouse for
                38 state leagues and more than 200 affiliated local committees. There were in 1946
                about 600 planned parenthood centres in hospitals, public health clinics and
                extramural clinics operated by volunteer committees.</p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
