<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/06/07 CE</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/06/20 CE</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1955-00-00">1955</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Birth Control, 1954</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp320985</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Britannica Book of the Year</title>(1955), pp.
                165-166</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="LFA">Lasker Foundations Award</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>For other articles in the <title>Britannica Book of
                the Year</title> series, see <xref from="320976.xml"
                    ><title>Birth Control, 1944</title></xref>; <xref
                from="320980.xml"><title>Birth Control, 1946</title></xref>;
                <xref from="320979.xml"><title>Birth Control,
                1947</title></xref>; <xref from="321981.xml"><title>Birth
                    Control, 1948</title>, 1949</xref>;<xref from="320981.xml"
                    ><title>Birth Control, 1949</title></xref>; <xref
                from="321981.xml"><title>Birth Control, 1950</title></xref>;
                <xref from="320983.xml"><title>Birth Control,
                1951</title></xref>; <xref from="320984.xml"><title>Birth
                    Control, 1952</title></xref>; <xref from="321984.xml"
                    ><title>Birth Control, 1953</title></xref>; <xref
                from="320986.xml"><title>Birth Control, 1955</title></xref>;
                <xref from="none.xml"><title>Birth Control, 1956</title></xref>;
                <xref from="320987.xml"><title>Birth Control,
                1957</title></xref>; <xref from="320988.xml"><title>Birth
                    Control, 1958</title></xref></p>
        <p>For a typed draft of the article, see MSM S72:903.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues"
            level3="in US"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="international"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="international conferences on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="international"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="efforts to reduce"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="population policies of"/>
        <index level1="Planned Parenthood Federation of America"/>
        <index level1="population" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="population growth" level2="natural resources and"/>
        <index level1="Southern States"/>
        <index level1="working classes" level2="birth control and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Birth Control.</head>
        <div type="section">
            <p>Events converged to make fertility control programs increasingly
                needed and wanted in many parts of the world in 1954. A major
                cause was the continued disbalance between available resources
                and population growth, particularly in underdeveloped countries.
                This was underlined by an exhaustive <org reg="United Nations"
                    >UN</org> study, “<title>The Determinants and Consequences
                    of Populations Trends</title>” (May 1954) that predicted
                world numbers would rise from 3,000,000,000 to 4,000,000,000
                within 30 years, with little promise of a corresponding increase
                in the production of basic resources.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">International.–</head>
            <p>Growing government interest in <place>Japan</place> in expanding
                national family planning efforts was evidenced by an invitation
                extended <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret
                Sanger</person>, president, <org>International Planned
                    Parenthood federation</org>, to testify before the <org
                    reg="Japan, House of Councillors Public Welfare Committee"
                    >Japanese diet's upper house welfare committee</org> (April
                1954). The first foreign woman to appear before this body, the
                birth control pioneer's guidance was enlisted on methods of
                accelerating the government program. Mrs. Sanger was also
                keynote speaker at the first national meeting of the <org>Japan
                    Federation of Family Planning</org>.</p>
            <p>Priority to <place>India</place>'s overpopulation problem was
                given in that government's census report (Nov. 1953). The
                <person reg="Gopalaswami, R.A.">census commissioner</person> warned against a
                population of 520,000,000 by 1981; presented a study of all
                available methods of conception control; and urged that Indian
                parents voluntarily limit their families to three children in
                order to achieve a stationary population of 450,000,000 in
                1969.</p>
            <p>The year 1954 marked the first <org>World Population
                    conference</org> of experts under UN auspices. Instigated by
                the <org reg="United Nations Economic and Social Council"
                    >Economic and Social council</org> of the UN, it took place
                at the <org
                    reg="United Nations Food and Agriculture Organization">Food
                    and Agriculture organization</org> headquarters, <place
                    reg="Rome, Italy">Rome, It.</place>, Aug. 31-Sept. 10, with
                a number of other leading international agencies collaborating.
                The conference had the co-operation of the Italian government,
                which also helped to finance the meeting. It was attended by
                experts nominated by governments, nongovernmental scientific
                organizations, interested specialized agencies and experts with
                scientific interest in population problems. The International
                Planned Parenthood federation was represented by two official
                observers invited by the UN, with ten of its leaders
                participating in the conference.</p>
            <p>In an effort to facilitate the use of birth control among peasant
                populations, a number of field tests in simple, low cost
                contraceptives were begun among villagers in India,
                    <place>Ceylon</place> and <place>Pakistan</place> by <person
                    reg="Gamble, Clarence James">Clarence J. Gamble</person>,
                U.S. medical authority in conception control.</p>
            <p>The <org>Family Planning Association of Puerto Rico</org> was
                established (March 1954) and launched a three-year campaign
                which included scientific studies in birth control, and a pilot
                project of mass education to increase public interest and draw
                patients to the existing 160 public health sponsored birth
                control clinics.</p>
            <p>U.S. visits of two outstanding Planned Parenthood leaders were
                sponsored by the <org>Planned Parenthood Federation of
                    America</org>. They were Lady <person
                    reg="Rama Rau, Dhanvanthi Handoo">Rama Rau</person> of
                India, chairman, International Planned Parenthood federation,
                whose coast-to-coast lecture tour on “<title>India's Social
                    Revolution</title>” served to broaden public understanding
                of family planning needs in an underdeveloped nation, and
                    <person reg="Ottesen-Jensen, Elise">Elise
                    Ottesen-Jensen</person>, Swedish birth control and sex
                education pioneer. Mrs. Ottensen-Jensen was the recipient of the
                1954 <org>Lasker foundation</org> award in Planned Parenthood,
                presented for “<q who="LFA">setting <place>Sweden</place>'s
                    family planning movement in the forefront of
                        <place>Europe</place> and the world</q>.”</p>
            <p>A colloquium on the social aspects of family planning and
                fertility control held at <org>Columbia university</org>'s Arden
                house (1954) brought together for the first time experts in
                sociology, religion, psychiatry, law, anthropology, gynaecology,
                public health and demography, to assist the federation assess
                and investigate attitudes toward the practice of fertility
                control and its effect on other social and cultural
                problems.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">U.S. Services.–</head>
            <p>During 1954, the <org>Planned Parenthood Federation of
                    America</org> was the national clearing house for 12 state
                leagues and 101 local committees, in 29 states. Birth control
                clinics numbered 532. These services were in 279 public health
                clinics, 74 hospitals and in 182 extramural clinics, sponsored
                by Planned Parenthood committees. Infertility referral services
                numbered 65. The seven states which included birth control in
                their public health department services were
                    <place>Alabama</place>, <place>Florida</place>,
                    <place>Georgia</place>, <place>Mississippi</place>,
                    <place>North Carolina</place>, <place>South
                Carolina</place>, and <place>Virginia</place>.</p>
            <byline>(M.SR.)</byline>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
