<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/06/07 CE</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/06/20 CE</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1956-00-00">1956</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Birth Control, 1955</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp320986</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Britannica Book of the Year</title>(1956), pp.
                104-105.</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>For other articles in the <title>Britannica Book of
                the Year</title> series, see <xref from="320976.xml"
                    ><title>Birth Control, 1944</title></xref>; <xref
                from="320980.xml"><title>Birth Control, 1946</title></xref>;
                <xref from="320979.xml"><title>Birth Control,
                1947</title></xref>; <xref from="321981.xml"><title>Birth
                    Control, 1948</title>, 1949</xref>;<xref from="320981.xml"
                    ><title>Birth Control, 1949</title></xref>; <xref
                from="321981.xml"><title>Birth Control, 1950</title></xref>;
                <xref from="320983.xml"><title>Birth Control,
                1951</title></xref>; <xref from="320984.xml"><title>Birth
                    Control, 1952</title></xref>; <xref from="321984.xml"
                    ><title>Birth Control, 1953</title></xref>; <xref
                from="320985.xml"><title>Birth Control, 1954</title></xref>;
                <xref from="none.xml"><title>Birth Control, 1956</title></xref>;
                <xref from="320987.xml"><title>Birth Control,
                1957</title></xref>; <xref from="320988.xml"><title>Birth
                    Control, 1958</title></xref></p>
        <p>For typed draft of the article, see MSM S72:972</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues"
            level3="in US"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="international"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="international conferences on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods" level3="research"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="American"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement"
            level3="goals and strategies"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="international"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="propaganda and publicity"/>
        <index level1="child spacing"/>
        <index level1="New York City" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Planned Parenthood Federation of America"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="government"
            level3="public health programs"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="freedom and rights of"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Birth Control.</head>
        <div type="section">
            <p>A growing awareness by government leaders and the public of the
                world’s dangerous imbalance between overpopulation and natural
                resources was becoming apparent in 1955. (A world population
                growth of 90,000 a day was estimated by the <org
                    reg="United Nations Department of Social and Economic Affairs"
                    >United Nations department of social affairs</org>.)
                Attention was focused on the need for developing a new,
                simplified and inexpensive contraceptive method–one which would
                be acceptable to people of diverse cultural backgrounds. Under
                the auspices of the <org
                    reg="Planned Parenthood Federation of America">Planned
                    Parenthood federation</org>’s <org
                    reg="Planned Parenhood Federation of America Dickinson Research Memorial Fund"
                    >Dickinson Research Memorial fund</org>, medical research
                pointing toward a contraceptive pill or injection made tangible
                progress during the year. <person reg="Chang, Min Chueh">M.C.
                    Chang</person>, research biologist at the <org>Worcester
                    Foundation for Experimental Biology</org> under the
                direction of <person reg="Pincus, Gregory Goodwin">Gregory
                    Pincus</person>, predicted that such a pill might be
                available to the general public within five years. Chang, who
                received a 1955 Lasker award in planned parenthood for
                outstanding research in animal and human fertility, announced
                that several compounds which worked well on laboratory animals
                were ready to be taken over by physicians for controlled tests
                on men and women.</p>
            <p>Lasker awards in planned parenthood were also given to <person
                    reg="Taylor, Howard Canning, Jr.">Howard C. Taylor</person>
                of <org>Columbia University College of Physicians and
                    Surgeons</org>, and to Lady <person
                    reg="Rama Rau, Dhavanthi Handoo">Dhanvanthi Rama
                    Rau</person>, founder and president of the <org
                    reg="Family Planning Association of India">Family Planning
                    association</org> in <place>India</place>, for their work in
                the family planning field.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">International.–</head>
            <p>The first international birth control conference ever held in
                    <place>Latin America</place> took place in <place
                    reg="San Juan, Puerto Rico">San Juan, P.R.</place>, where the International
                Planned Parenthood federation’s western hemisphere region held
                its pioneer conference in May 1955. An appeal was directed to
                the <org>World Health organization</org> to include child-spacing
                instruction in its program of preventive medicine. Resolutions
                were also sent to the <org
                    reg="United Nations Commission on Human Rights">UN
                    Commission on Human Rights</org> and the I<org>nter-American
                    Commission of Women</org> asking that the right to space
                children be recognized as a basic human freedom.</p>
            <p>Another major international family planning meeting was held in
                1955 when the International Planned Parenthood federation met in
                Tokyo in October for its <org
                    reg="Fifth International Conference on Planned Parenthood"
                    >fifth world conference on planned parenthood</org>.
                Delegates from 15 countries in <place>Europe</place>,
                    <place>Asia</place>, <place>Africa</place>,
                    <place>Australia</place> and <place>the Americas</place>,
                including some of the world’s most eminent scientists in the sex
                physiology and population fields, presented latest findings on
                world population trends, natural resources, family planning
                methods, marriage guidance and sex education, infertility,
                abortion and sterilization.</p>
            <p>A panel of experts in education, medicine, psychiatry, religion,
                social work and business made an intensive examination of family
                life patterns at a symposium during the American Planned
                Parenthood federation’s 35th annual meeting in May. Geared to
                the theme of “<title>The Family in Pursuit of
                Happiness</title>,” panelists traced the growth of family life
                from birth through marriage and parenthood into its relationship
                with community and the world.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">U.S. Services.–</head>
            <p>The year 1955 also marked the start of a long-range program
                designed to make the services of Planned Parenthood more readily
                available to all families that need it. The new emphasis on
                reaching more people was conducted with a wider use of
                communications mediums–literature, radio, TV and motion
                pictures. A graphic account of Planned Parenthood’s four-point
                program of birth control, aid to the childless, education for
                marriage and marriage counseling, and research was unfolded in
                the Planned Parenthood federation’s annual report for 1954
                (published in 1955): The program was being conducted by the
                federation and its 110 state leagues and local committees in 29
                states and the <place reg="District of Columbia"
                    >District of Columbia</place>, and had been endorsed by
                numerous religious bodies and prominent clergymen.</p>
            <p>At the <org>Margaret Sanger Research bureau</org>, <place
                    reg="New York City, NY">New York city</place>,
                physicians and students from medical colleges all over the
                country came to receive instruction in contraceptive techniques.
                The bureau was the only teaching center in the <place
                    reg="United States">U.S.</place> offering education and
                instruction in all phases of the planned parenthood program.</p>
            <p>Affiliates’ activities were conducted by nearly 4,500 volunteers
                and 450 employees. U.S. birth control clinics numbered 536–378
                of which were in public health clinics, hospitals and medicals
                schools, and 178 were sponsored by Planned Parenthood
                committees–reaching a total of nearly 250,000 people. Medical
                assistance to help infertile couples was provided by Planned
                Parenthood in 31 infertility clinics and 65 referral centers. An
                additional 119 infertility clinics were located in hospitals and
                medical schools across the country.</p>
            <byline>(M.SR.)</byline>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
