<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2012-05-30 AW Initial Tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/04/08 EK clean regs/index</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1917-01-29">29 Jan 1917</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Mass Meeting for Birth Control Address</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp321954</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="newspaper">New York Times</title>, Jan. 30, 1917</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger</person> gave this address, after discarding her
            prepared statement, at the Mass Meeting for Birth Control, held at <org>Carnegie
                Hall</org> in <place reg="New York, NY">New York City</place>. Attended by three
            thousand, largely women, the meeting was to support Sanger during her Brownsville Clinic
            trial. Others speaking included Dr. <person reg="Hurt, Mary">Mary Hurt</person> and
                <person reg="Todd, Helen">Helen Todd</person>.</p>
        <p>For a partial draft of Sanger's prepared statement, see <xref from="143430.xml">"Carnegie
                Hall Speech Notes, Jan. 29, 1917."</xref></p>
        <index level1="birth control"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues"/>
        <index level1="Brownsville Clinic"/>
        <index level1="Brownsville Clinic" level2="publicity"/>
        <index level1="family size"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <p>I come to you tonight from a crowded courtroom, from a vortex of persecution. I come not
            from the stake of <place reg="Salem, MA">Salem</place>, where women were burned for
            blasphemy, but from the shadow of <place reg="Blackwell's Island, NY">Blackwell’s
                Island</place>, where women are tortured for ‘obscenity.’</p>
        <p>Birth control is the one means by which the working man shall find emancipation. I was
            one of eleven children. My mother died when I was 17 because she had had too many
            children and had worked herself to death. I became a nurse to help support my family,
            and I soon discovered that 75 per cent. of the diseases of men and women are due to sex
            ignorance. I determined that the average person was as ignorant of sex matters as our
            most primitive ancestors. There has been progress in every department of our lives
            except in the most important--creation. So I came to the conclusion that the greatest
            good I could do was to help poor women to have fewer children to be brought up in want
            and poverty. I threw my nurse’s bag away and swore I would take it up no more. I went to
                <place>Europe</place> and studied the birth control clinics there and came back to
                <place reg="United States">America</place> to do what I could.</p>
        <p>Colonel <person reg="Roosevelt, Theodore">Roosevelt</person> goes all about the country
            telling people to have large families and he is neither arrested nor molested. But can
            he tell me why I got sixty-three letters in one week from poor mothers in <place
                reg="Oyster Bay, NY">Oyster Bay</place> asking me for birth control information? No
            woman can call herself free until she can choose the time she will become a mother.</p>
        <p>My purpose in life is to arouse sentiment for the repeal of the law, State and Federal.
            It is we women who have paid for the folly of this law, and it is up to us to repeal it.
            It is only by birth control that woman can prepare with man, her brother, for the
            emancipation of the race.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
