<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published statement">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014-04-14 EK initial tagging</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-04-14 EK clean regs and error</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-04-18 EK correct proof</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-04-21 CH Making it validate</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-12-18 CH proof and enter tags</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1917-01-27">27 Jan 1917</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Statement on Ethel Byrne's Hunger Strike</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp321975</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Stirring Appeal Written by Birth Control Advocates</title>,
					<title type="journal">Wilkes Barre Times-Leader</title>, Jan. 27, 1917, p.
				13</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="WBTL">Wilkes Barre Times-Leader</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Sanger's statement, distributed by the United Press, was also published
			in the <title type="journal">San Jose Evening News</title>, Jan. 27, 1917.</p>
		<index level1="Brownsville Clinic" level2="imprisonment"/>
		<index level1="Byrne, Ethel Higgins"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="New York"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="working women and"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Stirring Appeal Written by Birth Control Advocates</head>
		<byline>By Mrs. Margaret H. Sanger</byline>
		<p><dateline><place reg="New York, NY">New York</place>, Jan. 27.--</dateline> "<q
				who="WBTL">Discussing the hunger strike of her sister, Mrs. <person
					reg="Byrne, Ethel Higgins">Ethel Byrne</person>, Mrs. <person
					reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>, originator of the birth control
				campaign, to-day gave the <org>United Press</org> the following statement:</q>"</p>
		<p>To the people in the <place>United States</place> who would like to know why my sister
			was convicted and why she has gone on a hunger strike:</p>
		<p>She has gone on a strike, refusing all food, drink and work, because she was thrust into
			prison by a court which denied her the inherent right to test the constitutionality of a
			law which is the most outrageous piece of legislation on the statue books today. </p>
		<p>I mean the law forbidding the dissemination of birth control information. This archaic
			law which has been untested on the statute books since 1878, causes the death of more
			than 8,000 working mothers in <place>New York</place> every year. Similar laws in other
			states being the annual total to the terrible figure of mothers dead through law-imposed
			ignorance of nearly a quarter of a million.</p>
		<p>These unfortunate women go to their graves unnoticed and their agonies and deaths
			unknown. Mrs. Byrne feels that one more death laid at the door of the government of this
			state is of little consequence as a life.</p>
		<p>But if such should be her lot, and if her strike should end in her death, as well it may,
			it will, at least, be known that she died because of this same law.</p>
		<p>Women of the State of New York and of the nation:</p>
		<p>To let Mrs. Byrne die, will be the beginning of the end of your freedom for another
			generation. Already the hand of tyranny has throttled our every effort to obtain
			Justice. With you rests the power to voice your feelings.</p>
		<p>Birth control is practically a new subject in the United States. Birth control is not an
			attack on the birth-rate as such. It is a scientifically just and human effort to
			prevent the birth of more children than parents can endow with strong bodies and in the
			battle of life. Nothing more.</p>
		<p>Birth control is a social principal with a message to woman kind, especially to working
			women, already entrapped as she is in the meshes of ignorance.</p>
		<p>This ignorance is the lot of the working woman alone. It is the working man, his wife and
			his family that present the problems of this generation.</p>
		<p>The women of wealth can and have obtained this knowledge and put it into practice, have
			been relieved of overburdened maternity and are free to experience the joy of life which
			only welcome children and voluntary motherhood can bring.</p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
