<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/06/06 CE</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/06/20 CE</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1954-00-00">1954</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Birth Control, 1953</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp321984</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Britannica Book of the Year</title>(1954), p.
                104</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown, Japanese vice minister of health and
                welfare</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>For other articles in the <title>Britannica Book of the Year</title>
            series, see <xref from="320976.xml"><title>Birth Control,
                    1944</title></xref>; <xref from="320980.xml"><title>Birth
                    Control, 1946</title></xref>; <xref from="320979.xml"
                    ><title>Birth Control, 1947</title></xref>; <xref
                from="321981.xml"><title>Birth Control, 1948</title>,
                1949</xref>;<xref from="320981.xml"><title>Birth Control,
                    1949</title></xref>; <xref from="321981.xml"><title>Birth
                    Control, 1950</title></xref>; <xref from="320983.xml"
                    ><title>Birth Control, 1951</title></xref>; <xref
                from="320984.xml"><title>Birth Control, 1952</title></xref>;
                <xref from="320985.xml"><title>Birth Control,
                1954</title></xref>; <xref from="320986.xml"><title>Birth
                    Control, 1955</title></xref>; <xref from="none.xml"
                    ><title>Birth Control, 1956</title></xref>; <xref
                from="320987.xml"><title>Birth Control, 1957</title></xref>;
                <xref from="320988.xml"><title>Birth Control,
                1958</title></xref></p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues"
            level3="in US"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="international"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="international conferences on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="American"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="international"/>
        <index level1="family planning"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="population policies of"/>
        <index level1="Planned Parenthood Federation of America"/>
        <index level1="population growth" level2="natural resources and"/>
        <index level1="population growth" level2="regulation of"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="government"
            level3="public health programs"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Birth Control.</head>
        <div type="section">
            <p>The planning of family size as a basic means of alleviating
                family welfare problem, overcrowding and poverty, with their
                resulting local and international tensions, gained acceptance in
                many parts of the world during the latter part of 1952 and in
                1953.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">International.–</head>
            <p>An outstanding achievement was the establishment of the first
                global organization, the <org>International Planned Parenthood
                    federation.</org> It was formed at the <org>third
                    International Planned Parenthood conference</org>, held in
                    <place>Bombay, India</place>, in Nov. 1952, the first
                meeting of its kind to be held in the <place>far
                east</place>.</p>
            <p>When the <org>fourth International Planned Parenthood
                    conference</org> took place in <place
                    reg="Stockholm, Sweden">Stockholm, Swed</place>., in Aug.
                1953, the agency was formally ratified and officers were
                    elected.<person reg="Sanger, Margaret"> Margaret
                    Sanger</person>, founder of the birth control movement and
                honorary president of the <org>Planned Parenthood Federation of
                    America</org>, was designated president; Lady <person
                    reg="Rama Rau, Dhanvanthi Handoo">Rama Rau</person>, founder
                and president of the <org>Family Planning Association of
                    India</org>, was elected chairman. The aims of the new
                international body were set forth: to bring about the universal
                acceptance of planned parenthood in the interests of family
                welfare, social well-being and international good will by means
                of a program devoted to education, service and research. The
                federation’s membership comprised planned parenthood
                organizations in <place>Great Britain</place>, India, Sweden,
                the <place>Netherlands</place>, the <place>United
                States</place>, <place>Hong Kong</place>,
                    <place>Singapore</place>, and <place>west
                Germany</place>.</p>
            <p>Still another major event was the inclusion of a family planning
                program in the Indian government’s first five-year plan.
                Presented to both houses of Parliament by Prime Minister <person
                    reg="Nehru, Jawaharlal">Jawaharlal Nehru</person>, the
                program which was adopted was provided with a budget of
                $1,300,000 to carry hour family planning services in government
                hospitals and public health agencies. In addition, its aim was
                to make intensive studies in motivation regarding family
                planning and to carry on field experiment in different methods
                of fertility control, as well as medical and technical research
                in this area.</p>
            <p>Late in 1953 Lady Rama Rau embarked on a coast-to-coast lecture
                tour of the United States, speaking on “<title>India’s Social
                    Revolution</title>.” The tour was under the auspices of the
                Planned Parenthood federation. The lectures in 35 cities, with
                considerable corollary publicity in newspapers, magazines and on
                radio and television, were expected to broaden greatly American
                understanding of family planning as related to India’s pressing
                population problems.</p>
            <p>Asian concern and growing leadership in the population field were
                further evidenced by the sponsorship of a Japanese tour for Mrs.
                Sanger by the <org reg="Mainichi Press">Mainichi
                    newspapers</org> of <place reg="Tokyo, Japan">Tokyo</place>.
                The invitation, which was signed by 3,000 Japanese, brought the
                birth control pioneer to Japan in Oct. 1952, where, by means of
                public meetings, broadcasts and panel discussions with experts,
                she helped encourage, according to the <person
                    reg="Unidentified">vice-minister of welfare</person>, “<q
                    who="UNK">the Japanese Government’s campaign to control
                    conception by legal means</q>.”</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">Research.–</head>
            <p>The urgent need to balance the dwindling world resources and the
                expanding human population focused scientific and public
                attention on research efforts to develop a simple, safe and
                low-cost means of fertility control. Interest during the year
                1953 centered about physiological means of control by pills,
                teas or inoculations. Reports issued described the use of
                chemical agents for control of fertility in animals and human
                beings. Certain naturally occurring and certain synthesized
                products were found effective. Fertility control problems not
                yet fully resolved were toxicity, large-scale production and
                cost.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">U.S. Services.–</head>
            <p>The Planned Parenthood Federation of America was during 1953 the
                national clearinghouse for 12 state leagues and 120 local
                committees. Birth control clinics numbered 519. These services
                were in 274 public health departments, 48 hospitals and 175
                clinics sponsored by federation affiliates. There were 22
                referral services. The seven states which included birth control
                in their public health services were <place>Alabama</place>,
                    <place>Florida</place>, <place>Georgia</place>, <place>
                    Mississippi</place>, <place>North Carolina</place>,
                    <place>South Carolina</place> and <place>Virginia</place>.
                The known infertility clinics were 74, of which 12 were under
                federation auspices.</p>
            <byline>(M.SR.)</byline>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
