<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">

    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-03-12 JK initial tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/03/12 EK clean regs</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-19 CH proof tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-26 JK clean tags</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1928-11-25">25 Nov 1928</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Gives Context.</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp321990</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
         
            <bibl><title type="article">Birth Control Gain Explained</title><title type="journal">L.A. Times</title> Nov. 25, 1928</bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="LAT">L.A. Times</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger</person> gave a statement upon
        arriving in <place reg="Los Angeles, CA">Los Angeles</place> for a one-month speaking tour.
        This statement to the press was made at the <org>Biltmore Hotel</org>. <index level1="Califoria"
            level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="morality of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits and risks"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="legalization of"/>
        <index level1="birth control clinics and leagues" level2="in US"/>
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Federal"/>
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="books by" level3="Motherhood in Bondage"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="speaking tours" level3="1928 (U.S.)"/>
        <index level1="American Birth Control League"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Birth Control Gain Explained</head>
        <head type="sub">Margaret Sanger Arrives in City on Coast Tour</head>
        <head type="sub">Pioneer in Undertaking Says Great Steps Taken</head>
        <head type="sub">Better Country Envisioned if Frankness Prevails</head>
        <p><q who="LAT"> Visiting Los Angeles for the first time since 1916, Margaret Sanger,
                president of the <org>American Birth Control
                    League</org>, known for her books on the subject, arrived here yesterday on the
                    <org reg="Union Pacific Railroad">Union Pacific</org>> Los Angeles limited for a
                month’s stay on the Pacific Coast. </q>“I am particularly interested in the attitude
            of Southern <place>California</place> on the subject of birth control,” she
            said at the Biltmore. “When I was here before the very words, birth control, were taboo
            and were mentioned in whispers. But the movement which we feel is for the good of
            humanity and American citizenship now is commanding
            the attention of all classes of people and is soon to be called before <org
                reg="United States Congress">Congress</org>. I refer to the fact that while there
            are twenty-two clinics legally established in the <place>United States</place> the
            <name type="law" reg="United States Criminal Code, Section 211.">Federal law</name> still makes it unlawful to use the mails to state where these clinics are
            located. We expect to ask at the next session of <org reg="United States Congress">Congress</org> than an amendment be passed
            which will abolish this Federal legal technicality which we feel is blocking a
            humanitarian movement. </p>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Aims Explained </head>

            <p> “Please do not misunderstand me; birth control does not mean the resorting to
                illegal operations and procedure to curtail birth. The public must be educated to
                the fact that control means supervision of the problems of reproduction along clean,
                scientific lines in the interest of human welfare. It may mean prevention where the
                facts justify the adaptation of diet and science to obtain that end but birth
                control as we are advocating it does not mean violation of existing laws or
                distortion of nature. “Could the public know the facts as they exist in <place
                    reg="New York, NY">New York</place> City among the foreign element where
                children are being born into families already beyond rational lines of maintenance,
                the public would understand that the American Birth Control League is only
                endeavoring to minimize poverty and want. The subject is being carried further into
                all walks of life on the basis that dependable offspring is the very life of the
                nation and that there are as many reasons why women who want children should have
                them as there are reasons why women to whom children are an illogical menace should
                not have them. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Need Stressed</head>

            <p> “We do not look on the consideration of this all-important subject as a violation of
                modesty of public decency, but rather as the most important home science of the age
                in which we live. We feel that conditions have reached a point where in the interest
                of public welfare the subject should be handled with open frankness demanding the
                fullest co-operation of citizenship and legislation. To effect this will mean
                cleanliness in body and soul, curtailment of crime and a higher standard of human
                life in this nation. I believe that one generation will effect the change from
                veiled misunderstanding to safe and sane living.” <q who="LAT">Margaret Sanger will
                    speak at the <org>California Institute of Technology</org>, <place
                        reg="Pasadena, CA">Pasadena</place>, tomorrow at 4 p.m. and at the <org>Trinity
                    Auditorium</org>, Los Angeles, December 3. Her latest book, <title type="book"
                        >“Motherhood in Bondage”</title> came from the press just a week
                ago.</q></p>
        </div>

    </docBody>
</doc>
