<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2012-07-11 CH</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-04-13 EK clean regs</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1917-01-29">29 Jan 1917</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>Carnegie Hall Address</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp321960</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Mrs. Sanger Defies Courts Before
					3,0000,</title>
				<title type="journal">New York Times</title>, Jan. 30,
				1917</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="HUNMA">Hunt, Mary</name>
			<name id="NYT">New York Times</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger</person> spoke before three
			thousand at <org>Carnegie Hall</org> on the eve of her sentencing
			for opening the Brownsville Clinic. The only version of the speech
			located comes from newspaper reports. The <title type="newspaper"
				>New York Times</title> reported that, "<q who="NYT">Mrs. Sanger
				departed from the prepared copy of her speech in that she was
				not so severe on the judiciary as she had intended to be. She
				had evidently prepared her speech in the conviction that she was
				to be found guilty yesterday afternoon.</q>" Only portions
			quoting Sanger have been transcribed.</p>

		<index level1="birth control" level2="socio-economic benefits of"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation"/>
		<index level1="Brownsville Clinic" level2="arrests and trial"/>
		<index level1="censorship" level2="in United States"/>
		<index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="background of"/>
		<index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="biography"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<p>"I come to you tonight," she said, "from a crowded courtroom, from a
			vortex of persecution. I come not from the stake at <place
				reg="Salem, MA">Salem</place>, where women were burned for
			blasphemy, but from the shadow of <place
				reg="Blackwell's Island, NY">Blackwell's Island</place>, where
			women are tortured for 'obscenity.'</p>
		<p>"Birth control is the one means by which the working man shall find
			emancipation. I was one of eleven children. My <person
				reg="Higgins, Anne Purcell">mother</person> died when I was 17
			because she had had too many children and had worked herself to
			death. I became a nurse to help support my family, and I soon
			discovered that 75 per cent of the diseases of men and women are due
			to sex ignorance. I determined that when I was able I would do what
			I could to solve that problem. I found that the average person was
			as ignorant of sex matters as our most primitive ancestors. There
			has been progress in every department of our lives except in the
			most important--creation. So I cam to the conclusion that the
			greatest good I could do was to help poor women to have fewer
			children to be brought up in want and poverty. I threw my nurse's
			bag away and swore I would take it up no more. I went to
				<place>Europe</place> and studied the birth control clinics
			there and came back to <place reg="United States">America</place> to
			do what I could.</p>
		<p><person reg="Roosevelt, Theodore">Colonel Roosevelt</person> goes all
			about the country telling people to have large families and he is
			neither arrested nor molested. But can he tell me why I got
			sixty-three letters in one week from poor mothers in <place
				reg="Oyster Bay, NY">Oyster Bay</place> asking me for birth
			control information? No woman can call herself free until she can
			choose the time she will become a monther.</p>
		<p>My purpose in life is to arounse sentiment for the repeal of the law,
			State and Federal. It is we women who have paid for the folly of
			this law, and it is up to us to repeal it. It is only by birth
			control that woman can prepare with man, her brother, for the
			emanicipation of the race.</p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
