<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2012-06-27 AW Initial Tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-12 EK clean regs</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-05-19 CH used this as a basis for another and deleted this one. </prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1925-03-27">27 Mar 1926</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Does Marriage Interfere With a Career?</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp321970</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="newspaper">Brooklyn Daily Eagle</title>, Mar. 27, 1926</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="SANPE">Sanger, Peggy</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>This article was published under the same title in the <title>Winnipeg Free Press</title> on Sept. 25, 1926.</p>
        <index level1="child welfare"/>
        <index level1="marriage"/>
        <index level1="motherhood" level2="MS on"/> 
        <index level1="women" level2="freedom and rights of"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="children of" level3="MS on"/>  
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Does Marriage Interfere With a Career?</head>
        <head type="sub">Interview With <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret
                Sanger</person></head>
        <p>When a women finds that domestic work has become a drab, monotonous
            business in her life, she is wise if she finds something to do to
            fill up the gap. The moment she reaches a stage when her husband and
            children need only 50 per cent. of her creative energy, she is far
            more loyal to her family if she does something else than if she
            follows tradition and stays at home and grumbles. Her new work often
            disciplines a woman to appreciate her home more.</p>
        <p>In my own case, my children were still very young when I left them in
            the case of their grand-mother and went out nursing. I was a trained
            nurse before I married and when I found that my family could spare
            me, I left the children in competent hands and went back to
            work.</p>
        <p>Of course young children need their mother a great deal. But children
            are by nature selfish, and they will let you indulge them as much as
            you please. It isn’t good for them, though. As a matter of fact,
            they should be taught by example that a mother is not here merely to
            be their attendant, but she is a superior being, a personage as
            well. They have much more respect for her then.</p>
        <p>My children were very much interested in the influence I brought home
            from the outside world, especially the boys. It was unusual for a
            mother to tell her children about scientific things, and to let them
            read literature on science; so the boys thought I was a much more
            wonderful mother than any mother of their friends.</p>
        <p>But my little <person reg="Sanger, Peggy">girl</person> resented it
            when I went away. In the early days she would say to me when I put
            her to bed: “<q who="SANPE">Mother, must you go out to a lecture
                tonight</q>?” And if I answered in the affirmative, she would
            vent her anger on lectures, and cry: “<q who="SANPE">I hate
                lectures. . . I hate them</q>. . . ” I could easily have
            remedied her ills by promising not to go and going any way when she
            was asleep. But I didn’t see why I should lie to her even if she
            forgot about it the next morning.</p>
        <p>But I confess, nevertheless, that when my little girl cried that way
            it always gave me a dull feeling until I got back home again. And
            yet, can you see any earthly sense for a mother to stay at home
            merely to indulge her child?</p>
        <p>That is what I had in mind when I said that children were selfish
            little beings. Whether they need their mother or not, they want her
            to be near them all the time simply because they want her. To them
            that is reason enough.</p>
        <p>Remember, however, that not every marriage permits the woman to
            behave that way. It depends on the particular case and the kind of
            husband you marry. Only an intelligent, sensible husband will
            understand his wife when she wishes to go out and do something
            else.</p>
        <p>Otherwise the man who married a nice, sweet, home-loving girl will
            consider himself deceived, or at best disillusioned, when he finds
            out one day after many years that she has professional aspirations
            too. He isn’t prepared for it and will have none of that nonsense in
            his own house. Consequently. . . You know what happens then.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
