<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published statement">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2013/11/13 JK encoded</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-04-13 EK clean regs</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-22 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1928-04-24">24 Apr, 1928</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Statement on Parents' Exposition</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp321993</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>
				<title type="article">Mrs. Sanger Calls Catholics Bigots</title>, <title
					type="journal">New York Times</title>, Apr. 25, 1928, p. 14</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="NYT">New York Times</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>When the American Birth Control League's booth at the Parents' Exposition in New York
			City was cancelled, Sanger issued a statement.</p>
		<index level1="Catholic Church" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="American Birth Control League"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="politicians and"/>
		<index level1="censorship" level2="in United States"/>
		<index level1="Catholic Church" level2="political influence of"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Mrs. Sanger Calls Catholics Bigots</head>
		<head type="sub">Birth Control Leader Assails Church 'Tyranny' for Ban at Parents'
			Exposition</head>
		<div type="section">
			<p><q who="NYT">The <org>American Birth Control League</org>, whose contract for a booth
					was cancelled by the <org>Parents' Exposition</org> at the <org>Grand Central
						Palace</org> at the insistence of the <org
						reg="New York City Board of Education">Board of Education</org> officials,
					has retained <person reg="Hays, Arthur Garfield">Arthur Garfield Hays</person>
					to sue the management, Mrs. Margaret Sanger announced last night. She assailed
					Catholics as responsible for the ban and asserts that the election of <person
						reg="Smith, Alfred E.">Governor Smith</person></q> "as a representative of a
				church whose tyrannical intolerance is far worse than the lack of broad-mindedness
				which it criticizes in others would be a national calamity.</p>
			<p>"At a time when a Roman Catholic aspirant to the Presidency and the <org
					reg="Democratic Party">party he leads</org> are stressing the importance of
				religious tolerance," <q who="NYT">Mrs. Sanger said,"</q>the arbitrary action of
					<person reg="O'Shea, William J.">Dr. William J. O'Shea</person> in bullying the
				Parents' Association into submission and acquiescence to his Catholic prejudices is
				a flagrant example of the bigotry and usurpation of power exercised by officeholders
				born and bred in the Roman Catholic faith. "This conflict brings into the open the
				menace of intolerant tyranny in the educational institutions of the <place>United
					States</place>. If such power is to be given national scope, through a
				Presidential aspirant, its disastrous effect on the future of American civilization
				will be incalculable." </p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">Charges Insult by O'Shea</head>
			<p><q who="NYT">Mrs. Sanger explained that upon learning of the objections of Dr. O'Shea
					to the Birth Control League's exhibition she wrote to him requesting the
					appointment of a committee to review it and suggest any imrpovements.</q></p>

			<p>"Dr. O'Shea not only ignored this request but has chosen to insult us and cast
				aspersions on our work," <q who="NYT">Mrs. Sanger added.</q> "When conftronted with
				our organization, which has aroused the <org>Roman Catholic Church</org> in open and
				disguised warfare, he immediately gave orders to kick the American Birth Control
				League out of the Grand Central Palace without letting a vestige of it remain.</p>
			<p>"Such unwarranted usurpation of power can be made in <place reg="New York, NY">New
					York City</place> only because it is supported and backed by religious
				affiliations which are entrenched in political power."</p>
			<p><q who="NYT">Declaring that </q>"this is the first time we have been barred from an
				exposition," <q who="NYT">Mrs. Sanger added that Protestant and Jewish ministers and
					many social organizations in New York and throughout the country had praised the
					work of the birth control movement as </q>"the most vital agency for the
				improvement of the human race."</p>
		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
