<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2012-06-29 AW Initial Tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-14 CH Clean regs and proof codes</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-18 EK correct proof</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1916-04-25">25 Apr 1916</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>
                <supplied resp="MSPP">Birth Control</supplied>
            </titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp321958</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Birth Control Way to Welfare--Mrs. Sanger</title>, <title
                    type="journal">The Chicago Daily Tribune</title>, Apr 26, 1916, p. 17.</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="CDT">Chicago Daily Tribune</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>Margaret Sanger visited <place reg="Chicago, IL">Chicago, Illinois</place> as part of her
            1916 American tour, and delivered a lecture at the <org>West Side Auditorium</org>. For
            a possible draft of this speech see "<xref from="236132.xml"><title type="article">Birth
                    Control (Chicago Address to Women)</title></xref>". For an interview given at
            the same time, see "<xref from="421939.xml"><title type="article">Interview on
                    Chicago</title></xref>," Apr. 25, 1916.</p>
        <index level1="abortion" level2="frequency of"/>
        <index level1="censorship" level2="in United States"/>
        <index level1="prostitution"/>
        <index level1="working classes"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="speaking tours" level3="1916 (U.S.)"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Birth Control Way to Welfare--Mrs. Sanger</head>
        <div>
            <q who="CDT">
                <p>Mrs. Margaret Sanger lectured last night at the west side auditorium on "Birth
                    Control" to an audience of 1,200 people. So crowded was the hall, so large the
                    number that wished to get in, that a dozen times during the evening the lecture
                    had to be halted on account of the fire laws, for the police to put out the
                    people who were standing.</p>
                <p>The audience was composed in large measure of young people--girls and young women
                    and young men. There were high school girls with their hair down their backs in
                    curls.</p>
                <p>Mrs. Sanger, who has been fourteen years a trained nurse in obstetric cases in
                        <place reg="New York, NY">New York</place>, has devoted the last three years
                    to studying birth control here and in European countrieses. She says that 75 per
                    cent of all the diseases of men and women in this country are due to ignorance
                    of sex life.</p></q>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Nation of Abortions.</head>
            <p>"The first step to the goal for women is a knowledge of what to do. Only the wealthy
                have this knowledge today. For them abortions are possible and with them there are
                no deaths. But it is the poor who need this knowledge, and you will find that the
                doctors know the state and moral law by heart when it comes to treating poor women
                for abortion. There is no country in the world which has so many abortions and so
                many deaths from abortion as the <place>United States</place>."</p>
            <p>"After all, this is only a question of labor. The workmen are starved out of work by
                their own children, who enter into the competition at an incredibly early age."</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Big Families, Weak Units.</head>
            <p>"Statistics have determined that 85 per cent of the prostitutes in America come from
                families of eight and nine children, and that 50 per cent of these girls are
                defectives. And do you know that the fertility of a defective parent is four times
                greater than that of a normal parent?"</p>
            <p>"Has the state a better right to decide when a woman shall have a child than the
                woman herself? They call me immoral. Who is more immortal–-I, going around trying to
                help women to bring up their one or two offspring in comparative health, security,
                and mental perfection, or Mr. <person reg="Roosevelt, Theodore">Roosevelt</person>,
                who goes up and down the country urging women whose husbands get $10 a week, who may
                be diseased or idiots or what not to have just as many children as they can? And yet
                he is praised everywhere. Is that moral to delude a woman into producing cannon
                fodder for professional jingoes?"</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Decries Little Mothers</head>
            <p>"I know nothing more disgraceful in this country than the <org>Little Mothers'
                    league</org>. Think of little 10 year old girls spending all their time looking
                after smaller sisters, bending over them, deforming themselves so they can never
                properly bear motherhood themselves! All these palliatives–-the <org
                    reg="Better Babies Leagues">better babies movement</org>, the <org>Infant
                    Protective league</org>–-all make me think of the quack who cures the cancer by
                burning away the top in place of going after the root."</p>
            <p>"Every country has knowledge of birth control and is anxious to send it to us. But we
                are the only country the postal laws of which forbid the discussion of such matters
                in the malls. Do we realize the menace of this censorship? The postal service was
                never created to be a religious or ethical institution."</p>
            <q who="CDT"><p>Mrs. Sanger quoted <place reg="Netherlands">Holland</place>, which has
                    established fifty-two free clinics for instructing women in health hygiene and
                    in teaching them birth control. Her aim is to do the same thing in this country.
                    Already ten leagues have been formed, and last night hundreds of women signed
                    the slips asking for the forming of a similar league in Chicago.</p></q>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
