<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2012-06-29 AW Initial Tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-17 EK clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1916-10-21">21 Oct 1916</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Secret Clinics in New York and the
                Country</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp321961</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">The Wilkes-Barre Times</title>, Oct 21, 1916, p. 1.</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="United States" level2="birth control clinics and leagues in"/>
        <index level1="child labor"/>
        <index level1="poverty" level2="family size and"/>
        <index level1="prostitution"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="employment of"/>
        <index level1="working classes" level2="living conditions of"/>
        <index level1="New York" level2="birth control laws and legislation"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits of"/>
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation"/>
        <index level1="Brownsville Clinic" level2="publicity"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <div type="section">
            <p>The poor, century-behind-the-times public officials of this country, might just be as
                well forget their moss grown statutes and accept birth control as an establishment.
                My new national plan makes it as inevitable as night and day.</p>
            <p>The police are hunting my <org reg="Brownsville Clinic">clinic</org> today. They
                can’t find it. If they should, they can’t hurt it. It is an oral clinic and the law
                says nothing about not spreading birth control information orally. If they do try to
                interfere, I’m legally prepared to carry on a hard and bitter fight to the highest
                tribunal in the land with the best legal talent there is.</p>
        </div>

        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">Secret Clinics</head>
            <p>Four more secret clinics will be running <place reg="New York, NY">New York</place>
                within a week. In less than a year there will be clinics in <place
                    reg="Washington, D.C.">Washington</place>, <place reg="Cleveland, OH"
                    >Cleveland</place>, <place reg="Detroit, MI">Detroit</place>, <place
                    reg="St. Paul, MN">St. Paul</place>, <place reg="Minneapolis, MN"
                    >Minneapolis</place>, <place reg="Milwaukee, WI">Milwaukee</place>, <place
                    reg="Denver, CO">Denver</place>, <place reg="St. Louis, MO">St. Louis</place>,
                    <place reg="Los Angeles, CA">Los Angeles</place>, <place reg="San Francisco, CA"
                    >San Francisco</place>, <place reg="San Diego, CA">San Diego</place>, <place
                    reg="Portland, OR">Portland</place>, <place reg="Seattle, WA">Seattle</place>,
                    <place reg="Spokane, WA">Spokane</place>, and <place reg="Butte, MT"
                    >Butte</place>. They are every one organized and ready to open the minute I say
                the word. The Washington clinic will open within a few days.</p>
            <p>Do the women like it? Say, you ought to go down in the neighborhood we have canvassed
                with secret circulars the last 48 hours. The women have been coming in by the
                dozens. You can hear them calling from house to house in the congested districts:
                    “<q who="UNK">Oh, Mrs. <person>Rosenbaum</person>, you ought to see this, this
                    is something fine</q>.”</p>
            <p>Within two years every man and woman in this country will know how many children they
                can afford to have. And when they know that I predict that two generations of birth
                control will wipe out all the slums, eliminate the birth of mental defectives,
                minimize the number of humans in our insane asylums and automatically put a stop to
                child labor and prostitution.</p>
        </div>

        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">The Cures Promised</head>
            <p>I say it will wipe out child labor, because statistics show that 97 per cent of our
                child labor is recruited from families too large to be cared for by the parents.</p>
            <p>It say it will wipe out the worst of prostitution because statistics prove that 95
                per cent of the girls taken from lives of prostitution and placed in industrial
                homes come from poor parents with nine or more children.</p>
            <p>Poverty doesn’t force these girls into prostitution, but the lack of attention they
                get with so many children at home and the general sordid tone of their lives
                naturally leads them to such a life.</p>
            <p>My friends and myself are going to bring the people of this country to realize that a
                man making only $15 a week cannot afford to marry, much less have children. And
                they’ll learn that the average workingman’s family should not exceed two children,
                even under the most favorite physical conditions.</p>
            <p> This is the work the law and public officials are trying to stop.</p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
