<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/06/06 CE</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/06/20 CE</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1951-00-00">1951</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Birth Control, 1950</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp321980</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Britannica Book of the Year</title>(1951), p.
                110</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="AMLF"> Albert D. and Mary Lasker Foundation Award</name>
            <name id="PPFA">Planned Parenthood Federation of America</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>For other articles in the <title>Britannica Book of
                the Year</title> series, see <xref from="320976.xml"
                    ><title>Birth Control, 1944</title></xref>; <xref
                from="320980.xml"><title>Birth Control, 1946</title></xref>;
                <xref from="320979.xml"><title>Birth Control,
                1947</title></xref>; <xref from="321981.xml"><title>Birth
                    Control, 1948</title>, 1949</xref>;<xref from="320981.xml"
                    ><title>Birth Control, 1949</title></xref>; <xref
                from="320983.xml"><title>Birth Control, 1951</title></xref>;
                <xref from="320984.xml"><title>Birth Control,
                1952</title></xref>; <xref from="321984.xml"><title>Birth
                    Control, 1953</title></xref>; <xref from="320985.xml"
                    ><title>Birth Control, 1954</title></xref>; <xref
                from="320986.xml"><title>Birth Control, 1955</title></xref>;
                <xref from="none.xml"><title>Birth Control, 1956</title></xref>;
                <xref from="320987.xml"><title>Birth Control,
                1957</title></xref>; <xref from="320988.xml"><title>Birth
                    Control, 1958</title></xref></p>
        <p>For typed draft of the article, see MSM S72:610.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to"
            level3="in remote places"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues"
            level3="in US"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="medical community and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="methods"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="American"/>
        <index level1="Planned Parenthood Federation of America"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="government"
            level3="public health programs"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Birth Control.</head>
        <div type="section">
            <p>During 1950 the Planned Parenthood movement began a long-range
                education, service and research program. This program, adopted
                the previous year by the <org>Planned Parenthood Federation of
                    America</org> was: “<q who="PPFA">To provide leadership
                    toward universal acceptance of family planning as an
                    essential element of responsible parenthood and stable
                    family life</q>.” Intensified field work was carried on,
                especially on the Pacific coast. A program of work with
                minority-group families whose economic status denied them
                private medical care was expanded to educate them as to
                contraceptive clinic services available. Work was carried on
                with ten leading Negro organizations with the objective of
                encouraging their leaders to co-operate with national, state and
                local Planned Parenthood programs and to stimulate their
                interest in this health measure. Consultants also took part in
                courses or in family institutes under federation sponsorship in
                23 Negro colleges as a method of interpreting the program to
                students who would one day take their places as community
                leaders.</p>
            <p>The federation produced its first film <title>A Planned
                    Parenthood Story</title>, designed to reach married couples
                in need of accurate information on how conception control could
                strengthen their family life.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">Awards.–</head>
            <p>The sixth annual <org>Albert D. and Mary Lasker Foundation
                    Awards</org> in Planned Parenthood went to <person
                    reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>, founder of
                the birth control movement and <person
                    reg="Moses, Bessie Louise">Bessie L. Moses</person>, M.D.,
                of <place reg="Baltimore, Maryland">Baltimore</place>. Mrs.
                Sanger's citation read: “<q who="AMLF">To Margaret Sanger,
                    foremost in teaching families wise planning in birth
                    control: Leader in influencing nations towards balanced
                    population; living to see her beginnings in city slums grow
                    into plans for a planet</q>.” Dr. Moses, obstetrician and
                instructor in obstetrics, <org>Johns Hopkins university</org>,
                was recognized for “her brilliant record of forwarding the cause
                of Planned Parenthood among the public and medical
                profession.”</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">Research.–</head>
            <p>During the year the federation established its own research
                program in human reproduction and three studies in fertility and
                infertility were carried over from a previous research project
                that had been sponsored with the <org>National Research
                    council's Committee on Human Reproduction</org> and the
                    <org>National Committee on Maternal Health</org>.</p>
            <p>The final goal of research in this field was to develop a
                contraceptive method sufficiently simple, safe and effective to
                be used by families living in overpopulated world areas where
                existing methods cannot be widely disseminated because cost and
                complexity prohibit their use among illiterate submerged
                peoples.</p>
            <p>Clinical and laboratory research in contraception and other
                phases of human fertility were also carried on during the year
                at the <org>Margaret Sanger Research bureau</org>.</p>
            <p>The Planned Parenthood federation was in 1950 the national agency
                and clearinghouse for 15 state leagues and 98 local committees.
                Birth control clinics numbered 522. These services were in 252
                public health departments, 52 hospitals and 190 extramural
                clinics and there were 28 referral services. Of the 162,377
                yearly total of patients visiting birth control clinics in 1949,
                the majority or 150,693 were served in the extramural clinics,
                sponsored by federation affiliates. Of the 67 infertility
                clinics, 16 were under Planned Parenthood auspices.</p>
            <byline>(M.SR.)</byline>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
