<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2013/11/13 JK encoded</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/04/13 EK clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1931-03-23">23 March, 1931</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Statement on Endorsement of Federal Churches of Christ
                    in America</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp321963</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Acclaims Report on Birth Control</title></bibl>
            <bibl><title type="newspaper">Atlanta Constitution,</title> Mar. 24, 1931</bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="AC">Atlanta Constitution</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">While examining the outstanding work of the birth control movement, Mrs.
            <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger</person> issued a statement through the committee
        on marriage and the home. <index
            level1="Federal Council of the Churches of Christ in America"/>
        <index level1="religion" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="religion and"/>
        <index level1="sex and marriage"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="morality of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Margaret Sanger Acclaims Report on Birth Control</head>
        <p>Today is a most significant one in the history of the birth control movement. Today for
            the first time, a large, representatives group of churchmen and women has gone on record
            as beign aware of the tremendous mass of scientific information which we possess,
            medical, sociological and psychological -- and has applied it directly to the important
            question of the sex relation between married people. </p>
        <p>My work during all these years has gone steadily forward. Through education, through
            propoganda, through the establishment of clinics, the truths were brought before many
            men and women. Truths as to the need for the spacing of children, the limitation of the
            number of offsprings, the safeguarding of the health and ofttimes the lives of mother
            and child. How grateful we must then be to this progressive and representative body
            which in straightforward and unequivocal terms-- the result of clear thinking-- puts its
            stamp of approval on this subject of importance and necessity. Women's clubs,
            physicians, scientists, sociologists, isolated groups of churchmen have in the past
            added the weight of their approval. But this is the largest and perhaps the most
            significant group that has as yet expressed itself in whole-hearted accord with our
            movement. </p>
        <p>To admit that this knowledge of birth control will mean vice and immortality is to admit
            the failure of the church in its influence and education. This eminent group,
            representing as it does, the <org>Protestant church</org> in <place reg="United States"
                >America</place>, has recognized and accepted this responisbility of education and
            influence. They are to be congratulated on their recognition of birth control as a moral
            and a valid idea and for their clear and direct presentation of the findings of the
            committee. The statement inspires me with a wholesome respect for a group with influence
            such as that of the <org reg="Federal Council of the Churches of Christ in America">Federal
                Council of Churches</org> for its honesty and straight-forward thinking. They have
            not evaded--they have not hedged--they have met the issue fairly. </p>
        <p>Indeed, this is the largest step in the progress of the birth control movement. But the
            task before us is not over by any means. Encouraged and inspired by the action of the
                Federal Council of the Churches of Christ in America, we can now regard
            many of the obstacles as cleared away. But our aim is still to put birth control on a
            truly scientific basis, through research and education and the establishment of more
            clinic. There is still a world of work to be done. </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
