<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2012-06-29 AW Initial Tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2012-10-25 CH Proof tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-14 EK clean regs></prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-16 EK correct proof </prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1916-05-18">18 May 1916</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Statement on Emma Goldman</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp321959</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Discusses her Favorite Topic</title>
                <title type="journal">Daily Republican</title>, May 18, 1916, p. 5.</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="DR">Daily Republican</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>Margaret Sanger visited Idianapolis from May 15-18, 1916, speaking on birth control to
            the National conference of charities and corrections at the Claypool Hotel. she made two
            more speeches at the Hotel English and the Murat Theater. these remarks may have been
            drawn from one of these events, or from a press </p>
        <index level1="Netherlands, the" level2="clinics and leagues"/>
        <index level1="Goldman, Emma" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="poverty"/>
        <index level1="poverty" level2="family size and"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="differential"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Indiana"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="speaking tour" level3="1916 (U.S.)"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Discusses her Favorite Topic</head>
        <dateline>Indianapolis, Ind., May 18.-- </dateline>
        <p>"I am delighted with the reception which I received in <place reg="Indianapolis, IN"
                >Indianapolis</place> and from the people of <place>Indiana</place>. I have found
            them fully as receptive toward birth control as the communities of the east where
            information on the movement has been more widely circulated."</p>
        <p>"<q who="DR">This was the way Mrs. <name reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret
                    Sanger</name>, <place reg="New York, NY">New York City</place>, foremost advocate
                of birth control, summed up her three-day visit in indianapolis for the United Press
                today just before leaving for <place reg="St. Louis, MO">St. Louis</place>. From St.
                Louis Mrs. Sanger will go to the Pacific coast in her tour to
                    impart information on birth control.</q>"</p>
        <p>"<q who="DR">A small demure woman with a soft voice, quiet eyes with a slight twinkle,
                and dressed neatly in accordance with the prevailing styles is Mrs. Sanger, the
                woman who through indictment by the Federal Grand Jury in New York became one of the
                most widely known women in the country. Indeed Mrs. Sanger is a type of the
                profession she followed for fourteen years -- that of nursing.</q>"</p>
        <p>"I do not wish to be connected in any way with <person reg="Goldman, Emma">Emma
                Goldman</person>," emphasized Mrs. Sanger. "While some of the things advocated by
            Miss Goldman are similar to those, which I uphold yet Miss Goldman has her ideals and I
            have mine."</p>
        <p>"Birth control," she continued in her logical manner of speaking, "is not a new thing. It
            really is a very old practice. Today <place reg="Netherlands, the">Holland</place> has
            taken it up the most widely and there are 152 clinics and dispensaries where information
            concerning the prevention of conception can be secured. In Holland birth control even
            has been recognized by the state as a public utility."</p>
        <p>"The essence of my teaching is this; Not more babies but better babies. As I see it, the
            menace to our civilization is not the stationary birth rate of our upper classes but the
            steady increase of children in poor families. Three hundred thousand babies die in the
                <place>United States</place> every year from poverty and neglect while 600,000
            parents remain in ignorance as to how to prevent 300,000 more babies coming into the
            world next year."</p>
        <p>"I am glad that Indiana is among the states which have no laws prohibiting the
            dissemination of information for the prevention of birth control. I believe through my
            conferences during the past three days and with aid of your laws that the movement will
            have a rapid growth in Indiana."</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
