<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/06/06 CE</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/06/20 CE</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1949-00-00">1949</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Birth Control, 1949</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp321981</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Britannica Book of the Year</title>(1949), pp.
                119-120</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="ICPP">International Committee on Planned Parenthood</name>
            <name id="ORRJO">Orr, Sir John Boyd</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>For other articles in the <title>Britannica Book of
                the Year</title> series, see <xref from="320976.xml"
                    ><title>Birth Control, 1944</title></xref>; <xref
                from="320980.xml"><title>Birth Control, 1946</title></xref>;
                <xref from="320979.xml"><title>Birth Control,
                1947</title></xref>; <xref from="320981.xml"><title>Birth
                    Control, 1949</title></xref>; <xref from="321981.xml"
                    ><title>Birth Control, 1950</title></xref>; <xref
                from="320983.xml"><title>Birth Control, 1951</title></xref>;
                <xref from="320984.xml"><title>Birth Control,
                1952</title></xref>; <xref from="321984.xml"><title>Birth
                    Control, 1953</title></xref>; <xref from="320985.xml"
                    ><title>Birth Control, 1954</title></xref>; <xref
                from="320986.xml"><title>Birth Control, 1955</title></xref>;
                <xref from="none.xml"><title>Birth Control, 1956</title></xref>;
                <xref from="320987.xml"><title>Birth Control,
                1957</title></xref>; <xref from="320988.xml"><title>Birth
                    Control, 1958</title></xref></p>
        <p>For a typed draft of the article, see MSM S72:575.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="American opinion on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues"
            level3="in US"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="economic benefits and risks of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="in marriages"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="international"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation"
            level3="Massachusetts"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="legalization of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="medical community and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="American"/>
        <index level1="Planned Parenthood Federation of America"/>
        <index level1="population" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="population" level2="food supply and"/>
        <index level1="population growth" level2="natural resources and"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="government"
            level3="public health programs"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Birth Control</head>
        <div type="section">
            <p>The first comprehensive program on research in human reproduction
                was begun during 1948. Nine studies were started on factors
                governing fertility control and problems of infertility in as
                many institutions throughout the country. They were recommended
                by the <org>National Research council</org>'s <org>Committee on
                    Human Reproduction</org> to the board of the <org>National
                    Committee on Maternal Health</org>; funds were raised mainly
                by the <org>Planned Parenthood Federation of America</org>, one
                of the three collaborating organizations. The dearth of
                scientific work in fertility control resulted in numerous
                applications for study of fields other than conception
                control.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">Population.–</head>
            <p>The <org>International Congress on Population and World Resources
                    in Relation to the Family</org>, held in <place
                    reg="Cheltenham, England">Cheltenham</place>, England, was
                an indication of the rising interest among scientists and the
                lay public in world population problems. <person
                    reg="Orr, Sir John Boyd">Sir John Orr</person>, former
                director of the <org
                    reg="United Nations Food and Agriculture Organization">World
                    Food and Agricultural organization</org> told the congress,
                    “<q who="ORRJO">If we cannot <supplied resp="MSPP"
                        >solve</supplied> the problem of world resources in this
                    century, we are heading for the greatest catastrophe in
                    history...hungry people do not die quietly, and why should
                    they?</q>” Representatives from more than 20 countries
                participated. They were leaders in three fields: scientific and
                social inquiry, biological and medical research, and
                organizational activity in the promotion of planned parenthood.
                A provisional international committee was established with
                headquarters in <place reg="London, England">London</place>. Its
                purpose was “<q who="ICPP">to promote research and education for
                    the furthering of human welfare through planned parenthood
                    and progressive sex education</q>.” Members were the
                national Planned Parenthood organizations of <place>Great
                    Britain</place>, the <place>Netherlands</place>,
                    <place>Sweden</place> and the <place>United States</place>,
                the only four nations where such agencies existed.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">Magazine Poll.–</head>
            <p>A poll of more than 3,000,000 women was conducted by
                    <title>Woman's Home Companion</title>. Three-fifths favoured
                making birth-control information available to all adults, and
                97% of those polls approved birth control measures for use by
                married women.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">Committee on Clinic Studies.–</head>
            <p>A demonstration to evaluate the practical efficiency of simple
                existing contraceptive methods was developed in order to broaden
                the use of conception control in public health. The need for
                such a study was indicated by the small percentage
                (approximately 5%) of patients attending pre- and postnatal
                public health clinics receiving conception-control
                information.</p>
            <p>It was found after an investigation by <person
                    reg="Kling, Llewellyn E.">L.E. Kling</person>, federation
                medical director, of clinics in <place>Florida</place>,
                    <place>Mississippi</place>, <place reg="North Carolina"
                    >North</place> and <place>South Carolina</place>,
                    <place>Virginia</place>, <place>West Virginia</place>,
                    <place>Georgia</place> and <place>Alabama</place> that
                staffs were too overworked to give time to fitting and
                instructing patients, Many patients did not know this service
                was available, since neither the public health nurse nor health
                educator mentioned or encouraged it.</p>
            <p>A committee on clinic studies was appointed by the federation's
                    <org
                    reg="Planned Parenthood Federation of America, Medical Advisory Committee"
                    >Medical Executive committee</org>. It was given the support
                of private physicians who agreed on the need to encourage
                practical application of planned parenthood in public
                health.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub"><place>Massachusetts</place> Birth-Control
                Referendum.–</head>
            <p>A birth control referendum on the question of allowing physicians
                to prescribe contraceptives to married women whose health of
                life, in the judgment of the physician, required it, was
                defeated by 200,000 votes in the Massachusetts election.</p>
            <p>The measure, which aimed to place contraceptive advice in the
                hands of the medical profession, was endorsed by a majority of
                resident members of the <org>Massachusetts Medical society</org>
                and by more than 1,000 Protestant and Jewish clergymen. Four
                thousand voters in 300 local committees campaigned to repeal the
                state law.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">Organization.–</head>
            <p>The Planned Parenthood federation was in 1948 the national agency
                and clearinghouse for 15 state leagues and 166 local committees.
                The total number of birth control clinics stood at 557. These
                services were in 242 public health clinics, 62 hospital clinics,
                210 extramural clinics and 43 referral services. Of the 58
                fertility clinics in the U.S. listed with the federation, 13
                were under Planned Parenthood direction.</p>
            <p>(<byline><person reg="Sanger, Margaret"
                >M.SR</person></byline>.)</p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
