<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<doc type="Published Interview">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2013/12/18 JK encoded</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-01-22 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1928-03-15">
			<supplied resp="MSPP">15 Mar 1928</supplied>
		</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Statement on Overpopulation in Europe</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp321977</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Says Europe's Future Lies in Birth Control</title>, <title
					type="journal">New York Times</title>, Mar. 15, 1928, p. 17</bibl>

		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="NYT">New York Times</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<index level1="Europe" level2="birth control in"/>
		<index level1="Europe" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="American Birth Control League"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Says Europe's Future Lies in Birth Control</head>
		<head type="sub"><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Mrs. Sanger,</person> Back, says
			Overpopulation Threatens to Lead to Food Riots and War. </head>
		<p><q who="NYT"><place>Europe </place>has become so over-populated that within ten years it
				must either recognize the necessity for birth control or it will burst its confines
				and become involved in a chaos of food riots and war, according to Margaret Sanger,
				birth control advocate, who returned home <supplied resp="MSPP">from</supplied> the
				Isle de<place> France</place>. Mrs. Sanger spent two years in Europe lecturing and
				organizing the <org reg="World Population Conference, 1927">Population
					Conference</org> at <place reg="Geneva, Switzerland">Geneva</place>. </q>“The
			over-populated condition of Europe is fast becoming acute,” Mrs. Sanger said yesterday,
			“especially because of our restrictions on immigration.<place> Italy,</place>
			<place>Germany</place>, <place>Poland </place>and some other countries are particularly
			cross at us because of the immigration ban. Italy, the greatest foe of birth control in
			all Europe, is overpopulated.” <q who="NYT">Because she traveled under her second
					<person reg="Slee, J. Noah H.">husband</person>’s name. Mrs. M. S. Slee, Mrs.
				Sanger was not found by ship news reporters. She was interviewed late in the
				afternoon at headquarters of the <org>American Birth Control League</org>, 104 Fifth
				Avenue.</q> “Birth control in Europe was born of an economic necessity,” Mrs. Sanger
			said. “Here in <place reg="United States">America</place> it is recognized chiefly as a
			health measure. The greatest progress is being made in <place>England</place>, where the
			movement started. There birth control information can be distributed without conflicting
			with the law. Of course most physicians in England are still afraid to dispense such
			information because they fear they will lose their ‘grants.’ The <place
				reg="Scandinavia">Scandinavian countries</place> and Germany are also becoming
			organized.” <q who="NYT">The fight here, Mrs. Sanger said, will be concurrent with the
				Birth Control Bill introduced in the Legislature last month. A group of women’s
				clubs and other organizations have signified their intention to support it, she
				declared.</q>
		</p>


	</docBody>
</doc>
