<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2013-11-13 CH encoded</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-08-21 CH clean regs</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-12-19 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1917-04-21">
			<supplied resp="MSPP">21 Apr 1917</supplied>
		</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Chicago Strand Theatre Speech Excerpts</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp321966</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Mrs. Sanger May Defy Laws Here in Aid of Cause</title>,
					<title type="journal">Chicago Daily Tribune</title>, Apr. 22, 1917, p.
				17.</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="CDT">Chicago Daily Tribune</name>
			<name id="BEMAN">Bemis, Anna</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>Sanger spoke to a women's only meeting in the afternoon and open meeting in the evening
			at <place reg="Chicago, IL">Chicago</place>'s <org>Strand Theatre</org>. She was
			introduced by Anna Bemis at the afternoon meeting. No complete version of her speech has
			been found. </p>
		<index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="class-based"/>
		<index level1="&quot;feeble-minded&quot; persons" level2="allowed to reproduce"/>
		<index level1="abortion" level2="frequency of"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="in Illinois"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Mrs. Sanger May Defy Laws Here in Aid of Cause</head>
		<head type="sub">Predict Women Will Get the Right to Limit Children</head>

		<div>
			<p><q who="CDT">Mrs. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>, high
					priestess of the birth control cult in <place reg="United States"
						>America</place>, yesterday told two audiences at the Strand theater that
					every woman should have the legal right to determine how many babies she would
					bring into the world. She said the rich people now practice birth control, and
					she approved it--not because they were rich but because, she said, woman,
					whether rich or poor, should have </q>“absolute control of her body.” <q
					who="CDT">That, she added was what was coming in the new emancipation of woman
					throughout the world. She did not impart the specific information--as she did in
						<place reg="New York, NY">New York</place> and served a month in jail for
					it--as to how the women of today could regulate such things. She informed her
					audiences, however, that if they would communicate with her at her New York
					address she would see that in some way the desired information got to them.</q>
				“When I was here last year,” she said, “I had 4,000 inquires on the subject of birth
				control. All those inquires were answered.”</p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<head>Officials at Both Meetings</head>
			<p>
				<q who="CDT">Mrs. Sanger spoke to a meeting “for women only” in the afternoon, and
					went much more into detail than at the night meeting, which was a mixed
					gathering, the general public being admitted without regard to sex, color, or
					age. At both meetings representatives of the United States district attorney,
					State’s Attorney <person reg="Hoyne, Maclay">Hoyne</person>, and Chief of Police
						<person reg="Schuettler, Herman F.">Schuettler</person> watched closely for
					infringements of the laws. On several occasions Mrs. Sanger got right up to the
					edge of the narrow line that separated the audience from specific information as
					to how to do all these things. Each time she proceeded cautiously and steered
					away from the danger line with a sort of anti-climax, to the evident regret of
					her audience. Both audiences were made up almost entirely of her followers, in
					which representatives of the laboring classes predominated.</q>
			</p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<head>Wedding Ring for Ticket</head>
			<p><q who="CDT">One woman, according to the ticket seller, left her wedding ring as
					security for a $1.50 ticket after she had told him she was the mother of three
					children but would not get her allowance until today. The ring bore the initials
					“M. I. C.” under date of June 4, ‘16. <person reg="Bemis, Anna">Mrs. Edward
						Bemis</person>, wife of the <person reg="Bemis, Edward">city’s gas
						expert</person>, introduced Mrs. Sanger at both meetings with glowing
					eulogies of the “cause.” Mrs. Sanger has three children and Mrs. Bemis dwelt at
					some length on the “<q who="BENAN">splendid womanly woman and beautiful
						mother</q>” who had the courage to “<q who="BENAN">speak out on this
						subject.</q>” Mrs. Sanger told the women in the afternoon that if they
					deemed it necessary she would defy the <place>Illinois</place> laws, establish a
					birth control clinic in the stockyards district and help test the Illinois
					statutes, which, she said, gave physicians the right to regulate births in
					certain cases, but denied her the right to give the information which would
					prevent the </q>“undesired birth.” <q who="CDT">She spoke for </q>“voluntary
					motherhood,”<q who="CDT"> drawing a clear distinction between birth control, or
					non-conception, and abortion. It was to prevent abortions and the attendant
					ravages, she said, that her scheme had been sent forth the world. </q></p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<head>“Woman Demand Freedom”</head>
			<p>“Women,” she said, “long have been the brunt of unwilling motherhood. They now demand
				the freedom of their bodies. Woman has been, since history began, a mere breeding
				machine for children who fill our hospitals, our insane asylums, our feeble-minded
				institutions, and our prisons. The world is full of undesired babies because of
				ignorance of how to prevent them.</p>
			<p>“There are 250,000 abortions in the United States every year, with 50,000 deaths
				resulting therefrom. Four out of every seven women suffering with tuberculosis die
				because of pregnancy. </p>
			<p>“In Illinois, at your <org reg="Geneva Home for Girls">Geneva home for wayward
					girls</org>, 85 percent of the inmates come from families averaging nine
				children or more, while 50 percent of these are feeble minded. Last year in <place>New York</place>
				10,000 feeble minded girls were living in prostitution. </p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<head>
				<q who="CDT">“Poor Mothers Sufferers”</q>
			</head>
			<p>“The wealthy districts of our large cities yield one-third the number of births the
				poor districts do. The rich woman has the right to say for herself how many children
				she shall bear and, having the information and the means, she can carry out her
				ideas. It’s the poor and ignorant mother who peoples the world with undesired,
				unwanted children.” Mrs. Sanger said she went to jail in New York because she
				refused to promise to respect the law. </p>
			<p>“I would rather take thirty days in the workhouse,” <q who="CDT">she said, </q>“than
				promise to respect such a law when there are 8,000 abortions annually in New York
				state.” </p>
		</div>

	</docBody>
</doc>
