<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-03-05 JK initial tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-13 CH proof tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-26 JK correct tags</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1930-03-17">17 March 1930</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">The Need of Birth
                    Control</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp321982</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Says Birth Control is Quickest Means of
                    Effecting Peace on Earth</title>, <title type="journal"
                    >Madison Capital Times</title>, Mar. 18, 1930, pp. 1 and
                6.</bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="MCT">Madison Capital Times</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><index level1="birth control laws and legislation"
            level2="Comstock Act"/><index
            level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Federal"/><index
            level1="birth control clinics and leagues"/><index
            level1="Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="youth and"/><index
            level1="birth control" level2="rights associated with"/><index
            level1="birth control" level2="socio-economic benefits of"/><index
            level1="birth control" level2="definitions of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="economic benefits and risks of"
            /><index level1="birth control" level2="population and"/><index
            level1="birth control" level2="American opinion on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="and marriage"/>
        <index level1="adolescence"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Says Birth Control is Quickest Means of Effect Peace on
            Earth</head>
        <head type="sub"><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
            Talks to Crowded Hall Monday Night</head>
        <q who="MCT"><p>Birth Control must be the basis for any new social
                order: it is the most immediate step to be taken if we will
                bring peace on earth; and it must take parenthood out of the
                realm of chance. </p>
            <p> A small auburn-haired woman, introduced by Professor <person
                    reg="Ross, Edward Alsworth"> E. A. Ross</person> in a
                crowded Music hall Monday night as one contemporary whose name
                would be familiar to the historian 500 years hence, Mrs.
                Margaret Sanger, summed up her arguments on <title type="speech"
                    >“The Need of Birth Control”</title> with that sweeping
                assertion. </p>
            <p>She drew a picture, familiar to her through 16 years of struggle
                and argument of a minority of 20 millions of intelligent persons
                in the United States carrying the burden of 45,000,000 subnormal
                and mediocre persons; the intelligent limiting their families;
                the subnormal, multiplying unchecked.</p>
        </q>

        <div>
            <head type="sub">U.S. Sees Problem</head>
            <p>“The <place>United Sates</place> government recognizes its
                population problem,” she declared, “Its immigration laws exclude
                the unfit, the illiterate, the disease, the mentally deficient,
                those likely to become a charge on the community, and others. </p>
            <p>“But once in the country they are practically forced by law to
                multiply unchecked,” she declared. </p>
            <p>“It is time for the government to take up its population policy
                so far as controlling its future is concerned. But all we have
                are laws inspired by <person reg="Comstock, Anthony">Anthony
                    Comstock </person>56 years ago.” </p>
            <q who="MCT"><p>She declared that a minority in the United States
                    was limiting its families, that this minority held the best
                    positions, gave its children the best training, and paid the
                    $9,000,000,000 which last year was spent in taxes for
                    charitable institutions and institutions for the car of the
                    others. </p>
                <p>Questioned after the conclusion of her lecture for almost an
                    hour by interested students, faculty members, townspeople,
                    and even one physician, there was no trace of hostility in
                    the crowd. </p></q>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Which is Sin? </head>
            <p><q who="MCT">One voice which questioned,</q>
                <q who="UNK">“What can you say to someone who says that birth
                    control is a sin?” </q><q who="MCT">was answered with,</q>
                “You can ask right back, which is the greater sin, birth control
                of bearing a child for someone else to take care of.”</p>
            <q who="MCT">
                <p> The effect that knowledge of contraceptive methods might
                    have on encouraging promiscuity outside of marriage, Mrs.
                    Sanger declared to be nil and dependent upon the character
                    of the persons involved, in answer to another question.
                    Asked her opinion of compassionate marriage, she declared
                    that the regular institution of marriage has never really
                    been given a chance. </p>
                <p>The danger of applying to any physician for birth control
                    information, because of the possibility of falling in the
                    hands of a quack was little, she declared, because of the
                    possible harm in receiving contraceptive information from a
                    quack was less than that of too frequent pregnancy. </p></q>
        </div>
        <div>
            <div>
                <head type="sub">Men Don’t Know Women</head>
                <p>
                    <q> who="MCT">Declaring that men don’t know women she stated
                        in her main address: </q>“Men have never known women.
                    They have known them as girls and then as mothers. They have
                    made a good deal of motherhood, but nothing of womanhood. A
                    woman can flower and develop after marriage, but only if the
                    fear of pregnancy is removed. A husband has no opportunity
                    to know the bride who returns from the honeymoon pregnant
                    and in an abnormal condition. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head type="sub">Delay Having Children</head>

                <p>“I believe young people should begin to make something more
                    of marriage than the past generation has. They should have
                    at least two years free from the responsibility of
                    parenthood, to adjust themselves, one to the other. The tie
                    between them should be strengthened, it will give our young
                    people that chance to be free from that disturbing influence
                    that pregnancy has on a woman.” </p>
                <p>“It has been a struggle for a man to keep his earning
                    capacity ahead of his reproductive capacity,” she said. </p>
                <p> She pointed out that population can be controlled through
                    increasing the death rate or decreasing the birth rate.</p>
                <p>“We will not let famine and pestilence control population,”
                    she said, “So we must control our birth rate.”</p>
                <q who="MCT">
                    <p>The 83 millions of mediocre and subnormal, she declared,
                        resulted in slums, child labor, ignorance, and misery. </p>
                    <p>The small intelligent group has the small families, but
                        it brings in the largest number of children up to
                        maturity, from that group the best positions are filled,
                        according to Mrs. Sanger.</p></q>
                <p>“Some point to that group as being selected to increase its
                    birth rate,” she said. “But I believe they can not multiply
                    faster until we take the other crowd off their backs.” </p>
                <q who="MCT">
                    <p> She declared that the United States had the largest
                        maternity death rate in the civilized world with 20,000
                        mothers dying each year; and she stated that 200,000
                        infants died before they reach one year of age. </p>
                    <p> She found three conditions controlling the infant death
                        rate: <list>
                            <item>1. The infant rate goes up as the father’s
                                wage goes down. </item>
                            <item> 2. As children are spaced in the families,
                                their chances in life are increased-- three
                                years should separate each child. </item>
                            <item>3. Their place in the family-- the second
                                child has a greater chance to live than the
                                fifth; the fifth than the eighth; and 60 percent
                                of the twelfth children are doomed to die before
                                they take their first breath.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p></q>
                <p>“If we are going to make the world safe for mothers,” she
                    said, “We can not stop at milk stations and humanitarian
                    institutions. We must instruct parents. </p>
                <p> “Anyone can become a parent today,” she claimed. “The
                    insane, the diseased. Laws today permit one to give out
                    birth control information, but they forbid sending
                    information through the mail telling one where to get
                    it.</p>
            </div>


            <div>
                <head type="sub">13,000 Visit Clinic </head>

                <p> “We have had 13,000 women visit our <org
                        reg="Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau">birth
                        control clinic</org> in <place reg="New York">New York
                    </place>during the past four years. Of that number, 33
                    percent were Protestant; 32 percent, Catholic; and 31
                    percent, Jewish.” “In spite of the law of the church, the
                    Catholic women come to us.”</p>
                <q who="MCT">
                    <p>She outlined three means of control: <list>
                            <item>1. Continence. “We have no quarrel with this
                                method,” she said. “However our neurologists and
                                psychologist may quarrel with it.”</item>
                            <item> 2. Sterilization. It has already become a
                                part of the work of the state to prevent
                                defectives from having progeny, she said. </item>
                            <item> 3. Contraceptives.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p> According to Mrs. Sanger the last method is the only one
                        which arouses any opposition. She said persons with
                        transmissible diseases should not be parents, and should
                        be sterilized mothers with communicable diseases should
                        be thoroughly cured before attempting to bear children;
                        and normal parents who have already had several
                        subnormal children should have no more children. </p>
                    <p> Normal parents should allow a three year interval
                        between children, one year for the mother to care for
                        the infant; one year for her to enjoy life; and one year
                        to prepare for the coming of the next child. </p>
                    <p>Adolescents may marry, according to Mrs. Sanger, but they
                        should not have children until the girl reaches 22 and
                        the man 25. </p></q>
            </div>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
