<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/03/14 YG</prepDate><prepDate>2014-04-04 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1922-02-27">27 Feb 1922</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Honolulu Speech</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp321968</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Keynote of Social Awakening Is Economically Expedient the Message of Mrs. Sanger</title>
                <title type="journal">Unidentified newspaper</title>, Feb 27
                1922</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="UI">unidentified newspaper</name>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"> En route to <place>Japan</place>, <person
            reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person> stopped in
            <place>Hawaii</place> and gave this speech at the <org>M. Lester
            Dancing academy</org>to several hundred men and women. <person
            reg="Dole, Sanford Ballard">Judge Sanford B. Dole</person>introduced
        her. <index level1="birth control" level2="socio-economic benefits of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits and risks"/>
        <index level1="eugenics" level2="birth control and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Keynote of Social Awakening Is Economically Expedient the Message
            of Mrs. Sanger</head>
        <p>"Birth control is the keynote of a new social awakening - it is not
            only economically expedient but socially so," <q who="UI">said Mrs.
                Sanger yesterday in her address before several hundred men and
                women at the M. Lester Dancing academy.</q></p>
        <p><q who="UI">The speaker was introducted by Judge Sanford B. Dole who
                said that when people opppose birth control, their opposition is
                due partly to ignorance, and partly to the fact that people
                think of quantity, not quality. He also said that the greatest
                asset a family can have is promising children, while a great
                misfortune are children with ill health and weak minds.</q></p>
        <p>"The idea of birth control is as old as nature istelf-in fact nature
            has been and is today the most ruthless advocate of the movement.
            Our methods of birth control are fairly new and modern and those
            known today have been used for about 50 years," <q who="UI">said
                Mrs. Sanger</q>.</p>
        <p>"Nature's method is that of killing off the unfit, and in this way
            has kept the population within the means of subsistence, and she has
            weeded out those unable to compete in life. Nature has by this
            method perfected types.</p>
        <p>"Nature realized that something had to be done to keep the population
            down. In all countries where they do not allow nature to take its
            course you find the population question one of great importance.</p>
        <p>"When you look out on life today, in every country of the world you
            find two groups of people. On the first hand there is the small
            family group made up of men and women who have gone into marriage
            with understanding and have lmited the numbers of their family
            according to the health and financial status of the parents. In the
            great majority of cases you find the children of these families
            brought to full adult life with all the advantages of education.
            This group sends their children to the colleges and give their
            offspring the best condition society has to offer."</p>
        <p>"It is not in this group that we find our problem of today, but if we
            urged them to have larger families they would slide down a
            grade."</p>
        <p>"The other group has perpetuated itself for generations. Mothers have
            children more often than they can endure to bear them. You find that
            they are kept in ignorance and the father who is only able to
            support two children finds himself a family of 10 or 12. In this
            group you find infant mortality and maternal mortality prevalent,
            and you find there every problem the first group is trying to
            solve.</p>
        <p>"Our intelligence is unable to cope with the chaotic condition this
            group has caused. We do everything we can to stop their misery but
            do nothing to stop their multiplication.</p>
        <p>"In the <place>United States</place>infant mortality numbers 300,000 yearly and the
            majority of these die before they have reached one year of age: they
            die from poverty and neglect, and still we allow 600,000 parents to
            remain in ignorance of how to prevent more children from coming into
            the world.</p>
        <p>"Instead of helping these parents not to have any more children we
            encourage their perpetuation.</p>
        <p>"When we take mortality of mothers into consideration we find the
            condition disgraceful. Many of these mothers pass out of life from
            preventable causes.</p>
        <p>"Then we turn from the tuberculosis question and we find women
            suffering from heart trouble, kidney trouble and other diseases and
            it is a crime to allow these women to become mothers. Some of the
            ideas people of today have are like the old quacks who claimed they
            could cure cancer by burning off the top - so our charities and
            welfare organizations are only patching up.</p>
        <p>"Parenthood is an international business and it should be made a
            privilege not an accident."</p>
        <p><q who="UI">In many states objection has been raised towards birth
                control, but Mrs. Sanger said yesterday that she has never known
                an argument which could hold against birth control.</q></p>
        <p>"There are a number of objections made against birth control; for
            instance people always say every new thing is against the laws of
            <name type="deity">God</name>. I will not argue the religious question - if you believe that
            your conduct is in accordance with the law of your God you must
            decide the question, but I believe that it is in accord with the law
            of God to bring creation to a normal condition.</p>
        <p>"Another objection raised is that birth control is against the laws
            of nature. To this we must partly plead guilty and yet almost
            everything else we do is contrary to nature's laws.</p>
        <p>"Many fine things we do are against the laws of nature - civilization
            means controlling nature for man's highest use.</p>
        <p>"Then some people claim it is going to cause race suicide - that if
            women knew how to control birth there would be no children at all.
            But I believe that the maternal instinct is one of the deepest
            things in women, and I do not think that instinct will be thwarted
            because of knowledge.</p>
        <p/>
    </docBody>
</doc>
