<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014/04/11 VS initial tagging</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-23 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1928-09-28">28 Sept 1928</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>Birth Control Advocated to Decrease Maternal Mortality</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp321991</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>
				<title>Montana Standard</title>, Sept. 28, 1928, p. 4. </bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">A short biographical introduction of Sanger was omitted. <index
			level1="birth control" level2="health benefits and risks"/>
		<index level1="birth control movement" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="mortality rates" level2="infant"/>
		<index level1="mortality rates" level2="maternal"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Birth Control Advocated to Decrease Maternal Mortality</head>
		<byline>By Mrs. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>, Founder
				<org>American Birth Control League</org></byline>
		<p> Statistics on the subject of maternal mortality are of doubtful value, but the record
			shows that, in 1925, 647 mothers died of every 100,000 live births. </p>
		<p> Work to lower the death rate of mothers in child birth has been ineffective in the last
			10 years, and I have advocated proper birth control as the solution of the problem. </p>
		<p> In 1926 656 mothers in every 100,000 gave their lives. Since then there has been no
			decline in these figures, which include only about 76 percent of the total population of
			the United States. </p>
		<p> I have been interested in this problem since 1914, and it was my interest in this
			particular aspect of the situation that led to the beginning of a birth-control
			movement. I feel now that the time has come when I can turn over to others the
			organization, legislative and educational features of active birth-control work. </p>
		<p> As I have long wished to do, I will devote myself to a scientific study of the causes
			and cures of this terrific sacrifice of the lives of child-bearing women. I feel
			confident that a serious study will lead to a scientific demonstration of the fact that
			maternal mortality can be reduced by the application of birth-control knowledge. </p>
		<p> Infant mortality in the <place>United States</place> been appreciably lowered in the
			last 10 years, but nothing of consequence has been accomplished in lowering the death
			rate of mothers. </p>
		<p> I am preparing to spend a period of from three to five years in that collection of
			material, in sociological investigation and in gathering facts generally pertinent to
			the situation. In this work I will have the aid and co-operation of some of the foremost
			authorities in the world. </p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
