<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/07/07 NC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>CH 7/22/2011 correction</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011-11-21 CH correct typo</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-30 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1947-00-00">1947</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Birth Control</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp321953</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="book">Grolier Encyclopedia</title> (New York, Grolier Society, 1947),
                p. 198</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="PLAFR">Place, Francis</name>
            <name id="CSCPAP">Committee to Study Contraceptive Practices and Allied Problems</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>For typed draft see Library of Congress Microfilm 129:32B</p>
        <index level1="birth control"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="New York "/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="legal cases"
            level3="U.S. v. One Package of Japanese contraceptives"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="American"/>
        <index level1="Birth Control Review, The"/>
        <index level1="Birth Control Federation of America"/>
        <index level1="physicians" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="Woman Rebel" level2="articles in "/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Birth Control</head>
        <p>A movement to limit the number of offspring in the family. It dates back to <person
                reg="Malthus, Thomas Robert">Thomas Malthus</person>, an English clergyman, who in his
            essay on population in 1798 advocated population control through moral restraint as a
            social method. A neo-Malthusian, <person reg="Place, Francis">Francis Place</person>, in
            his <title type="book">Illustrations and Proofs of the Principle of Population</title>, 1822, new
            ed., 1930, held that moral restraint is not enough and advocated "<q who="PLAFR"
                >preventives</q>." <person reg="Carlile, Richard">Richard Carlile</person> in
                <place>England</place> published his <title type="book">Every Woman's Book</title>, 1826, the
            first book in English exclusively on contraception, both in theory and in practice.
                <person reg="Owen, Robert Dale">Robert Dale Owen</person> in 1831 published his
                <title type="book">Moral Physiology</title> which advocated and described methods of
            contraception, but the first publication by an American physician was <title>The Fruits
                of Philosophy</title> by <person reg="Knowlton, Charles L.">Charles L.
                Knowlton</person>, 1832, new ed., 1937. Forty years later the <org
                reg="Malthusian League">Neo-Malthusian League of England</org> was started as a
            purely educational movement.</p>
        <p>In 1914 the words "birth control" came into use, when <person reg="Sanger, Margaret"
                >Margaret Sanger</person>, a trained nurse, aroused to the need for information of
            contraceptive methods among the poor with whom she worked, began a national campaign of
            education, agitation, and organization. Publication of an article on "<title type="article">The
                Prevention of Conception</title>" in the monthly magazine, <title type="journal">The Woman
                Rebel</title>, which she sponsored, led to her indictment under federal law. The
            indictment was dropped in 1916 and that year Mrs. Sanger and her sister <person
                reg="Byrne, Ethel Higgins">Ethel Byrne</person>, another trained nurse, opened the first
            control clinic in <place reg="United States">America</place>, in one of the poorest
            sections of <place reg="Brooklyn, NY">Brooklyn</place>.</p>
        <p>They were both arrested and served workhouse terms for "maintaining a public nuisance."
            The case was appealed and a decision handed down by the <org>Appellate Division of the
                New York State Supreme Court</org> in 1918 established the legal right of physicians
            in the state to advise on contraception "for the cure or prevention of disease"-a great
            legal victory.</p>
        <p>The <title rend="italics" type="journal">Birth Control Review</title> began publication in 1917 and was
            issued until 1940.Continuous organization resulted in the formation of the <org>American
                Birth Control League</org> in 1921, and of numerous state and local organizations
            later. Interest in the movement was widespread. Magazines, pamphlets, literature
            covering all angles of the problems, and lectures were effective as propaganda, and
            newspaper publicity which accompanied efforts to stop the movement by interference with
            the constitutional right of free speech, or by arrests of prominent people, all gave
            great impetus to the cause and advertised its theories.</p>
        <p>A second national organization, The <org>Voluntary Parenthood League</org>, was formed in
            1919, and attempted to change the Federal laws on contraception, but has been inactive
            of recent years.</p>
        <p>In 1923 the <org>Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau</org> was opened in <place
                reg="New York, NY">New York</place> by Mrs. Sanger, with a woman <person
                reg="Stone, Hannah Mayer">physician</person> as clinician. The growth of clinics
            continued and in June, 1942, they totaled 805, covering all but four states and
            extending into <place>Alaska</place>, <place>Hawaii</place>, <place>Puerto Rico</place>,
            and the <place>Virgin Islands</place>--with 225 in hospitals, 262 in health department
            quarters, and 352 supported wholly or in part by public funds. Three states, <place
                reg="North Carolina">North</place> and <place>South Carolina</place> and
                <place>Alabama</place> had included child spacing in the programs of their state
            departments of health by 1941.</p>
        <p>Support for the movement through endorsement of over 1000 organizations, largely the
            result of the work of the <org>National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth
                Control</org>, organized by Mrs. Sanger in 1929, resulted in action. Every poll of
            public opinion has shown a favorable majority. National and international converences
            have accentuated the growth of the movement. Action of the <org>American Medical
                Association</org>, through its <org>Committee to Study Contraceptive Practices and
                Allied Problems</org> in 1937, which accepted birth control as "<q who="CSCPAP"
                >desirable for the health and well-being of mothers and children</q>" and
            recommended that the <org reg="American Medical Association">A.M.A.</org> promote
            instruction in contraception in the medical schools, was a great step forward. This
            followed the decision of the <org>United States Circuit Court of appeals for the Second
                Circuit</org> in the case of <title>U.S. vs. One Package</title>, which stated that
            the design of the section of the Federal law, on which the suit was based, was "not to
            prevent the importation, sale, or carriage by mail of things which might intelligently
            be employed by conscientious and competent physicians for the purpose of saving life or
            promoting the well-being of their patients."</p>
        <p>In 1939 <org>Birth Control Federation of America, Inc.</org>, was formed by a merger of
            the American Birth Control Leage and the Birth Control Clinical Research Burea, and in
            1942 the organization, at its annual meeting changed its name to the <org>Planned
                Parenthood Federation of America, Inc.</org>, as more expressive of its aims and
            purposes. These had grown to include treatment for infertility and education for
            marriage and parenthood. An increasing number of local planned parenthood organizations
            were offering expert medical help to childless couples who desire children, or were able
            to refer these couples to hospitals and private physicians for diagnosis and
            treatment.</p>
        <p>The first post-war international sex conference was held in <place
                reg="Stockholm, Sweden">Stockholm</place> in August, 1946, with the United States
            among the countries which were represented unofficially to discus the problems raised by
            the crowded populations of the world. Resolutions endorsing planned parenthood
            objectives in strong terms were adopted.</p>
        <byline>MARGARET SANGER</byline>
    </docBody>
</doc>
