<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2009/03/30 CH Initial tag/transcribe</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-04-08 CH clean regs</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-18 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1922-07-13">13 July 1922</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Speech to the Fifth International Neo-Malthusian and Birth
					Control Conference</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp400080</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><person reg="Pierpont, Raymond">Raymond Pierpont</person>, ed. <title type="book"
					>Report of the <org
						reg="International Neo-Malthusian and Birth Control Conference, 5th">Fifth
						International Neo-Malthusian and Birth Control Conference</org>,
						<org>Kingsway Hall</org>, <place reg="London, England">London</place>, July
					11 to 14, 1922.</title> (<org>W. Heinemen</org>, London: 1922), 198-206.</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name/>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>Margaret Sanger gave this speech as part of a public meeting held in concert with the
			Fifth International Neo-Malthisian and Birth Control Conference, at Kingsway Hall.
				<person reg="Wells, H. G.">H.G. Wells</person> was the chairman of the meeting;
			other speakers were: <person reg="Cox, Harold">Harold Cox</person>, <person
				reg="Drysdale, Bessie Ingham">Bessie Ingham Drysdale</person>, <person
				reg="Millard, C. Killick">C. Killick Millard</person>, <person
				reg="Swanwick, Helena Marie">Helena Marie Swanwick</person>, and Rev. <person
				reg="Lang, Gordon">Gordon Lang</person>.</p>
		<index level1="Asia" level2="birth control in"/>
		<index level1="Japan" level2="political situation"/>
		<index level1="Japan" level2="population policies"/>
		<index level1="Japan" level2="birth control in"/>
		<index level1="Germany" level2="population policies"/>
		<index level1="Japan" level2="liberals in"/>
		<index level1="Sanger, Margaret " level2="speaking tours" level3="1922 (Japan)"/>
		<index level1="Sanger, Margaret " level2="speaking tours" level3="1922 (Korea)"/>
		<index level1="Sanger, Margaret " level2="speaking tours" level3="1922 (China)"/>
		<index level1="conferences"
			level2="International Neo-Malthusian and Birth Control Conference" level3="1922 (5th)"/>
		<index level1="censorship" level2="in Japan"/>
		<index level1="Japan" level2="birth control leagues and clinics"/>
		<index level1="China" level2="birth control leagues and clinics"/>
		<index level1="China" level2="birth control in"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<p>Mrs. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person> (President, <org>American
				Birth Control League</org>): Mr. Chairman, Ladies and Gentlemen, all of us, in
			advocating the national and international practice of Birth Control, have met arguments
			from our opponents, and even from our friends, that Birth Control would never be
			accepted by Oriental peoples. There have been articles in magazines, even books have
			been written, in which the most pessimistic views were brought forward, to show us that
			our whole civilisation was in danger of being wiped out because the white people were
			not increasing their population as rapidly as the yellow and colored races.</p>
		<p> I am pleased to say, from my brief experience, that I can repudiate at least part of
			that statement. Whether or not the white races will be ultimately wiped off the face of
			the earth depends, to my mind, largely upon the conduct and behaviour of the white
			people themselves. (Applause.) But that the people of <place>China</place>,
				<place>Japan</place>, <place>Korea</place> and <place>India</place> desire Birth
			Control knowledge, that they may reduce the numbers of their families, and that they may
			also give the women health and freedom, I am quite convinced. </p>
		<p>Before I go into the experiences I met with in Japan and China, I would like to tell you
			a little something of the problem that confronts Japan to-day. Japan has a population of
			about 57 millions. She has an area of about 150,000 square miles. Now if all of this
			land were tillable perhaps there would be less excuse for Japan's attitude than there is
			today. When we look through that little country we find that five-sixths of Japan proper
			is mountainous, and that her huge population must live upon one-sixth of her
			territory.</p>
		<p> This means that Japan is thrown upon the outside world for her foodstuffs, and must
			depend upon other countries for subsistence for her population. For more than two
			centuries Japan's population was practically stationary, but within the last sixty-five
			years her population has practically doubled. For instance, in 1621 she had 25 millions
			; in 1721 she had still 25 millions. In 1774 she had 25.9 millions, in 1804 she had 25.4
			millions, and in 1846 she had 26 millions. But in 1920 she had, as I have said, 57
			millions.</p>
		<p>The birth rate in Japan averages 1 millions a year. The death rate is enormous, but even
			so her survival rate is between 700,000 and 800,000 souls a year. Naturally, with this
			problem and with this increase, Japan must ask the world what she is to do. She may be
			able today to take care of her population, but she is looking ahead, and she says to the
			world: "What is to become of us and all our increasing numbers in twenty or twenty-five
			years?" </p>
		<p>In some ways today Japan is in much the same condition as <place>Germany</place> was in
			1910. I will not go ino detail to show you how much alike they are in their industrial,
			commercial, and even moral and spiritual development. More than 90 per cent, of the
			Japanese people are considered literate. They can read and write. There is a strong
			development along industrial lines, and, in fact, Japan to-day is experiencing with her
			people very much the same difficulty that Germany developed and had to face up to 1914,
			the year of the outbreak of war. Germany found herself with highly skilled artisans and
			men who were civil engineers, chemists, and others of that sort of ability. Japan finds
			herself to-day with more technical men--men of fine technical ability--in her population
			than she herself can use.</p>
		<p>Now, while Germany had the whole world for her people to develop in--the doors of the
			world were open to those efficient men and women--that is not the case with Japan. Most
			of the world is closed today to the skilled artisan of Japan, so, naturally, Japan has a
			very unusual problem, and one that not only concerns herself, but concerns every other
			nation in the world.</p>
		<p>Now that is something of the condition of affairs that I found when I was invited to go
			to Japan. We, many of us, have had the erroneous idea that Japan was strongly
			militaristic, but I want to say that more than 70 per cent, of the people of Japan are
			not militaristic. It is safe to say that there is that number of young men and women in
			Japan who are strongly inclined towards Liberalism, and who are opposing the military
			party most violently.</p>
		<p>I found that this Young Liberal group had been interested in Western customs and Western
			civilization, and the members of the Government who are in this Liberal group had been
			sending round the world a number of men to ascertain the facts of our everyday life and
			the movements that were going on, and the progress that we were making in the Western
			world. While some of these young men were coming to <place reg="United States"
				>America</place>, they came upon our propaganda of Birth Control and seemed to be
			very much interested in this great movement. Within one year's time we had more than
			twenty-five representatives from Japan, who came to study the subject of Birth
			Control.</p>
		<p>After that I was invited by a group of Liberals, who call themselves the "<org
				reg="Kaizo">Kaisha</org>" group, to go to Japan and to give four lectures on war and
			population. Now this young group represents the Liberal group in Japan. They have
			already planned a series of lectures, mostly of philosophic character. Mr. <person
				reg="Russell, Bertrand">Bertrand Russell</person> had gone before me. I was next on
			the programme. <person reg="Einstein, Albert">Einstein</person> was the next and, I
			believe, although he does not know it, Mr. <person reg="Wells, H. G.">Wells</person> is
			to be invited to complete the series.</p>
		<p>Plans had already been made for me to go to Japan, and I had purchased or rather engaged
			my passage when, to my surprise, on arriving at <place reg="San Francisco, California"
				>San Francisco</place>, when I applied for the visa at the Japanese Consulate, I was
			told that the <org reg="Japan, Government of">Government of Japan</org>--the Home
			Office--had sent a cable to the Consul-General that if I applied for a visa it was to be
			refused, as they did not want the subject of Birth Control to be discussed in Japan.
			That was rather surprising to me, inasmuch as the plans had been made for my work there.
			However, I felt that it was very necessary for me to meet some of the Japanese,
			especially those intellectual men who were going back from the <org
				reg="Washington Naval Conference">Washington Conference</org> after representing
			their Government. So I was able to get on the steamboat and get my ticket for <place
				reg="Shanghai, China">Shanghai</place>. I had no difficulty in getting a visa from
			the Chinese officials on the steamboat, and I had the great pleasure of the opportunity
			of meeting many of the delegates returning from the Washington Conference. <person
				reg="Kato, Tomosaburo">Admiral Cutto</person> was on board and also one of their
			Ministers. I was there only a few days when, with their usual alertness, they asked me
			if I would speak to the delegates, about 150 in number. I did so with pleasure, and the
			result was that their Minister cabled to his Government, urging them, not only to let in
			the advocate of Birth Control, but also to open the doors wide to the free discussion of
			that subject for Japan's own good. The interest that was shown by the Japanese on board,
			not only in the first, but second class, was simply tremendous. There was great
			interest, and great help was given to me, even great resentment was expressed towards
			the Government that such a furore had been made, and that a ban had been put upon any
			one entering the country with so vital a message.</p>
		<p>When we arrived at <place reg="Yokohama, Japan">Yokohama</place> I was told by a member
			of the Japanese Government that there was more interest in the subject of Birth Control
			than there was in the returning delegates from <place reg="Washington, DC"
				>Washington</place>. More than sixty-five members of the Press applied for
			permission to meet the boat, and in making their application they said their object was
			to meet us and discuss the subject of Birth Control. If any of you have been to Japan
			you know what a passion they have for photographs and flashlights. It is said that more
			than 150 flash-light photographs were taken of me and my son while we were touring
			through Japan. It is almost a madness with them to have pictures of everything you do in
			practically every position that you take up. This, of course, gave us a great deal of
			publicity, for the whole country was aroused to the discussion, and the scientific
			discussion, of the subject. </p>
		<p>There were meetings with the members of the <org reg="New Woman Association">new women's
				organisation</org>, and it was quite remarkable how all those women came to express
			sympathy and interest in the subject of Birth Control, and to express to me their desire
			for knowledge whereby they could be emancipated from maternal slavery. Representatives
			from the Medical Association were also present and representatives of Labour. In fact,
			all the progressive, intellectual world of Japan was interested in this subject of Birth
			Control. It would be impossible to go into the detail of all the interesting experiences
			that both my son and I had. One of the interesting things to me was that <person
				reg="Sanger, Grant">my son</person>, who was only thirteen years old, seemed to
			receive all the attention from the time we entered Japan until we left. Chairs were
			pulled out for the male member of the family, but I was left to pull out the chairs for
			myself. There was great respect and deference shown to this youngster, but altogether I
			think they had a considerable respect for me, not only in Japan, but in China and Korea,
			from the fact that I was able to produce a son.</p>
		<p>My entrance into Japan, as I have said, came through one of the members of the Young
			Liberal group in Japan, and I want to point out that if the difficulty to which I have
			referred had occurred fifty years ago I should never have been allowed to enter Japan.
			If the Government had said " You will not enter," that would have been the end of it.
			To-day the Government is not so firm in its opposition to liberty. As soon as the
			Government said " You cannot come into Japan," the Young Liberals started to make a
			noise, and to protest and to ask why. Then the Government moved down a step or two, and
			said " She may come in, but she must not speak." More noise, more protests from the
			Liberal group, and then the Government moved down another step, and said " She may
			speak, but not in public." More noise, more protests, and the Government stepped down
			again, and said " She may speak in public, but she must not give the methods of Birth
			Control." On that we all agreed. I had no intention of giving the methods of Birth
			Control to a promiscuous audience; I simply wanted to speak on the theory of the
			subject, and the practical side would have been given in private.</p>
		<p>So, after my arrival, I wanted to ascertain from the <org reg="Japan, Home Office">Home
				Office</org> why I was barred from Japan. It is very important for a propagandist to
			see to it that she is never barred out from any place. It is a very bad precedent for
			your work. So I went to call on the <person reg="Oka, Kischichiro">Chief of
				Police</person>, who seemed to have been the instigator of the difficulty. They
			speak a good deal of "Mysterious Japan," and I think that in many cases one would
			naturally believe that there was a great mystery about Japanese life. I had no idea, up
			to half an hour before I decided to go to the police station, that I was to go there. I
			simply made up my mind that I would call upon the Chief of Police and I told no one,
			except Baron <person reg="Ishimoto, Keikichi">Ishimoto</person>, who was escorting me.
			Nevertheless, on my arrival, every one knew we were coming. Tea was served, and it is
			very difficult to be indignant with a Police Department when they serve you tea first.
			The photographers were there ahead of us, and in every way we were received with great
			courtesy, and given great attention. The Chief of Police himself was not there, but his
			Assistant was, and he explained to me that one of the reasons why I was not allowed to
			speak was that my subject would come under a Bill then pending, which was called "<name
				type="law">The Dangerous Thought Bill</name>." When I asked if they would explain
			what that meant, they said there was a Bill pending in the House forbidding any
			foreigner to come to Japan and bring a "dangerous thought." I am glad to say that Bill
			was "tabled" a few weeks later, again because of the young and rising Liberal Group in
			Japan, who made fun of this "Dangerous Thought Bill," so that it was shelved. That was
			one of the reasons.</p>
		<p>But, finally, our meetings were allowed to go on, and if the <org
				reg="Yokohama Police Department">Police Department</org> had been a real friend
			instead of a bitter enemy and opponent, it could not have done more for the cause of
			Birth Control than it did in its opposition to us, for the whole Press was aflame. It is
			said that out of 105 magazines that came out in April, eighty-eight carried articles on
			the subject of Population and Birth Control. Every day the papers for the whole of the
			weeks I was there carried scientific articles as well as propaganda articles on the
			subject.</p>
		<p> We were able in this time to give ten lectures in <place reg="Tokyo, Japan"
				>Tokio</place>, and if it had not been for illness I think I should have been there
			for the next two years, because the invitations and letters that came in asking for
			addresses and lectures made us turn the whole business organisation into an office to
			answer them. However, we were able to give ten lectures in Tokio and fifteen lectures
			throughout Japan, and in all except one of those lectures we were able to discuss the
			methods of Birth Control quite freely. This was done in small groups of from 150 to 200.
			They were divided into commercial groups, labour groups, industrial groups, and the
			physicians of the Women's Organisation, and they did this very efficiently and to my
			satisfaction, because I prefer speaking to small audiences when it comes to the
			practical side rather than to large promiscuous audiences. </p>
		<p>Finally, a League was formed--the first <org reg="Japan Birth Control League">Birth
				Control League in Japan</org>. Since then I find that this little League has brought
			out a <title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title>, a monthly magazine in the
			Japanese language. They published, and have been publishing, the pamphlet "<title
				type="book">Family Limitation</title>," which gives the practical methods, and they
			have, in the past two years, been giving out this pamphlet to the number of 10,000, so
			that there is already a great deal of dissemination of the practical side of the
			subject.</p>
		<p>One of the interesting things to me was the keen mind which the Japanese statesmen bring
			to bear on this subject. They do not intend to duplicate our errors. They do not intend
			that the birth rate and the increase of population shall be among the unfit and the
			diseased. They intend to direct the force of their organisation and of this movement
			against anything in that direction. This organisation has for its president a <person
				reg="Unknown">sociologist</person>, a <person reg="Abe, Isoo">professor in one of
				the universities</person>, and also a <person reg="Unknown">member of the medical
				profession</person>. They have also a <person reg="Unknown">Labour leader</person>
			and a very- well known <person reg="Unknown">social worker</person>, so that all
			branches of their social and intellectual life are represented in the Birth Control
			League.</p>
		<p>I think it is safe to say that Japan is keenly alive to the subject of Birth Control.
			Just how long this will last none of us can predict, but if we were able to send our
			missionaries there as the Church has done, I think we should go a very long way towards
			bringing real Christianity and humanitarianism and international peace into the entire
			world.</p>
		<p>I was rather pleased to find in the arguments against Birth Control in China and Japan
			something besides the moral argument. Not once was that argument used. They brought
			forth arguments based upon science and sociology--arguments it was a pleasure to refute
			and to argue about.</p>
		<p>From Japan I went to Korea, and though my time was limited I was able to give an address,
			and again the Press was very generous in its statements and in giving out the means of
			Birth Control to the people. There again, there were many requests for addresses from
			the Koreans themselves and promises that an organisation would be established there in
			the very near future.</p>
		<p>Then we went to China, where we had not at first intended to go, as my original plan was
			only to go to Japan and return home. The interest in China was just as great. I was able
			to speak to 2,500 young students at the <org>National University</org>. The <person
				reg="Unknown">Chancellor</person> himself and the Professors of the University
			formed the first <org>Birth Control League of China</org>. There also they got busy at
			once. This group met after dinner and organised the League. They took the practical
			leaflet "<title type="bookj">Family Limitation</title>," translated it that night into
			Chinese, and it was on the press next morning ready for printing. Five thousand of these
			pamphlets were distributed later on in a few days, so that China took practically at
			once to the subject, and especially to the practical side of it. They were, when I left
				<place reg="Beijing, China">Pekin</place>, looking for a physician to open a clinic,
			especially in their poor sections, for the women. The <org>Rockefeller Institute</org>,
			especially the nurses, were very keen on knowing something of the practical methods, and
			they got up a meeting which I had the pleasure of addressing, and we were able to
			discuss the practical side of carrying on the work in China.</p>
		<p>In Shanghai it was very interesting, although there was not the same interest shown,
			perhaps, in the groups I was able to speak before. There was one group, however, the
				<org>Family Reformation Society</org>, which has for its rules that you cannot
			smoke, you cannot drink, and you cannot gamble. My suggestion to them was that you
			should not have children you cannot support and take care of. </p>
		<p>The <org reg="Commercial Press">commercial Press</org> of Shanghai was most generous in
			its propaganda. For one whole week they brought out scientific articles. They translated
			practically everything they could put their hands on. For one whole week while I was in
			Shanghai, the Chinese Press was aflame with the subject of Birth Control.</p>
		<p>That is just briefly an outline of the experiences and the interest shown in my brief and
			hurried trip to the Orient. I think we all know that this movement is, perhaps, slow in
			development. None of us, possibly, will really see the results of its success. We know
			that the Crucifixion took place 180 years before Christianity was established, or rather
			started, in the <org>Roman Empire</org>. We know that the <place>New World</place> was
			discovered 150 years before the first English colony was established there. None of
			those who see the beginning of these historical movements can realise and grasp their
			full significance, and I think it is safe to say that none of us will probably realise
			or live to see this movement in its fullest culmination, but I think it is safe to
			say--and we claim it--that if Birth Control is accepted by the Eastern nations, it will
			hasten very greatly our progress towards international peace and human emancipation.</p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
