<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2001-11-13 MH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2002-08-15 KH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2003/08/08 CH corrections</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/19 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007-05-30 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-05 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1914-04-00">Apr 1914</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Humble Pie</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp420055</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">The Woman Rebel</title>, Apr. 1914 , 9</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> C16:0523</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Comstock Laws"/>
        <index level1="censorship"/>
        <index level1="family size"/>
        <index level1="Woman Rebel, The"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>HUMBLE PIE</head>
        <p>The <person reg="Morgan, Edward M.">Postmaster</person> did not like the first number of
            the <title type="journal">WOMAN REBEL</title>. He even took the trouble to tell the
                <title type="journal">WOMAN REBEL</title> so. He advised her not to send any more
            copies through the <place>United States</place> mails. He said the <title type="journal"
                >WOMAN REBEL</title> was unmailable under <name type="law"><rs
                    reg="United States Criminal Code, Section 211">Section 211 of the Criminal
                    Code</rs></name>, as amended by the act of March 4, 1911. Of course the
            Postmaster was acting within his rights. He is empowered by the federal government to
            stop the circulation of any printed expression of honest convictions. It is a crime to
            have honest convictions in these United States. It is a crime to express them publicly.
            It is a crime to send them through the mails. Therefore the <title type="journal">WOMAN
                REBEL</title> has not yet been informed which of her views were so displeasing to
            the Postmaster, but whatever they were, she hastens to agree with the Postmaster that
            she was absolutely mistaken in these views. She realizes that the <org
                reg="United States Post Office">Postoffice</org> is always "right," since it has the
            monopolized POWER to enforce that "right." Therefore the <title type="journal">WOMAN
                REBEL</title>, humbled and repentant, curtseys coyly to the Postmaster and
            apologizes for the expression of any opinion that is unmailable under Section 211 of the
            Criminal Code as amended by the act of March 4, 1911.</p>
        <p>The <title type="journal">WOMAN REBEL</title> has decided to be patriotic. It pays, you
            know. If, last month, the <title type="journal">WOMAN REBEL</title> suggested "race
            control" the daily papers discreetly expressed the problem, this month she switches over
            for large families, like <person reg="Roosevelt, Theodore">Mr. Roosevelt</person>. This
            great and glorious country needs children--to uphold its great and glorious industrial
            system, its great and glorious public schools, its great and glorious silk mills and
            mush factories, its great and glorious, its magnificently equipped, and efficiently
            conducted asylums for the insane and feeble-minded, its reformatories and juvenile
            courts, its noble slums. Let us sing "<title type="song">My Country, Tis of
            Thee</title>!" And "<title type="song">My Country Tis of Thee</title>" is mailable under
            Section 211 of the Criminal Code as amended by the act of March 4, 1911.</p>
        <p>In order to comply with the rules and regulations of the government, the <title
                type="journal">WOMAN REBEL</title> may be forced to become indecent and to advocate
            a total ignorance of Sexual Hygiene for woman. As the purpose of the <title
                type="journal">WOMAN REBEL</title> is to stimulate her readers <emph rend="bold">to
                think for themselves</emph>, and to act according to their own convictions, let them
            be not surprised or dismayed at her mildness and meekness this month. Mildness and
            meekness, the attributes of a feeble mentality, are mailable according to Section 211 of
            the Criminal Code as amended by the act of March 4, 1911. This suppression may not be as
            important to you as to us, for you are not suppressed. Do not forget that you have a
            voice to protest and fight against a censorship that is busy suppressing scientific
            truths that the working people are demanding.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
