<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2001-11-05 MH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2002-08-27 KH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/03/10 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/26 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007-05-30 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-05 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1914-03-00">Mar 1914</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>
                <supplied>Short Pieces from the March 1914 "The Woman Rebel"</supplied>
            </titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp420071</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">The Woman Rebel</title>, Vol. 1, No. 1, Mar. 1914, 8</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Collected Documents Series</title> C16:0522</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
        <index level1="women" level2="freedom and rights of"/>
        <index level1="working class" level2="women and girls"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <div type="section">
            <head>PAST AND PRESENT</head>
            <p>On another page of this paper space will be devoted to the actions and views of the
                women of all ages in all walks of life who have rebelled against oppression and who
                have fought for their individual freedom and the emancipation of their sex.</p>
            <p>It will be my pleasure to resurrect their deeds or words and herald them forth for
                the woman of to-day as examples of women who dared to speak and act in times and
                under circumstances compared to which even the most outspoken women of to-day seems
                quite mild.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head>GUSSIE MILLER</head>
            <p>A striking comparison of the spirit of a working woman and that of our middle class
                curiosity seekers was vividly shown at the time of the arrest of the 190
                unemployed.</p>
            <p><person reg="Miller, Gussie">Gussie Miller</person>, a working girl interested in the
                unemployed because she belonged to them--to their class--refused to be left out of
                the wholesale arrests for the reason she was a woman. She insisted that if her
                fellow workers were to be arrested because they were hungry and wanted shelter--she
                being in the same condition--must share their fate.</p>
            <p>Another woman--a well know suffragist, also in the church at the same time--was
                careful to avoid being classed with the down and outs and quickly slipped out of the
                church when she saw what was going to happen.</p>
            <p>Gussie Miller is the type who can be depended upon in the class struggle--the Rebel
                type.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head>WOMAN REBEL GROUPS</head>
            <p>All those interested in the ideas advocated by the <title type="journal">WOMAN
                    REBEL</title>, who are willing to help us spread the propaganda towards
                achieving the freedom of woman, can help materially by forming groups for the
                circulation of the paper in all industrial centres, large or small. We shall be glad
                to hear from any desirous of taking up this work.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head>A WOMAN"S DUTY</head>
            <p>To look the whole world in the face with a go-to-hell look in the eyes; to have an
                ideal; to speak and act in defiance of convention.</p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
