<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2001-11-13 MH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2002-08-27 KH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2003-07-09 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/03/11 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/26 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007-05-31 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-05 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1914-04-00">Apr 1914</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>She Should Worry</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp420051</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">The Woman Rebel</title>, Vol. 1, No. 2, Apr. 1914 ,
                11.</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Collected Documents Series</title> C16:0525</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="CHRSA">Christopher, Sarah</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
        <index level1="working class" level2="women and girls"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>SHE SHOULD WORRY</head>
        <p>Three years have passed since the Triangle fire. The <org reg="Triangle Waist Company"
                >Triangle shirtwaist factory</org> fire, in which 145 working girls were murdered,
            provided conclusive evidence of the fact that women working in the garment trades in
                <place reg="New York, NY">New York City</place> must risk their lives daily for the
            miserable pittance they receive from their employers. For we were assured the other day
            in one of the papers that even three years after the Triangle tragedy <emph rend="bold"
                >the whole thing could be repeated any day in New York</emph>. The <org>Committee on
                Safety</org>, as a memorial to the crushed and mangled bodies of the Triangle
            victims, reported that the chances of the recurrence of the crime had decreased about 25
            per cent. But Mrs. <person reg="Christopher, Sarah">Sarah Christopher</person>, who has
            been receiving a very comfortable salary from the <org>Association of Garment
                Manufacturers</org>, as "fire prevention adviser" (!), and has been conducting some
            perfectly sweet fire drills among the girls in the factories, disagrees with the
            committee. With an exhibition of brilliant tact that must have brought joy to her
            employers the manufacturers, she declared, according to the <title type="journal"><org
                    reg="New York Herald Tribune">Tribune</org></title>:</p>
        <p>"<q who="CHRSA">They have perhaps decreased a little, but we could have a Triangle fire
                any day in New York. It isn't the fire; it's the girls, who are well organized in
                comparatively few factories. They are none too brilliant, and the manufacturers
                won't comply with the law, so their chances in a fire have not improved
            much.</q>"</p>
        <p>"<q who="CHRSA">Even where there are drills the girls don't see the need of them. I once
                took a fireman with me to a drill, and they were so curious about his uniform and
                his good looks that they stood giggling and waiting to be burned up. I had to box
                their ears to bring them to life.</q>"</p>
        <p>"<q who="CHRSA">After all, the real sufferers from the Triangle fire are the proprietors
                and the manufacturers. They have to pay for remodeling their premises to suit the
                law. That is the reason why so many of them do not comply.</q>"</p>
        <p>What puzzles us is--did she mean it seriously? Or was Mrs. Christopher having a little
            joke at the expense of the 145 "none too brilliant" girls who were murdered three years
            ago as a tribute to business acumen and enterprise?</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
