<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/06/22 CE</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/09/08 CH corrections</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1925-03-26">26 Mar 1925</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Address at the Pioneer's Dinner</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp420076</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
            <bibl><title>LCM</title> 122:154-157</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="BROHE">Broun, Heywood</name>
            <name id="CW">Catholic Weekly</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Sanger delivered this speech at the Pioneer's
            Dinner of the <org>Sixth International Neo-Malthusian and Birth
                Control Conference</org> at the <org>Hotel McAlpin</org> in
                <place reg="New York, NY">New York City</place>. Sanger was
            introduced by meeting chairman <person reg="Broun, Heywood">Heywood
                Broun</person> who discussed Catholic opposition to birth
            control and then said: "<q who="BROHE">Nine years ago this spring,
                at about this time, <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret
                    Sanger</person> was in prison. She is here tonight."</q> The
            audience arose and applauded.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues"
            level3="in US"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="international conferences on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation"
            level3="Federal"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation"
            level3="State"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="mainstreaming of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="history of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="MS on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="religion and"/>
        <index level1="conferences"
            level2="International Neo-Malthusian and Birth Control Conference"
            level3="1925 (6th)"/>
        <index level1="England" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="immigration" level2="U.S. policy"/>
        <index level1="New York City" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="poverty" level2="family size and"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="biography"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="nursing and"/>
        <index level1="&quot;unfit&quot; to reproduce" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="population policies"/>
        <index level1="woman suffrage" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="enslavement of"/>
        <index level1="working classes" level2="fertility of"/>
        <index level1="working classes" level2="living conditions of"/>
        <index level1="working classes" level2="women and girls"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <p>MRS.MARGARET SANGER: Mr. Chairman: I did not think that you would
            quite overwhelm me like this.</p>
        <p>Ladies and gentlemen, I feel that more than fifty per cent of the
            people who are here tonight have been pioneers with me in this cause
            for Birth Control. I think it is right and fitting that we should
            honor those pioneers who have fought before us for this great
            Movement. I find that there are two kinds of pioneers. The ones who
            go out into the firing line and brace perhaps the storms, the stress
            of public opinion and prejudice and of ignorance, and the other kind
            who stays back and really prepares the ammunition.</p>
        <p>I could tell you of those early pioneers who in this country nearly a
            century ago fought for the idea which we call today Birth Control–
                <person reg="Owen, Robert Dale">Robert Dale Owen</person>
            (applause) who wrote the treatise and it was published in this
                <place reg="New York City, NY">City of New York</place> on
                “<title>Moral Physiology</title>”; then there was Dr. <person
                reg="Knowlton, Charles">Charles Knowlton</person>, who in 1832
            published his famous book, “<title>The Truths of Philosophy</title>”
            in <place reg="Boston, MA">Boston</place>; then there was <person
                reg="Noyes, John Humphrey">John Humphrey Noyes</person> and his
                <org reg="Oneida Community">Oneida Colony</org>; then there was
            that splendid pioneer women and feminist, <person
                reg="Stockham, Alice Bunker">Alice Stockum</person>, who was
            persecuted almost to her death by <person reg="Comstock, Anthony"
                >Anthony Comstock</person>; then there was a fine old hero,
                <person reg="Harman, Moses">Moses Harmon</person> (applause),
            who at the age of seventy-five years was sent to break stone at <org
                reg="United States Penitentiary, Leavenworth">Leavenworth</org>,
            and who, when he came out of jail continued with his work – his
            educational work – and was again sent back to jail. I could tell you
            of the splendid inspiring words of <person
                reg="Emerson, Ralph Waldo">Ralph Waldo Emerson</person>; I could
            tell you of the splendid vision of <person
                reg="Ingersoll, Robert Green">Robert Ingersoll</person>
            (applause), and also of Dr. <person reg="Jacobi, Abraham">Abraham
                Jacobi</person>, who at one time was President of the
                <org>American Medical Association</org>.</p>
        <p>There were many, many others almost forgotten tonight. But one
            especially forgotten hero and pioneer was Dr. Charles Knowlton, whom
            I have just mentioned. He would be almost entirely forgotten were it
            not for the famous little book he wrote which really linked up the
            English Neo-Malthusian Movement with the Movement in the
                <place>United States</place>. It is almost impossible to find
            much about his life. I have hunted in the libraries of Boston and
            the libraries here, and all that I can find about him is that he was
            sent to jail for publishing his little book, “<title>The Fruits of
                Philosophy</title>”. He was not discouraged; he was not
            dismayed, for the very day that he came out of jail in <place
                reg="Cambridge, MA">East Cambridge</place> he crystallized his
            philosophy and his ideas by forming a society called the
                “<org>Friend of Mental Liberty</org>”. There is nothing more
            that we find about Dr. Knowlton except that his book wandered around
            the world for more than forty years. It got itself translated and
            reprinted again and again and finally led to the famous case or that
            famous trial, <name type="legal case" reg="Bradlaugh-Besant Trial"
                >the Bradlow-Besant trial</name>, of which <person
                reg="Drysdale, Charles Vickery">Dr. Drysdale</person> will tell
            you more of a little later on.</p>
        <p>The next that we know was perhaps my own coming into this work in the
            year of 1914. (Applause) Some people have accused us today of this
            being an emotional movement. I said that I plead guilty. I had been
            a nurse for over ten or twelve years here in New York City, mainly,
            and I was quite impressed by the fact that there were two kinds of
            people here – those whom we would call of the small family group,
            and others of the large family group.</p>
        <p>I investigated both groups again and again. I found in the small
            family group there were all the nice things that we like in this
            world– health, happiness, comfort, intelligence, and all the things
            that we almost all aspire to. But in the large family group I found
            quite the opposite. There was all the disease, the misery and the
            ignorance, and the poverty. There we had our slums. There we had all
            the things that we did not like, and yet I found it was perfectly
            moral and patriotic to go up and down from one end of the country to
            another and talk about having large families, when it was considered
            quite immoral, and a jail sentence was almost given to you if you
            talked about having small families.</p>
        <p>It was moral, in other words, for one group, while it was quite the
            other for the other group. This seemed a peculiar condition, a
            peculiar situation. And after having many, many experiences with
            women who were practically enslaved, who were practically awaiting
            death sentences, year in and year out because they were told if they
            bore another child that they would face the grave. After living with
            this group, after living with this idea for more than two or three
            years consciously, I decided that it was time for someone to do
            something other than talking about these conditions. And I tried to
            get people to listen, tried to see if there could not bee something
            done about the conditions that I saw. I was told by some of the most
            advanced women in this country at that time, to wait until we got
            the vote, but I could not wait.</p>
        <p><person reg="Anthony, Susan Brownell">Susan B. Anthony</person>
            started nearly fifty years ago and I felt it was not fair to keep
            women of this country enslaved, bound to the chains of maternal
            slavery – because that is really where they are – for another fifty
            years. Something had to be done to break those chains. I won’t go
            into detail telling you what happened, but always want it to be
            understood that the sentence that was imposed upon me of going to
            jail was not an accident. I challenged of the law, definitely and
            deliberately. (Applause)</p>
        <p>There was no other way to crystallize and focus public opinion upon
            the conditions that I saw, except by – as <person
                reg="Besant, Annie">Anna Besant</person> said – going to the
            “dock” to do it.</p>
        <p>I don’t know how far we would have been today had it not been for
            those other pioneers; the silent kind; those who stood behind me and
            who have helped me from the very beginning. Those splendid
            courageous women like <person reg="Delafield, Charlotte Wyeth">Mrs.
                Lewis G. Delafield</person>, <person reg="Young, Virginia C."
                >Miss. C. Young</person>, <person reg="Ackerman, Frances">Mrs.
                Frances Ackermann</person>, and like Mrs. <person
                reg="Rublee, Juliet Barrett">Juliet Barrett Rublee</person> have
            been the women who have taken the subject of Birth Control out of
            the police court, out of the “dock” and have established it in the
            dining room and in the drawing room. They have made it respectable.
            It is those women who have really broadcasted the idea and the
            ideals of Birth Control. They are the real pioneers of today.</p>
        <p>After all, pioneering still continues. When you look out and see what
            we have had to do for the past ten years, there are many. I began to
            count up and I found that the landlord where we have our office was
            really a pioneer. No other landlord for some distance around would
            allow us to have our office in their building. (Laughter) When we
            had a book to publish we walked the streets of New York and visited
            all the publishers before we could find a publisher, so our
            publisher becomes a pioneer. When you have something to say you have
            got to have a hall; when you have got a magazine to publish, you
            have got to have a printer, so your printer becomes a pioneer,
            especially when he is the kind of printer who will wait from month
            to month to get his money. (Applause) And even the management of the
            Hotel McAlpin is a pioneer (applause) because they came out and
            invited us to have our <org
                reg="Sixth International Neo-Malthusian and Birth Control Conference"
                >International Conference</org> here. (Applause)</p>
        <p>Then, ladies and gentlemen, I want to say also that our Toastmaster,
            Mr. <person reg="Broun, Heywood Campbell">Haywood Broun</person> is
            also a pioneer. (Applause) If he is not a pioneer in the Birth
            Control Movement, he certainly is a pioneer in journalism. He is
            pioneering for truth in journalism. (Applause)</p>
        <p>And last, but not least, the <org>United States Government</org> has
            become a pioneer by its immigration laws. It is really putting into
            effect today in it immigration laws, exactly what most Birth
            Controllers want. The only thing is, while it applies its laws in
            keeping out of this country the mentally defective and the
            physically weak and defective, the paupers and the other kind of
            so-called undesirables, we only wish it would extend its laws a
            little bit more and stop the multiplication of the same undesirable
            type within. (Applause)</p>
        <p>I also want to pay tribute to those scientists in the United States
            who have been courageously with us almost from the beginning of our
            organized movement. If you will just look at our program and see our
            “Who’s Who”, I think you will agree with me that we can well be
            proud of the courage that the scientists of this country have had in
            coming in with us and giving us a splendid boost. We know they have
            been far more courageous in helping use and in guiding us than the
            medical profession has been. And what we ask tonight is that this
            same group of scientists just steer us and guide us a little further
            on for the next few years, pilot us, in other words, through the
            stormy waters, and I believe we will really be through our journey.
            I think if they have the courage to continue with us that they will
            find that courage, like virtue, brings with it its own reward.
            (Applause)</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
