<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2001-12-05 MH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/20 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007-05-31 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1914-08-00">Aug 1914</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Confiscated</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp420017</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">The Woman Rebel</title>, Vol. 1, No. 6, Aug. 1914,
                48</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Collected Documents Series</title> C16:562</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
        <index level1="censorship"/>
        <index level1="free speech and free press"/>
        <index level1="Edelsohn, Rebecca"/>
        <index level1="Thorpe, Herbert A."/>
        <index level1="Woman Rebel" level2="suppression of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>CONFISCATED</head>
        <p>Once again I must announce that another issue of the <title type="journal">WOMAN
                REBEL</title> has been debarred from transmission by the <org
                reg="United States Post Office">Post Office</org>authorities, and all the copies
            found in the mails have been CONFISCATED.</p>
        <p>That will account for the loss of your July number, if you did not get it.</p>
        <p>It will be interesting to learn just what article in the July issue was considered
            OBSCENE. My suspicions are that it was one of two articles. One an excellent and
            scientific <title type="article">DEFENCE OF ASSASSINATION</title>, by <person
                reg="Thorpe, Herbert A.">Herbert A. Thorp</person> of which only one half was
            published in the July issue and the remaining part following later. The other was an
            editorial "<title type="article">ARE PREVENTIVE MEANS INJURIOUS?</title>" written in
            answer to the many questions I have received on this subject.</p>
        <p>Both are questions which should be openly discussed, and through which enlightenment may
            be gained.</p>
        <p>The farce of Freedom of Speech is being forcibly recognized on <org>Blackwell's
                Island</org> where <person reg="Edelsohn, Rebecca">Becky Edelsohn</person> is
            resisting an unjust imprisonment for speaking the truth about the Mexican war. The farce
            of Freedom of Press is again being demonstrated by the three suppressions of the <title
                type="journal">WOMAN REBEL</title> within five months.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
