<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2001-11-14 MH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2002-08-29 KH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/07 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007-05-31 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-05 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1914-05-00">May 1914</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Abortion in the United States</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp420006</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">The Woman Rebel</title>, Vol. 1, No. 3, May 1914 , 24</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Collected Documents Series</title>
                C16:0538</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
        <index level1="abortion"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>ABORTION IN THE <place reg="United States">UNITED STATES</place></head>
        <p>It is a well recognized fact that "criminal" abortion prevails to-day to such an extent
            that it is estimated that one-third of all pregnancies result in criminal abortion.</p>
        <p>It is said 100,000 criminal abortions occur each year in the <place>United States</place>
            and 6,000, at the lowest estimate, die yearly from the direct result of this.</p>
        <p>"Criminal" abortions arise from a perverted sex relationship under the stress of economic
            necessity, and their greatest frequency is among married women.</p>
        <p>Prominent authorities claim that criminal abortions are 50 per cent. of all abortions
            that occur, and this is considered a conservative estimate.</p>
        <p>Just why there is such danger in abortions can be readily understood when we realize the
            process of growth of the embryo. During the first six weeks after conception the ovum
            becomes implanted in the uterus. The second six weeks is occupied with the formation of
            the placenta (afterbirth). This is the period when abortion most easily occurs, because
            of the firmly adhering covering of the embryo to the walls or lining of the uterus.</p>
        <p>When instruments are used they often rupture the membrane and the entire placenta may be
            left, though the foetus comes away. The covering or envelope of the ovum may come away
            in a shred-like discharge after an abortion, all of which necessitates a careful
            curettage (or scraping) to avoid resulting conditions of blood-poisoning and disease.
            Most of the deaths are the result of sepsis (or decay) of some kind. Often the foetus is
            found macerated (or softened) and the whole region of the reproductive organs is in a
            highly inflamed condition. Rarely if ever is an abortion complete, and only in a very
            small percentage, authorities claim, is there reason to believe the ovum is expelled
            unbroken. Consequently the uterus needs careful investigation after each case of
            abortion.</p>
        <p>When an abortion is properly done by one specialized to do so, the cost is usually
            tremendous. What a wholesale lot of misery, expense, unhappiness and worry will be
            avoided when woman shall possess the knowledge of prevention of conception!</p>
        <p>In <place reg="Paris, France">Paris</place> up to a few years ago the instruments to
            produce abortion were sold openly in the market place, while all the mechanical
            preventatives were, and are, openly displayed in the windows of the drug stores.
            Abortions, with their horrible consequences, are quite needless and unnecessary when the
            subject of preventive means shall be open to all to discuss and use. How soon this shall
            be, depends on you.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
