<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2001-12-10 MH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/20 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007-05-31 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/03/10 CH Entered corrections suggested by Andy Carloff.</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-18 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1914-09-00">Sep-Oct 1914</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>No Defense Fund</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp420036</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">The Woman Rebel</title>, Vol. 1, No. 7, Sept.-Oct. 1914,
                53</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> C16:567</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
        <index level1="law breaking and direct action"/>
        <index level1="labor movement" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="Woman Rebel" level2="legal case"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>NO DEFENSE FUND</head>
        <p>The workers of <place reg="United States">America</place> are always emptying their
            pockets for everlasting defense funds. The leaders and the agitators are always making
            their eloquent, frantic, irresistible appeals for money. Money is collected to sustain
            and give work to that ever-growing group of pseudo-radical lawyers who seldom do
            anything toward keeping the revolutionary issue clear cut and definite, who fight cases
            on technicalities and who, in spite of extraordinary goodwill and sympathy with the
            revolutionists, can not--it goes without saying--be of any use in the fight of the
            revolutionists with the forces of Government and Exploitation.</p>
        <p>The workers themselves must carry on the battle--by acting, by living it, by keeping
            alive with renewed effort those very ideas that the Powers of Darkness are trying to
            stamp out.</p>
        <p>Revolution does not grow by the contribution of a few pennies or a few dollars to some
            defense fund. You must create revolution by <emph rend="italics">living</emph> it--not
            by mushy sentimentality over some comrade who has tried to act not according to the
            modern commercialism of the so-called radical agitator and publisher, who is just daring
            enough to keep out of jail and just hypocritical enough to make Revolution pay, but
            according to honest conviction. If this attitude can be sustained, it may prove of some
            slight value to the revolutionary movement in the United States.</p>
        <p>Whatever support and help the <title type="journal">WOMAN REBEL</title> may receive to
            carry out this fight for the freedom of working women must come from them, if not in
            money, in their own activity in fighting for their own freedom. The formation of active
            groups would do much to bring this all-important matter to light and to interest more
            and more women.</p>
        <p>Those who are already aware of the importance of the work must realize that only through
            their renewed and energetic activity will the battle ever be won.</p>
        <p>No defense fund--but that does not mean that help is not needed. It means that greater
            activity and greater solidarity must be brought into play.</p>
        <p>No time should be lost in forming organizations to discuss the idea of Birth Control and
            to increase the activity of all working women who are conscious of the attempt of the
            Government to invade their most private rights and powers.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
