<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2001-11-13 MH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2002-08-27 KH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/26 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007-05-30 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-05 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1914-04-00">Apr 1914</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Marriage</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp420046</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">The Woman Rebel</title>, Vol. 1, No. 2, Apr. 1914, 16</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Collected Documents Series</title> C16:0530</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
        <index level1="marriage"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>MARRIAGE</head>
        <p>Marriage, which is a personal agreement between a man and a woman, should be no concern
            of the State or of the Church. Never have either of these institutions interested
            themselves in the happiness or health of the individual. Never have they concerned
            themselves that children be born in healthy and clean surroundings, which might insure
            their highest development. The Church has been and is anxious only if a child be trained
            Catholic, Baptist, Methodist and so forth. The State and the Church are so concerned
            only in maintaining and perpetuating themselves even to the detriment and sacrifice of
            the human race. In the willingness to accept without protest or questions the
            indignities imposed through the barbarities of the Law, together with the stupid
            superstitions of the Church, can be traced a great proportion of the world's misery.</p>
        <p>That there exists in all Nature an attraction which takes places between particles of
            bodies and unites to form a chemical compound is not doubted. This same attraction
            exists in men and women and will, unconsciously perhaps, cause them to seek a mate just
            as other organisms do.</p>
        <p>Priests and marriage laws have no power or control over this attraction nor can they make
            desirable a union where this attraction does not exist.</p>
        <p>Marriage laws abrogate the freedom of woman by enforcing upon her a continuous sexual
            slavery and a compulsory motherhood.</p>
        <p>Marriage laws have been dictated and dominated by the Church always and ever upon the
            unquestionable grounds of the wisdom of the <title type="book">Bible</title>.</p>
        <p>A man and a woman who under a natural condition avow their love for each other should be
            immediately qualified by this to give expression to their love or to perpetuate the race
            without the necessity of a public declaration.</p>
        <p>A reciprocal, spontaneous voluntary declaration of love and mutual feelings by a man and
            woman is the expression of Nature's desires. Were it not natural it would not be so and
            being natural it is right.</p>
        <p>The marriage institution viewed from the light of human experience and the demands of the
            individual has proven a failure. Statistical reports show that one out of every twelve
            marriages in the <place>United States</place> has resulted in a divorce--which does not
            include the thousands of women who want divorces--but on account of the Church and
            conventions are restrained from obtaining them. Nor does it mention the thousands of
            women too poor to obtain the price to set in motion the ponderous machinery of the
            divorce courts. The divorce courts give us only a hint of the dissatisfaction and
            unhappiness underlying the institution of marriage.</p>
        <p>Superstition; blind following; unthinking obedience on the part of working women;
            together with the pretense, hypocrisy and sham morality of the women of the middle class
            have been the greatest obstacles in the obtaining of woman's freedom.</p>
        <p>Every change in social life is accomplished only by a struggle. Rebel women of the world
            must fight for the freedom to harmonize their actions with the natural desires of their
            being, for their deeds are but the concrete expressions of their thoughts.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
