<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/06/29 NC</prepDate>
        <prepDate>CH 2011/07/22 corrects</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/11/30 CH typos</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-01 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Providence Journal</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1935-04-08">8 Apr. 1935</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Mrs. Sanger Hits New Deal Attitude on Birth Control</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp420081</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Providence Journal</title> 9 Apr. 1935 p. 3-4</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="HEPKA">Katherine Houghton Hepburn</name>
            <name id="PJ">Providence Journal</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>This newspaper report is the most complete version of Margaret Sanger's
            speech at the Plantations Club in <place>Providence, RI</place>, on April 8, 1935. For
            draft notes prepared for Sanger by <person reg="Hanau, Stella">Stella Hanau</person>,
            see "<xref from="236523.xml">Providence Speech Notes,</xref>" Apr. 8 1935
                (<title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> S71:744).</p>
        <index level1="birth control"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to" level3="international"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues" level3="in US"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="the Bible and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="socio-economic benefits of"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="population growth and"/>
        <index level1="fertility limitation" level2="of physicaly disabled and diseased"/>
        <index level1="New York Society for the Suppression of Vice"/>
        <index level1="population" level2="food supply and"/>
        <index level1="population" level2="war and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="in marriages"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Mrs. Sanger Hits New Deal Attitude on Birth Control</head>
        <head type="sub">Says Relief Agences Even Encourage Motherhood in Jobless Families; Calls
            Regulation Only Way to Lead Civilization Out of Chaos</head>
        <div type="section">
            <q who="PJ">
                <p><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person> last night told an
                    audience of about 700 persons at the <org>Plantations Club</org> that the
                        <place>United States</place> in its gigantic program of relief is ignoring
                    birth control, which, she declared, is the one factor in human development that
                    can lead civilization out of chaos, assuring international peace and human
                    development on a par with industrial development.</p>
                <p>Instead of recognizing the vital need for population control, Mrs. Sanger said,
                    those charged with administration of the fabulous funds for relief in some
                    instances actually are suggesting to mothers applying for relief that they would
                    stand a better chance of obtaining it if they could be presented as expectant of
                    motherhood.</p></q>
            <p><q who="PJ">The noted pioneer of the birth control movement in the <place>United
                        States</place> declared that with such methods employed in administering
                    relief, it were better to</q> "throw open doors of the insane asylums and let
                the inmates run our country."</p>
            <q who="PJ">
                <p>In the face of the present chaotic conditions in this country, she said, due
                    largely to the fact that human development has not kept abreast of the
                    industrial development, surveys in <place>Wisconsin</place>, <place
                        reg="Philadelphia, PA.">Philadelphia</place>, and <place>New York</place>
                    showed that the birth rate was rising 45 to 60 per cent in families on the
                    relief rolls over families of the employed.</p></q>
            <p>"Another survey in Philadelphia," <q who="PJ">Mrs. Sanger said,</q> "showed the birth
                rate was higher among unskilled unemployed that among the skilled employed."</p>
        </div>
        <div type="Section">
            <head type="sub">Quotes <person reg="Wells, H.G.">H.G. Wells</person></head>
            <p>"Some years ago," <q who="PJ">she said,</q> "H.G. Wells stated we were about to come
                into an age of confusion, because the fertility of mankind can far outrun the
                intelligence of man. He said this chaos would come unless we showed a growth in
                intellect through an elective birth rate.</p>
            <p>"In February, the <org reg="United States Federal Reserve System">Federal
                    Reserve</org> gave an industrial report that indicated production had risen
                within 90 per cent of the normal average. At the same time the <org>National
                    Emergency Council</org> announced that more than 10,000,000 people were
                unemployed, and two weeks later, the <org
                    reg="United States Federal Emergency Relief Administration">FERA</org> said more
                than 22,000,000 persons or over 5,000,000 families were on relief. And more than
                $150,000,000 had to be spent every month--out of the taxpayers' pockets--to provide
                for the relief rolls."</p>
            <p>After citing figures to show that the birth rate was increasing rapidly among those
                on relief rolls, as compared with figures for those not on relief, Mrs. Sanger
                asked:</p>
            <p>"If we have come almost back to normal industrial production with 22,000,000 on
                relief what is the matter? I believe it will not be solved by turning out one set of
                politicians and putting in another set.</p>
            <p>"I believe we will see a great percentage of these unemployed carried for some
                time--probrably for 20 years or more. This condition has been coming on steadily for
                years, with the differential birth rate and the advance of machinery.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="Section">
            <head type="sub">No Voice Said "Stop!"</head>
            <p>"Machinery has taken the place of human labor. Organized labor has seen this
                situation coming. Social agencies have seen in coming. Yet not one voice was raised
                to say, "Stop! It is not necessary to have a high birth rate among unskilled labor
                groups"</p>
            <p>"The birth rate has gone up and up. We today have 125 millions of people in this
                country, a population increase of 20,000,000 since 1920. The population has actually
                increased nearly 5,000,000 during the depression years since 1930."</p>
            <q who="PJ"><p>Mrs. Sanger said it was idle to talk of balancing the national budget
                    until the United States balanced its birth rate with its industrial needs.</p>
                <p>She declared that in every town there is a group of families that have spaced
                    their children, giving consideration to the mother's health, the father's
                    earning power, and the ability of both to assume responsibility for the
                    children's welfare.</p></q>
            <p>"They haven't had to send their children to the factory or the farm to labor when
                they should be in school," she said. "They have had as large families as they could
                have, consistent with family welfare, and it is to this group that we must look for
                most of the things that mean civilization.</p>
            <p>"I refuse to quarrel with this group for not increasing the number of their
                children--at least until we take that other and rapidly growing group off their
                back."</p>
            <q who="PJ"><p>Mrs. Sanger asserted that it was the group with an uncontrollable birth
                    rate and an unplanned scheme of life that in the last quarter of a century had
                    given the nation great numbers of children unequipped to carry the
                    responsibilities of life.</p></q>
        </div>
        <div type="Section">
            <head type="sub">"What to Do?" She Asks</head>
            <p>"What are we to do with these defectives?" <q who="PJ">she asked.</q> "Is there any
                nation that will take them off our backs? No. They wouldn't even take them as
                conscripts of war."</p>
            <p>"Even the <org reg="Roman Catholic Church">Catholic church</org>, which opposes a
                reduction of the birth rate--even the church will not take care of its own mental
                defectives, but puts them back on the State or nation."</p>
            <p>The birth control advocate declared that greater than the financial debts which
                future generations would inherit from this age will be the terrific debt of the
                mental and physical defectives now permitted to reproduce their kind.</p>
            <p>"Future generations may repudiate the monetary debts passed along but they cannot
                refuse to pay for the inferior quality of life which they inherit because of the
                uncontrolled reproduction of those not able to assume life's responsibilities," Mrs.
                Sanger said.</p>
            <p>"Business men will look close when making investments in securities, particularly if
                they are to be given to their children, but at the same time will pay no attention
                to the biological problems and blunders that must be solved by the next generations
                out of their other investments for their children. I tell you the investments are
                very inconsistent."</p>
            <q who="PJ"><p>Mrs. Sanger berated the fact that while billions were being spent on
                    diseased, defective and delinquent members of the national family, not one thing
                    has been done to halt social retrogression, with defectives allowed to reproduce
                    their kind in unlimited number.</p></q>
        </div>
        <div type="Section">
            <head type="sub">The Finger of Scorn</head>

            <p>"I hold those religious and social organizations responsible on which we came to
                depend to look after these conditions." <q who="PJ">Mrs. Sanger said.</q> "The
                finger of scorn must be pointed at them by those who have contributed to their
                coffers. And now the time has come to demand something be done to curb the increase
                of those who have transmissable diseases."</p>
            <q who="PJ"><p>Mrs. Sanger said the medical profession, the schools, parents, teachers,
                    and the courts should be held responsible to see that insanity, epilepsy and
                    other human curses should not be promoted through reproduction.</p>
                <p>She would control births among:</p>
                <p>Those with transmissible diseases or the feeble-minded.</p>
                <p>Women who have temporary diseases such as heart disease or tuberculosis.</p>
                <p>Parents who already have produced children of subnormal type.</p>
                <p>Normal healthy mothers, who should have periods of spacing with at least three
                    years between children.</p>
                <p>Among the adolescents so that persons would not become parents until after their
                    22nd or 23rd year.</p>
                <p>Parents who have more children than they are able to care for economically and
                    morally.</p>
                <p>Among married couples, who, for the first two or there years of their married
                    life should have no children, but should devote themselves to adjusting their
                    personalities, one to the other.</p></q>
            <p>"We've never given marriage a real chance." <q who="PJ">Mrs. Sanger said.</q> "First,
                our married women have been unmarried girls, and next they have been mothers."</p>
        </div>
        <div type="Section">
            <head type="sub">"Any Typical Couple"</head>
            <p>"Take any typical couple. They go on a honeymoon for three weeks, then, when they
                return, the girl already is thinking of motherhood. That marriage hasn't been given
                its real chance. It is unfair to the girl and the man, both. He never has known her
                as a woman. And he never will know her as the woman she might have been.</p>
            <p>"A period of two or three years of marriage without children would make a great
                difference in the future lives of the man and woman. Take the fear of pregnancy out
                of the equation, and there would be more marriages and more children."</p>
            <q who="PJ"><p>Mrs. Sanger said birth control embraced continence, sterilization and
                    contraceptives. She said continence was not considered ideal, according to the
                    psychiatrists. Sterilization she said, was no legal in 24 States and was the
                    best plan for halting reproduction among defectives.</p>
                <p>The third method, she said, has been satisfactorily practiced in New York, where
                    a record of nearly 50,000 cases show that it is not injurious to women's
                    health.</p></q>
            <p><q who="PJ">She said that while birth control advocates want all married women to
                    have the information concerning birth control, they want the information given
                    by those properly qualified to instruct--</q>"this means the medical
                profession."</p>
            <q who="PJ"><p>The outmoded Federal law, which prohibits transmission of birth control
                    informations or materials from one State to another, works against mothers of
                    the poorer classes because they usually ask for information of a physician at a
                    public house or dispensary, she said. She said that doctors, who in their own
                    offices give birth control information to private patients, will not give the
                    same information when it is requested of them in a public institution.</p></q>
        </div>
        <div type="Section">
            <head type="sub">Enacted in 1873</head>
            <p>"Here's where the Federal law begins to work,"<q who="PJ"> she said. She said that
                    law, <name type="law">section 211</name> of the <name type="law"
                        reg="United States Penal Code, Section 211">U. S. Penal Code</name>, was
                    enacted in 1873 at the behest of the <org
                        reg="New York Society for the Suppression of
                    Vice"
                        >Society for the Suppression of Vice</org>, and that during the intervening
                    years, through placing birth control in the category of the obscene it had</q>
                "been responsible for the death of a million women and 15,000,000 children, many
                doomed before they were born."</p>
            <q who="PJ">
                <p>It has required 60 years, Mrs. Sanger said, to bring the question to the point
                    where it might be discussed openly by intelligent people without the cry of
                    obscenity being raised.</p></q>
            <p>"All this despite the fact that birth control has been practiced through the years by
                a group of citizens that has stood for the decent things of the community,"<q
                    who="PJ"> Mrs. Sanger said.</q></p>
            <p>"Today, in nearly all States it is legal for physicians to tell--for any reason they
                may see fit--how to control birth. The Federal law interferes here with State
                rights.</p>
            <p>"In <place>California</place>, for instance, there are 28 birth control clinics. But
                physicians, fearing the Federal law, which provides punishment of $5000 fine or five
                years in prison, must have laymen bootleg their supplies from the East.</p>
            <p>"You have a perfectly legal thing, yet the Federal law interferes with the
                physician's right to save lives."</p>
        </div>
        <div type="Section">
            <head type="sub">Turns to War</head>
            <q who="PJ">
                <p>Mrs. Sanger spoke of uncontrolled population and its part in war.</p>
                <p>Concerning the Biblical injunction to multiply, Mrs. Sanger pointed out that at
                    the time it was given, there were five persons in the world.</p></q>
            <p>"Population, its growth and distribution, are tied up with birth control,"<q who="PJ"
                    > she said.</q> "Ignore birth control and it affects international relations.
                Look at <place>Japan</place>, <place>Italy</place>, and <place>Germany</place>, if
                you do not think the international problem is tied up with population.</p>
            <p>"Japan has a population of 64,000,000, with an area not as large as California, and
                two-thirds of that area untillable. She cannot produce food for that population. Yet
                over a million new babies are born there each year--not to mention the million
                babies that die each year.</p>
            <p>"When population expands in a country such as Japan, something has to happen. The
                population grows and burst forth, either in revolution or expansion. Japan, like a
                chicken in an eggshell, broke through. Germany's birthrate today is higher than in
                1914, when she started bursting out.</p>
            <p>"In <place reg="Providence, RI">Providence</place>, in <place>Rhode Island</place>
                and the nation, we have problems of population, but as we solve our own problems, we
                will be helping to solve our national and international problems.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="Section">
            <head type="sub">Wants New Type of Beings</head>
            <p>"We want to consider environment and quality of life--a new type of human beings,
                sound in body and sound in mind. We want young people to look on marriage as a
                preparation for parenthood, something by which they will prepare for
                parenthood."</p>
            <q who="PJ">
                <p>Those in the birth control movement in Rhode Island, Mrs. Sanger said, were
                    building beyond themselves, for a new type of civilization in the United
                    States.</p>
                <p>Mrs. Sanger appeared here under the auspices of the <org>Rhode Island Birth
                        Control League</org>. She was introduced by <person reg="Stone, Eric">Dr.
                        Eric Stone</person>, president of the league. <person
                        reg="Hepburn, Katherine Houghton">Mrs. Thomas Hepburn</person> of <place
                        reg="Hartford, CT">Hartford</place> appeared on the platform with Mrs.
                    Sanger, and made a brief address.</p></q>
            <p>She said, "<q who="KATHEP">nothing ever happens about anything until some one gets to
                    work.</q>" <q who="PJ">She declared money was needed in the fight at Washington
                    to amend the law of 1873.</q></p>
            <p><q who="PJ">Mrs. Sanger, in opening her address, said she was glad to be in
                    Providence,</q> "glad in fact to come anywhere from <place reg="Washington, DC"
                    >Washington</place>."</p>
            <q who="PJ">
                <p>Mrs. Sanger later invited questions from the floor. In response to one, she said
                    that <place>India</place> today had the largest body of women interested in
                    birth control of any country in the world.</p>
                <p>Another question was whether in the wide range of relief today, any recognition
                    was taken of the population problem. Mrs. Sanger said that none was taken so far
                    as she knew.</p></q>
        </div>
        <div type="Section">
            <head type="sub">For Good or Bad</head>
            <q who="PJ">
                <p>Asked whether she believed birth control promoted immorality, Mrs. Sanger said
                    she did not. She conceded that birth control knowledge might be used for good or
                    bad, the same as automobiles, firearms, alcohol. She pointed out, however, that
                    when she first took up the study of birth-control in <place reg="Netherlands"
                        >Holland</place>, the authorities challenged her to find any native woman
                    engaged in prostitution. None ever was found by her, she said.</p>
                <p>She answered another question by saying that birth control knowledge was most
                    easily taught those who most needed it, once they were desirous of learning.</p>
                <p>Asked how pressure might be brought to bear on Washington, in behalf of amending
                    the 62-year-old Federal law, Mrs. Sanger suggested individual letters to members
                    of both Houses of <org reg="United States Congress">Congress</org>.</p>
                <p>In conclusion, Mrs. Sanger read a letter from a woman in <place
                        reg="Tokyo, Japan">Tokyo</place> seeking knowledge of birth control.</p></q>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
