<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2001-11-30 MH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2002-08-29 KH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2003-07-28 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/07 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/08/13 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007-05-31 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-05 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1914-06-00">Jun 1914</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>The Militants in England</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp420005</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">The Woman Rebel</title>, June 1914, 25, 31.</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Collected Documents Series</title>
                C16:0539</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
        <p>For a follow-up article, see "<title type="article">Militants in England</title>," <xref
                from="420029.xml">July 1914.</xref></p>
        <index level1="feminism and feminists" level2="in England"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="enslavement of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>THE MILITANTS IN ENGLAND</head>
        <p>Among the causes which have made <place reg="Great Britain">Britain</place> the
            battlefield of feminism, are, firstly, the preponderating number of women over men;
            secondly, the conservative temperament of Englishmen--their dread of change and of
            liberty, and thirdly, the whole-hearted opposition springing from Imperial
            interests.</p>
        <p>Since <person reg="Wollstonecraft, Mary">Mary Wollstonecraft</person> first raised her
            voice in protest against the subjugation of her sex, women in <place>England</place> had
            gradually imbibed the intellectual ideas of feminism. Not until the close of the
            Victorian reign, however, was this dormant intellectual spirit, stimulated by the
            writings of <person reg="Mill, John Stuar">John Stuart Mill</person> and others, aroused
            to make a definite demand for political representation. But Englishmen, while prepared
            to admit the theoretical justice of womens' claim, never seriously considered the
            question of yielding to it. Promises were given, women were bidden to educate and make
            themselves fitted for their new "responsibilities" but their rights were deliberately
            ignored.</p>
        <p>After twenty years of promises on the one side and of patient, wearisome petitioning on
            the other, a handful of women idealists determined that the time for patience and
            submission had passed. Action was required and direct action against property, to awaken
            English stupidity and show that these women were serious. In 1903 Mrs. <person
                reg="Pankhurst, Emmeline">Pankhurst</person> and her daughter <person
                reg="Pankhurst, Christabel">Christabel</person>, with a fund of $10, organized a
            fighting <org reg="Women's Political and Social Union">union</org>, including <person
                reg="Kenney, Annie">Annie Kenney</person>, a millhand from <place
                reg="Lancashire, England">Lancashire</place>, and Mrs. <person reg="Drummond, Flora"
                >Drummond</person>. Mrs. Pankhurst had become almost obsessed with the idea of the
            subjugation of her sex. She and her followers quickly realized the intensity and breadth
            of the struggle that was before them. From the low, brutal, British wife-beater, from
            the middle-class "husband," whose wife served as domestic and sexual slave, to the
            aristocracy and the Court with its unclean conception of women; to the Monarchy itself,
            stretched one vast solid phalanx of stupendous opposition. Weak in body but
            unconquerable in spirit, Mrs. Pankhurst and her followers suddenly flung themselves
            against this insufferable mass of prejudice, stupidity and hypocrisy; against the male
                <name type="deity">Moloch</name> who had for centuries crushed the soul of woman and
            trafficked in her body. They made attacks on the propertied class from every conceivable
            point. Acids were poured into letter boxes, telegraph wires cut, plate glass windows
            smashed, fire engines called out on false alarms and ministers baited wherever they
            went. Thus, with a burning faith and a faith in burning, militancy arose.</p>
        <p>The middle classes, alarmed, hastily revived the sleeping suffrage societies and made a
            respectable, peaceable demand for the vote in an attempt to outdo the militant
            organization. But in vain, militancy continued to spread throughout the land despite the
            opposition of the majority of men. Suffragettes were stoned, assaulted, hounded and
            beaten yet their organization daily grew in strength. They drew monster audiences and
            thousands of class-conscious workers extended their sympathies and support.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile the persistent refusal of the government to give a political status to women
            determined the militants and only added fuel to the flames that had been lighted.
            Sheltered behind the government, as yet unmolested, was the sovereign; indifferent
            because undisturbed. Symbolizing in his person the political and social inequality of
            the sexes, the <person reg="George V (England)">king of England</person>, emperor of
                <place>India</place>, defender of the Faith, the fountain head of privilege,
            monopoly and property, remained singularly secure. His time was yet to come.</p>
        <p>When the torch and the hatchet laid low historic buildings and priceless paintings the
            public hysteria broke out in all directions. The militants were roughly handled by
            hooligans and "yahoos." In addition to chasing a rat and hunting a fox, hounding a
            suffragette has become the sport of English gentlemen.</p>
        <p>But the militants, strong in the equity of their cause and the historical justification
            for their methods, are out to win. Imprisonment, forcible feeding and persecution cannot
            crush the indomitable spirit of the womanhood which had arisen to inflame the world with
            a new passion for liberty. With its battle scarred heroines ennobled by a high idealism
            militancy is stronger today than ever before.</p>
        <p>The monarchy, the church and the selfish millions who would have woman remain a source of
            sexual excitation and a kitchen slave all now are combined in one towering mass to crush
            that organization which has behind it a decade of unparalleled activity, exuberant
            heroism and an awakened womanhood. In the fight that is now being waged by women against
            the domination of man, the torch and the hatchet may be followed by the bomb and the
            bullet. All these weapons will be justifiable for all may be needed in effacing forever
            the white-livered monster that fattens upon child labor, that hounds women into filthy
            dens, into factories and prostitution and that denies to her the right of her body and
            of civic and economic equality.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
