<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2001-11-12 MH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2002-08-27 KH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2003/03/10 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007-05-30 CH Oxygen cleanup</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-05 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1914-03-00">Mar 1914</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>The New Feminists</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp420042</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">The Woman Rebel</title>, Vol. 1, No. 1, Mar. 1914, 1</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Collected Documents Series</title> C16:0515</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
        <index level1="women" level2="freedom and rights of"/>
        <index level1="feminism and feminists" level2="MS on"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>THE NEW FEMINISTS</head>
        <p>That apologetic tone of the new American feminists which plainly says "<q who="UNK"
                >Really, Madam Public Opinion, we are all quite harmless and perfectly
                respectable</q>" was the keynote of the first and second mass meetings held at
                <org>Cooper Union</org> on the 17th and 20th of February last.</p>
        <p>The ideas advanced were very old and time-worn even to the ordinary church-going woman
            who reads the magazines and comes in contact with current thought. The "right to work,"
            the "right to ignore fashions," the "right to keep her own name," the "right to
            organize," the "right of the mother to work"; all these so-called rights fail to arouse
            enthusiasm because to-day they are all recognized by society and there exist neither
            laws nor strong opposition to any of them.</p>
        <p>It is evident they represent a middle class woman's movement; an echo, but a very weak
            echo, of the English constitutional suffragists. Consideration of the working woman's
            freedom was ignored. The problems which affect the working girl who slaves in the home
            or the nurse girl who spends her days and nights in the care of the babies of the
            feminists, were not dwelt upon. The freedom which the new feminists expound can only be
            obtained through a greater enslavement of the already enslaved workingwoman, and "where
            slavery is there liberty cannot be." Instead of launching a movement for woman's freedom
            the impression gained was that they aimed to combat the contentions of the conventional
            anti-suffragists.</p>
        <p>To those who have been on the firing line for woman's freedom for the past several years,
            the new movement is sadly lacking in vitality, force, and conviction.</p>
        <p>Any movement with fear lurking in the background, fear of the press, of public opinion,
            of our neighbors, or of the enemy, can not have that spirit which fearlessness of
            opposition brings. It is not for rights women should ask, all rights are here--rather is
            it for you to inculcate into her the desire to get these rights.</p>
        <p>Feminists--Come out from under the cover of morbid respectability and let's get a look at
            you!</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
