<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2001-11-14 MH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2002-08-29 KH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/07 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007-05-31 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-11 CH clean up errors</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1914-05-00">May 1914</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Blood and Oil</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp420014</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">The Woman Rebel</title>, Vol. 1, No. 3, May 1914, 17</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm </title> C16:0531</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
        <index level1="capitalism"/>
        <index level1="Mexico" level2="descriptions of"/>
        <index level1="working classes" level2="revolution and"/>
        <index level1="socialism"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>BLOOD AND OIL</head>
        <dateline>VOL. I. <date value="1914-05-00">May, 1914.</date> NO. 3.</dateline>
        <p><person reg="Huerta, Victoriano">Huerta</person>, the murderer of <person
                reg="Madero, Francisco">Madero</person> and the minion of capital, has proven a
            failure. This is the main reason why <place>Mexico</place>, the great oil country, into
            which millions of dollars haven been sunk by the investors of <place reg="United States"
                >America</place> and <place>Europe</place>, is now to be invaded and "pacified" by
            the workers of the United States.</p>
        <p>Because, owing to the successes of the peons and of the social revolutionists, the title
            deeds of <person reg="Hearst, William Randolph">William R. Hearst</person> are now so
            much waste paper; because the oil industry, the copper and other industries of Mexico
            are endangered, and because certain fusillades and cannonades did not take place in
            honor of 'the flag'--whatever that may be -- we and the Mexican people are now bidden to
            rush at each other like wild beasts and rip up each others' bellies.</p>
        <p>And this startling order, issued in accordance with the supposed public opinion of the
            United States and of other civilized countries, is coolly repeated in every Liberal and
            advanced organ of the Press as well as by the leading prelates of the <org
                reg="Roman Catholic Church">Catholic</org> and other Christian Churches.</p>
        <p>Because, moreover, in the last 104 years, the Mexican people have been enslaved,
            terrorized, brutalized, tortured, maimed and murdered under the iron rule of sixty-one
            successive dictators; because they have endured no less than 253 revolutions in that
            period of time, we are now bidden to take part in plundering and murdering these people,
            already distracted by continual war and revolution.</p>
        <p>Those who have devised and prepared for these plunders and murders and who are
            instigating us to quarrel with Mexico are doing so only in the interests of Capital, on
            behalf of the Oil Octopus and for the legalized banditti who control the industries of
            Mexico. The insolence of these imposters has now reached its extremist development, for
            they form but an insignificant minority who live in luxury and idleness upon our
            labor.</p>
        <p>Comrades, the deluded men now being rushed to fight the Mexican people to indulge in
            savagery and killing, are as truly fighting in the interests of Hearst, <person
                reg="Guggenheim, Benjamin">Guggenheim</person> and other magnates as the militia in
                <place>Colorado</place> are murdering women and children in the interests of <person
                reg="Rockefeller, John D., Jr.">Rockefeller</person>.</p>
        <p>The government which supinely tolerates the slaughter of our women and children in
                <place>Colorado</place> by the machine guns of the rapacious Rockefeller is the same
            government which now calls on you to exterminate the Mexican people in the interests of
            this Rockefeller and his accomplices.</p>
        <p>Shall the workers of America join the ignorant and ignoble rabble who now seek to stamp
            out the flickering flames of liberty burning in Mexican breasts? Shall the republic that
            freed the negro from chattel slavery cynically struggle to maintain the equally
            degrading form of chattel slavery now rampant in Mexico?</p>
        <p>Comrades and fellow-workers. The Cause for which the Mexican peons battle; their revolt
            against the iniquitous regime initiated by <person reg="Diaz, Porfirio">Porfirio
                Diaz</person> and his imitator Huerta is the Cause of the working people against the
            tyranny of Capital. The revolutionary war now being fought by the peons is not for
            markets or for money, but for land and liberty. It is a social war, a war fought for the
            principle of liberty.</p>
        <p>Hands off Mexico! Let the peons achieve their emancipation from chattel slavery! On with
            the Social Revolution!</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
