<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2001-12-05 MH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/20 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007-05-31 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-05 CH cleaning regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1914-08-00">Aug 1914</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>The War's Lesson</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp420015</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">The Woman Rebel</title>, Vol. 1, No. 5, August 1914,
                48</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Collected Documents Series</title> C16:562</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
        <index level1="class warfare"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="war and"/>
        <index level1="peace movement and pacifism"/>
        <index level1="working classes"/>
        <index level1="World War I" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="World War I" level2="anti-war efforts"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>THE WAR'S LESSON</head>
        <p>If this European war does not convince the workers of the absolute necessity of
            SOLIDARITY, if this thrilling slaughter does not show working women that they must
            control the true destinies of a newer Civilization not based on Murder, then there is no
            reason for any revolutionary movement at all. We are hearing much cant and hypocrisy
            these days about peace and anti-militarism. The truth is that we do not want peace based
            on inevitable and certain Murder, on potential warfare. We are glad to witness the
            collapse of a hypocritical Civilization that can end only in whole-sale Murder.</p>
        <p>Exponents of birth-control have long pointed out why nations need men--why rulers need
            them. Now every woman can see this in the savage slaughter of the children she brings
            into the world.</p>
        <p>The war is good. No better education could be given the workers.</p>
        <p>After the tumult and the murder ceases, workers will realize to what ends availed their
            slavish toil--what was the aim of this flamboyant civilization. Comrades killed, life
            made even more precarious, the burden of it all on the shoulders of working men and
            women.</p>
        <p>The war is good. It is a challenge to the working class. It is a challenge we cannot
            avoid. It proves the murderous insanity of present day barbarism. Let us accept the
            challenge, and begin a new era at once.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
