<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2001-11-13 MH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2002-08-29 KH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/07 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007-05-31 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2001/03/11 CH Entered corrections suggested by Andy Carloff.</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-18 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1914-05-00">May 1914</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Watchful Waiting</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp420007</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">The Woman Rebel</title>, Vol. 1, No. 3, May 1914, 24</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm </title>, C16:0538</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
        <index level1="socialism"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>WATCHFUL WAITING</head>
        <p>Forty thousand women belonging to the <org reg="Socialist Party of America">Socialist
                party of the <place>United States</place></org> wired their
            protest against the brutalities of the militia in <place>Colorado</place> to <person
                reg="Wilson, Woodrow">President Wilson</person>.</p>
        <p>Forty thousand women! A splendid army this. An army of women supposed to represent the
            class spirit and class consciousness of America.</p>
        <p>Is there nothing more fitting to the occasion that these women can do, than protest?
            Words--ever and always words--words of protest, or words of petition, even when blood is
            being shed and lives are being extinguished by the murderous officials to whom they are
            protesting.</p>
        <p>Doubtless the gracious protest found itself amidst others in the waste basket. And
            rightly so, for as long as the present system can keep the working class
            petition-minded, the masters need have no fear of an uprising, and the social and
            industrial revolution will be far away.</p>
        <p>Women of the Socialist party! If there is no fighting spirit among you impelling
            initiative other than to imitate the gentle suffragists, then at least take your
            cue--follow the lead of those whom you would represent. The protests of the <org>Cigar
                Makers</org> and <org>Typographical Union</org> and the <org>Miners of Wyoming</org>
            consisted in sending arms and ammunition to the striking miners of Colorado, and these
            are good enough examples of working-class solidarity for all to follow.</p>
        <p>When 40,000 women cannot follow up a protest by action, then truly it would appear that
            they have something other than their "chains to lose."</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
