<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2001-11-13 MH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2002-08-29 KH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/03/11 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/26 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007-05-30 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-05</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1914-04-00">Apr 1914</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Food and Love</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp420048</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">The Woman Rebel</title>, Vol. 1, No. 2, April 1914 ,
                15</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Collected Documents Series</title> C16:0529</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="DRYGE">Drysdale, George</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
        <index level1="birth control"/>
        <index level1="free love"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>FOOD AND LOVE</head>
        <p>Sixty years ago <person reg="Drysdale, George">George Drysdale</person>, one of the great
            pioneers in the fight for sexual freedom, put the central problem of the workers in the
            following form:</p>
        <p>
            <q who="DRYGE">The hopes of man lie in a nutshell. They are all comprehended in this
                question of questions--IS IT POSSIBLE TO HAVE BOTH FOOD AND LOVE? Is it possible
                that each individual among us can have a due share of food, love and leisure? In
                other words, is it possible to reconcile the antagonism of the two laws of nature,
                and to escape from the horrors of mutual destruction?</q>
        </p>
        <p>"<q who="DRYGE">I firmly believe that it is perfectly possible, and that this greatest of
                human difficulties has only to be clearly perceived and determinedly approached to
                be ultimately overcome. But it is evident at the outset that the means by which this
                is to be effected, must be very different from any that have been hitherto tried,
                since all these have been so utterly inadequate. It is evident that it can be by no
                slight palliative measures, such as have hitherto been resorted to and which have
                all been rendered abortive that any real improvement can be effected; but we must go
                to the true root of the matter, which a sexual one, and that some great radical
                change in the sexual life and opinions of mankind is required before it is possible
                to escape from these evils...</q>"</p>
        <p>"<q who="DRYGE">The means I speak of, the only possible means by which the virtue and
                progress of mankind are rendered possible, is preventive sexual
            intercourse.</q>"</p>
        <p>"<q who="DRYGE">By this is meant sexual intercourse, where precautions are used to
                prevent impregnation. In this way love would be obtained without entailing upon us
                the want of food and leisure by overcrowding the population.</q>"</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
