<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2001-11-19 CN</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2002-08-29 KH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/07 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007-05-31 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011/03/11 CH Entered corrections suggested by Andy Carloff.</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-12 CH clean errros and regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1914-06-00">Jun 1914</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Mary, Mother Mary</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp420001</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">The Woman Rebel</title>, Vol. 1, No. 4, June 1914, 32</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title>, C16:0546</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
        <index level1="child labor"/>
        <index level1="birth control"/>
        <index level1="working classes" level2="women and girls"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Mary, Mother Mary </head>
        <p><person reg="Minora, Mary">Mary Minora</person> is 14 years old. She has a baby three or
            four months old. For the past ten months she has been earning sixty cents a day--working
            from eight in the morning until nine at night--as a finisher on trousers. Her mother, a
            woman in her thirties, earns seventy cents a day. The husbands of Mary and her mother
            have been of the unemployed of <place reg="New York, NY">New York City</place>. Mary had
            to work hard during her pregnancy to help support husband and father and little brother.
            These facts were brought out at the recent investigation by the federal <org>Commission
                on Industrial Relations</org>. The evidence in full will be printed in the bulky
            report of this benign commission, along with several more volumes of similar edifying
            testimony. Mary and her mother will go on finishing trousers. Mary will have more
            children. The Government Commission will go on investigating--oh, so many highly
            interesting labor situations! And the Government will try to suppress as obscene all of
            us who teach birth-control. That, you see, might interrupt this process of creating
            generation after generation of cheap labor for the manufacturers of shoddy
            trousers--generations of women chained to Misery by enforced maternity.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
