<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2001-11-13 MH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2002-08-29 KH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/07 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007-05-31 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-05 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1914-05-00">May 1914</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>"<title>The Menace's</title>" Advice</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp420010</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">The Woman Rebel</title>, Vol. 1, No. 3, May 1914, 23</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Collected Documents Series</title> C16:0537</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="WESWA">The Western Watchman</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
        <index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="freedom and rights of"/>
        <index level1="Catholic Church"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>"<title>THE MENACE'S</title>" ADVICE</head>
        <p>The <title type="journal">Western Watchman</title> (Catholic) says, according to <title
                type="article">The Menace</title>: "<q who="WESWA">We say, a young girl's business
                is to get a husband. Having got a husband, it is her business to beget children.
                Under ordinary conditions of health a young wife ought to have a child in her arms
                or on her bosom all the time. When she is not nursing a child she should be carrying
                one. This will give her plenty to do, and she will have no time for political
                meetings or movements.</q>"</p>
        <p>How do the women like that program for a life vocation? According to this authority a
            woman is to look upon herself merely as a vehicle for the breeding of children. Her mind
            is of no consequence, her body is the main thing. The feminine business is to get a
            husband, and then to get children as fast as time will permit. This <person
                reg="Unknown">editor</person> would not even give her the protection that is
            bestowed upon cattle; "<q who="UNK">when she is not nursing a child she should be
                carrying one</q>." The home of such a couple instead of being a place of comfort and
            refinement, with food for the mind and the amenities of social life is to be a rabbit
            warren, a sty filled with anemic, undeveloped children whose mother is compelled to work
            over the washtub or in some sweatshop up to the time of her delivery, and then drag
            herself back to the slavery of toil as soon as she is able to crawl, with the assurance
            that she has already started on the road for a repetition of the dutiful event, and so
            continue until she drops into the grave the victim of man's distorted and perverted
            sense of duty. Out upon such a theory! The man is a degenerate who makes such a specious
            argument. For the protection of the female sex, let her be taught how to defend herself
            against such teachings as these.</p>
        <p>Interest in "political meetings and movements" may induce women to <emph rend="bold"
                >think</emph> independently of the Catholic teachings--and in thus thinking she will
            know that the <org reg="Roman Catholic Church">Catholic Church</org> is one of the
            greatest enemies against the achievement of her economic, intellectual and sexual
            independence.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
