<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2001-11-13 MH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2002-08-29 KH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2003/03/11 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/26 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007-05-30 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-05 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1914-04-00">Apr 1914</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Into the Valley of Death--For What?</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp420049</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">The Woman Rebel</title>, Vol. 1, No. 2, Apr. 1914, 12</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Collected Documents Series</title>
                C16:0526</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="SHICH">Shipley, Canon Charles</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="class-based"/>
        <index level1="working classes" level2="birth control and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>INTO THE VALLEY OF DEATH--FOR WHAT?</head>
        <p>Every woman who gives birth to a child goes down into the valley of death to do so.</p>
        <p>Very few of the thousands of women who become mothers every year do so because they
            desire a child, or because of their patriotism, or any other stupid reason, but because
            they have motherhood forced upon them through ignorance of its prevention. "<q
                who="SHICH">The nation lives in its children!</q>" shout the priests from the
            thrones of the powerful, and "<q who="UNK">the children of to-day are the society of
                tomorrow!</q>" echoes the philanthropist. Let us see how much they care about the
            child of to-morrow. The women of the rich do not produce children for the society of
            to-morrow. They call upon the working women--insist that she produce a future society so
            that they and their miserable few will have slaves to feed them. They know that as long
            as the working class bear children, this fact alone will keep it in poverty and usually
            in ignorance as well.</p>
        <p>Both physically and mentally the children of the rich are developed to the highest
            degree. Schools, colleges, universities are built for them. The children of the working
            class are developed only that profits may be wrung from them as early in life or as soon
            as the masters dare to. Thousands of them have no school privileges, thousands more with
            only part time at school. Nine million little ones under fifteen years of age were at
            work as breadwinners in 1900. One million defectives fill the hospitals and charitable
            institutions. Reformatories and juvenile asylums are full to overflowing most of the
            time. Hospitals, insane asylums, jails and poor houses, old people's homes--these are
            the refuges for the children of the working class.</p>
        <p>If all the children could be gathered together from the orphanages, jails and
            reformatories, together with the crippled and feeble-minded, the child victims of the
            cotton and silk mills and the sweated home industries, this huge army of little victims
            would open the eyes of the working woman to the realization that she must take the
            matter into her own hands and decide whether she wants to add to this number of
            unfortunates. This realization will force her to the greatest revolt of the ages--the
            revolt against introducing into the world another class of human beings to be starved,
            crippled and maimed for the masters.</p>
        <p>The <place>United States</place> is the richest country in the world. Its industries are
            not so important that children should be murdered to keep them running. If it were a
            young country, toppling over under the stress of wars and famines, there might be some
            excuse for this outrage against unprotected childhood. As it is, the only explanation is
            the greedy desire for profit.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
