<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2001-12-03 MH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2002-08-29 KH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2004/07/20 CH</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2007-05-31 CH Oxygen update</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2011-11-02 EK correct transcriptions and index</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-26 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1914-07-00">Jul 1914</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Editorial on "The Militants in England"</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp420029</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">The Woman Rebel</title>, Vol. 1, No. 5, July 1914, 35</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm</title> C16:549</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote>
        <p>For initial article, see "The Militants in England,"<xref from="420005.xml"> June
                1914</xref>.</p>
        <index level1="anarchism and anarchists"/>
        <index level1="Witcop, Rose"/>
        <index level1="England" level2="militants in"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="freedom and rights of"/>
        <index level1="sex reform"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>MILITANTS IN ENGLAND</head>
        <p>On another page of this paper appears a letter from our English Comrade, <person
                reg="Witcop, Rose">Rose Witcop</person>, in answer to an article in the June issue
            on "<title type="article">The Militants in England</title>."</p>
        <p>In reply to this letter I would point out that the sympathy and admiration I have shown
            for the Militants is not because of petty persecutions they have suffered, but in their
            revolt against sex subjugation, and their militant, courageous attitude in demanding the
            vote, not because it is necessarily a weapon against sex subjugation. They demand this
            recognition of the principal of political equality because it has been denied them by
            men on account of sex.</p>
        <p>Conflicting views held by the Militants as to the utility of political action, socialism,
            anarchism, free love, etc., have really little to do with the issue, which is
            essentially a revolt of a few women against an age long sex subjugation.</p>
        <p>What will come out of militancy will not be reflected in the attainment of the right to
            vote but in the control and freedom women will obtain over their bodies. To the extent
            that militancy succeeds in arousing "married" women to a realization of their
            subservience and implants in them and their children the ideal of a new erotic ethic, to
            that extent will militancy in <place>England</place> have shown itself to be a
            revolution. That the militants in England are doing this, consciously or unconsciously,
            is unquestionable, and the most daring of them have been impelled to action by outraged
            feelings which have awakened their womanhood and inspired them with an extraordinary and
            amazing courage.</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
