<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2013/12/18 JK encoded</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-11-10 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-12-15 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1917-02-05">
            <supplied resp="MSPP">5 Feb 1917</supplied>
        </docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>
                <supplied resp="MSPP">Remarks from the Raymond St. Jail</supplied>
            </titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421006</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Liberty Scorned By Mrs. Sanger</title>, <title
                    type="journal">New York Tribune</title>, Feb. 6, 1917, 9. </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="NYT">New York Tribune</name>
            <name id="FREJO">Freschi, John</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>The following article quotes Sanger's remarks made during her trial for opening the <org
                reg="Brownsville Clinic">Brownsville birth control clinic</org>.</p>
        <index level1="jails and imprisonment" level2="Blackwell's Island Workhouse (New York)"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="arrests"/>
        <index level1="Brownsville Clinic" level2="arrests and trial"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Liberty Scorned By Mrs. Sanger</head>
        <head type="sub">She Prefers Thirty Days on Island to Justices' Clemency Offer</head>
        <p>
            <q who="NYT"><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Mrs. Margaret Sanger</person> was confronted
                in the <org reg="Kings County, NY, Court of Special Sessions">Court of Special
                    Sessions</org>, <place reg="Brooklyn, NY">Brooklyn,</place> yesterday with the
                choice of spending thirty days on <org>Blackwell’s Island</org> or of promising
                hereafter to observe the law in her campaign for the legalization of birth control.
                She turned her back upon the offer made by Justices <person reg="Freschi, John"
                    >Freschi</person>, <person reg="O'Keefe, George">O’Keefe</person> and <person
                    reg="Hermann, Moses">Herman</person>, and replied calmly:</q> “I cannot respect
            the law as it stands to-day.” <q who="NYT">Then she was sentenced for maintaining her
                birth control clinic at 45 Amboy Street, Brooklyn, and left the courtroom to serve
                her time. She will not go on a hunger strike.</q> “So far as I am concerned,” <q
                who="NYT">said Mrs. Sanger in <org reg="Raymond Street Jail">Raymond Street
                    jail</org>,</q> “I have accomplished as much as is possible at this time. We
            have aroused public opinion and created and agitation which will bear fruit. I shall
            submit to finger-printing, if that is necessary, and I intend to obey all workhouse
            regulations. What do trifles like that matter when you are working for a great cause? “I
            am happier than if I had been acquitted. Expecting to be sentenced, I came all
            prepared.” <q who="NYT">Mrs. Sanger then showed two books which are to be her companions
                for the next month-- '<title type="book">Julius Lavallon</title>,' by <person
                    reg="Blackwood, Algernon">Algernon Blackwood</person>, and '<title type="book"
                    >Lessons in Truth</title>,' by <person reg="Cady, Harriet Emil">H. Emil
                    Cady</person>.</q> “I intend to study prison conditions while I am in the
            workhouse and shall make a report upon my release,” Mrs. Sanger resumed. “It is also my
            intention to carry on my work not only after I am released, but while I am doing my bit.
            “It was impossible for me to accept the offer of the court to suspend sentence. I could
            not promise to give up my life work. You cannot change the color of your soul any more
            than the color of your eyes.” <q who="NYT">Before sentencing Mrs. Sanger, Justice
                Freschi said:</q> "<q who="FREJO">If you promise faithfully to obey the law in
                future this court will exercise extreme clemency.</q>" “I will promise to obey the
            law pending the appeal of my case to a higher court,” <q who="NYT">Mrs. Sanger answered,
                later refusing to give an unqualified promise. When Mrs. Sanger was led from the
                courtroom to the prison van she headed a procession of eight handcuffed men. As they
                were about to leave the building one of her friends rushed up with a cup of coffee,
                which she hurriedly swallowed. A bundle of sandwiches shoved into her hands by
                another friend, were distributed among the men prisoners. Miss <person
                    reg="Mindell, Fania">Fannie Mindell</person>, who acted as interpreter at the
                Brownsville clinic, was fined $50. This was paid by Mrs. <person
                    reg="Pinchot, Gertrude">Amos Pinchot</person> on behalf of the <org>Committee of
                    One Hundred</org>.</q>
        </p>

    </docBody>
</doc>
