<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Interview">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2013/12/11 JK encoded</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-09-10 CH clean up</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1934-01-17"><supplied resp="MSPP">17 Jan 1934</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">"Interview with United Press"</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421059</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Congressional Birth Control Probe Starts</title>, <title
                    type="journal">Dunkirk Evening Observer</title>, Jan. 18, 1934</bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="DEO">Dunkirk Evening Observer</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><index level1="birth control" level2="population and"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="population growth in"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="overpopulation in"/>
        <index level1="United States Congress"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Congressional Birth Control Probe Starts</head>
        <head type="sub">Hearings Begin on Legislation Which <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret
                Sanger </person>Has Backed.</head>
        <p><q who="DEO">On the eve of the Congressional hearing, Mrs. Margaret Sanger, foremost
                champion of the movement, said to the <org>United Press</org>:</q> “In a period when
            we are permanently reconstructing our national economic order by regulation of industry,
            and the production of our basic necessities of life, it is even more important that we
            give attention to the control and proper distribution of our population. “It is an
            acknowledged fact that the big battalions of babies have made the workman’s life a
            constant battle to keep his productive labor powers up to the need of his reproductive
            powers. We also know that the revolution in modern industry has made the necessity for
            man-power of less value than the ox or dray horse. “Populations have been kept down in
            the past by keeping the death rate almost equal to the birth rate. The survival rate was
            very low, but it allowed for a healthy, fit population and enabled it to compete in the
            struggle for existence. “Today we have changed all this. We cannot allow disease,
            floods, and famine to spread over a civilized land. We must deal with our birth rate
            scientifically, as we have dealt with our other problems. “Science has been applied to
            the improvement or selection of every type of human activity, including the means of
            destruction in war, except to humanity itself. </p>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Already Control Population </head>
            <p> “We have already an element of population control in immigration restrictions which
                bar economically dependent or diseased persons. But we must go further. I predict
                that with the continuation of advance in machine production we will never again need
                the hordes of workers needed in the past and we must provide against the suffering
                of those who will thus be deprived of work. “We are seeking passage of Federal
                legislation which will permit physicians, hospitals and public health agencies to
                give out birth control information. This will automatically enable thousands of
                medical institutions to provide needed assistance for wives of unemployed men, as
                well as for overburdened mothers who cannot afford service of private physicians.”
                    <q who="DEO"> Mrs. Sanger said that more than 13,000 women die each year from
                    the results of criminal abortions alone, most of which might be avoided. The
                        <place>United States</place> Penal Code classes birth control with obscenity
                    and forbids the use of the mails for supplying information on the subject, or
                    any carrying agency to carry materials for birth control. The bill under
                    consideration would allow doctors these privileges.</q>
            </p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
