<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/01/17 CH first pass</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-11-10 CH cleanup regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1931-09-17"><supplied resp="MSPP">17 Sept 1931</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Call for a Moratorium on Babies</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421041</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">2-Year Holiday on Babies Urged by Mrs. Sanger</title>,
                    <title type="journal">New York Herald Tribune</title>, Sept. 18, 1931, 17.
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="NYHT">New York Herald Tribune</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Sanger made a statement to the <place reg="New York, NY">New
                York</place> press. No other versions found. </p>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="efforts to reduce"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="economic benefits and risks of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="class-based"/>
        <index level1="Great Depression"/>
        <index level1="working classes" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="upper classes" level2="birth control and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>2-Year Holiday on Babies Urged By Mrs. Sanger</head>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Birth Control Leader Calls for a Moratorium Until Unemployment is Past.
                For Rich and Poor Alike. Says Better Uses Can be Found for Money Now.</head>
            <p><q who="NYHT">A moratorium on birth -- </q>"No more babies for two years"<q
                    who="NYHT"> -- was proposed yesterday by Mrs. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret"
                        >Margaret Sanger</person>, leader of the birth control movement as one means
                    of meeting the economic crisis. Facing a winter of unemployment, parents should
                    not bring more children into the world, to complicate their own economic
                    problems and burden further the charitable institutions, she said.</q></p>
            <p><q who="NYHT">Returning from a vacation in the <place reg="Adirondack Mountains"
                        >Adirondacks</place> Mrs. Sanger found that the <org>Birth Control Clinical
                        Research Bureau</org>, 17 West Sixteenth Street, had received an unusually
                    large number of patients since September 1, of whom at least one-third were
                    women whose husbands were out of work.</q></p>
            <p>“No woman should have any more children this year or until the industrial situation
                has returned to normal,” <q who="NYHT">said the advocate of birth limitation.</q>
                “Every child that is born now will only add to the financial distress of the family,
                imperiling the health of the older children and adding a presumably ill-nourished
                and puny specimen of humanity to a world that is already overburdened with
                dependents. </p>
        </div>

        <div>
            <head type="sub"><q who="NYHT">Includes All Classes</q></head>
            <p>“This moratorium should apply not only to the very poor, but also to the well-to-do.
                This is a period of anxiety for the rich as well as the poor--perhaps of greater
                anxiety for them, as they are not so accustomed to financial insecurity. The poor
                have always a narrow margin between security and peril. They can endure the nervous
                strain of today better than some of those who actually have more money. Even in a
                well-to-do family a child would be better off not to be norn just now, while the
                mother is anxious and nervous. I am perfectly sure that a nervous mother’s condition
                is reflected in the child. There is no doubt about it. </p>
        </div>

        <div>
            <head type="sub"><q who="NYHT">Better Uses for Money Now</q></head>
            <p>“Moreover,” <q who="NYHT">she said,</q> “if a family has money there are better uses
                for it just now than in bringing more children into the world. It would be better to
                keep alive those we already have than to complicate the social structure by adding
                more.” </p>
            <p><q who="NYHT">Asked if a moratorium on births would not add to unemployment by
                    depriving doctors, nurses and manufacturers of infants’ wear of their normal
                    livelihood, Mrs. Sanger replied that they could find other sources of income
                    better than a family could find ways of supporting a child of
                unemployment.</q></p>
            <p>I<q who="NYHT">n order to meet the increased demand for birth control information in
                    the industrial crisis, Mrs. Sanger’s committee have decided to add a third
                    period to the hours when the clinic on West Sixteenth Street is open for
                    business.</q></p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
