<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">

    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/03/14 VS initial tagging</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/03/19 CH proof tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/03/26 VS</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1935-03-02">02 March, 1935</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Speech before the Indianapolis Jewish Association</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421068</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Birth Control Plea is Made</title><title type="journal">
                    Indianapolis Star, March 4, 1935</title></bibl>
            <bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, </title>S71:799</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="IS">The Indianapolis Star</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">No complete version of Sanger's talk to the Indianapolis Jewish Community
        Association at the Kirschbaum Community Center on March 2, 1935. For some draft notes used
        for the speech, see Margaret Sanger Microfilm S71:799. For other comments made before this
        meeting, see <xref from="421929.xml">Indianapolis Statement on Relief Agencies</xref>, March
        2, 1935. 
        <index level1="birth control" level2="and war"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="as a term"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="in marriages"/>
        <index level1="birth control methods" level2="safe period"/>
        <index level1="child spacing"/>
        <index level1="physicians" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="Soviet Union"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <div>
            <head>Birth Control Plea is Made</head>
            <byline>Mrs. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger</person> Urges Laws Be Amended to
                Permit Giving of Information</byline>
            <p>
                <q who="IS">Humanity has a horror greater than any single major catastrophe in the
                    day-after-day fear of unwanted pregnancy that exists in thousands of homes,
                    Margaret Sanger told the open forum of the <org>Jewish Community Center
                        Association</org> in the <org>Kirshbaum Community Center</org> last
                    night.</q></p>
            <p>
                <q who="IS">Speaking before one of the largest audiences in the history of the
                    forum, Mrs. Sanger pleaded for amendments to <name
                        reg="United States Penal Code">existing Federal laws</name> that would
                    permit dissemination of birth control information and allow physicians,
                    hospitals, and clinics not only to prescribe for women but to use the mails to
                    give information.</q></p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Bill Now Before Committees</head>
            <p>
                <q who="IS"><name type="law" reg="S. 600"><name type="law" reg="H.R. 2000">A
                            bill</name></name> to this end prepared by the <org>National Committee
                        on Federal Legislation for Birth Control</org>, with which Mrs. Sanger now
                    is connected, is before the <org
                        reg="United States House of Representatives Committee on the Judiciary"
                        >judiciary committee</org> in the <org reg="House of Representatives"
                        >House</org> and the <org reg="United States Senate">Senate</org>. Senator
                        <person reg="Van Nuys, Fredrick">Fredrick Van Nuys</person> voted against
                    the amendment in the <org reg="United States Senate, Judiciary Committee">Senate
                        judiciary committee</org>, Mrs. Sanger reported.</q></p>
            <p> “If a woman were to write me and ask for information about improving her cows or her
                chickens could forward the request to the <org
                    reg="United States Department of Agriculture">Department of Agriculture</org>
                and she would be showered with literature and suggestions,” Mrs. Sanger said. “But
                if I were to answer question about matters vitally affecting the well-being of her
                children and of herself, Federal law would make me liable for a fine of $5,000 and
                five years’ imprisonment.”</p>
            <p>
                <q who="IS">Mrs Sanger asserted that the medical profession should take the
                    responsibility of prescribing birth control methods. Successful prevention of
                    conception is as much an individual matter as the fitting of a pair of
                    spectacles, she said. She criticized the Federal administration’s handling of
                    the relief problem on the ground that the problem was being met
                    superficially.</q></p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Stresses Need for Quality</head>
            <p> “We’ll have to go back to the principle of raising the quality of life before we can
                hope for national security,” <q who="IS">she said.</q> “At present, 43 percent of
                the increase in population comes from families on relief. If, when we began our
                fight for birth control twenty years ago, we had received the support of labor
                organizations and those social and religious institutions organized to relieve
                misery, the dilemma of the mounting burdens on the shoulders of unemployed fathers
                would not face us today. We must face the fact that not for years in this country
                will everyone who is able to have the opportunity to sustain himself.”</p>
            <p>
                <q who="IS">Mrs. Sanger said she coined the term “birth control” in 1914. She listed
                    the following seven reasons for birth control derived from her investigations
                    since that time: (1) In cases where either parent has a transmissible disease;
                    (2) where the wife has an illness liable to serious aggravation by pregnancy, as
                    in tuberculosis, where four out of ever seven woman victims die from their
                    pregnancy rather than from the disease; (3) in families where children already
                    born have been subnormal; (4) for the spacing of children, at least three years
                    apart being recommended; (5) for adolescent married couples, who should not
                    become parents until they have attained maturity; (6) wherever the father is
                    unable to earn enough to support a family; and (7) as a means to the fulfillment
                    of companionship in marriage.</q></p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Elaborates on the 7th Point</head>
            <p>
                <q who="IS">Elaborating on the seventh point, Mrs. Sanger said that pregnancies that
                    begin with the honeymoon are unfair both to the wife and the husband.</q></p>
            <p> “The wife should not become pregnant until she has been married two years,” Mrs.
                Sanger said. “In that two years there is time for physical, spiritual and financial
                adjustment between the couple. There is an opportunity for the husband to know his
                wife as a woman, not as a potential mother. Too many have never been women at all.
                They have been girls until they were married and became mothers suddenly thereafter,
                without the opportunity to be and to express themselves.”</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Doubts “Rhythm Method.”</head>
            <p>
                <q who="IS">Responding to questions following the address Mrs. Sanger placed but
                    little reliance in the recently publicized “rhythm method” of birth control and
                    said that the method had not had the benefit of extensive research. She praised
                        <place>England</place> as the first nation to lay a foundation for true
                    birth control and said the British are more advanced than <place
                        reg="Soviet Union">Soviet Russia</place>. Russia, however, has lagged behind
                    in birth control work largely because of lack of supplies, she pointed out. She
                    denied that low-birth-rate nations would fall under the military attack of
                    high-birth-rate countries, asserting that the low-rate nations would muster
                    better fighting men.</q></p>
            <p>
                <q who="IS">About eleven hundred persons attended. Dr. <person reg="Segar, Louis H."
                        >Louis H. Segar</person> presided.</q></p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
