<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/02/19 JK initial tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-13 CH proof tags</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1936-02-19">19 Feb. 1936</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Interview Aboard the S.S.
                    Corfu</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421088</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>South China Morning Post</title> Feb. 19, 1936</bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="SCMP">South China Morning Post</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger</person> was
        interviewed on board the <ship>S.S. Corfu</ship> en route to <place
            reg="Hong Kong, China">Hong Kong</place>. The interview was
        published as "<title type="article">Birth Control</title>," <title
            type="journal">South China Morning Post</title>, February 20, 1936,
        and in the <title type="journal">Hongkong Telegraph</title> on the same
            date.<index level1="China" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="China" level2="birth rate in"/><index
            level1="population growth" level2="regulation of"/><index
            level1="population growth" level2="standard of living and"/><index
            level1="India" level2="birth control in"/><index
            level1="birth control" level2="in India"/><index
            level1="birth control"/><index level1="conferences"
            level2="All India Women's Conference" level3="1935-36 (10th)"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>BIRTH CONTROL.</head>
        <head type="sub">WORLD ADVOCATE NOW IN HONGKONG</head>
        <head type="sub">Margaret Sanger</head>
        <p><q who="SCMP">In an interview with a representative of the <org
                    reg="South China Morning Post">S.C.M. Post</org>, Mrs.
                Sanger said she was going back to the <place>United
                    States</place>, after a tour of India, via <place>China
                </place>and <place reg="Japan">Japan</place>. She was invited by
                the <org>All-India Women’s Conference</org> to address that
                great body when it met in <place reg="Travancore, India">
                    Travancore</place> in December last and to conduct a
                campaign for birth control throughout the country. At the
                Conference a resolution was passed in favour of birth control by
                a vote of 85 for and 25 against.</q> “I went to <place
                reg="India">India</place> not to persuade everybody to have a
            small family. I wanted rather to convince them of the desirability-
            for themselves and posterity- of having families of the right size
            and right quality. We all agree that healthy parents of good stock,
            and with an income that will support several children, should have
            them; and if they have normal instincts, will want to have them,”
            said Mrs. Sanger. </p>

        <div>
            <head type="Sub">Not Unknown to India</head>
            <p> “The practice of birth control is not unknown to India. But
                there, as in countries like <place>England </place>and America,
                it is still highly concentrated among the economically most
                prosperous and the educationally best endowed classes. So in my
                campaign I did not introduce into India views and a practice
                which did not, to some small extent, exist there already; but I
                hope I have produced a better distribution of birth control
                practices, that is to say to disseminate it among the social,
                economic and biological classes in which it is most urgently
                needed. “In my campaign in India I tried to show that the
                maternity and infant mortality rates in that country were a
                direct consequence of the present birth rates; that if we waned
                to lower the former we must lower the latter. I tried to show
                too that the low expectation of life in India was a consequence
                of the high birth rate, and could be raised by bringing that
                rate down. Above all it was my purpose to convince the Indian
                people that between the practice of birth control and their
                highest conception of ethics and religion there was no
                inconsistency whatsoever. “I consider that I had an overwhelming
                success in India, having delivered more than 65 addresses and
                traveling over 10,000 miles. I met most of the prominent men and
                women and was most cordially received by <person
                    reg="Gandhi, Mohandas K.">Mahatma Gandhi</person> and
                    <person reg="Tagore, Rabindranath">Dr. Tagore</person>, both
                of whom I visited for some days. Both of these great men agree
                that there must be some regulation of the family, especially
                among working people whose economic standard is low and whose
                earning power is insufficient to take care of a large family,”
                she added. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Visit to China</head>
            <p> “China has the same problem as India and other countries with
                thick populations-- to high a death rate and too rapid a growth
                in population,” she said. “A country can stand a good-sized
                population if it doesn’t grow too rapidly.” <q who="SCMP">The
                    establishment of clinics apart from hospitals, according to
                    Mrs. Sanger, was most essential.</q> “Thousands of women
                will go for social and economic reasons to clinics when they
                will not go to hospitals. They will go to hospitals only for
                sickness and disease. Outside clinics will take care of a large
                part of the population and save them from being sick.” </p>
            <p/>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
