<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-02-19 JK initial tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-02-27 CH proof tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-02-19 JK corrected tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-11-14 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1926-03-27">27 Mar 1926</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>
                <supplied resp="MSPP">War and Over-Population</supplied>
            </titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421074</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">20th Century Club Hears Mrs. Sanger</title>, <title
                    type="journal">Boston Globe</title>, Mar. 28, 1926, p. A13.</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="BG">Boston Globe</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>Sanger delivered this speech to the <org>Twentieth Century Club</org>, a women's social
            club, in <place reg="Buffalo, NY">Buffalo, New York</place>. The other speaker that
            night, Professor H. A. Overstreet, spoke on "What Shall we do with the Older
            Generation?" The summary of his remarks were not included.</p>
        <index level1="marriage"/>
        <index level1="overpopulation" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="overpopulation"/>
        <index level1="population growth"/>
        <index level1="population control" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="freedom and rights of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>20th Century Club Hears <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Mrs. Sanger</person></head>
        <head type="sub">'War and Over-Population' Topic of Lecture</head>
        <head type="sub">Prof. <person reg="Overstreet, Harry Allen">H. A. Overstreet</person> Discusses "The Older Generation"</head>
        <div>
            <p>There are two phases of the population question which concern the serious, scientific
                thought of the world--and one is the pressure of population on the food supply,
                which I will not attempt to take up here.</p>
            <p>
                <q who="BG">She then referred to the book by Professor <person
                        reg="East, Edward Murray">East</person>, <title type="book">"Mankind at the
                        Crossroads"</title>.</q>
            </p>
            <p> The other side of the problem concerns the reconciling humanitarianism with the
                races of men. There are two ways of controlling population--by increasing the death
                rate or decreasing the birth rate. We have increased the types of men in <place
                    reg="United States">America</place> and we no longer think of disease and the
                inroads of the feeble-minded as necessary to increase and multiply. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Cites Progress</head>
            <p>What does it mean in our time than in 1923 we spent $8,000,000 on the diseased and
                defectives, this being a function of public charity? Is that expenditure, to wipe
                out disease? It means that 10 years from now we will double the amount to be
                expended in the same cause.</p>
            <p> If we are as we consider ourselves really a very generous, big-hearted people, if we
                apply the same efficiency to clear up our conditions here, as we do in other
                matters, we should wipe out this condition in one generation. We establish milk
                stations, but we allow thousands of parents to remain in utter ignorance of the
                conditions of proper living. </p>
            <p>People with 10 children don’t want to be told how to raise additional children. The
                mothers of these much prefer to be told how to keep them alive without the coming of
                the extra 11th child. </p>
            <p>
                <q who="BG">The speaker opposed child labor outside the family.
                        <place>England</place>, <place>Japan</place>, <place>Italy</place>, and
                        <place>Australia</place> have great child labor and population problems.</q>
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Marriage Problems</head>
            <p><q who="BG">Mrs. Sanger then said that marriage should be preceded in all lands by
                    education as to motherhood and the control of child-bearing be given until
                    economic ways of preservation were fully studied and understood.</q> We want to
                have young married couples accorded a year or two after marriage just to play
                together and develop the cultural side of their relations. </p>
            <p>It is not an easy thing for men and women to live together now as they did 40 or 50
                years ago. We are trying to leave these young people to enjoy themselves; we are
                trying to recreate and build up new homes and we want to make women free. </p>
        </div>


    </docBody>
</doc>
