<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">

    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate> 2014-03-12 JK initial tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-19 CH proof tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-26>JK correct tags</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1934-11-23">23 Nov 1934</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Speech at the Santa Rita Hotel,
                    Tucson</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421058</idno>
        <sourceDesc>

            <bibl><title type="article">Margaret Sanger Addresses
                    Women</title>,<title type="journal">Tucson Daily
                    Citizen</title>, Nov. 23, 1934</bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="TDC">Tucson Daily Citizen</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><index level1="birth control" level2="in Arizona"
            /><index level1="overpopulation" level2="MS on"/><index
            level1="mortality rates" level2="infant"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="maternal"/><index
            level1="motherhood"/><index level1="United States"
            level2="overpopulation in"/><index level1="United States Congress"
            level2="MS on"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Margaret Sanger Addresses Women</head>
        <head type="sub">Urges Tucsonians To Forward Cause Of Birth Control In
            United States</head>
        <p><q who="TDC">Speaking before a group of women whose numbers taxed the
                catering resources of the Santa Rita hotel to the limit and
                whose personnel represented every woman’s organization of <place
                    reg="Tucson, AZ">Tucson</place>, Mrs. <person
                    reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person> urged her
                hearers to forward the cause of birth control in <place
                    reg="United States">America</place>. Mrs. <person
                    reg="Keddington, Iva M.">Iva M. Keddington</person>,
                president of the <org>Tucson Business and Professional Women’s
                    Club</org>, introduced the guest speaker. Stating that no
                question has so large a practical significance and at the same
                time cuts so deeply into the foundation of social evolution as
                birth control. she told of a law passed by Congress in 1873,
                forbidding any one to send books, pamphlets, letters or articles
                relating to the prevention of contraception through the
                    <place>United States</place> mail or by common carriers. She
                said, </q>“That law is still on the statute books. Our
                <org>committee on federal legislation for birth control</org> is
            trying to amend it, so that doctors and hospitals and public health
            clinics shall be able to instruct poor women, coming to these
            institutions for the medical care, in methods of scientific birth
            control. </p>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Mortality is High</head>
            <p>“Every day in the United States approximately 82 women die as a
                result of pregnancy, 560 infants die or are born dead, and 3,000
                pregnancies end in abortion-daily. “Every year in the United
                States there are 800,000 to 1,000,000 abortions and one
                pregnancy in every three ends in abortion; 200,000 infants are
                born dead. “The population of this country is approximately
                125.000.000 and according to the census, January, 1934, federal
                report, our population has increased 17 million from 1920 to
                1930. We have a birth rate of 17.3 per 1,000 population, or
                2,544,450 births a year, and our death rate is 10.9 per
                thousand, or 1,308,397 deaths in the same year. This is
                exclusive of <place reg="TX">Texas</place>. But we lose more out
                of these deaths, for 120,000 of these are children, infants
                under one year of age.” <q who="TDC">Going into another phase,
                    the speaker said that 12,500,000 persons were receiving
                    relief in the United States in January, 1934, according to
                    federal reports, and 42 per cent of these were children
                    under 16 years of age, and that large families, having six
                    or more children, were bearing a large proportion of the
                    hardships that come with unemployment distress.</q>
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Hypocrites Chided</head>
            <p><q who="TDC">Mrs. Sanger chided women who have advanced
                    themselves, many of them obtaining contraceptive information
                    and applying it in their own lives, who have developed their
                    own personalities and have controlled the size of their
                    families, and have condoned the pracice in public and have
                    not raised a voice or lifted a hand to help the millions of
                    other women to receive the same advice. She continued:
                </q>“One normal couple can, from the age of puberty and during
                their lifetime, be responsible for approximately 100 other
                lives. Every normal woman, during the period of child-bearing,
                can have from ten to fifteen children. “According to <person
                    reg="Myers, William Starr">William Starr Myers</person>,
                professor of history of <org>Princeton University</org>, who
                made a cross-section study of our population a few years ago, 85
                per cent can be classed as intellectuals. This, in my opinion,
                is why we have such a chaotic condition in legislative enactment
                today, and why there is such confusion and inability on the part
                of our congressmen and legislators to really advance the public
                good and the cause of civilization."</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Could Lessen Number of Criminals </head>
            <p> “Within 20 years we could wipe out the increase of these
                defective criminal classes if we would have public birth control
                clinics established, open our hospitals and dispensaries and
                maternity wards to the free access of women to the scientific
                knowledge as to how to prevent the birth of undesirable
                children. This would within 20 years relieve the taxpayer and
                the overburdened mother, and establish a foundation for a new
                civilization and a great nation.” <q who="TDC">Mrs. Sanger
                    quoted <person reg="Shaw, George Bernard">Bernard
                        Shaw</person> as saying that this is the most
                    revolutionary discovery of the twentieth century.</q> “There
                are 34 million women of child-bearing age in the United States,”
                she continued. “Twenty-six million of these women are married
                and these women are facing the helplessness of the future, many
                of them unemployed and handicapped physically or mentally to
                bear the burdens of child-bearing or to have a large family.
                “Less than one-third of our population has a controlled birth
                rate and that one-third is spending most of its energy and its
                efforts and giving its very life to help solve the problems that
                the unrestricted fertility of the other group is causing,” she
                asserted. “By that, I mean social workers, nurses, doctors,
                relief agencies and allied forces. They are dealing with the
                results and not with the causes, and we have got to get down to
                the facts and the causes, to the sources of our social problems,
                if we are going to really cure these social diseases.” She spoke
                of the fact that the majority of delinquent children come from
                large families, from overcrowded homes, with no place for them
                to play, with no direction to their activities. She said, “They
                soon find themselves in courts, with truant officers trying to
                keep them in schools, and they eventually end up as juvenile
                criminals. The institutions for the feebleminded and the insane
                are overcrowded, and too many of our legislators and governors
                are priding themselves, about election time, with the millions
                they have spent for such institutions, wasting the taxpayers’
                money in these palatial buildings, while none of us has
                challenged these statements and asked them what they are doing
                to relieve the taxpayer or diminishing the need for such useless
                expenditures.”</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> “Nothing Horrible Really Matters” </head>
            <p><q who="TDC"> Mrs. Sanger agrees with Bernard Shaw, she says,</q>
                “that nothing that is admittedly horrible really matters any
                more, because if it is only horrible enough it frightens people
                into seeking a remedy to prevent its happening again. “If an
                automobile falls over a cliff, if a building caves in and kills
                hundreds of people, all horrible catastrophes, we admit, but if
                these horrors arouse communities and nations out of their
                lethargy and indifference, if they bring improvements, if they
                bring groups together into closer realization and form that
                collective mind of humanity which adds to the community of world
                wisdom, then these have ennobled and advanced the spiritual
                progress of mankind. “But the real horrors and tragedies of our
                civilization are these, which happen every day, needles,
                useless, senseless, ceaseless, futile sufferings, which some
                good religious folks call 'natural,' which take place all around
                us, day after day, year after year, and are perpetuated from
                generation to generation. “I mean the suffering and the fear of
                undesired pregnancy of innocent women, too poor to defend
                themselves, too weak to rebel, too inarticulate to cry out.
                “These are the sufferings we are organized to eliminate-- these
                are the woman we are dedicated to defend.” </p>
        </div>

    </docBody>
</doc>
