<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014-12-04 CH encode</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-09 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1924-04-00">Apr 1924</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>Margaret Sanger's Own Corner</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp431034</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title>, Apr. 1924, p. 108</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>The <title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title> published a series of letters
			written to Margaret Sanger with occasional commentary. For others in this series see
			Margaret Sanger's Own Corner, <xref from="421032.xml">Jan. 1924</xref>, <xref
				from="421033.xml">Feb. 1924</xref>, <xref from="301463.xml">Mar. 1924</xref>, <xref
				from="421009.xml">May 1924</xref>, and <xref from="421010.xml">June 1924</xref>.</p>
		<index level1="client letters"/>
		<index level1="working classes" level2="birth control and"/>
		<index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
		<index level1="men" level2="birth control and"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>MARGARET SANGER'S OWN CORNER</head>
		<div type="section">
			<q who="UNK">
				<salute>Dear Mrs Sanger</salute></q>
			<p><q who="UNK">I have intended for some time to write to you, and thank you for the
					freedom I feel I owe you. I now enjoy motherhood fuller and better because I
					know, with just an ordinarily amount of common sense applied, you can control
					it, and that takes away the “can’t help yourself” feeling. Oh, it is so good to
					feel that you are master of situations. You can give little outgrown things to
					some other baby and not think, “Will I need that for my next one?”</q>
			</p>
			<p><q who="UNK">I know you get thousands of letters from grateful women, but I can’t
					help taking a little more of your time to thank you, as it has been just a year
					since I wrote my letter of appeal to you. And if I hadn’t written, and if events
					had transpired as usual, I would have been over half-way in another
					pregnancy.</q>
			</p>
			<p><q who="UNK">We were careful in a way, but the <name type="deity">Lord</name> only
					knows how ignorant we were about the real facts about these human bodies of
					ours.</q>
			</p>
			<p><q who="UNK">My three kiddies are fine, healthy children and I expect to put the
					proper ideas into them about Birth Control as soon as they are responsible
					enough.</q>
			</p>
			<p><q who="UNK">Now I don’t think that I have reaped the benefit and sat down. I agitate
					Birth Control every time there’s half an opportunity, and I assure you I meet
					warm approval from nearly every one. I wish there was some way I could really
					help the cause in a big way I know I have helped my little circle of friends,
					but I “Kinder” feel that I have reneged you. I have given subscription blanks
					and passed my paper, but that’s about the limit of my efforts, and, yes, I do
					get so much mental food out of the paper and I am glad to see your little
					“Corner” start, too.</q>
			</p>
			<p><q who="UNK">Mrs. Sanger, we all write to you with the absolute certainty that you’ll
					give all of our letters your individual attention, when that is an
					impossibility, isn’t it? However, I’d like your “secretary person” to say to you
					that “I thank you” anyway.</q>
			</p>
			<q who="UNK"><signed><person reg="Unknown">B M McM</person>,
					<place>Louisana</place></signed></q>

		</div>
		<div>
			<p>Every day we receive hundreds of letters full of pain and sorrow and difficulties. It
				is certainly a joy now and again to find one full of happiness and content, and to
				feel that is Birth Control that that has changed the life of at least one woman from
				uncertainty and dread to joy and confidence. The writer may feel assured that her
				letter reached my eyes, and that I am grateful to her for writing it. <person
					reg="Sanger, Margaret">M S</person>
			</p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<q who="UNK">
				<salute> Dear Madam </salute></q>
			<p><q who="UNK"> I am 36 and about to be married to a fine woman of 31 with her own
					farm. Both of us are fine specimens. If I bring her with child each two years
					until her change of life, would that be fair enough, provided everything else is
					looking bright? I love children, so does she, and we both think a lot of each
					other. Or how would you suggest? But if those able to have them won’t, then
					where is the country going to?</q></p>

		</div>
		<div>
			<p> Two years is rather short as an interval between babies. Few women are able to
				recuperate thoroughly in this time, especially if they have already had several
				children, and no mother should be called upon to bear another child until she has
				fully regained her health from her last pregnancy and childbirth. Also in planning
				for your family–which, according to your estimate, might consist of from eight to
				ten children–economic conditions must be taken into consideration. Will you be able
				to educate and to start in life all these children? Will each one, both boy and
				girl, be able to find opportunity for a start in life? I take it that your wife will
				be in full accord with you as regards the number of children, for childbirth is a
				woman’s question first of all, and no woman should be forced to bear children
				unwillingly. Perhaps after you have had the third or fourth you will both decide
				that you have done your duty. </p>
			<p> M S</p>

		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
