<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Interview">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2013/12/11 JK encoded</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-09-10 CH clean up</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1932-02-28">28 Feb 1932</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Interview with the Charleston Gazette</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421072</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Interview Given by Mrs. Sanger</title>, <title
                    type="journal">Charleston Gazette</title> Feb. 28, 1932</bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="CG">Charleston Gazette</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="awards"/>
        <index level1="sex education"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
        <index level1="overpopulation" level2="MS on"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Interview Given by Mrs. Sanger</head>
        <head type="sub">Says Efforts to Spread Ideas in Charleston Fairly Successful</head>
        <p><q who="CG">Although the number of Charleston’s citizens attending the lectures of Mrs.
                    <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger,</person> secretary for <org
                    reg="National Committee for Federal Legislation on Birth Control"> commission
                    for federal legislation on birth control</org>, were not as large as in a number
                of other cities, Mrs. Sanger feels that they </q>“made up in quality what they
            lacked in quantity,” <q who="CG">she said when interviewed yesterday at the <org
                    reg="Daniel Boone Hotel">Daniel Boone hotel</org>. The lecturer believes that
                her attempts to bring practical knowledge of birth control to the public have been
                fairly successful in <place reg="Charleston, SC">Charleston</place> and the outlying
                vicinity. Mrs. Sanger gave a lecture at the <org
                    reg="Thomas Jefferson Junior High School">Thomas Jefferson junior high
                    school</org> building Friday afternoon, one of a series of lectures she is
                giving throughout the <place>United States</place> in behalf of the commission for federal
                legislation for birth control. They keynote of Mrs. Sanger’s drive is to bring about
                the amending of federal laws to conform with state laws so that they will not
                interfere with the distribution of scientific information in the respective states.
                Visits made to outlying mining towns near Charleston have shown that the persons in
                those districts as well as those living in the city are anxious for scientific
                knowledge concerning birth control. Mrs. Sanger has made plans to send literature to
                these persons and do all in her power to bring about the cooperation of county and
                city health officials in relieving the existing conditions. The lack of laws
                adjusted so as to cover the needs of birth control, she said, has brought about many
                undesirable conditions throughout the United States. Women are being
                completely broken in health, she said, from too frequent child bearing. Fathers of
                such large families find themselves unable to bear the burden of support. Instead of
                being a privilege, as Mrs. Sanger believes parenthood should be, it becomes a curse.
                If proper information were within reach of the poorer classes their children might
                be fewer in number, worth more to society, and less of a burden. This information
                should not be shouted from the street corners or housetops but should be in the
                hands of well trained clinics and nurses. Mrs. Sanger first became interested in the
                birth control movement upon her return from <place reg="Netherlands">Holland</place>
                where she spent one year as a student under eminent physicians. Mrs. Sanger opened a
                    <org reg="Brownsville Clinic">clinic</org> in <place reg="New York, NY">New
                    York city</place> in 1917, within ten days over 800 women of all classes sought
                instructions and information. This clinic was closed by the <org
                    reg="New York City Police Department">New York police</org>. It was reopened in
                1918. There are more than one hundred such clinics throughout the United States at
                this time. Mrs. Sanger will be presented with a medal by <org
                    reg="American Woman's Association">Forty Business and Professional Women’s
                    clubs</org> in New York city this April. This medal is awarded to a woman who
                has achieved “the most in vision, integrity, and courage.” The lecturer’s latest
                book is entitled <title type="book">“My Fight for Birth Control.”</title></q>
        </p>


    </docBody>
</doc>
