<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2013-11-30 JK transcription</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-12-16 CH encode</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-07 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1921-02-03">3 Feb 1921</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Speech to the Philadelphia Women's Economic Club</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp421028</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Woman Would Kill Starving Children</title>, <title
					type="journal">Philadelphia Inquirer</title>, Feb. 4, 1921</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="PI">Philadelphia Inquirer</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>The following is a news summary of a speech Sanger gave at the Bellevue-Stratford Hotel
			in <place reg="Philadelphia, PA">Philadelphia</place>.</p>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="economic benefits and risks of"/>
		<index level1="charity" level2="MS on"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>WOMAN WOULD KILL STARVING CHILDREN</head>
		<head type="sub">Chloroform Instead of Food Best Thing, Declares Mrs. Sanger</head>
		<p> “If, instead of contributing $23,000,000 to feed the starving children of
				<place>Europe</place>, the people of the <place>United States</place> would send
			over a quantity of chloroform to put them out of their misery, it would be ‘the best
			thing for the children and for the future of the world.’” </p>
		<q who="PI">
			<p>This was the startling opinion expressed last night by Mrs. Margaret Sanger, of
					<place reg="New York, NY">New York</place>, and enthusiastically applauded by
				the men and women who attended the dinner given in her honor at the <org
					reg="Bellevue-Stratford Hotel">Bellevue-Stratford</org>, under the auspices of
				the <org>Woman's Economic Club</org>. Mrs. Sanger will speak tonight at the <org>New
					Century Club</org> on the subject of "Birth Control and the Coming Race."</p>
		</q>
		<p> “The great responsibility for the future of the world,” <q who="PI">the lecturer
				declared,</q> “rests upon the shoulders of the women. Diplomats may make treaties of
			peace, but as long as women continue to breed an explosive population they will
			transform these agreements into scraps of paper. You cannot reconstruct the world and
			make a universal peace without reckoning with women.”</p>
		<q who="PI">
			<p>Mrs. Sanger strongly urged that the women of this country unite to demmand the repeal
				of the Federal and State laws forbidding the dissemination of birth control
				knowledge, declaring that in this respect <place>Germany</place> and other countries
				are far ahead.</p>
		</q>
		<p> “We are the only civilized nation in the world,” <q who="PI">she asserted,</q> “that
			classes the subject with obscenity and relegates it to the gutter.”</p>
		<p> “The whole woman’s movement in America,” <q who="PI">she continued,</q> “is
			over-sentimental.”</p>
		<p> “The woman of today is exceedingly generous and tender-hearted. but she is inclined
			toward alleviation of the problems that confront her, rather than prevention and cure.
			Take, for instance, the matter of the various maternity bills to which she is devoting
			so much attention at present. Throwing a few pensions to mothers is not going to make a
			better race; it merely temporarily alleviates conditions. What is really wanted is some
			action that will strike at the root of the matter, and this can only be done by
			eliminating the physically and morally unfit from the world.”</p>
		<p> “When the world’s population,” <q who="PI"> she continued, </q> “is decreased to such an
			extent that those left will be able to develop themselves into the best, we will have a
			race of supermen and superwomen, and all the problems before us today will be
			automatically solved. We can never legislate them out of existence, because they are
			fundamental in society, but when the over-burdened mother is over-burdened no longer,
			then there will be no economic question, either.” </p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
