<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014-07-20 JK transcribe</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-28 CH encode</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-02-04 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1929-02-00">Feb 1929</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>Havelock Ellis</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp421029</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Editorial</title>, <title type="journal">Birth Control
					Review</title>, Feb. 1929, pp.37-38</bibl>

		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="ZWEST">Zweig, Stefan</name>
			<name id="PETHO">Peterson, Houston</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<index level1="Ellis, Havelock" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="religion" level2="MS on"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Havelock Ellis</head>
		<p>“<q who="ZWEST">Our generation does not look for saints who are regarded as messengers
				from a superhuman realm, but for saints whom it can honor as the most human of
				men</q>.” So declares <person reg="Zweig, Stefan">Stefan Zweig</person>, whose
			illuminating studies of <person reg="Tolstoy, Leo">Tolstoy</person>, <person
				reg="Casanova, Giacamo">Casanova</person>, and <person>Stendahl</person> have
			recently been published in <place reg="United States">this country</place>. It might be
			nearer the truth to say that our generation does not look for saints at all. Confronted
			with a saint, how many of this twentieth century would recognize him? How many have? In
			active and violent revolt against traditional and orthodox religion, we have developed a
			phobia for all things that even suggest the old religion--even its vocabulary. “Saint”
			or “saintliness” are words in bad odor with us. They mean somebody or something
			excessively--or even hypothetically--sanctimonious. For the majority of the younger
			generation the “saint” connotes a holy man or woman untouched by the problems or the
			sufferings of our workaday world. But there are certain heroic lives, certain giants of
			the spirit, a few radiant personalities today whose example compels us to resort to the
			now discarded vocabulary of primitive religion. Certain men we can only adequately
			characterize as saints. <person reg="Ellis, Havelock">Havelock Ellis</person> is one--
			to me the foremost-- of these contemporary saints. </p>
		<p>What is a saint? How can we define a saint without evoking the symbols or the images of
			institutional religion? “<q who="ZWEST">When we talk of a life as saintly,</q>” declares
			Stefan Zweig, “<q who="ZWEST">we mean that it is heroical in the sense of entire
				devotion to a religiously conceived ideal.</q>” I am not quite satisfied with that
			word “religiously.” It confuses rather than clarifies. I would rather define the saint
			as one who radiates spiritual truth and energy. I see him living in a realm above and
			beyond the shouting and the tumult of the day’s “news.” Current events do not trouble
			him. Captains and kings come and go. Lilliputian warriors strut their hour upon the
			world stage, and boundary lines between nations are made and unmade. The saint takes no
			active part in this external trafficking. Yet he does not swell apart in an ivory tower
			of his own construction.</p>
		<p>Detached as he seems to be from the pain and suffering of our workaday world, Havelock
			Ellis has penetrated profoundly into the persistent problems of the human race. Nothing
			human is alien to his sympathy and charity. The knowledge of this saint is broad and
			deep, his wisdom is even deeper. He makes no strident, blatant effort to shout out his
			method to the world. He makes no rash promises of eternal salvation or happiness. But
			gradually, and in ever-increasing numbers, men and women pause to listen to his serene
			voice. There is indeed something miraculous in the manner in which men and women in all
			parts of our world have stopped to “listen in” to the voice of Havelock Ellis. Here is a
			phenomenon far more amazing than the achievements of radio-activity. Despite all the
			obstacles and obstructions that have hindered his expression, his truth has filtered
			through to the minds ready to receive it. It is not the place here to attempt to define
			his “message”--if indeed there can be said to be any definite “message,” other than that
			of life more abundant, attained through a more complete understanding of ourselves and
			unruffled charity toward all the variations of which this all-too-human race has
			demonstrated itself capable. Ellis is much more than a “<q who="PETHO">philosopher of
				love</q>,” as he was described by <person reg="Peterson, Houston">Houston
				Peterson</person> in the biography published last year. He is more than a
			psychologist preoccupied with probing into sexual abnormalities. Like <person
				reg="Assisi, Francis of (St.)">Francis of Assisi</person> he has opened the eyes of
			the spirit to new and heretofore ignored aspects of life. Saint Francis has been
			acclaimed as the real father of Italian art--he taught men the beauty of external
			nature, of his brother the sun and his sister the moon, of animal life and all the
			pageantry of the passing seasons.</p>
		<p>To Havelock Ellis more than any other contemporary, we owe our concept of that kingdom of
				<name type="deity">God</name> which is really within us, that inner world which
			hides all our inherent potentialities for joy as well as suffering. Thanks to his serene
			and heroic assertion of fundamental truths, we realize today, as never before in the
			history of humanity, that happiness must be the fruit of our own activity, our own
			attitude towards life, and that it is in no way dependent upon the wards of the fights
			of external fortune. This spiritual energy which Havelock Ellis has for so many years
			radiated is thus a merciful, beneficent, and, above all, a fertile and life-giving
			force.</p>
		<p>Like Saint Francis of Assisi, Havelock Ellis has awakened us to a new life and a new
			world. We can never--even if by some inexplicable stubbornness we would--turn back into
			that cabined and confined world in which at the beginning of his career, he found
			himself, and which by the quiet and progressive assertion of his own values, he has done
			so much to dissolve. The truth is that since the world recognition of Havelock Ellis, we
			are all different people today. Unafraid and alone, he was one of the first to strike
			boldly as a pioneer into an uncharted jungle of human nature. Anyone less than saint
			would have fallen. Havelock Ellis not only penetrated unharmed through that purgatory,
			but has led the rest of us with him. Taboos have been destroyed. Fears have vanished.
			And even though practically everything still remains to be done of the vast labors of
			the twentieth century <person>Hercules</person>, we have the example of this modern
			saint to encourage and to inspire us for decades to come.</p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
