<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2013-11-30 JK transcribed</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-12-16 CH encoded</prepDate><prepDate>2015-01-07 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1921-01-03">3 Jan 1921</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">What Every Man Should Know</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp421026</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Short Skirts Help Morals</title>, <title type="journal"
					>Kansas City Star</title>, Jan. 3, 1921</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="KCS">Kansas City Star</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>For a draft version, see "What Every Man Should Know," Dec. 26, 1920 (MSM S70:877). This
			article was also published in the <title type="journal">Milwaukee Journal</title>.</p>
		<index level1="men" level2="sexuality of"/>
		<index level1="sexuality" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="women" level2="sexuality and"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>"SHORT SKIRTS HELP MORALS".</head>
		<head type="sub">Feminist Says It Has Removed the Lure of Draperies.</head>
		<q who="KCS">
			<p><dateline><place reg="New York, NY">New York--</place></dateline> Take it from a
				woman who ought to know, these diaphanous gowns, low-necked dresses and knee-length
				skirts displayed by the fairer sex haven't led the poor, harrassed, male astray.
				Perish the thoughts!</p>
		</q>
		<p><q who="KCS">The answer? Why these feminine fashions have actually raised the standards
				of morality among men. So says Margaret E. Sanger, feminist and birth control
				addvocate of the most "modern school"--and Mrs. Sanger professes to know. She said
				as much in delivering what she termed her</q> "most intimate lecture to men."<q
				who="KCS"> She spoke on "What Every Man Should Know."</q>
		</p>
		<p> “Woman’s dress hasn’t aroused the worst in men,” <q who="KCS">she declared.</q> “It has
			removed the lure of draperies. Woman has moved toward a higher plane of morality,
			because she is accustoming man to view her as she is.</p>
		<p> “Down on the beach where the girls are barelegged there isn’t half the mischief brewing
			in the minds of men spectators as in the heads of chaps who used to hang about the drug
			store corners waiting for a puff of wind. At the beach bare legs are taken for granted.
			Now that women are wearing knee-length skirts on the streets men will soon take for
			granted also what used to tempt them on drug store corners.” </p>
		<q who="KCS"><p> Belief that woman resorts to abbreviated costumes to arouse man is all wrong, according
			to Mrs. Sanger. She believes it the natural reaction for morals to be raised when necks
			are lowered. </p></q>
		<p> “It would be impossible,” <q who="KCS">she said,</q> “to go into every phase of what men should know--
			especially about women.”</p>
		<p> “Man can never know the secret emotions of woman. It is high time they should know how
			woman approaches the mystery of her calling.” </p>
		<q who="KCS">
			<p> Mrs. Sanger is the mother of two boys. </p>
		</q>
	</docBody>
</doc>
