<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2011/07/29 RT Initial Tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2012/03/28 CH proofed tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-08 EK clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1928-03-00"><supplied resp="MSPP">March 1928</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>What Margaret Sanger Thinks About Marriage</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421000</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Homecrofter</title> Mar-Apr. 10:5 1928, pp. 4-5</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp>
                <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
            </resp>

            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>The article begins with the following introduction: "<q><person
                    reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person> in her book, "<title type="book"
                    >Happiness in Marriage</title>," gives for its purpose the proper education of
                all those young people who are about to enter matrimony and of all those who are
                married, but who, because of ignorance in the beginning of their matrimonial career,
                have done considerable mischief by almost destroying the happiness which should
                continue through the married state.</q>"</p>
        <index level1="marriage" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="love" level2="concept of"/>
        <index level1="love" level2="and sex"/>
        <index level1="sex education"/>
        <index level1="men" level2="sexual fulfillment of"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="sexual fulfillment of"/>
        <index level1="sex" level2="and marriage"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>What Margaret Sanger Thinks About Marriage</head>
        <div>
            <p><emph rend="italics">Here is an enlightening and thought-evoking article that any man
                    or woman can well afford to read.</emph></p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <p>"<q who="UNK">And so they were married and lived happily ever afterwards,</q>" quotes
                the authoress. Such is the conventional ending of most love stories. In life,
                however, the real love story does not end with marriage. It begins with it.
                Happiness is not the inevitable consequence of marriage. Marriage does not
                necessarily create happiness. Too often it destroys it. If husband and wife are to
                live joyously together, they must create their own happiness. Most people agree that
                happiness in marriage is often the exception rather than the rule. It is not a prize
                guaranteed with every marriage certificate. Even though bride and bridegroom be
                romantically in love with each other they may find, after a few months of life
                together, that this mysterious reward has been witheld from them. They often
                discover that love is gradually fading. Marriage love died a long, lingering death.
                They awake to reality disillusioned, surprised to find themselves deprived of that
                abiding happiness they had expected.</p>
            <p>This tragedy of modern marriage is ususally the outgrowth of ignorance and
                misunderstanding. Happiness in marriage is not a matter of chance. It is a growth.
                Like all living and growing organisms, it must first germinate, then strike root,
                and then, after careful tending and cultivation, be brought to maturity. Only thus
                may it bloom and bear fruit. Sex attraction alone or the instinctive love of husband
                for wife and wife for husband is not enough. All these fine traits may enter into
                the marriage relationship, and yet, notwithstanding, martial happiness may be
                destroyed.</p>
            <p>Fear and ignorance are the greatest destroyers of love. Fear alone will often kill
                the happiness that is born of real love. Therefore, where marriage is bound by fear
                and ignorance, there can be no happiness. The first essential in the establishment
                of happiness in marriage is the uprooting of fear and the banishing of sex
                ignorance. When this is done the foundation of hapiness is laid.</p>
            <p>Let us not forget that ignorance and fear often assume the form of shame. Married
                love is possible when men and women have acquired a clean, healthy conception of
                sex, and through it a clean, wholesome fund of knowledge. In modern life,
                particularly in this country, the reproductive and sexual have been fenced off as
                mysterious facts, seperate and distinct from the other activities of every-day life.
                Modesty has defeated itself in prurience and prudery. For women to remain in
                ignorance concerning the most important phase of their nature was until a few years
                ago considered good taste. Even biologists of the past generation ignored the facts
                of reproduction and sex as not intricately and organically connected with the
                well-being of the individual and the race. Sex remained a deep, dark mystery, to be
                spoken of only in whispers, or not at all. This mystery was the cause of ignorance.
                Ignorance was the cause of disease and disease in its many forms was the cause of
                unhappiness and innumerable family tragedies.</p>
            <p>The cost of this shameful sentimentality is too great. We cannot afford to remain in
                ignorance. Our own personal health is at stake. The future well-being of the human
                race is at stake. We must learn to view sex life and sex love as sometimes other
                than physiological functions unrelated to the rest of our bodies and minds. Modern
                scientists are showing us that there is no part of our being that is not organically
                and intimately related to sex love and sex life.</p>
            <p>Romance based on ignorance cannot bear healthy fruit. In the past, when men and women
                were the victims of a huge conspiracy of silence concerning sex, experience was
                bought at a high cost. Young men were tacitly permitted to 'sow their wild oats';
                venereal scourges resulted. Tragic and widespread and destructive as syphilis and
                gonorrhea are, spiritual destruction is even worse. Promiscuity, prostitution and
                disease destroy, sometimes forever, a clean and reverent attitude toward the
                physical sex relation. Pre-marital promiscuity has created in man an attitude of
                ruthless selfishness. More than any other single factor this has been destructive of
                mutual happiness in the lives of married people.</p>
            <p>But women have, in the past, been too willing victims of this conspiracy of silence.
                Even today, with all our education, with all our organizations for social uplift,
                girls are brought up in absolute fatal ignorance of the true meaning of the sexual
                function. To their normal, healthy curiosity the only answer has been that the sex
                instinct is in some mysterious way a lewd, lascivious and unmentionable subject or
                too sacred and holy to mention.</p>
            <p>Marriage based on a young man's experience without knowledge and a girl's ignorance
                without experience is fore doomed to inevitable failure. If love survives despite
                such an initial handicap, improves its greatness. As a matter of fact few marriages
                do. Divorces, seperations, ruined lives, cynical husbands, hysterical wives,
                infidelities and all manner of family tragedies attest to the failure of the
                traditional approach to marriage. If they dared to give a frank answer, most men and
                women would tell you that love after marriage disappears and happiness is a
                gamble.</p>
            <p>For marriage built on the shifting sands of fear, shame and ignorance can never lead
                to happiness, yet if contracted with a frank recognition of the central importance
                of the beauty of sex in life, alike in its physiological, psychological and
                spiritual aspects, happiness becomes a glowing possibility. This is a buried
                treasure to be unearthed by true lovers. It may be imbedded in the rich soil of
                mutual respect and consideration. Carefully nutured, it will strike deep roots in
                both lives, entwine and unite them together in ever-growing joy. It will grow
                mature, bear fruit.</p>
            <p>Few as they are, marriages of this type are nevertheless possible. To such unions we
                must look for guidance. Participants in happy relationships of this type are
                creators in the truest sense. Their intimate experience becomes a guide for all to
                follow. All the world loves such lovers. These are the creative artists pointing the
                way to the spiritual awakening, that is possible to all men and women of the next
                generation, affecting all generations to come.</p>
            <p>Sex educators today insist upon the so-called single standard of morality. The
                'wild-oats' theory and its practice have proved ruinous. After years of effort, the
                educators have broken through the Chinese wall of silence erected by misguided
                prudery, and insist upon the necessity of purity and cleanliness of both parties in
                the marriage relation. This is undoubtedly a step in the right direction, but let us
                not delude ourselves into believing that the single standard is a cure-all and
                end-all of sexual difficulties.</p>
            <p>Such a practice may succeed in protecting our youth from the grosser evils of
                venereal infection and the dangers of promiscuity, but it does not touch the real
                problem of mating. No man or woman should leave to chance or the play of blind
                instinct, the most complex of all human ties. For even though young men and women
                bring to the marriage bed clean bodies and minds, they bring at the same time a lack
                of experience and understanding which may forever destroy the foundations of
                happiness. Even for those who believe the procreative act to be solely for the
                propagation of the race it would be necessary to master and guide and have knowledge
                of the powerful instinct of sex.</p>
            <p>Sex expression is not merely a propagative function, nor the satisfaction of an
                animal appetite. It should not be considered merely as a necessary evil preliminary
                to the production of a family. Sex expression, rightly understood, is the
                consummation of love, its completion and its consecration. Sex expression is an art.
                To become artists in love, men and women must learn to master and control the
                instruments by which the art is expressed.</p>
            <p>Until husband and wife have come to a realization of the necessity of complete union
                of the body and spirit, happiness cannot grow out of the marriage relation. This
                union is possible only when both have acquired mastery of the physical instruments
                of expression. The body is not an enemy of the spirit. Our bodies are a visible
                expression of our inner selves. Every factor, every gesture, every organ and
                function of our bodies is given us for the expression of our impulses, thoughts and
                desires. More than any other bodily act, sex expression is a sacred gift which
                awakens men and women to the innate beauty of life. We must learn to use this gift
                instead of misusing it. We must learn how to master the instrument of bodily
                expression so that passion is transmuted into poetry, so that life itself becomes
                lyric. In his grotesque attitude and use of sex in the life the average man today is
                truly said to be like an orang-outang trying to play the violin. Discord instead of
                harmony has resulted.</p>
            <p>Never be ashamed of passion. If you are strongly sexed, you are richly endowed. You
                possess the greatest and most valuable inheritance a human being can enjoy. To be
                strongly sexed means that the life force can suffuse and radiate through body and
                soul. It means radiant energy and force in every field of endeavor. It means driving
                power, ambition, attainment, but on condition that this great dynamic power be
                mastered and directed, stored and controlled, instead of dissipated and misspent.
                Without passion, love would be a flaccid, lifeless thing. Passion is the driving
                power of life. It cannot be denied, destroyed, or thrust aside. It must and it will
                find expression.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">MAN'S STRONGEST INSTINCTS</head>
            <p>Human beings, as well as all other animals, have two very strong natural appetites;
                the appetite for food and drink and the sexual appetite. The purpose of the desire
                for food and drink to preserve the body in health and strength and enable it to
                perform physical and mental labor. It affects the individual only. But the purpose
                of sexual appetite is, primarily, the preservation of the species. If we did not
                have a sex feeling, the race would soon die out. If there were no gratification in
                the sexual act itself, and if it were indulged in only to keep the world inhabited,
                the race would soon become extinct. Scientists say that primitive man very probably
                did not see any connection between sexual intercourse and the production of
                children. A child born so long after sexual intercourse was not necessarily
                associated in the minds of our early ancestors with the sexual act. So a strong
                desire, at least in men, was necessary to make sure that the race was
                replenished.</p>
            <p>Men have intercourse to satisfy a natural and very powerful appetite, and do not at
                the time think of perpetuating the species. So while hunger and thirst and the
                sexual appetite have certain definite purposes, these purposes are lost sight of
                when the appetites are being gratified. The pleasures of satisfying the cravings are
                so great that they often drive men to excesses; and a man, rarely a women also, may
                become a glutton because of desire for food, or licentious because of appetite for
                sexual indulgence. So natural desires, which are necessary for the preservation of
                the health and life of an individual and for the perpetuation of the species, become
                vices.</p>
            <p>For some reason, sex desrie in human beings is much stronger in man than in woman; at
                least many women deny possessing any sexual feeling or any pleasure in sexual
                intercourse. Some allowance must be made for misrepresentation; some women will deny
                anything from a feeling of modesty. But even when all allowances are made, the
                sexual urge in the male seems to be far more powerful than in the female, not only
                in human beings but also in animals. In fact, in most animals, except the man-like
                apes, the female has a definite period ane does not permit the approach of the male
                except at these times. In these animals the sexual organs are grown together, except
                at the periods, so that intercourse is not possible. It may also be mentioned that
                is some animals the male as well as the female has a period. In this respect of
                course the lower animals differ from human beings, who may be sexually stimulated at
                all times, though the strength and intensity vary greatly under different
                circumstances. Such desire is aroused and increased by certain living conditions.
                Persons who live a luxurious life, with a rich diet of animal food and particularly
                if they indulge moderately in wines and liquors, are much more strongly sexed than
                those who live simple, industrious lives. The half-fed student has a weaker stimulus
                than the well-fed good-liver. The imagination also has much to do with stimulating
                sex desire. The reading of books on sex, particularly stories about illicit love,
                and looking at pictures or figures which suggest sexual indulgence, have a very
                strong tendency to arouse the imagination to sexual acts.</p>
            <p>Both men and women differ greatly in their power and self-control, in many
                directions. Some persons are weaker-willed than others and cannot control their
                feelings; they indulge every appetite. So it is quite impossible to find any hard
                fast rules which apply to everyone. But it is probably true that any normal person,
                leading an ordinary natural life with interesting occupations, can control his or
                her passions; and anyone who is lisentious becomes so by indulging in unclean
                thoughts, or by leading a life of self-indulgence in other ways."</p>
        </div>

    </docBody>
</doc>
