<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech ">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-06-26 CH proof tags</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1936-01-03 ">)3 Jan 1936</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP"
                >Contraception</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421097</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Dissemination of Knowledge</title>,
                <title type="journal">Madras Mail</title>, Jan. 3, 1936 and <title
                    type="article">"Birth Control"</title>,
                <title type="journal">The Hindu</title>, Jan. 4, 1936</bibl>


        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="MM">Madras Mail</name>
            <name id="TH"> The Hindu</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger</person> spoke
        to the first <org>All-India Obstetrics and Gynaecological congress</org>
        at the <org>Museum Theater</org> in <place>Madras, India</place>. This
        summary comes from two articles: "<title type="article">Dissemination of
            Knowledge</title>" in the <title type="journal">Madras Mail</title>,
        Jan. 3, 1936 and "<title type="article">Birth Control</title>," <title
            type="journal">The Hindu</title>, Jan. 4., 1936.</p> <index
            level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Federal"/><index
            level1="India" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="birth control movement in"/><index
            level1="India" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="population policies of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Dissemination of Knowledge</head>
        <head type="sub">Mrs. Sanger's Address to Doctors</head>
        <dateline><date value="/1936/-01-03 "/>Jan. 3, Madras</dateline>
        <p>“I think that the people of <place>India</place> should demand from
            the medical profession the scientific knowledge which is available
            in other countries and in medical and scientific societies regarding
            methods of birth control.”</p>
        <p><q who="MM"> This remark was made by Mrs. Margaret Sanger (President
                of the <org>Birth Control International Information
                Centre</org>) in an address to members of the medical profession
                this evening at the Museum Theater. The lecture was illustrated
                with films.</q></p>
        <p><q who="MM"> Mrs. Margaret Sanger said: </q>“My message to the
            medical profession in India is that it has a wonderful opportunity
            to avoid the mistakes which have been made by Western countries,
            where they have rigid laws, as in <place reg="United States"
                >America</place>, against the dissemination of birth control
            information. If, through maternity hospitals and other hospitals and
            Health Week, doctors will provide proper instruction to women as
            well as men, first for health reasons and next for social and
            economic reasons, they can help to direct the birth control movement
            along the proper channel.</p>
        <p> “The well-to-do-people in all countries have some knowledge, which
            the poor are denied. But the poor people, the sick and the diseased,
            should be the first to have it.” </p>
        <p><q who="MM">The lecturer then exhibited scientific films on
                contraception and birth control as known in Western
                countries.</q></p>
        <p> “One-fifth of the babies born in India,” Mrs. Sanger continued, “die
            before they reach their fifth year.” </p>
        <p><q who="MM">The death rate among infants from the first to the fourth
                born was not heavy. But there was higher mortality among those
                born after the fourth up to the seventh. From the seventh to the
                eleventh the wastage was still more tremendous. Sixty per cent,
                of the twelfth-born children died generally in the first
                year.</q></p>
        <p> “The average Indian family,” Mrs. Sanger remarked, “could support
            fairly about three children.”</p>
        <p><q who="MM">The lecturer added: </q> “The people should ask
            municipalities and public health agencies to open birth control
            clinics, especially for the poor who have not the means to pay for
            private advice. I would also stress that the young men and women in
            the medical schools and colleges should be given proper instruction
            in contraceptive technique.” </p>
        <div>
            <head>BIRTH CONTROL</head>
            <head type="sub">Mrs. Sanger's Address</head>
            <dateline><date value="/----/-01-04 "/>Jan. 4, <place
                    reg="Madras, India">Madras</place></dateline>
            <q who="TH"><p>Under the auspices of the First All-India Obstetric
                    and Gynecological Congress, Mrs. Margaret Sanger delivered a
                    lecture on “Contraception,” last evening, at the Museum
                    Theater, <place reg="Egmore, India">Egmore</place>. Dr.
                    (Miss) <person reg="Scudder, Ida S.">Ida S. Scudder
                    </person>presided. There was a large gathering of medical
                    men and students.</p>
                <p> The birth control movement, Mrs. Sanger said, had come to
                    stay and nothing in the world could push it back. In the
                    interests of humanity, and in the interests of the welfare
                    and happiness of the future generations, a knowledge of
                    birth control methods, she urged, should be imparted to
                    women. Otherwise, there would be a colossal waste of child
                    life and mother life. She had been advocating birth control
                    methods for the past twenty years, as she was convinced that
                    the same would improve the health of women and children. She
                    had worked among the poorer classes in America. She knew
                    what was meant by a large family. She herself was born in a
                    family of eleven members. She had been a nurse and was the
                    mother of children. She therefore knew the pros and cons of
                    birth control. She knew what the responsibilities of a large
                    family were and how women suffered from too frequent
                    pregnancies.</p></q>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">“Not a New Idea”</head>
            <p>Out of ignorance and fear, women were undergoing, the speaker
                continued, unnecessary suffering, which could be avoided with a
                little care and a proper understanding of scientific methods of
                birth control. Control of an action, when necessary, was not a
                sin. Birth control meant conscious control of the birthrate by
                preventing conception. Preventing conception did not mean taking
                away life nor did it mean interfering with life. By means of
                scientific birth control, the human race could be made healthier
                and sound in body and mind. Birth control was, as they knew, not
                a new idea. Only the methods advocated were new. She felt
                strongly that the medical men were the proper persons to
                disseminate knowledge of scientific birth control methods to the
                people. One of the great dangers that beset the movement was the
                spread of wrong ideas about the methods to be adopted. Therefore
                she felt that the medical profession ought to take charge of the
                movement and lead it along right lines.</p>
            <p> In America the movement was making headway in spite of
                handicaps. The Federal laws stood to some extent in the way of
                the movement spreading quickly especially among the poorer
                classes. But in India there were no such handicaps. The medical
                profession in India out to lead the movement. A good deal of
                infantile and maternity mortality rates could be reduced through
                a proper application of scientific birth control methods. </p>
            <p>Dr. <person reg="Mudaliar, A. Lakshmanaswami">A. Lakshmanaswami
                    Mudaliar</person> proposed a vote of thanks to the lecturer.
            </p>
        </div>

    </docBody>
</doc>
