<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2013/11/20 JK encoded</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-08-21 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1935-10-00">Oct 1935</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>From Mrs. Sanger, U.S.A.</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421067</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Birth Control News</title> Oct 1935, 18. </bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="BCN">Birth Control News</name>
            <name id="MURJO">Murray, John Gregory</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Sanger comments on the news that Archbishop Murray had instructed the
            clergy of the St. Paul Archdiocese to announct that no individual may retain membership
            in any organization supporting birth control.</p>
        <index level1="Catholic Church" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
        <index level1="Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau" level2="Catholicism and"/>
        <index level1="Parent Teacher Association"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>From Mrs. M. Sanger, U.S.A. </head>

        <p>From Mrs. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">M. Sanger</person>, <place reg="United States"
                >U.S.A.</place> “If Catholic prelates follow the example of Archbishop <person
                reg="Murray, John Gregory">John Gregory Murray</person>, Catholics will have to
            withdraw completely and irrevocable from civic, public, and professional life,” <q
                who="BNC">said Margaret Sanger, commenting on the recent news that Archbishop Murray
                has instructed the clergy of the <org>St. Paul Archiocese</org> to announce at all
                masses on August 18 that “<q who="MURJO">no individual or group may accept or retain
                    membership in any organization recognizing or supporting birth control or
                    sterilization, and that persons employed in any position that involved
                    co-operation effecting birth control must withdraw from such
                employment.</q>”</q> “Follow Archbishop Murray’s orders to their logical conclusion,
            and what have we? “Every Catholic physician who is a member of the <org>American
                Gynecological Society</org>, the <org>American Neurological Society</org> and the
                <org reg="American Medical Association, Obstetrical Section">Obstetrical Section of
                the American Medical Association</org> will have to sever his connection with these
            professional groups, for they endorse the principles of birth control. In the field of
            social work, every Catholic member of the <org>New Jersey State Conference of Social
                Work</org>, of the <org reg="North Carolina Conference of Social Work">North
                Carolina Conference</org>, and the <org reg="Vermont Conference of Social Work"
                >Vermont</org> and <org reg="Arkansas Conference of Social Work">Arkansas
                Conferences</org> will have to withdraw and forfeit the benefits that come from
            contact with co-workers. And all Catholic social workers in these states, presumable,
            will give up their positions. Any Catholic who belongs to the <org>California Parent
                Teacher Association</org> must resign; likewise Catholic parents and teachers of the
                <org reg="Indianapolis Parent Teacher Association">Indianapolis P.T.A.</org>
            Catholic members of the <org reg="Virginia State Federation of Labor">Virginia</org> and
                <org reg="Utah State Federation of Labor">Utah State Federations of Labour</org>
            must walk out, and among business men, who see so clearly the value of fellowship, the
            Catholic members of the<org reg="Tacoma Rotary Club"> Rotary Club of Tacoma,
                Washington</org>, to cite one example, must ask to have their names removed from the
            roster. Six state groups of <org>Business and Professional
                Women</org>-<place>Michigan</place>, <place>Texas</place>, <place>Virginia</place>,
                <place>Arkansas</place>, <place>Nevada</place>, and <place> Tennessee</place>--
            would find themselves without their Catholic sisters. Need one elaborate?” <q who="BCN"
                >All these groups have placed themselves on record in favour of scientific birth
                control and in support of birth control legislation. They are some of 700
                organizations, religious, educational, political, social and medical -- with
                membership totaling into the millions--which have taken such action.</q> “Does the
            Archbishop propose that intelligent Catholic doctors, social workers, parents, business
            men and club women should actually withdraw from all the affiliations represented by
            these 700 groups?” asked Mrs. Sanger. “And what orders does he give to the thousands of
            Catholic women who avail themselves of birth control services t birth control clinics.
            The report of the <org>Birth Control Clinical Rsearch Bureau</org>, <place>New
                York</place>, for 1934, shows that of the 5.515 patients, 24% were Catholic. These
            figures are typical. A study of 10,000 cases at the same clinic over a period of nine
            years showed that 26.1% were Catholic.”</p>


    </docBody>
</doc>
