<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-02-26 JK initial tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-02-28 CH proof tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-05 JK corrected tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-11-14 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1935-22-12">Dec. 22 1935</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>
                <supplied resp="MSPP">Speech at the Taj Mahal Hotel
                    Luncheon</supplied>
            </titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421064</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Mr. Gandhi's Views on Birth
                    Control</title>, <title type="journal">The Times of
                    India</title>, Dec. 23, 1935, p. 9.</bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="ToI">The Times of India</name>
            <name id="GANMO">Gandhi, Mohandas K.</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>This is a summary of <person reg="Sanger, Margaret"
                >Sanger</person>'s talk to members of the <org>Society for the
                Study and Promotion of Family Hygiene</org> at a tea held at the
                <org>Taj Mahal Hotel</org>,<place reg="Bombay, India"> Bombay,
                India.</place>
            <person reg="How-Martyn, Edith">Edith How-Martyn</person> also spoke
            at the meeting which was chaired by Lr. Col.<person
                reg="Sokhey, S. S."> S. S. Sokhey. </person></p>
        <index level1="Gandhi, Mahatma"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="women in"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Mr. Gandhi's Views on Birth Control</head>
        <head type="sub">DISCUSSION WITH MRS. SANGER</head>
        <q who="ToI">
            <p> The details of a conversation between <person
                    reg="Gandhi, Mohandas K. ">Mr. Gandhi</person> and Mrs.
                Sanger on the subject of birth control were disclosed at a
                select gathering in Bombay on Sunday evening. The occasion was a
                tea party given at the Taj Mahal Hotel by the Society for the
                Study and Promotion of Family Hygiene to Mrs. Margaret Sanger,
                who recently returned to <place reg="Bombay, India"
                    >Bombay</place> after a tour during which she met Mr.
                Gandhi. </p>
        </q>
        <p><q who="ToI">Mr. Gandhi, Mrs. Sanger said, agreed with her on all
                points in regard to birth control except the methods of adopting
                it. The question when she went to him was whether she would
                convert him or he would convert her. </q>“And believe me,” she
            added, “he did not convert me.” (Laughter). </p>
        <p>
            <q who="ToI">“But was he converted?” asked a voice.</q>
        </p>
        <p>“I do not know,” replied Mrs. Sanger. </p>
        <q who="ToI">
            <p>Mr. Gandhi, the lecturer continued, agreed with her that birth
                control was an important question, but he, like many other
                people, believed that "<emph rend="italics">control</emph>" was
                a wide term and that it meant something more than limitation.
                The method which Mr. Gandhi advocated was continence and
                restraint, not only outside marriage but in marriage also. </p>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger continued that she had asked Mr. Gandhi whether he
                considered that a practical solution, knowing that of all the
                women in the world Indian women were less equipped economically
                and socially to go out into the world. He had replied that they
                could have divorce laws. </p>
        </q>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> View of Mothers in Slums</head>
            <p>Mrs. Sanger further said: “I told him ‘all this sounds rather
                chaotic to me, and I believe the men will be on my side. Men
                would prefer the methods of birth control that I advocate rather
                than yours’. He said: <q who="GANMA">‘Women will be on my side.’
                </q>(Laughter). We have yet to find out of that will be so,”
                added Mrs. Sanger. </p>
            <q who="ToI">
                <p> Before she came to <place>India</place>, Mrs. Sanger said,
                    she had been told that she was not likely to succeed in her
                    mission because Indian mothers were fond of children and
                    liked to have many, irrespective of what she state of their
                    (mothers’) health was. On questioning mothers during their
                    visits to slums in Bombay and in northern India, however,
                    she had invariably got the reply that they had had enough
                    children and wanted no more. They were anxious to have some
                    means by which they could space their children. </p>
                <p> Mrs. How-Martyn, who was present at the gathering, stated
                    that those working on behalf of birth control in India had
                    an advantage over their colleagues in the West, as they
                    could have the benefit of the experience of the latter. </p>
                <p> A silver casket was presented to Mrs. Sanger, who has been
                    elected vice-president of the Society, by Lt.-Col. <person
                        reg="Shah, Jelal M.">Jelal M. Shah</person>, on behalf
                    of the editor of <title type="journal">Marriage
                        Hygiene</title>. </p>
                <p> Lt.-Col. S. S. Sokhey, the chairman of the Council of the
                    Society, proposed a vote of thanks to Mrs. Sanger. </p>
            </q>
        </div>

    </docBody>
</doc>
