<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2013-11-13 JK encoded</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-08-21 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docAuthor/>
        <docDate value="1932-12-10"><supplied resp="MSPP">10 Dec 1932</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Speech to Connecticut Birth Control League, Hartford
                    Branch</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421046</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Mrs. Sanger Lectures on Birth Control</title>, <title
                    type="journal"> The Hartford Courant" </title>, Dec. 10, 1932.</bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="HC">The Hartford Courant</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>No other version of this speech has been found, but it was likely
            similar to Sanger's <xref from="236563.xml"><org reg="Wesleyan University"
                    >Wesleyan</org>address,</xref>given Dec. 9, 1932.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="MS on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="Connecticut"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="State"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="morality of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits and risks"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="infant"/>
        <index level1="population growth" level2="regulation of"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Mrs. Sanger Lectures on Birth Control </head>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Speaking at St. John's Parish House, She Hits <place reg="Connecticut"
                    > Conn. </place> Laws on Dissemination of Information</head>
            <p>
                <q who="HC">Maintaining that this country should be at least as careful of the type
                    of citizens born here as it is of the type of citizens admitted, Mrs. Margaret
                    Sanger of <place>New York</place> presented the case for birth control at a
                    lecture held under the auspices of the <org reg="Connecticut Birth Control League, Hartford Branch">Hartford Branch</org> of the <org>Connecticut Birth
                    Control League</org> in the parish house of <org>St. John’s
                        Church</org>, Saturday afternoon. The lecture was attended by nearly 500
                    persons, many of whom signed cards pledging support of action to liberalize the
                    state and Federal laws on dissemination of birth control information.</q>
            </p>
        </div>

        <div>
            <head type="sub">Connecticut Laws Scored.</head>

            <p><q who="HC">Mrs. Sanger repeated her assertion that Connecticut laws on the
                    dissemination of birth control information are “unique," pointing out that there
                    are only two other states in the county where even physicians are forbidden to
                    give even oral information to patients on the subject. The state law which
                    prohibits the use of contraceptives is unenforceable, she declared, unless the
                    State proposes to station a policeman in every home. In opening her lecture Mrs.
                    Sanger pointed out that the old methods of keeping the population relatively
                    stable such as pestilence, famine, floods, etc., have been largely overcome by
                    science. It is obvious, she said, that there are only two methods to control the
                    population, increase deaths or decrease births and the former is much too cruel.
                    In times past persons have resorted to infanticide as a method of controlling
                    the number of children, but this is to be deplored, as is abortion, which
                    followed infanticide as a method of controlling the size of the family, she
                    said. </q></p>
        </div>

        <div>
            <head type="sub">Says Question Affects All. </head>

            <p><q who="HC">Once contraception is generally known there will be no necessity for
                    either of the previous two methods of control, she said. She pointed out that
                    the so-called “social problem” group is in a large part composed of families
                    where contraception is unknown, while in the other group both parents and
                    children benefit through improved conditions. The question of birth control, she
                    said, then affects every man and woman, and indirectly every child.</q> “The
                immigration laws bar certain aliens who are feeble-minded, or who have certain
                diseases, from admission to this country,” she said. “Certainly if it is desirable
                to control the rate at which such persons are permitted to multiply once they are
                here.” <q who="HC">Birth control is desirable to prevent the transmission of
                    disease, to insure the proper spacing between children so that both mother and
                    child shall have the benefit of better physical condition, to prevent child
                    bearing adolescence, to permit families to have no more children than they can
                    afford, and to permit a period of mutual adjustment after marriage, she said.
                </q></p>
        </div>


    </docBody>
</doc>
