<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-04-02 JK initial tag</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1935-11-29">29 Nov. 1935</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">What Municipalities in the West
                    Have Been doing to Promote Birth
                Control</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421080</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">"Benefits of Birth Control"</title>,
                    <title type="journal">Times of India</title>, Nov. 30, 1935,
                p. 22.</bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="ToI">Times of India</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>A summary and quotes of <person
                reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger</person>'s Nov. 29, 1935 speech to
            the <org>Bombay Municipal Corporation </org>came from "<title
                type="article">Benefits of Birth Control</title>," <title
                type="journal">Times of India,</title> Nov. 30, 1935, p. 22.</p>
        <index level1="Birth Control Federation of America"/>
        <index level1="Birth Control International Information Centre"/><index
            level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="MS on"/><index
            level1="India" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="birth control movement in"/><index
            level1="India" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="population policies of"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="overpopulation and"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="women in"/><index level1="India"
            level2="mortality rates" level3="infant"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="mortality rates" level3="maternal"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Benefits of Birth Control</head>
        <head type="sub">Mrs. Sanger's Plea to Bombay Municipality</head>

        <p>“Close on 50,000 of our women have benefit[t]ed by the practice of
            birth control, and if today they are living, it is because of the
            useful information they got at our clinics.” <q who="ToI">declared
                Mrs. Margaret Sanger, Chairman of the <org>National Committee on
                    Federal Legislation for Birth Control</org>, <place
                    reg="New York, NY">New York</place>, in reply to a question
                put to her at a meeting held in the <place reg="Bombay, India"
                    >Bombay</place> Municipal Corporation hall, on Friday
                evening. The theme of her lecture was “What Municipalities in
                the West have been doing to promote birth control.” She was
                accompanied by<person reg="How-Martyn, Edith"> Mrs. Edith
                    How-Martyn</person>, Honorary Director, <org>Birth Control
                    International Information Centre</org>, <place
                    reg="London, England">London</place>, who also addressed the
                meeting. There was a large gathering.</q>
        </p>
        <p><q who="ToI">The mayor, <person reg="Nariman, Khurshed Framji"> Mr.
                    K. F. Nariman</person>, who presided, accorded the visitors
                a cordial welcome on behalf of the citizens of Bombay and
                appealed to them to confine their humanitarian mission not
                merely to large cities in <place>India</place>, but to spread it
                in the villages, where relief was urgently needed.</q></p>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Control of Population</head>
            <p><q who="ToI">When they were able to control their appetite and
                    other things, said Mrs. Sanger, they could as well control
                    the greatest of all problems, that of population. In <place
                        reg="United States">America</place> and <place
                        reg="Netherlands">Holland</place> the knowledge of birth
                    control was widely spread, and consequently there were fewer
                    deaths among infants and less maternal mortality. Greater
                    attention was being paid to social welfare and to allied
                    problems. In Holland she found that the population had
                    increased on sound lines. Birth control was not at all
                    harmful; it was on the other hand, beneficial, and helped to
                    decrease maternal mortality.</q></p>
            <q who="ToI">
                <p>Mrs. Sanger asked the Bombay Municipality to take the lead in
                    the movement by starting birth control clinics, as other
                    western municipalities had already done. If the knowledge of
                    birth control were systematically and scientifically spread
                    among the masses, it would do them enormous good, and within
                    a hundred years the people would appreciate the efforts of
                    the municipality and raise a statue to the Mayor for having
                    successfully launched the movement. (Laughter.) </p>
                <p>Mrs. How-Martyn explained how attention was being paid to the
                    movement in <place>England</place>, pointing out that large
                    sums of money were being spent on social service. Hundreds
                    of women took advantage of the birth control clinics started
                    in various parts of the country.</p>
                <p> The visitors answered several questions asked by members of
                    the audience and cleared their doubts on the subject.
                </p></q>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
