<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-04-09 JK initial tags</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1931-11-09 ">09 Nov 1931</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>
                <supplied resp="MSPP"> Interview with The San Antonio
                    Light</supplied>
            </titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421051</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">"New Thinking of Younger Generation
                    Praised,"</title>
                <title type="journal">The San Antonio Light</title>, Nov. 9,
                1931, p. 1.</bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="SAL">The San Antonio Light</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"
            level3="negative consequences of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="American opinion on"/>
        <index level1="adolescence"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
        <index level1="society" level2="responsibility and"/>
        <index level1="population growth" level2="regulation of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>NEW THINKING OF YOUNGER GENERATION PRAISED</head>
        <head type="sub">Mrs. Sanger, Birth Control Crusader, in S.A. for
            Lecture.</head>
        <q who="SAL">
            <p>Definition of the American younger generation as the avenue to a
                solution of problems that have been ignored by puritanical older
                people, was made by <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret
                    Sanger</person>, birth control crusader, who will lecture on
                the subject before the <place reg="San Antonio, TX">San
                    Antonio</place> Open Forum Monday night.</p>
            <p> Mrs. Sanger, in her suite at the <org>Gunter hotel</org> Monday
                morning, said:</p>
        </q>
        <p> “The younger generation has done away with hypocrisy. They are
            directing a new manner of thinking towards morals in the right way.
            They are unconsciously pioneers in their insensate desire for
            knowledge, their frank talk, and their frank lives.”</p>
        <p>
            <q who="SAL">She defined the widespread youthful revolt against
                prohibition as a normal reaction to the lack of satisfactory
                food for spiritual hungers:</q>
        </p>
        <p> “The determined desire many youths have for strong drink without
            gaiety, with real appreciation for taste, is owing to the fact that
            they have nothing to fight for. Everything has been won. The worst
            has been laid at their feet. Then, too, they are fearless
            experimenters. There is a courage about their lives.”</p>
        <q who="SAL">
            <p> Connecting her subject with the problems of poverty, Mrs. Sanger
                said that if the billions of dollars used for charitable work
                within the last 10 years had been directed to wiping out the
                slums by scientific methods such as birth control and
                recreational facilities, the <place>United States</place> would
                today be closer to solving its tenement problems.</p>
            <p> Speaking of the large foreign population of San Antonio, Mrs.
                Sanger said: </p>
        </q>
        <p>“Wherever the foreigners are isolated in sections, left to devise a
            social system complete and segregated, left to breed without
            control, they haven’t the standards necessary to limit disease and
            poverty. The existence of a slum district in any city is caused by
            the lackadaisical attitude of the more normally situated
            natives.”</p>
        <q who="SAL">
            <p> Mrs. Sanger remarked briefly on organized opposition to her
                beliefs in most of the cities on her lecture tour, and lamented
                opposition to free discussion of knowledge and beliefs.</p>
            <p>She said:</p>
        </q>
        <p> “Any opposition who may disagree in an opinion has the right to
            adhere to their beliefs, and make reasonable statements of
            opposition. An effort to restrict free discussion or public argument
            is the wrong way to impose their tenets on other people. </p>
        <p>“It is encouraging to see the development of open forums in
                <place>Texas</place>. There is no activity which makes more for
            liberal and progressive thinking. It is regrettable that there
            should be an organized opposition to the free expression found in
            them.”</p>
        <q who="SAL">
            <p> Mrs. Sanger pointed out that at her birth control clinic in New
                York more than 25,000 women had received advice and treatment
                within the last five years, and that one-third were Protestants,
                one-third Catholics, and one-third Jews. She said: </p>
        </q>
        <p>“The day has gone when we can expect people to live by the attitudes
            of the Middle Ages. Science is here to help solve some of the
            problems of humanity. Birth control is one way of solving a very old
            problem.”</p>
        <q who="SAL">
            <p> Mrs. Sanger’s lecture will be given at the municipal auditorium
                at 8:30 p.m. Monday. She is the second Open Forum lecturer of
                the season. </p>
            <p>She was honored with a luncheon at the <org>St. Anthony
                    Hotel</org> Monday noon by officers and directors of the
                forum. She came to this city from <place reg="Houston, TX"
                    >Houston</place>, where a crowd 4,000 people attended her
                lecture there on the same subject, “Birth Control.” </p>
        </q>
    </docBody>
</doc>
