<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article ">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2013/11/20 JK encoded</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-06-01 EK clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1932-10-09 ">09 Oct 1932</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Statement on Birth Control in Puerto
                Rico</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421049</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Mrs. Sanger Aids Beverley</title><title type="newspaper">New
                    York Times</title></bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="NYT">New York Times</name>
            <name id="SANMA">Margaret Sanger</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">MS made public a telegram sent to <person reg="Hoover, Hebert">President
            Hoover</person> protesting against the opposition of the <org>National Catholic Alumni
            Federation</org> to the advocacy by <person reg="Beverley, James R.">Governor James R.
            Beverley</person> of <place>Puerto Rico</place> of birth control for the natives of the
        island. </headNote>
    <index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="in Puerto Rico"/>
    <index level1="National Birth Control League"/>
    <index level1="National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control"/>
    <index level1="Catholic Church" level2="birth control and"/>
    <docBody>
        <head>Mrs. Sanger Aids Beverley </head>
        <head type="sub">Protests to Hoover on Criticism of Birth Control Proposal.</head>

        <p><q who="NYT"><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>, head of the
                    <org>National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control</org>, at 17
                West Sixteenth Street, made public yesterday a telegram sent to <person
                    reg="Hoover, President Herbert">President Hoover </person>protesting against the
                opposition of the <org>National Catholic Alumni Federation</org> to the advocacy by
                    <person reg="Beverley, Governor James R.">Governor James R. Beverley</person> of
                    <place>Puerto Rico</place> of birth control for the natives of the island.</q>
            <q who="SANMA">“On behalf of the National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth
                Control," I wish to emphatically protest against the deliberate misstatements made
                by the National Catholic Alumni Federationas reported in <title rend="italics">The
                    New York Times</title>,”</q> her telegram said. “<q who="SANMA">Over 200
                national and State organizations in medical, religious, social and educational
                fields have publicly endorsed the principles of birth control and are sponsoring the
                amendment of anti-birth control laws in this country. It is an arrogant interference
                on the part of any religious group to attempt to suppress the economic and social
                facts and to intimidate public officials who dare to present such facts when these
                are contrary to medieval theology.</q>” </p>

    </docBody>
</doc>
