<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-01-08 CH transcribe and encode</prepDate><prepDate>2015-01-21 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1924-01-00">Jan 1924</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>Margaret Sanger's Own Corner</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp421032</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title>, Jan. 1924, p. 22</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="BCR">Birth Control Review</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>Under this column name, the <title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title> published
			letters written to Margaret Sanger with occasional commentary. For others in this series
			see Margaret Sanger's Own Corner, <xref from="421033.xml">Feb. 1924</xref>, <xref
				from="301463.xml">Mar. 1924</xref>, <xref from="421034.xml">Apr. 1924</xref>
			<xref from="421009.xml">May 1924</xref>, and <xref from="421010.xml">June
			1924</xref>.</p>
		<index level1="client letters"/>
		<index level1="birth control clinics and leagues" level2="legal status of"/>
		<index level1="child spacing"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Margaret Sanger's Own Corner</head>
		<div type="section">
			<p rend="italics"><q who="BCR"/>Under this heading, month by month, Margaret Sanger will
				reply to some of the hundreds of questions that come to her. Sometimes one reply
				will answer many people, for the problems presented are often the same, though sent
				from far distant States and cities. Sometimes one person may voice a question that
				is in the minds of hundreds of other people, who perhaps have found no way of
				uttering it. If you have such a question in mind address it to 'Margaret Sanger's
				Own Corner' Birth Control Review.</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<p>STRANGER AND WIFE-- Your letter received. I sympathize with you in your difficult
				problem, of which there is not reason to be ashamed. If you will send address will
				write you personally.</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<p>ALH-- It is certainly not advisable for a woman, however healthy, to have a second
				child within two years of the first. Three years is a better interval. One of the
				great advantages of Birth Control is the possibility it presents of spacing the
				babies.</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<p><place reg="Chicago, IL">CHICAGO</place> CLINIC-- The operation of clinics is a matter of State law, and is not
				affected by the fact that the Federal law prohibits the sending of Birth Control
				information through the mails.</p>
		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
