<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">

    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-03-12 JK initial tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-19 CH proof tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-26 JK correct tags</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1936-01-03"><supplied resp="MSPP">03 Jan
            1936</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Interview with the Madras
                    Mail</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421096</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Need For Birth Control
                    Clinics</title><title type="journal">Madras Mail</title>
                Jan. 3, 1936</bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="MM">Madras Mail</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">This is from <title type="article">"Need for Birth
            Control Clinics"</title>, Madras Mail, Jan. 3, 1936.<index
            level1="National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control"
            /><index level1="India" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="birth control movement in"/><index
            level1="India" level2="overpopulation and"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="women in"/><index level1="birth control"
            level2="international conferences on"/><index level1="birth control"
            level2="religion and"/><index level1="birth control movement"
            level2="international"/><index level1="birth rate"
            level2="efforts to reduce"/><index level1="birth control"
            level2="distribution of information about"/><index
            level1="birth control" level2="in India"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>NEED FOR BIRTH CONTROL CLINICS</head>
        <head type="sub">Mrs. Sanger's Views</head>
        <dateline>
            <date value="1936-01-03"/>Jan. 3, 1936 <place reg="Madras, India"
                >Madras</place></dateline>
        <q who="MM">
            <p>Mrs. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>,
                Chairman of the <org> National Committee on Federal Legislation
                    for birth control</org>, <place reg=" New York City, NY">New
                    York</place>, and President of the <org> Birth Control
                    International Information Centre</org>, <place
                    reg="London, England">London</place>, arrived in Madras this
                morning from <place reg="Trivandrum, India">Trivandrum</place>,
                after attending the <org>All-India Women’s Conference</org>. </p>
            <p> Mrs. Margaret Sanger started the birth control movement 25 years
                ago and has been responsible for the existence of more than 200
                birth control clinics in<place reg="United States">
                    America</place>. </p>
            <p> Interviewed, Mrs. Sanger first gave her impressions of the
                all-India Women’s Conference at Trivandrum. The proceedings, she
                said, were conducted in an admirably democratic manner,
                notwithstanding the absence of some of the leaders of the
                women’s movement like Mrs. <person reg="Naidu, Sarojini"
                    >Sarojini Nayudu</person>. She paid a tribute to Her
                    Highness<person reg="Bayi, Sethu Lakshmi"> Maharani Setu
                    Parvathi Bai</person>, president of the conference, for the
                manner in which the deliberations were conducted. </p></q>
        <p>“The delegates,” said Mrs. Sanger, “did a very fine piece of work.
            They had been fully informed of the problem of child marriage, of
            women in mines, of illiteracy, and of traffic in women and other
            questions placed before the conference. </p>
        <p>“I was much impressed with the fact that only unmarried women opposed
            the birth control resolution, and most of them were Christian
            delegates.</p>
        <p>“It was very sad to find so many women coming down to have an
            interview with me,” added Mrs. Sanger, referring to her experiences
            in <place>India</place>. “Some of them brought their children. They
            came from distance places, which the consent of the population, who
            are for adopting birth control methods.”</p>
        <q who="MM">
            <p>Mrs. Margaret Sanger is staying at the <org>Connemara Hotel</org>
                and, according to present arrangements, will leave Madras on
                Jan. 10. She will visit <place reg="Mysore, India"
                    >Mysore</place> and <place reg="Hyderabad, India"
                    >Hyderabad</place>, and will attend the first <org
                    reg="Indian Population Conference, 1st">Population
                    Conference</org> at <place reg="Lucknow, India"
                    >Lucknow</place> on Jan. 27. She will then proceed to <place
                    reg="Calcutta, India">Calcutta</place>, where on Jan. 30 she
                will attend the <org
                    reg="Joint Conference of the International Council of Women and the National Council of Women in India"
                    >International Women’s Conference</org>. She proposed to
                leave India on Feb. 2 for <place reg="Rangoon, Burma"
                    >Rangoon</place>. Mrs. Margaret Sanger was the organizer of
                the first <org reg="World Population Conference">International
                    Population Conference</org>, held at <place
                    reg="Geneva, Switzerland">Geneva</place> in 1927. </p></q>

        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Dissemination of Knowledge</head>
            <head type="sub"> Mrs. Sanger’s Address to Doctors</head>



            <p> “I think that the people of India should demand from the medical
                profession the scientific knowledge which is available in other
                countries and in medical and scientific societies regarding
                methods of birth control.”</p>
            <q who="MM">
                <p>This remark was made by Mrs. Margaret Sanger (President of
                    the Birth Control International Information Centre) in an
                    address to members of the medical profession this evening at
                    the Museum Theatre. The lecture was illustrated with films.
                </p></q>
            <p>Mrs. Margaret Sanger said: “My message to the medical profession
                in India is that it has a wonderful opportunity to avoid the
                mistakes which have been made by Western countries, where they
                have rigid laws, as in America, against the dissemination of
                birth control information. If, through maternity hospitals and
                other hospitals and Health Week, doctors will provide proper
                instruction to women as well as men, first for health reasons
                and next for social and economic reasons, they can help to
                direct the birth control movement along the proper channel. </p>
            <p>“The well-to-do people in all countries have some knowledge,
                which he poor are denied. But the poor people, the sick and the
                diseased, should be the first to have it.”</p>
            <q who="MM">
                <p> The lecturer then exhibited scientific films on
                    contraception and birth control as known in Western
                    countries. </p></q>
            <p> “One-fifth of the babies born in India,” Mrs. Sanger continued,
                “die before they reach their fifth year.”</p>
            <q who="MM">
                <p> The death rate among infants from the first to the fourth
                    born was not heavy. But there was higher mortality among
                    those born after the fourth up to the seventh. From the
                    seventh to the eleventh the wastage was still more
                    tremendous. Sixty per cent of the twelfth-born children died
                    generally in the first year. </p></q>
            <p> “The average Indian family,” Mrs. Sanger remarked, “could
                support fairly about three children.”</p>
            <p>The lecturer added: “The people should ask municipalities and
                public health agencies to open birth control clinics, especially
                for the poor who have not the means to pay for private advice. I
                would also stress that the young men and women in the medical
                schools and colleges should be given proper instructions in
                contraceptive technique.” </p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
