<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Interview">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2013/12/11 JK encoded</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-11-10 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1933-11-19"><supplied resp="MSPP">19 Nov. 1933</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Interview with the Washington
                Post</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421054</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Birth Control Not Race Suicide, Says Mrs. Sanger</title>,
                    <title type="journal">Washington Post</title>, Nov. 20, 1933, p. 9. </bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="TWP">The Washington Post</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues" level3="in US"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="in Washington D.C."/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="consequences on"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="efforts to reduce"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="population growth and"/>
        <index level1="American Birth Control League"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Birth Control Not Race Suicide, Says Mrs. Sanger</head>
        <head type="sub">New Researches Show It Does Not Affect Population, She Insists. </head>
        <p><q who="TWP">Birth control has succeeded in meeting the attacks of those who represent it
                as synonymous with race suicide, Mrs. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret
                    Sanger</person>, foremost American exponent of the movement, who has just
                arrived in <place reg="Washington DC">Washington</place>, declared yesterday in an
                exclusive interview with the <title type="journal">Washington Post</title>. </q> “As
            a matter of fact,” she said, “birth control neither adds to nor subtracts from the
            normal increase of population. Studies of population over long periods of time and in
            many countries have convinced experts that the increase bears a direct ratio to the
            ability of the territory under observation to support human life. “If people are left to
            their own resources, to increase their kind beyond the possibility of its being
            maintained according to the living standard of the environment in which they find
            themselves, infant mortality will act as the check which reduces the adult population to
            the normal total. Or congestion will incite nations to war on each other and the
            reduction of population will be brought about in that way. “Birth control simply means
            that the mother who has 12 children in a family which can only support four will not
            suffer the immense misery of losing eight of her family through disease, malnutrition
            and like causes, but will be the happy and healthy mother of only four children–the four
            who were all she should have had. “The latest proof of the working of this theory has
            been had recently in a report just issued by <person reg="Edin, Karl">Prof. Carl
                Edin</person>, of the <org>University of Copenhagen</org>. “The poorest people of
                <place reg="Copenhagen, Denmark">Copenhagen</place> have for the past five years had
            access to birth control information. As a result, Dr. Edin finds that the poor are
            limiting the size of their families. “But the intelligentsia of Copenhagen during the
            same period have increased their families, he reports, and the increase has been
            sufficient to precisely offset the decrease among the families of the poorer class.
            “This astonishing fact he attributes to very simple causes. The burden of taxation of
            the intelligentsia for the support and relief of the poorer families has been lightened;
            and with the greater means they have been able to gratify their desire for as many
            children as they could rear and educate.” </p>


    </docBody>
</doc>
