<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">

    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/03/14 YG</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-19 CH proof tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-26 JK correct tags</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1936-01-03">03 Jan 1936</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Interview with The Hindu</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421098</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">"Birth Control in India : An Interview
                    with Mrs. Sanger"</title>
                <title type="journal">The Hindu</title>, Jan 3, 1936</bibl>
           
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="TH">The Hindu</name>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="birth control" level2="in India"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Gandhi, Mahatma"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="MS on"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Birth Control in India</head>
        <head type="sub">AN INTERVIEW WITH <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">MRS.
                SANGER</person></head>
        <div>
            <p><q who="TH">Mrs. Margaret Sanger, Chairman of <org>the National Committee on
                Federal Legislation for Birth Control</org>, New York, and President
                of the <org>Birth Control International Information Centre</org>, <place reg="London, England">London</place>,
                arrived in <place reg="Madras, India">Madras</place>, this morning, from <place reg="Trivandrum, India">Trivandrum</place>. </q></p>
            <p><q who="TH">Interviewed by “<title type="journal">The Hindu</title>,” she said that the object of her visit
                to India was to see the people and to awaken the responsibility
                of the medical profession to take a lead in giving correct
                information on birth control methods, which were an absolute
                necessity for better health and happiness of both mothers and
                children. Unless a scientific study fo the subject was taken on
                hand by the medical profession and proper knowledge disseminated
                among the people, the birth control movement would, she said,
                get into the hands of quacks. </q> </p>
            <p><q who="TH">Proceeding, she expressed the view that as far as she had been
                able to understand the position in India, she found that there
                was a keen interest among the people to have correct knowledge
                of the methods of birth control and that people were also
                anxious to understand the implication and the importance of the
                birth control movement. </q></p>
            <p><q who="TH">What she wanted to emphasize was that the birth control
                movement had no desire to force the practice of birth control
                upon any one. But people should have birth-control knowledge. In
                <place reg="Travancore, India">Travancore</place>she found that opposition to birth control only came
                from unmarried Christian women. But they must never forget that
                in every country it was the people who had too many children
                that supported the movement. People with large families, she
                found, were not against the movement. They knew the value of
                birth control. Clinics must be established for the poor people,
                who could not afford to consult private doctors, to impart
                knowledge on birth control methods. When a woman was discharged
                from a maternity hospital, she must be given proper advice on
                the necessity for “spacing” birth of children. If proper advice
                was given and the women were made to understand the need for
                birth control, she was sure, there would be an appreciable
                reduction in infantile and maternity morality. From a study of
                infantile mortality statistics, she found that in India and in
                some other countries as well, the death rate among the first to
                the four the children was 22 per cent, from fourth to the
                seventh children was 42 per cent and 60 per cent in the case of
                eleventh and twelfth children. An average Indian family must
                have only three children in the interest of the happiness and
                health of the mother and the children. </q></p>
            <p><q who="TH">The fact that children were dying of starvation, the fact that
                there were people who could not get even one full meal a day and
                the fact that all people were not provided with the necessaries
                of life, these were sufficient factors in her opinion, to
                justify a birth control movement in India. </q></p>
        </div>

        <div>
            <head type="sub"><person reg="Gandhi, Mohandas K.">GANDHIJI</person>'S
                VIEW</head>
            <p><q who="TH">Referring to Gandhiji’s attitude, she stated that Gandhiji
                advocated continence. She would contend that this method was
                suitable only for a few people who possessed a true spiritual
                development, the growth of whose spiritual powers must have
                commenced years before. For the average man, she strongly
                advocated chemical and mechanical methods of birth control. In
                fact she believed that these methods would even help people to
                develop spiritual values, if their minds were so bent. For
                younger people between 21 and 35, it would be terrific hardship
                to practice continence, unless such people had dedicated their
                lives to some noble cause, involving prayer, fasting etc. She
                did not also believe that the mechanical methods would lead to
                overindulgence as was stated by some, nor would it lead to
                immortality. She firmly believed from the experience she had
                gained, that this movement tended to decrease immorality. </q></p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">CLINICS</head>
            <p><q who="TH">She urged that literature on the subject in all languages should
                be printed and published and mass meetings should be arranged
                through public health organizations. Education of the people on
                this subject should, she suggested by undertaken by the
                authorities and the public bodies. Birth control clinics should
                be established by the State and philanthropic persons, to give
                proper advice on the subject. In educational institutions, the
                theory of birth control from the population point of view and
                general health should be imparted, along with other lessons. </q></p>
            <p><q who="TH">Mrs. Sanger will remain in Madras till the 10th inst. After
                visiting <place reg="Mysore, India">Mysore</place>and attending two conferences in <place reg="Lucknow">Lucknow</place> and
                <place reg="Calcutta, India">Calcutta</place>, she will leave for <place reg="Rangoon, Burma">Rangoon</place>on 2nd February. </q></p>
        </div>



    </docBody>
</doc>
