<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2013/12/11 JK encoded</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-08-21 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1929-11-18"><supplied resp="MSPP">18 Nov 1929</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Mt. Holyoke Lecture</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421047</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Mrs. Sanger Urges Spread of Education for Relief</title>,
                    <title type="journal">Mt. Holyoke News</title>, Nov. 23, 1929</bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="MHN">The Mount Holyoke News</name>
            <name id="HEAAR">Heath, Arthur (Sir)</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Sanger's speech was not located; press coverage provides details.</p>
        <index level1="American Birth Control League"/>
        <index level1="conferences" level2="World Population Conference" level3="1927"/>
        <index level1="child labor"/>
        <index level1="children" level2="unwanted"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="efforts to reduce"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Mrs. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger</person> Urges Spread of Education for
            Relief</head>

        <p>“The United States is particular about who comes into the country from the outside. It
            has found the selective quota to be a success. Why doesn’t it try a selective quota to
            judge who should come into the country from the inside?” <q who="MHN">Birth control, she
                explained, does not mean limiting the number of children in every family in the
                United States. It merely means the weeding out of the socially undesirable, the
                unwanted before their conception. The <place> United States</place> spent $9,000,000
                in 1927 on the four D’s-- disease, defect, delinquency and death, and in the last
                three years has spent $18,000,000 in crime in one way or another. According to Mrs.
                Sanger, families that do not want more children, that have too many already, that
                cannot support them should be given a fair chance to limit their offspring. In the
                United States there are seven million children under fourteen years of age working
                in factories or in the field. Many of the parents of these children are getting
                wages scarcely sufficient to support themselves, much less a large family.
                Child-labor legislation is helpful in a way, but it does not go far enough. Mrs.
                Sanger mentioned the various ways of controlling and regulating the birth rate, and
                said that of course the <org reg="American Birth Control League">Birth Control
                    League</org> did not intend to force anything upon people who did not wish it.
                In closing the speaker quoted Sir <person reg="Heath, Arthur">Arthur Heath</person>
                who has declared:</q> “<q who="HEAAR">There is developing in the United States the
                greatest experiment in race building the world has ever seen, and birth control is
                an integral part of that movement</q>.”</p>

        <div>
            <head>Interviewer Notes Charm of Birth Control Advocate</head>
            <p>“Birth control inspires parents to consider not only the physical welfare of the
                child, but to consider its inheritance and its potentialities as a race bearer.”</p>
        </div>

        <div>

            <head>Noted Mrs. Sanger is Forum Guest</head>
            <head type="sub">World Leader Will Present Problems Facing Youth</head>
            <head type="sub">Forum Members Must Present Cards or Pay Admission</head>
            <head type="sub"> Lecture on Monday</head>
            <p>
                <q who="MHN">Margaret Sanger, leader of the birth control movement in the United
                    States, will speak in the chapel at eight o’clock, Monday evening, November 18.
                    She is the author of several well-known books, <title type="book">“Women and the
                        New Race,”</title>
                    <title type="book">“Happiness in Marriage,”</title>
                    <title type="book">“What Every Boy and Girl Should Know,”</title> and has been
                    for some years the editor of the <title type="journal">Birth Control
                        Review</title>. In addition to her fervent written please for betterment of
                    a situation to which people everywhere have been careless or wilfully blind for
                    any number of years, Margaret Sanger has spent her life in crusading for this
                    cause. After an extensive cultural and medical education and years of practical
                    observation Mrs. Sanger is well qualified to speak with authority. She has
                    endured notoriety and even arrest for her staunch views and clear speaking. She
                    has traveled around the world and held many meetings in <place>Japan</place> and
                        <place>China</place>, leaving birth control leagues in both countries. She
                    organized in 1927 the first <org reg="World Population Conference, 1st">World
                        Population Conference</org> held at <place reg="Geneva, Switzerland"
                        >Geneva</place>. She presents a problem of vital interest to all those
                    concerned with the future welfare and happiness of the nation. The lecture is
                    under the auspices of the Forum and all members will be admitted free of charge.
                    Fifty cents admittance will be charged to all others wishing to attend Monday
                    night. Tickets for the Forum’s season program will also be on sale at the door.
                    Mrs. Sanger will be the guest of honor at a dinner given Monday night, at
                    Hillside. <person reg="Dresser, Ruth">Mrs. Dresser</person> has opened her
                    private dining room, and <person reg="Holmes, Sarah">Sarah Holmes</person>,
                    President of Forum will be the hostess.</q>
            </p>
        </div>


    </docBody>
</doc>
