<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Testimony">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/01/31 VS innitial encoding</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/02/11 CH proof tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/02/12 VS correct tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-11-12 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1926-06-21">21 June 1926</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Norman Harris Foundation 6th Institute Round Table
                    Proceedings</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421048</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Norman Wait Harris Foundation, <title type="journal">Round Table Discussion of
                    Preventive Checks to Population Growth</title>, p. 203-253</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="WRIQU">Wright, Quincy</name>
            <name id="ROSED">Ross, Edward Alsworth</name>
            <name id="HUNEL">Huntington, Ellsworth</name>
            <name id="BAKJO">Baker, John Randal</name>
            <name id="FAIHI">Fairchild, Henry Pratt</name>
            <name id="BURGU">Burch, Guy Ivring</name>
            <name id="TAYPA">Taylor, Paul Schuster</name>
            <name id="OGBWI">Ogburn, Fielding William</name>
            <name id="MSPP">Margaret Sanger Papers Project</name>
            <name id="SMITH">Smith, Thomas Vernor</name>
            <name id="KUCRO">Kuczynski, Robert Rene</name>
            <name id="Latin">Latin</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
            <name id="DAWBE">Dawson, Bertrand</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Margaret Sanger led this roundtable discussion in Chicago. Others who
            participated included: <person reg="Baker, John Randal">John Randal Baker</person>,
                <person reg="Burch, Guy Ivring">Guy Ivring Burch</person>, <person
                reg="Chaddock, Robert Emmet">Robert Emmet Chaddock</person>, <person
                reg="Coats, Robert Hamilton">Robert Hamilton Coats</person>, <person
                reg="Crocker, Walter Russell">Walter Russell Crocker</person>, <person
                reg="Fairchild, Henry Pratt">Henry Pratt Fairchild</person>, <person
                reg="Freund, Ernst">Ernst Freund</person>, <person reg="Gini, Corrado">Corrado
                Gini</person>, <person reg="Gosnell, Harold Foote">Harold Foote Gosnell</person>,
                <person>Mr. Hooker</person>, <person reg="Huntington, Ellsworth">Ellsworth
                Huntington</person>, <person reg="Kiessling, Oscar Edward">Oscar Edward
                Kiessling</person>, <person reg="Kuczynski, Robert Rene">Robert Rene
                Kuczynski</person>, <person reg="Lyon, Leverett Samuel">Leverett Samuel
                Lyon</person>, <person>Mrs. McLean</person>, <person reg="Nasu, Shiroshi">Shiroshi
                Nasu</person>, <person reg="Ogburn, Fielding William">Fielding William
                Ogburn</person>, <person>Mr. Okada</person>, <person reg="Pearl, Raymond">Raymond
                Pearl</person>, <person reg="Reuter, Edward Byron">Edward Byron Reuter</person>,
                <person>Mrs. Rich</person>, <person reg="Ross, Edward Alsworth">Edward Alsworth
                Ross</person>, <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>, <person
                reg="Schultz, Samuel Johnson">Samuel Johnson Schultz</person>, M<person>r.
                Schuman</person>, <person>Mr. Simpson</person>, <person>Mr. Smith</person>, <person
                reg="Smith, Thomas Vernor">Thomas Vernor Smith</person>, <person reg="Stehlc, Mr."
                >Mr. Stehlc</person>, <person reg="Steiner, Jesse Fredrick">Jesse Fredrick
                Steiner</person>, <person>Mr. Simon</person>, <person>Mr. Swen</person>, <person
                reg="Taylor, A. E.">Mr. A. E. Taylor</person>, <person reg="Taylor, G.">Mr. G.
                Taylor</person>, <person reg="Taylor, Paul Schuster">Paul Schuster Taylor</person>,
                <person reg="Thomas, Warren Simpson">Warren Simpson Thompson</person>, <person
                reg="Wright, Phillip Green">Phillip Green Wright</person>, <person
                reg="Wright, Mrs. Q.">Mrs. Q. Wright</person>, <person reg="Wright, Sewall">Sewall
                Wright</person>, <person reg="Yarros, Rachelle">Rachelle Yarros</person>, <person
                reg="Wright, Quincy">Quincy Wright</person>.</p>
        <p>The discussion was the Seventh Session of the <org>Norman Wait Harris Foundation</org>'s
                <org reg="Institute on Population and Migration, 6th (Chicago)">Sixth Institute on
                Population and Migration</org>, held on the afternoon of June 21, 1929</p>
        <p>The discussion focused on three points: 1. The general principles underlying the practice
            of birth control; 2. The extent and growth of birth control in England and the United
            States, including effects on the birth rate, laws, and clinical studies of birth control
            clinic patients; and 3. The role of birth control in the problems of population,
            including a more even distribution of wealth, increases in production and control of the
            birth rate. Other points rased were whether birth control practice was an inevitable
            result of civilization and whether population growth rate can be lowered without birth
            control</p>
        <p>Portions of the transcript were omitted by the MSPP if they did not include a back and
            forth with Sanger.</p>
        <index level1="abortion" level2="frequency of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to" level3="international"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="in marriages"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="class-based"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="in Chicago"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="physical justifications for"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="religion and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="upper classes and"/>
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Comstock Act"/>
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="doctor's only laws"/>
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="New York "/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="consequences on"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="population growth and"/>
        <index level1="Catholic Church" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="censorship" level2="in England"/>
        <index level1="censorship" level2="in United States"/>
        <index level1="England" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="eugenics" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="family size" level2="class-based"/>
        <index level1="mentally disabled and diseased" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="Netherlands, the" level2="birth control clinics in"/>
        <index level1="physically disabled and diseased" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="physicians" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="&quot;unfit&quot; to reproduce" level2="social burden of"/>
        <index level1="working classes" level2="birth control and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Round Table Discussion of Preventive Checks to Population Growth</head>
        <q who="WRIQU"><p><person reg="Wright, Quincy">The Chairman</person>: This afternoon our
                subject is Preventive Checks to Population Growth, and our leader is Mrs. <person
                    reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>, who will open the discussion.
            </p></q>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: Mr. Chairman, Ladies and Gentlemen: I first want to express my appreciation
            to the Chairman and the <org reg="The Norman Wait Harris Memorial Foundation Committee"
                >Committee</org> for the invitation to attend this conference; and also for the
            privilege of having this question of birth control or preventive checks discussed here
            this afternoon, and especially do I wish to say that I have appreciated so much the
            opportunity of listening to the discussion on population problems by such distinguished
            experts. </p>
        <p>My part this afternoon is going to be very insignificant, because I want to cover the
            first part of this outline down to question 3 and leave these questions for the
            discussion of those here. </p>
        <p>I feel that there is one significant fact in the birth control movement that must have
            recognition, and that is that it is one of the very few social movements in modern life
            which needs no missionaries. It is different from the other movements, such as the
            eugenic or social hygiene, or the other movements, because no one has to go to the mass
            of the people to tell them what they should do. The people in almost all of the
            countries, especially of the so-called civilized countries, are ready and eager to get
            information, to control the size of their families. That to me is an important fact. </p>
        <p>I think, too, that it seems almost a tie-up with that fact that almost at once people
            recognize the meaning of the words “birth control”. For instance, when I was going to
                <place>Japan</place> in 1922, I was met at <place reg="Yokahoma, Japan"
                >Yokahoma</place> by a number of representatives from the <org
                reg="Japan Government">government</org>, and not altogether welcoming me to Japan,
            and after the newspaper men with their clicking of cameras and so forth had departed, a
            group of women, about twenty or twenty-two, came forward through the gangway, and one of
            them was pushed forward to welcome me to Japan. She spoke English in a very charming and
            most accurate manner and made an address something like this: </p>
        <p>She Said: “<q who="UNK">We represent the modern, the new, the forward-looking women of
                Japan. We have much difficulty,” she said, “we have been for years trying to explain
                the importance of the women of their gaining political freedom.</q>” She said, “<q
                who="UNK">They were not interested. We have tried to tell the women of the
                importance of gaining their economic freedom; it has been difficult for them to
                understand</q>,” and she then enumerated the other trials and tribulations the
            modern woman has had in Japan and then she ended up by saying that “<q who="UNK">When
                the message of birth control came from <place reg="Honolulu, HI"
                >Honolulu</place></q>,” where we had stopped and made some addresses, she said, “<q
                who="UNK">like lightening the women understood</q>,” and I believe that also has a
            significant bearing on the subject and foreshadows the progress that this movement is
            bound to make. </p>
        <p><person reg="Dawson, Bertrand">Lord Dawson</person>, that glorious churchman and
            statesman, a few years ago went before the <org reg="The Lambeth Conference">bishops at
                Lambeth</org> and plead with the churches to take up this idea to try to help the
            younger people and the younger generation mold their lives on a sensible basis; and he
            said, “<q who="DAWBE">You may shake your heads and disclaim the right of knowledge of
                birth control, but you might just as well try to push back the ocean with a broom,
                because it is here, and it is here to stay</q>,” and I think that a great many
            people today, especially those who are thinking of the question of population and the
            future of the race, agree that Dawson was right. </p>
        <p>Naturally, I look upon the question of birth control as not only a health and economic
            expedient, but I look upon it as a very great social principle, and that principle is
            interlocked with the progress of the nation and the future of the race. I think too that
            it represents a new moral responsibility on the part of our people, and especially of
            the younger generation, and that responsibility is shown in the consciousness of
            accepting responsibility for their conduct, for their acts, not only for their own
            children who are born, but also a responsibility for those who are unborn. </p>
        <p>I think, too, that these preventative checks that we know now, while they come over
            rather a long distance from the preventive checks such as infanticide, or abortion, that
            birth control or preventing conception is the logical outcome of this long attempt on
            the part of human beings to control the size of their families. </p>
        <p>We claim that the definition of birth control is best when we say it is the conscious
            control of the birth rate by means of preventing conception. </p>
        <p>I like to emphasize the consciousness of our acts, because I think that there is a
            difference between the old laws or the attitude that there was no consciousness in
            birth, that <name type="deity">God</name> sent the children and he sent the food to feed
            them. I think today we have a different attitude when we say that it is the conscious
            control of the birth rate. </p>
        <p>We say also to prevent conception, which we say does not mean interruption, does not mean
            interference, but it means prevention, and I take issue with the group who claim that to
            prevent conception is an interference with life. I say that if it is an interference
            with life, it is no more an interference than continence or remaining single is, and if
            that is an interference with life, then I say all right, we have got to make the most of
            it. </p>
        <p>Another fact that we place great emphasis on in our educational work is that control does
            not necessarily mean limitation. When you control it means a letting out or a letting
            in, you do not necessarily put out desire when you control it, or necessarily shut off
            your engine when you control it. Control, I consider, is a word that means more and is a
            more progressive word, a more progressive attitude for us to take than limitation. </p>
        <p>The birth control movement aside from what we might call the Malthusian movement, which I
            won’t dwell upon here, but the modern birth control movement which in my estimation
            differs considerably even from the neo-Malthusian movement in <place>England</place>,
            began after the publication written by a doctor in <place reg="Boston, MA"
                >Boston</place>, Dr. <person reg="Knowlton, Charles">Knowlton</person>. That
                    <title><rs reg="Fruits of Philosophy">pamphlet</rs></title>, the first one I
            believe, was published in 1833, went its way around the world for more than 40 years. I
            don’t quite know what effect the information in that pamphlet had upon the birth rate,
            but nothing particularly striking happened until 1877, when it found its way into a
            bookseller’s shop in England in <place reg="Bristol, England">Bristol</place>, and it
            came just about the time when there were a few champions of the freedom of the press and
            freedom of speech, <person reg="Bradlaugh, Charles">Charles Bradlaugh</person> and
                <person reg="Besant, Annie">Annie Besant</person> and a number of people that
            belonged to the secular movement. This book, this pamphlet, which gives means and
            methods of contraception, was perhaps one of the first of that kind of pamphlet that had
            been published in the English language. </p>
        <p>The book dealer who was selling that pamphlet was arrested, and it was claimed the
            pamphlet came under the obscenity law of England. </p>
        <p>Besant and Bradlaugh would not allow that arrest to go unchallenged, and they took the
            case out of the bookseller’s hands and challenged the law themselves. They made quite a
            time about it, published over 40,000 of the pamphlets, slightly revised, and then went
            into the court and spent-–I believe the trial took three days, and Bradlaugh, who was
            his own attorney, and Besant threshed out the question and came through fairly
            victorious. They won, it is true, on technicalities, but, nevertheless, that information
            to prevent conception has not from that time to this day been considered in the
            obscenity class in England. </p>
        <p>When in 1914 I came upon the horizon of my maternal and domestic background, I had
            previously been working in the nursing field where anyone who had eyes could not help
            but recognize that the large families were tied up very fundamentally with most of us on
            our social problems. You looked out and saw that your large families went hand in hand
            with the problems of poverty, infant and maternal morality, ignorance, slums,
            overcrowding, and almost all of them problems that most of the social workers and the
            medical profession were trying to solve. The only way they had in solving them was
            mainly through charities, or through palliative philanthropies. </p>
        <p>On the other hand, if you were observant, you saw that the small family had very much of
            the best of it; it was not the children from the small families that were going into the
            fields and factories to labor for a mere existence. </p>
        <p>I realize there is no use taking this up with you, because you doubtless recognize it
            too, but those were the conditions that I met and I became cognizant of the fact that
            there was something fundamentally wrong with the generation, my own generation, that was
            not trying to do something fundamental about it. </p>
        <p>I saw day after day and practically month after month women who were living about us,
            that most of the energies of the nurses, and doctors and social workers would be spent
            in helping, doing what they could to alleviate the immediate suffering and going away
            feeling that our task was fairly well done, come back in another month or two, or after
            two or three months to find the same condition meeting us again, and especially is that
            so so far that women’s lives were concerned, and as far as abortions were concerned. </p>
        <p>We spent a few years of time in bringing women out of septicemia, which were conditions
            that unwanted pregnancy had put them in, and then to come back in a few months and find
            them pregnant again, and you would go through it over and over again. Such a waste of
            mother power, of woman power, of child life that was going on at that time, one who had
            been brought up individually, could not help but revolt at the conditions they saw, and
            it seemed as if there was nothing more to do than to challenge the laws that surrounded
            us in the <place>United States</place>. </p>
        <p>Well, you know that they say fools rush in where angels fear to tread, so I shot out and
            decided to challenge the constitutionality of the Federal law, under the assumption that
            all people are entitled to life, liberty and the pursuit of happiness. I challenged the
            Federal law, <title type="law"><rs reg="United States Penal Code, Section 211">Section
                    211</rs></title>, which perhaps copied the old English law – not exactly,
            because in England the laws there did not mention the prevention of conception, it was
            simply the interpretation of the judge who had a right to include anything in that
            statute, but in this country through the efforts of <person reg="Comstock, Anthony"
                >Anthony Comstock</person> the words “and prevention of conception” had been
            carefully put in Section 211, the obscenity law, so that there was no question of what
            it meant. </p>
        <p>It was not a question of opinion, it was a question of facts. </p>
        <p>To make a long story short, I brought out 100,000 pamphlets called “<title type="book"
                >Family Limitation</title>,” giving information on preventing conception. I
            challenged the law by saying that I was perfectly willing to go to jail, but if I was
            going to go I was going to go for doing something, and I thought 100,000 pamphlets would
            have a little effect upon relieving the conditions which distressed me considerably. So
            these went forth through the country, and there were seven indictments, which would have
            cost me about forty-five years in jail had convictions taken place, but then I am
            pleased to say after a fight of about a year or so, that case was dropped and so there
            has been no further work on the Federal bill. The Federal law stands exactly as it did,
            in spite of the fact that 100,000 pamphlets went through the mails and have continued to
            go through to a certain degree since that time. </p>
        <p>When I first began the issuance of these pamphlets, I believed that the question of birth
            control was one of the freedom of press and speech. I had known very little of the
            Besant-Bradlaugh trial until after 1914, when I went to England and of course knew very
            much more about it then, but I believed it was a question of free speech and free press,
            and under that assumption challenged the law. After I had been to <place
                reg="Netherlands">Holland</place>, however, in 1916, I reversed my opinion. </p>
        <p>In Holland up to 1914 there were fifty-four birth control clinics; they had been
            established and had been the outcome of the Besant-Bradlaugh trial. At this trial the
            medical profession in <place reg="Amsterdam, Netherlands">Amsterdam</place> had sent a
            physician or two physicians to sit through the trial in <place reg="London, England"
                >London</place> and out of that came Dr. Jacobs who established the first birth
            control clinic in the world. This was in Amsterdam. </p>
        <p>Dr. <person reg="Jacobs, Aletta">Jacobs</person>, after she had established that one
            clinic and saw the conditions around that clinic, within a region of so many miles,
            tremendously improved, summarized the story at a considerable length in her memoirs. Not
            only was there less deaths of mothers, less deaths of infants, children went to school,
            but there were better conditions altogether. </p>
        <p>After that a group of enthusiastic people got together in Holland and formed the <org
                reg="Dutch Neo-Malthusian League">Neo-Malthusian League</org>, and up to 1915 they
            had constantly and continuously established these various clinics. </p>
        <p>Now, the word “clinic” differs when you use it in <place>Europe</place> from the meaning
            that we have for it here; nevertheless, when I say fifty-four clinics, those were places
            with either doctors or nurses and mostly nurses, who were in charge of giving individual
            contraceptive advice and instruction. I visited, myself, in 1915 more than twenty of
            these clinics and saw, myself, largely through Dr. <person reg="Rutgers, Johannes"
                >Rutgers</person>, the technique of contraception. </p>
        <p>Then I spent three months at <place reg="The Hague, Netherlands">The Hague</place>. </p>
        <p>So I cam back from Europe at that time and had to change my opinion, that it was not a
            question of free speech, it was not a question of freedom of the press, but it was
            question of technique, and it was a question of having, inasmuch as the modern methods
            of contraception depended upon some physiological means, that it was necessary to have
            somebody who knew the physiology and anatomy of the human body, and that meant the
            medical profession, and that has been our work from 1916 up to the present time. We have
            been directing the movement through the channel of the medical profession, not trying to
            originate more methods, but to provide the best kind of methods to be employed suitable
            to the individual concerned. </p>
        <p>In this country we have twenty-four states in which there is some limitation, not only to
            the average individual in obtaining information, but even for the physician. In New York
            State the law allows the physician to give contraceptive advice for the cure or
            prevention of disease only. We are not at all satisfied with that, because it seems that
            if a woman or man comes to us, brought to us from one of the charitable associations,
            and that individual has been unable to support himself even for the last ten years, or
            support his family, and we can find no definite disease or ailment, it seems that the
            individual has to be turned back or sent away from the clinic, or from the doctor in
            charge, and told to go back home until he or she gets a proper disease, or she has a few
            more children, and come back and get some information, and then the absurdity of it is
            simply unthinkable. Yet that is the status of the law in <place>New York</place> State. </p>
        <p>In many of the other states, in fact, in twenty-four states, there is some sort of
            limitation even on the medical profession, but I believe throughout the United States
            that there is no state that will not allow the physician to give information for the
            cure or prevention of disease. I think New York has set the precedent for that, and not
            only in the law and amendments to the law, but also in a court decision that was
            rendered, in which the <person reg="Crane, Fredrick">judge</person> of the <org
                reg="New York State Court of Appeals">Court of Appeals</org> stated that a physician
            actually practicing could give information for the cure or prevention of disease, and he
            did not take the medical dictionary’s interpretation of the word disease, but <title
                type="book"><rs reg="Webster's Dictionary">Webster’s</rs></title>, so that is rather
            broad, and we hope that will be interpreted in a broader sense in some of the other
            states, especially the Western states, than it is at this time. </p>
        <p>Now, as for clinics, the first <org reg="Clinical Research Department">clinic</org> that
            was established in <place reg="New York, NY">New York City</place>, even under this
            restriction, has up to the present day had 13,000 women who have come to it and applied
            for information. Far more than 13,000 have really applied because almost one-fourth of
            that number have been sent away because of the restrictions of the law. But 13,000 have
            come and have been examined by the physicians, and a larger percentage of those have got
            information. </p>
        <p>We are at present making a survey of the case histories of 10,000 of these women, and I
            will give you just some of the facts, just a little later, that we are finding in the
            conditions of these case histories. </p>
        <p>Since that first clinic has been established in the United States, there have since that
            time been about twenty-one others, so that altogether we have twenty-two, if not more
            than that, because you almost have to put mucilage on your feet to keep track of the
            birth control movement these days, it develops so rapidly. </p>
        <p>In England the last time I heard of the development there, it was also growing very
            rapidly; there being twenty-five or twenty-six clinics in England.
                <place>Germany</place> has three in <place reg="Berlin, Germany">Berlin</place>.
            There are some twenty in <place>Austria</place>, and Holland has the same number of
            clinics today that it had in 1914. There are various reasons why they have been,
            perhaps, cut in half. One on account of the new radical element coming in to take charge
            of the work, believing that the birth control movement and the whole idea of
            contraception belong to the workers, so that there have been various conditions there
            altering the situation. </p>
        <p>The most of the clinics give information for the same reasons. We started off at first by
            saying that anyone who has a transmissible disease, syphilis, insanity, feeble
            mindedness, and various other transmissible diseases, should not have children; the
            second is that women suffering from temporary disease, such as tuberculosis, heart or
            kidney trouble should not have children or have more than they already have until the
            disease is cured; and in the third place we claim that there should be a spacing out of
            children, there should be a time between the births for the woman to recuperate from the
            birth of one child, and try to rest and try to prepare for the coming of another child;
            and fourth, we claim that the couple who already have subnormal children should not have
            more children, even on the possible chance of having a normal child, because we know
            that it takes all the care and the attention human beings can give to children that are
            subnormal. At least we discourage their having more children. </p>
        <p>In the fifth place, we say that couples should not have children, and especially the
            mother should not have children, until she has finished her adolescent development, That
            is the age from the fourteenth to the twenty-second year. We believe that, while there
            is a large percentage of us perhaps who have been born of young mothers, we consider
            that it is a very much better thing for the mother and for the child if she is fully
            developed first, both mentally and physically, before she takes up the burden of
            pregnancy and of motherhood. </p>
        <p>We further state that the couple who is not able to support themselves and not able to
            support two children should not have ten more. People, many people, may differ with
            that, but nevertheless, that is part of our educational plan; and then, last, is the
            belief and the encouragement of young people after marriage to wait a year or two years
            before they undertake the responsibility of parenthood. </p>
        <p>We believe that marriage after all today in its modern sense is not as easy of adjustment
            as it was in the old days, when women had to take the man’s word as gospel. Things have
            changed considerably, and that adjustment isn’t so simple. When you put a marriage
            certificate in the hands of your young people and throw a few pounds of rice after them,
            it is by no means certain that they are going to live happily ever after, as our divorce
            records and other records show. </p>
        <p>So we ask our young people to take a period of a year or two years to strengthen the
            bonds between them and make the development of the woman so and of the man so, and to
            make the development of marriage something before parenthood, and we believe that this
            practice will not only make for a more permanent and happier marriages, but it will make
            for bigger families; that if pregnancy is not an accident, if it is planned for, if
            there is a possibility of recuperation after the ordeal of a birth, that there is a very
            much better chance of that couple having their children slowly and spacing time, of
            having more children than there would be if they should come along by accident, and by
            chance, and they had to make the best of it. </p>
        <p>Now, there are three we will say, groups of methods, continence, sterilization and the
            chemical or mechanical means of prevention. You will all probably recognize that the
            first one, of continence, there is very little objection to, as far as the opposition of
            this work is concerned. The churches all stand back of that and applaud it, in fact,
            even the <org>Roman Catholic Church</org>, which is opposing the movement quite
            vigorously in all countries, claims that it has no quarrel with the principle of birth
            control, but with the methods of contraception; that when continence is employed, it is
            perfectly willing to agree that that is alright. </p>
        <p>So that after all even the opposition has recognized that there is a necessity for
            limitation of the family, or for control of the birth rate. </p>
        <p>Sterilization, of course, belongs to the province of the medical profession, and I think
            that there is no doubt it is coming to play an important, a large part in the whole
            question of the prevention of disease. </p>
        <p>But the real fight and the real war seems to be waged around the third group or the
            chemical and mechanical means of preventing conception. As I stated before, we placed
            this in the hands of the medical profession because we believe that is where it belongs.
            We know that every woman is different in her construction and anatomy, and particularly
            after she has had children; the woman who has had seven or eight or nine or ten children
            and had no particular care, who has had to go back to work three days after the birth of
            a child, is quite likely to have a condition differing from the woman who has only had
            one or two children. The economic condition makes a difference. So, after all, the
            methods of contraception have to be individually applied. The economic and physiological
            condition of the individual, and in many cases even the mental condition of the
            individual, determine to a certain extent the methods of birth control applied to the
            woman even more than considering the application to the man, because we have found that
            the methods that are known, especially those discovered by <person
                reg="Mensinga, Wilhelm Peter">Mensinga</person>, and that have been down to the
            present day more generally used, we might say by applying them to the women, are more
            economically applied, are easier of adjustment, more satisfactory as to the results in
            all ways than methods used by men. </p>
        <p>Now, as to our work in the <org reg="Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau">Research
                Bureau</org>, perhaps it would be of some interest to you: The 10,000 case records
            are being analyzed and will be ready perhaps for distribution sometime about the first
            of the year, and I should be most pleased if anyone here is interested in having a copy
            of this record, I should be most pleased to have you send for it or give me your name
            and address, and it will be sent to you when it is ready, – of course, it was impossible
            to take the 10,000 records, so we took 200 cases out of 10,000. These ran from January
            8, 1926, to May 2, 1926, taken in sequence from the files and fairly exhaustively
            studied. </p>
        <p>In the 200 cases, at lease 29 months had elapsed since the first visit, and mentioning
            that in passing, with regard to these cases, many women returned to the clinic many
            times, returned for supplies, returned to give an account of themselves and of their
            condition, so that we have a pretty good method of follow-up on most of these cases. </p>
        <p>Of these 200 cases, 198 were examined by <person reg="Stone, Hannah Mayer">one
                doctor</person> and advised accordingly. It was fortunate at this time that we had
            but one physician, now we have eight, so that it will be a little more difficult to have
            the same consistency perhaps in questions and in the conditions as it was with these
            first 200 cases. </p>
        <p>Only eleven women out of the 200 in this preliminary report stated they had never used
            any contraceptive methods and the remaining 189 used not only one contraceptive method,
            but more than one kind. Of the 200 women reported, there were 674 pregnancies, and 93 of
            these had more than two pregnancies; 167 of these were abortions and 93 of these had
            more than one abortion, and an interesting thing which is going to show up rather badly
            perhaps for the medical profession is that 78 per cent of these abortions had been
            induced by the medical profession, by doctors and midwives. 172 of these patients
            totaled 546 ailments, 440 were gynecological, and 97 were general medical. </p>
        <p>I just want to emphasize that, that these women who came into this clinic do not know of
            the restrictions of the law; a large majority of these women come and do no know that it
            is necessary for them to have a disease or some ailment in order to get instruction.
            They think they are quite all right, they do not know they have something the matter
            with them, in the great majority of cases, and yet, you see, of these 175 had ailments
            of which they were unconscious. </p>
        <p>As to the religious composition of these people, 37 per cent were Jewish, 34 per cent
            were Protestants and 24 per cent Catholics, and in this early study that is a little
            different than that which we believe will show in a full record, because we have
            practically every reason to think they go along more nearly one-third; in a different
            report we will show 33, 32 and 31 per cent for the religions. </p>
        <p>Twenty-six per cent of them came from social agencies, 37 per cent came from former
            patrons that had told their neighbors or their relatives, and they came along, 31 per
            cent came from publicity. Three-quarters of the wives and husbands were of foreign
            parentage, and one-half of them were foreign born. The average income of this number
            studied was rather higher than we had anticipated; it was $43 a week, it averaged that.
            While one-fourth of the number had an income of less than $35 a week; another
            one-fourth, had an income of more than $75 a week; and we found that much of it came
            from the wife’s work outside of the home, so while the income of some of these was
            large, it meant a double income from husband and wife, when the combined income was that
            amount. </p>
        <p>Now, this is just a brief survey of this question and of the work done there, but I hope
            it may be of interest to you. </p>
        <p>Now, I consider, just to conclude, it was very interesting to me the last few days,
            especially yesterday, to hear the demolishment, you might say, of the theory of <person
                reg="Malthus, Thomas Robert">Malthus</person>, that the pressure of food supply
            governs population. As far as America is concerned, it seems we do not have to wrestle
            with that problem in the immediate future, but I do believe there is a second problem
            that confronts civilization, and especially confronts us in this country where we have
            such a heterogeneous population, and that is the reconciliation of humanitarian efforts
            for race improvements. I believe that is one of the great problems that confronts us in
            this country, when you recall that in 1927, nine billions of dollars were spent on
            defectives and delinquents and dependents and that is no more than nine billion dollars
            foolishly spent to let a certain number of people live and propagate and to increase the
            needs for more billions in the next five or ten years. </p>
        <p><q who="WRIQU">The Chairman: Mrs. Sanger has presented this subject in a way which I am
                sure will suggest many questions. I believe that Mrs. Sanger suggested that the
                third topic on the outline which is before you would be the most suitable to raise
                questions about. The floor is open for general discussion. </q></p>
        <p><q who="ROSED">Dr. <person reg="Ross, Edward Alsworth">Ross</person>: Mr. Chairman, I
                would like to ask Mrs. Sanger if such information is given to the unmarried.
            </q></p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: In our clinic it is not given to the unmarried, first, on account of the
            laws; and, second, because we are making a study of the subject and we are rather
            careful. On occasion women do not come to us saying they are about to be married, in
            many cases the man comes with them, and they say that they are to be married, and they
            would both like to have any instructions given; and in many other cases the mother comes
            with a daughter saying that her health is thus and so and she should not have children
            immediately, but we have not given information to the unmarried. </p>
        <p><q who="ROSED">Dr. Ross: Is it given to those who are married where there is no reason
                why they should not have children, but where the woman, for example, for one reason
                or another, wants to sidestep maternity entirely? </q></p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: You mean in case where she does not wish to? </p>
        <p><q who="ROSED">Dr. Ross: Yes, in other words, if she wishes not to have children, is that
                conclusive, or do you use your own judgement whether she is entitled to sidestep
                children?</q>
        </p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: In this case it has to be given on disease in our clinic. A woman in coming
            to our clinic there has to have something the matter with her physically or mentally,
            some ailment in order to get information. </p>
        <p><q who="ROSED">Dr. Ross: Would that be true elsewhere in the United States. </q></p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: No, not at all. I think in <place reg="Chicago, IL">Chicago</place> and in
            almost every one of the other clinics, I think they would perhaps – Dr. <person
                reg="Yarros, Rachelle">Yarros</person> is here and will probably give you some
            information upon the clinics in Chicago, how they are conducted, but I think there is a
            much broader interpretation of the needs in the other clinics than there is in ours. </p>
        <p><q who="HUNEL">Dr. <person reg="Huntington, Ellsworth">Huntington</person>: Mrs Sanger, I
                would like to ask, since the clinic began, has there been any change in the social
                status of the people who come? Naturally, such things begin with a higher level and
                is there any evidence that birth control is going down to the lower levels? </q></p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: As to the kind of people who come to the clinic? </p>
        <p><q who="HUNEL">Dr. Huntington: Yes. </q></p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: Very definitely; very definitely, there is a change. In fact, if we should
            have our clinic supported so that we didn’t have to depend upon it, we do try to make it
            self supporting, but if we could have it supported from the outside, we can devote the
            entire time of our seven doctors to giving attention to people who come from the
            charities and from the associations, who are dependent upon outside help for their
            existence. </p>
        <p><q who="HUNEL">Dr. Huntington: Are you making any special effort to reach those who are
                dependent? </q></p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: Oh, yes, a very great effort, but I say we don’t have to, we have more
            people coming to us than we can take care of. </p>
        <p><q who="HUNEL">Dr. Huntington: Are you making any effort to reach them more than to reach
                others? </q></p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: Well, I think it is safe to say all of our – we call it propaganda--is
            directed to what we call the unfit, or those who should have it for eugenic or other
            considerations. </p>
        <p><q who="ROSED">Dr. Ross: Mrs. Sanger, are the lines of the Catholic Church holding firm,
                or are some of the priests beginning to shake a little? </q></p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: Yes, I think we have had, in the last year several women come to us who have
            been sent by one Catholic priest in New York, and even some of the Catholic charities,
            and their social workers have brought us cases to give instruction to. I think there is
            a gradual giving way on the part of the Catholic Church, especially part of the church,
            at least some of those in the church. </p>
        <p><q who="BAKJO">Dr. <person reg="Baker, John Randal">Baker</person>: May I ask, Mrs.
                Sanger, as to the percentage of individuals who have not individually practiced
                contraception, I forget it. It seemed very significant; it does not seem to be a
                means for disseminating information, but merely of disseminating better information.
            </q></p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: Yes, eleven women out of 200, I don’t think I gave the percentage, only
            eleven had never used any contraception; 189 had used more than one contraceptive
            method. </p>
        <p><q who="WRIQU">The Chairman: Does that include abortions, that 189? </q></p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: It would include abortions, yes. I mean sometimes the contraceptive method
            fails and would result in abortion. </p>
        <q who="FAIHE"><p>Dr. <person reg="Fairchild, Henry Pratt">Fairchild</person>: In reference
                to that inquiry of Dr. Ross’ about the <org reg="Roman Catholic Church">Catholic
                    Church</org>, Mrs. Sanger, I would like to suggest a qualification. An amount of
                the Catholic literature, it is perfectly true, a good deal of Catholic literature
                seems to me, all the way up from the <foreign lang="Latin">pater dicta</foreign> by
                the bishop, but there is also other authentic Catholic literature in pater dicta,
                that protests against any family limitation, no matter how achieved, on the ground
                that it interferes with the maximum number of people to furnish a world which is
                pleasing to divinity. There is, however, a good deal of Catholic literature that
                seems to leave the way open for family limitation by continence. </p>
            <p>If any of you care for a complete reference on that, I can give you one or two
                references that give the foremost Catholic authorities on the subject of the
                predetermination of the family of the married couples, the weight of authority is
                that it is contrary to the Catholic doctrine. </p></q>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: Dr. Fairchild, may I ask you if there has ever been a pronouncement from the
                <org>Vatican</org>, for instance? </p>
        <p><q who="FAIHE">Dr. Fairchild: The most empathetic statement that I have in mind on this
                movement is in a book by a Catholic priest, which bears the sign manual of
                Archbishop <person reg="Hayes, Patrick J.">Hayes</person>, and the signet of the
                official censor, in which the statement is very positively made, another which I
                recall at the moment is the fact that a publication some few years ago issued as a
                rule of conduct for, I think the <org reg="Holy Name Society">Holy Name Order</org>,
                an argument for large and holy families, which was a matter of the subject of an
                editorial in one of the leading Catholic magazines. That does not necessarily say
                that large and holy families means the largest possible families, but there is no
                doubt at all that the implication was that Catholic families, to meet the standards
                set up by the <person reg="Pius, XI">Pope</person>, were to be as large as possible.
                That was a doctrine which, I believe, bears the technical name of an interpretation.
            </q></p>
        <p><q who="BURGU">Mr. <person reg="Burch, Guy Ivring">Burch</person>: Mr. Chairman, I think
                perhaps I might be able to throw a little light on that subject, in the Forum of the
                    <org reg="New York Academy of Medicine">Academy of Medicine</org> about a month
                ago, one of the speakers was a priest, and there are certain passages from various
                Councils and various pronouncements of the authorities in <place reg="Rome, Italy"
                    >Rome</place> condemning birth control. That was supposed to be the word of an
                official from Rome. </q></p>
        <p><q who="ROSED">Dr. Ross: Mrs. Sanger, do you know whether in this country the priest is
                at liberty in the confessional of women to inquire as to why there have been no
                children born for two or three or four years? I understand in <place>France</place>
                public opinion obliged them to abandon that entirely, they do not inquire into that,
                but I know in some parts of this country they are doing that right now. Do you know
                how that is? </q></p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: Yes, I think I do, they do ask that here, I have heard that they do, that is
            a question that is asked. </p>
        <p><q who="HUNEL">Dr. Huntington: I know that they do and Catholic neighbors of mine told my
                    <person reg="Damon, Cornelia Huntington">sister</person> so; this neighbor
                already had a large family of four or five and she said that the priest said she
                ought to have more, and that was a family of fairly well to do people. </q></p>
        <p><q who="TAYPA">Mr. P. S. Taylor: Mr. Chairman, may I ask the basis of that statement,
                that birth control sometimes meant more children per family, do I understand Mrs.
                Sanger to say that? </q></p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: Yes, I do; I do think that birth control when it is properly disseminated is
            likely to mean more children in many cases than if the individuals had to bring children
            into the world by chance. We have had in a good many cases, and there are records of
            women who became perhaps after the birth of one child, nervous, irritable, on the verge
            of a divorce or separation, and after an adjustment and after four years’ time there has
            been an increase in the family and plans of more in the future. We have records of that,
            but I cannot give them to you now on account of this very limited record, but they will
            show up, I think, quite well in our larger study. </p>
        <p><q who="FAIHE">Dr. Fairchild: Did you urge that as a compensation, that that would be the
                total social effect? </q></p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: I don’t know as I would urge it as a compensation, but I believe it will
            make its appearances in many families. I think it will make an increase in many families
            that would not otherwise have had the same number. </p>
        <p><q who="OGBWI">Mr. <person reg="Ogburn, William Fielding">Ogburn</person>: May I ask Mrs.
                Sanger about the selection of these 200 cases. You had how many thousand, ten
                thousand cases which you studied? </q></p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: Yes. </p>
        <p><q who="OGBWI">Mr. Ogburn: You selected for study 200 cases about which you are reporting
                this afternoon? </q></p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: Yes. </p>
        <p><q who="OGBWI">Mr. Ogburn: How did you select these? </q></p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: Well, we took just the first 200 in the record, we took them out from March
            8 to May 2, 1926, just in one year, because <person reg="Stone, Hannah Mayer">one
                physician</person> was taking care of all the cases over the period of that time, of
            two years, of 1926. They might have been any other 200 cases, they pick them out, and he
            took them out in sequence. </p>
        <p><q who="OGBWI">Mr. Ogburn: Took them out in sequence because they were at a particular
                time when a particular physician handled them? </q></p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: Yes. </p>
        <p><q who="OGBWI">Mr. Ogburn: Did you believe these 200 samples were representative of the
                whole 1,000, or if not in what way would they be considered? </q></p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: Well, I think they are fairly representative except in this way: That as the
            movement advances, I mean since 1926 to the present time, we have in the first place I
            think poorer patients who are coming to us, this may change that in some degree. I think
            that any piece of work done by one person is likely to give a little more consistency
            perhaps than by several people, I mean in the examination by several doctors. That may
            make a little change but not material, it will not have any great effect. I think the
            whole change will probably be as far as the individuals are concerned, assisted, a
            higher percentage from the various organizations, and also lower social status. </p>
        <p><q who="WRIPH">Mr. <person reg="Wright, Phillip Green">P. G. Wright</person>: I should
                like to ask one question of Mrs. Sanger: I have heard it stated that one of the
                problems at the present time was the fact the well to do class already practiced
                birth control successfully to a great extent, but the lower class did not, and that,
                therefore, there was a disturbing movement in the population to an inferior racial
                type. Have you anything to say on that question? </q></p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: Well, I think that that is probably true, I think that is so. We can tell to
            a certain extent from our birth rate that there has been a certain group of the natives,
            those that are better able in the country, who have been having fewer children, and I
            think this, and that is my reference to the contingencies affecting the differential
            birth rate, I believe that it can be brought about, I think it can be quite effective
            upon the differential birth rate, if this movement is properly directed. I believe that
            is what appears today to be more than anything else its direction. </p>
        <p><q who="WRIPH">Mr. P. G. Wright: And one of the advantages would be an economical one.
            </q></p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: Yes, particularly with what I would call a hook-up with the social agencies.
            The social agencies in this country are well organized, they come in contact with all of
            the people in the conditions that are having large families, which we say they should
            not have, either way they are not able to maintain them and not able to take care of
            them, and I think that could be done within a generation, I should say, I believe there
            could be a tremendous change in the differential birth rate if that were done. </p>
        <p><q who="MSPP">[Comment by Dr. Yarros was omitted] </q></p>
        <p><q who="MSPP">Mr. <person reg="Lyon, Leverett Samuel">Lyon</person>: [Portions of Mr.
                Lyon’s comment were omitted]</q>
            <q who="LYOLE">What I am anxious to know is whether you think the question-–I suppose I
                am not giving any information on that matter that you do not have–-as to whether you
                think there is probably real danger now from that sort of thing, not on the question
                of there being too much freedom of speech unless you consider all advertising too
                much freedom of speech, but whether there is a danger of a restrictive sort through
                the facilities of the law apparently permitting a commercial enterprise, making it
                possible to obtain this sort of thing without any clinical examination or clinical
                service, in view of what seems to be happening in the neighborhood drug stores, for
                we are talking about a few clinics where that information can be obtained. I wonder
                whether it may get us in a position where we have as much concern about controlling
                and preventing information as we have had in the past about disseminating it.
            </q></p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: Of course, that same condition applies to European countries in England they
            seem to have all the devices for contraception in book shops and not in the drug stores,
            and certainly in Holland it is much the same, except in Holland they try to direct
            people to go to the clinics and receive some instruction as to the application and the
            kind of method used. I think the only answer to promiscuous information is that it is on
            a par with getting your glasses at the ten cent store. If we get people to recognize it
            is a personal application, just as the proper shoe fitted to your feet, then I think the
            matter is safe, but it is very interesting what you tell about Chicago. I had not
            imagined it was going to grow as fast as that. </p>
        <p><q who="MSPP">[Comment by Dr. Yarros was omitted] </q></p>
        <p><q who="HUNEL">Dr. Huntington: In this connection, I had a question I was going to ask.
                On the train coming here this morning I picked up a copy of <title type="journal"
                    >Liberty</title>, I don’t read <title type="journal">Liberty</title> very often,
                but in that copy I found an advertisement of a birth control device which was
                veiled, but it was perfectly clear what it meant. There we have a direct challenge
                of the National law about carrying things through the mails, so it looks to me in
                view of what has just been said, as if things were going so rapidly that the
                difficulty soon might be to prevent birth control information from being given in
                the wrong way. What do you think? </q></p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: Well, I think it needs direction, I certainly agree that it does need it,
            and in fact to me that is the whole thing, that we have simply got to give the
            direction, we have got to have clinics and have it established in the organization and
            institutions where it would be accessible to those who applied. I think if there were
            more easily accessible proper information for the people that they would prefer to go
            there, where it is given in the proper way than to take it hit or miss. I think that is
            especially so far as women are concerned. </p>
        <p><q who="WRIQU">The Chairman: I wish we might have some of the questions relating to the
                influence of birth control on the solution of social problems suggested in the third
                question, and suggest that to Dr. <person reg="Kuczynski, Robert Rene"
                    >Kuczynski</person>. </q></p>
        <p><q who="MSPP">[Comment by Dr. Kuczynski was omitted] </q></p>
        <p><q who="MSPP">Mr. P. G. Wright: [Portions of Mr. P. G. Wright’s comment was omitted]
                </q><q who="WRIPH">Now, perhaps the chief thing to make such an adjustment is to
                have this general sentiment broadcast, that it is an obligation for a man and woman
                to have as many children as they feel they can bring up to an economic status a
                little better than their own. That would seem pretty nearly adjusting population to
                means of substance, if it were carried out by widespread public sentiment. I should
                like to have Mrs. Sanger’s opinion on that. </q></p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: Yes, I quite agree. I should like to have Professor Ross answer Dr.
            Kuczynski’s question. It seems to me, as I have seen in families, and I don’t know why
            it should not apply to a nation or to a population, that it seems more like a question
            of absorption in the family. I mean four children can come to a man and woman with great
            rapidity before they are adjusted, before they have the equipment to take care of four
            children, but if these same four children come over a long period of time with more
            experience, with better organization of the home, having more equipment to look after
            four children, without pushing down their standards, I believe, and I have seen it, that
            these four children are not only more welcome, but are an asset to the family, and I
            don’t see why the same thing would not apply to a nation. </p>
        <p>Dr. Ross, will you answer Dr. Kuczynski’s question? </p>
        <p><q who="MSPP">[Comments by Dr. Ross, Dr. Kuczynski, Mr. P. G. Wright, Mr. Ogburn, Dr.
                Fairchild, and Mr. <person reg="Chaddock, Robert Emmet">Chaddock</person> were
                omitted] </q></p>
        <p><q who="SMITH">Mr. <person reg="Smith, Thomas Vernor">T. V. Smith</person>: I wonder if
                it is accurate to emphasize in the application of the so-called regulator that Mr.
                    <person reg="Wigmore, John Henry">Wigmore</person> proposes, of a constitutional
                amendment in this country, where the contest between the sociologist and physician-–
                Are you a physician, Mrs. Sanger? </q></p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: No, I am not a physician. </p>
        <p><q who="MSPP">[Comments by Mr. T. V. Smith, The Chairman, Dr. Yarros, Dr. Huntington, Dr.
                    <person reg="Schultz, Samuel Jonathan">Schultz</person>, Mr. P. G. Wright, and
                Dr. <person reg="Thompson, Warren Simpson">Thompson</person> were omitted] </q></p>
        <p><q who="KUCRO">Dr. Kuczynski: I think the question of income is not so essential in this
                connection. The essential and the interesting point is: does the more
                efficient-–with birth control – have more children than the less efficient? If this
                is the case, it would, of course, be in contradiction to what we have usually
                assumed, that is, that the so-called proletarians have the largest number of
                children while the more successful have less children. But if birth control has the
                effect that it will bring about a stronger increase among the superior class we
                should be aware that it is only a small minority of the population, which are really
                efficient, and it would, of course, have a very strong numerical effect if in the
                future the ten per cent efficient would have a family of three surviving children,
                and the ninety percent inefficient, and probably those who have not taken an
                academic degree would be still less than efficient – would have one child only. From
                the standpoint of eugenics birth control would then certainly be most welcome, but
                it would certainly very greatly diminish the total number of the population.
            </q></p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: May I suggest that I brought up the question on that point about some of the
            cases having more children, because I think Dr. Fairchild-–Dr. Fairchild, you read the
            case, and you suggest I relate this, because of some of the cases. </p>
        <p>We had dinner in New York, a money raising scheme, and we had some of the women
            themselves come there and tell about their own family conditions, and many people were
            much impressed with the fact that one young Russian woman got up and said that she, I
            think, had been born just previous to the outbreak of the war, and had tuberculosis, and
            she came to this country and had to go to <place reg="Saranac Lake, NY">Saranac</place>, or
            some such place, she was very much in love with a young man who was working his way
            through the university, she had been told on account of the tuberculosis she must not
            marry, to have children would endanger her life, and she heard about birth control, she
            came to get information, went to one of the doctors and got information and was
            eventually married and was eventually cured of tuberculosis, and she now had her baby
            and turned around to her audience and said, “<q who="UNK">I have a baby and I am going
                to have another, but I want to have a little time</q>”. That was quite impressive to
            the people there. </p>
        <p>It might be interesting also, the number of children recorded at this clinic. Twenty
            families of unskilled laborers had seventy-four children, 3.7 per family, I think that
            is about what you would expect; twenty-five families in a small trade group; eighty-six
            children, 3.7; sixty-four families, 127 children, or two per family; seventeen families
            in the transportation group had thirty-six children, or two per family; eight families
            in the domestic group, eleven children, or 1.3 per family; twenty-nine families in the
            big business group, thirty children or one per family; miscellaneous group had one. </p>
        <p><q who="WRIQU">The Chairman: That would be the reverse: Dr. Huntington’s group was chosen
                from university graduates, this was from the whole population. </q></p>
        <p>Mrs Sanger: You must recognize that in the clinic after all, we do have a more selective
            group, we have to take those who have something to matter with them, so there is
            something different. I would like to ask Professor Smith, is your objection to the
            medical profession on grounds of education or on technical grounds? </p>
        <p><q who="SMITH">Mr. Smith: Oh, not technical, but we were talking here of an optimum
                population and the medical profession hasn’t any standard, individual or collective,
                and I wouldn’t expect it to have a standard at the present time. </q></p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: I think as far as the birth control movement is concerned, the whole point,
            and I think Dr. Yarros will bear me out, is that were are not asking the medical
            profession to judge for us how many children we may have, as much as what methods would
            be most suitable for us to use for success. </p>
        <p><q who="WRIQU">The Chairman: This Round Table cannot last very much longer. I should like
                to give an opportunity to everyone who has not spoken yet who wishes to say
                something. </q></p>
        <p><q who="MSPP">[Comments by Mr. P. G. Wright, Dr. Huntington, The Chairman, Dr. Kuczynski,
                Mr. Ogburn, Mr. Thompson, Mr. Fairchild, Dr. Simpson, Dr. <name reg="Shiroshi"
                    >Nasu</name> and Mr. Crocker are omitted] </q></p>
        <p><q who="KUCRO">Dr. Kuczynski: As to <place>Spain</place>, I don’t see any reason, in
                fact, I know there is a good deal of birth control, and I wonder why in the city of
                    <place reg="Barcelona, Spain">Barcelona</place>, which is their most modern
                city, there should not be birth control. We have just heard that in Japan there is
                after all also birth control. In France there are more births in cities than in
                rural districts, because for more than a hundred years there has been a new law
                which compels every farmer to divide his land among his children. </q></p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: You are quite right about Spain, because I was there in 1915, and there was
            a lot of information going through there, which was quite a surprise to me. </p>
        <p><q who="OGBWI">Mr. Ogburn: I would like to ask Mrs. Sanger if she would make a guess, if
                she doesn’t know the answer to this question, what percentage of families in England
                have knowledge of contraception, about what percentage? </q></p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: I should say within the last five years that it is safe to say over sixty
            per cent. </p>
        <p><q who="OGBWI">Mr. Ogburn: And how about a state like New York, for instance? </q></p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger: That might be less. </p>
        <p><q who="MSPP">[Comments by Mr. Thompson, Dr. Kuczynski and Dr. Fairchild were
                omitted]</q></p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
