<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Interview">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2013/12/11 JK encoded</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-08-21 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1933-01-17"><supplied resp="MSPP">17 Jan 1933</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Interview with the Los Angeles
                Times</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421055</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Birth Control Progress Told</title>, <title type="Journal"
                    >Los Angeles Times</title>, Jan. 17, 1933, A3 </bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="LAT">Los Angeles Times</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Sanger's speech was not found; coverage from news provides some
            extracts. </p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="movement" level3="in California"/>
        <index level1="progress"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Birth Control Progress Told</head>
        <head type="sub">
            <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person> Reports on Educational
            Strides</head>

        <p>
            <q who="LAT">In spite of the storm of opposition which has raged around the subject of
                birth control, remarkable progress is being made in the matter of education,
                according to Mrs. Margaret Sanger.</q> “Prejudices are being broken down rapidly,”
            she said, “and while public opposition has died down to a large extent, unfortunately
            there still is much organized opposition. Education concerning the necessity for birth
            control is the basis of our whole problem and then we must have recognition of the
            movement by governments in order that birth control information will come under the
            jurisdiction and direction of qualified persons. Poor women, for instance, must have
            places where they can go to receive scientific instruction."</p>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Importance Cited</head>
            <p>“It is important that this movement should make progress, for I believe that
                civilization soon will be swamped if the birth-control movement fails. It is a fact
                that there is a larger percentage of incompetents being born now because there is a
                larger number of them reproducing.” <q who="LAT">In this connection Mrs. Sanger said
                    many of the countries of <place>Europe</place> are looking toward
                        <place>California</place> with great interest to see what will be the
                    results and effects of the State’s sterilization law, which is quite generally
                    regarded, she asserts, as one of the greatest forward strides in legislation in
                    the direction of humanitarianism.</q>
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Student Attitude </head>
            <p><q who="LAT">Mrs. Sanger said it has been her experience when attending conferences
                    of college students on the subject of birth control that mixed groups approach
                    the subject from a purely scientific angle, with an utter lack of
                    self-consciousness.</q></p>
        </div>

    </docBody>
</doc>
