<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-03-05 JK initial tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-19 CH proof tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-26 JK correct tags</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1936-02-20">20 Feb 1936</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP"> Comments at Hong Kong
                    Luncheon</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421090</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Mrs. Sanger Welcomed</title>,
                    <title>South China Morning Post</title>, Feb. 20,
                1936</bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="SCMP">South China Morning Post</name>
            <name id="HOKO">Ho, Kom-tong</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger</person> spoke
        briefly at a luncheon party hosted by Mr. and Mrs. <person
            reg="Ho, Kom-tong">Ho Kom-tong</person> home in <place
            reg="Hong Kong, China">Hong Kong</place>. After a toast by Ho
        Kom-Tong, Sanger made short comments which were summarized in "<title
            type="article">Mrs. Sanger Welcomed</title>," <title type="journal"
            >South China Morning Post</title>, Feb. 21, 1936. <person
            reg="How-Martyn, Edith">Edith How-Martyn</person> also spoke. <index
            level1="China" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="China" level2="birth rate in"/>
        <index level1="China" level2="overpopulation and"/>
        <index level1="China" level2="population policies of"/><index
            level1="children" level2="unwanted"/><index level1="birth rate"
            level2="efforts to reduce"/><index level1="birth control movement"
            /><index level1="birth control" level2="international"/><index
            level1="birth control" level2="in China"/><index level1="Asia"
            level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Asia" level2="overpopulation and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Mrs. Sanger Welcomed</head>
        <head type="sub">Mr. Ho Kom-tong's Tribute at Luncheon Party</head>
        <q who="SCMP"><p>Mrs. Sanger Welcomed Mr. Ho Kom-tong’s Tribute At
                Luncheon Party A luncheon party was held yesterday afternoon at
                the residence of Mr. and Mrs. <person reg="Kom-tong, Ho">Ho
                    Kom-tong</person> in honour of Mrs. Sanger and Mr. and Mrs.
                    <person reg="Martyn, Herbert">How-Martyn</person>, birth
                control advocates. Among those present were: - Mr. and Mrs. Ho
                Kom-tong, Sir <person reg="Hotung, Robert">Robert</person> and
                Lady <person reg="Lin-kok, Clara Cheung">Ho Tung</person>, Hon.
                Mr. and <person reg="Hotung, Victoria">Mrs.</person>
                <person reg="Lo, Man-kam">M. K. Lo</person>, Professor and
                    <person reg="Nixon, Siddy">Mrs.</person>
                <person reg="Nixon, W.C.W">W. C. W. Nixon</person>, Mrs.<person
                    reg="Dunbar, L."> L. Dunbar</person>, Mr.<person
                    reg="Raymond, E.M."> E. M. Raymond</person>, Mr. and Mrs.
                    <person reg="Forrest, R. A. D.">R. A. D. Forrest</person>,
                Mrs. <person reg="Biggar, D.M.">D. M. Biggar</person>,
                    Mr.<person reg="Morris, A."> A. Morris</person>, Dr. and
                Mrs. <person reg="Woo, Arthur">Arthur Woo</person>, Mrs. <person
                    reg="Gee, C.">C. Gee</person>, Mr. <person
                    reg="Zimmerman, W.">W. Zimmerman</person> and Dr. <person
                    reg="Tseung, F. I.">F. I. Tseung</person>.</p></q>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Need of Birth Control</head>
            <p><q who="SCMP">Mr. Ho Kom-tong, addressing those present, said:
                    </q><q who="HOKO">- Ladies and Gentlemen,- I cannot allow
                    the occasion of the memorable visit of social pioneers of
                    the reputation of Mrs. Sanger and Mrs. How-Martyn to pass
                    without a few words of welcome and appreciation. Mrs. Sanger
                    and Mrs. How-Martyn come for the first time to Hongkong to
                    show us how greater happiness for the home can be helped, by
                    means of scientific limitation of the size of the family.
                    Being a medical man myself, and living in the midst of one
                    of the most populous areas of the world, I cannot help
                    feeling that poverty and over-population are intimately
                    inter-connected. It is a fact that many of the married
                    couples in <place>China</place>, have not the means to
                    maintain a family, of six or seven children, which is so
                    typical of Chinese life. We in Hongkong spend, throughout
                    the <org
                        reg="The Society for the Protection and Care of Children"
                        >Society for the Protection of Children</org>, some
                    $30,000 a year in relief of needy children, but even that
                    amount only touches the fringe of the work. The mothers
                    themselves are not necessarily anxious to have six or seven
                    children tied to their apron-strings;. Some of them soon
                    have to part with the superfluous children which they cannot
                    afford to feed, while others, before such children are born,
                    use harmful means to prevent their birth. Further, the rate
                    of maternal mortality is so great that womenfolk in China
                    generally will only be too glad to welcome a simple,
                    harmless and inexpensive method, whereby the birthrate can
                    be regulated and lowered. I am sure that Mrs. Sanger and
                    Mrs. How-Martyn have perfected such a method, and I
                    sincerely hope that they will leave behind a keen band of
                    converts to carry on the good work which they are starting
                    here. Given such zeal, and an efficient organization, I have
                    no doubt that the future of many homes in China will be
                    brighter and the lot of the average Chinese mother will be
                    much happier. I wish you, Mrs. Sanger and Mrs. How-Martyn,
                    every success in your human work here as well as in other
                    places. Ladies and gentlemen, will you rise and drink
                    heartily with me and to the health of Mrs. Sanger and Mrs.
                    How-Martyn and to the success of their work here? </q></p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Mrs. Sanger Replies </head>
            <p>
                <q who="SCMP">Mrs. Sanger replied and thanked Mr. and Mrs. Ho
                    Kom-tong for their charming hospitality. She appreciated so
                    much the fine understanding of her host relating to the
                    conditions of the people in Hongkong, and what birth control
                    would do for them. She agreed with Mr. Ho Kom-tong that the
                    mothers of large families would be happy and contented to
                    have half the number properly spared and brought into the
                    world with some consideration of the mother’s health and the
                    father’s earning capacity. All normal parents want children
                    but there is a difference between the mother having three or
                    four spared children that she can bring up properly and the
                    woman with a pregnancy year after year resulting in six or
                    seven children and the same number dying before the first
                    year. Mr. Ho Kom-tong is right in assuring that we have
                    found a method simple, harmless, inexpensive and suitable to
                    the masses which will not cost more than a dollar a year
                    when properly dispensed under public health auspices, she
                    said. </q></p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
