<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article ">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-04-09 JK initial tag</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1957-00-00 ">1957</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Birth Control, 1956</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421076</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Birth Control, 1956</title><title
                    type="journal">Britannica Book of the Year</title> (1957),
                pp. 163-164</bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>For other articles in the <title type="journal"
                >Britannica Book of the Year</title> series, see<xref
                from="320980.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control,
                    1946</title></xref>; <xref from="320979.xml"><title
                    type="article">Birth Control, 1947</title></xref><xref
                from="321981.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control,
                    1948</title></xref><xref from="320981.xml"><title
                    type="article">Birth Control, 1949</title></xref><xref
                from="321981.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control,
                    1950</title></xref>; <xref from="320983.xml"><title
                    type="article">Birth Control, 1951</title></xref>; <xref
                from="320984.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control,
                    1952</title></xref>; <xref from="321984.xml"><title
                    type="article">Birth Control, 1953</title></xref>; <xref
                from="320985.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control,
                    1954</title></xref>; <xref from="321986.xml"><title
                    type="article">Birth Control, 1955</title></xref>; <xref
                from="320987.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control,
                    1957</title></xref>; <xref from="320988.xml"><title
                    type="article">Birth Control, 1958</title></xref>.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="international"/><index
            level1="China" level2="overpopulation and"/>
        <index level1="China" level2="population policies of"/><index
            level1="India" level2="population policies of"/><index
            level1="Italy" level2="population policies of"/><index
            level1="Planned Parenthood Federation of America"/>
        <index level1="International Planned Parenthood Federation"/><index
            level1="Japan" level2="population policies of"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Birth Control.</head>
        <p> A considerable increase in the number of government grants to
            support and encourage the spread of family planning programs in
            underdeveloped countries was noted during 1956. In
                <place>India</place>, a program for intensive expansion of
            family planning services, especially in rural areas, was drawn up by
            the government for inclusion in its second five-year plan. The
            program called for an expenditure of $6,300,000 to establish 1,100
            health centers providing children welfare and maternity services as
            well as family planning.</p>
        <p> The first elected (1955) representative government of
                <place>Singapore</place> granted $28,335 to the <org
                reg="Singapore Planned Parenthood Association">Family Planning
                association of Singapore</org>, which operated 14 clinics whose
            total attendance numbered 10,168. A government grant totaling
            $10,000 was made to the <org>Family Planning Association of <place
                    reg="Hong Kong, China">Hong Kong</place>
            </org>for assistance in operating a new central clinic and
            headquarters which were being built by the association. The Hong
            Kong family Planning association sponsored nine clinics, serving a
            total of more than 15,492 women. Under government auspices, an
            organized campaign for birth control was launched in
                <place>Egypt</place>, aimed at curbing the country’s rapidly
            rising population. The Population Commission’s medical committee was
            charged with opening 12 family planning clinics. Eight clinics
            opened during 1956.</p>
        <p> The government of <place>Japan</place>, which adopted a national
            family planning program in 1951, allotted nearly $90,000 in 1956 to
            teach birth control methods and supply free contraceptives to the
            indigent; 783 nationally administered health centers gave wide
            publicity to family planning, and more than 28,600 persons, mostly
            midwives, took the concept control course offered by the
            prefectures. </p>
        <p>Italy’s first consulting office for information on scientific
            contraceptive methods was opened in <place reg="Rome, Italy"
                >Rome</place> under sponsorship of the <org>Italian Association
                for Demographic Education</org>. The first office of its kind to
            exist in Italy, the association waged a campaign to overcome
            religious and political prejudice against birth control, and to
            repeal Italy’s anti-birth control law, adopted by the government in
            1930.</p>
        <p> Official and unofficial reports were received during 1956 indicating
            the spread of birth control in the communist world. <place>Hungary
            </place>approved contraceptives as a means of fighting the country’s
            abortion menace early in the year. In <place>Czechoslovakia</place>,
            a treatise on birth control <title type="article">Anticonception and
                the Fight Against Abortion</title>, was published by the <org
                reg="State Health Publishing House Czechoslovakia">state Health
                Publishing office</org>. </p>
        <p>In Communist <place>China</place>, where the net daily increase in
            population was 34,000, or more than a third of the entire world’s
            net daily increase, the government, in a sharp departure from
            communist policy, launched an all-out birth control program.
            Twenty-seven birth control information centers were opened in <place
                reg="Peking, China">Peking</place>, and it was reported that
            government newspapers were issuing detailed instructions on the use
            of contraceptives. </p>
        <p>A world-wide essay contest to find a solution to the problem of
            overpopulation in underdeveloped countries was sponsored during 1956
            by the<org
                reg="International Catholic Institute fo rSocial-Ecclesiastical Research"
                > International Institute for Social-Ecclesiastical
                Research</org> in <place reg="Geneva, Switzerland"
                >Geneva</place>, an official Roman Catholic institution. The
            unprecedented contest offered a $5,000 prize for the best proposed
            solutions to the overpopulation problem, within the framework of
            Catholic principles. The contest prospectus recognized the
            difficulty of increasing food supplies and raising living standards
            fast enough to keep up with population growth.</p>
        <p><org>The International Planned Parenthood Federation</org> added
            three new countries to its membership rolls-
            -<place>Belgium</place>, <place>Denmark</place>, and <place> New
                Zealand</place>-- bringing the total membership to 18. Other
            member countries were: <place>Australia</place>,
                <place>Ceylon</place>, the <place reg="West Germany">German
                Federation Republic</place>, Great Britain, Hong Kong, India,
            Italy, Japan, <place>the Netherlands</place>,
                <place>Pakistan</place>, <place>Puerto Rico</place>, Singapore,
                <place>Sweden</place>, <place>Union of South Africa</place> and
            the <place>United States</place>. </p>
        <p>More than 850 persons attended the 36th annual meeting of the
                <org>Planned Parenthood Federation of America</org>, held in
                <place reg="New York, NY">New York City</place> in May 1956.
            Annual <org reg="The Lasker Foundation">Lasker</org> Awards in
            Planned Parenthood were presented to <person reg="Nelson, Warren O."
                >Warren O. Nelson</person>, medical director of the
                <org>Population Council</org>, and <person reg="Cook, Robert C."
                >Robert C. Cook</person>, editor of the <title type="journal"
                >Population Bulletin</title>, for their contributions in the
            field of family planning. There were 110 state leagues and local
            committees in 29 states and the <place>District of Columbia</place>,
            including the <org>Margaret Sanger Research Bureau</org> in New
            York, affiliated with the Planned Parenthood Federation of America.
        </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
