<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article ">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2013/11/20 JK encoded</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-08-21 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1933-05-05 ">05 May 1933</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Letter to the Editor of the New York
                Times</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421056</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Mrs. Sanger Disputes Some of Mr. Caravati's
                    Statements</title>
                <title type="journal">The New York Times</title>, May 10, 1933, 16.
            </bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">Sanger wrote this to the editor of the New York Times in response to statements made by Henry L.
        Caravati, executive secretary of the National Council of Catholic Men.<index
            level1="United States" level2="overpopulation in"/>
        <index level1="Catholic Church" level2="birth control and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Birth Control.</head>
        <head type="sub">Mrs. Sanger Disputes Some of Mr. Caravati's Statements</head>

        <p> I wish to correct several statements made by<person reg="Caravati, Henry L."> Henry L.
                Caravati</person>, executive secretary of the <org>National Council of Catholic
                Men</org>, in his letter to <org reg="New York Times">The Times</org>. Mr.
            Caravati states that at Congressional hearings twenty-one responsible and outstanding
            national organizations made known their disapproval of any attempt to amend the present
            Federal laws. He failed to state that practically all these organizations were Catholic.
            Mr. Caravati refers to the <org>American Gynecological Society</org>, but fails to state
            that in 1925 this outstanding group went on record in favor of amending the present
            Federal laws. It is significant to note that the medical organizations most directly
            concerned with the health of American mothers have also gone on record in favor of
            amending these laws. Mr. Caravati states that it is a matter of record that not more
            than a few hundred thousand individuals are represented by the religious groups that
            have publicly expressed their approval of removing the present restrictions. It would be
            interesting to know where Mr. Caravati obtains his figures, and I am sure that the
            religious groups endorsing our work would also resent this absurd claim. I agree with
            Mr. Caravati that it is important that the people of this country be informed of the
            facts, but these must be presented without religious bias. </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
