<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-04-09 JK initial tags</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>
            <supplied resp="MSPP">Margaret Sanger</supplied>
        </docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1932-01-19">19 Jan 1932</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>
                <supplied resp="MSPP">Interview with Corning Leader</supplied>
            </titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421044</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">"Would Like to See Clinic in
                    Corning,"</title>
                <title type="journal">Corning Evening Leader</title>, Jan 20,
                1932, pp 9-10.</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="CL">Corning Leader</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger </person>gave an interview to
            the <title type="journal">Corning Leader</title> after her speech at
            the <org>Baron Steuben Hotel</org> in <place reg="Corning, NY"
                >Corning</place>. For a summary of her speech see <xref
                from="421906.xml">Speech at Corning, N.Y.</xref></p>
        <index level1="Comstock Laws"/><index
            level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="New York "
            /><index level1="birth control laws and legislation"
            level2="Federal"/><index level1="birth control clinics and leagues"
            level2="in US"/><index level1="birth control" level2="religion and"
            /><index level1="birth control" level2="in New York"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Would Like to See Clinic in Corning</head>
        <head type="sub">Mrs. Sanger Gives Interview Following Talk Here;
            Affected by Corning Greeting</head>

        <p>"I was quite moved; in fact, it seemed as though I was seeing faces
            of dear, remembered friends in a dream and I wanted to blink back
            the tears." <q who="CL">answered Mrs. Margaret Sanger Slee, when
                asked how she felt about the reception given at her public
                appearence in Corning Tuesday evening at the Baron Steuben Hotel
                when the ball room was packed to capacity to hear her speak.
                There was standing room only at 8 o'clock and many people stood
                through the entire lecture. Enthusiastic applause greeted her as
                she finished.</q></p>
        <p>
            <q who="UNK">“What are you doing along practical lines of birth
                control”</q>
            <q who="CL">was the next question.</q>
        </p>
        <p>“First of all we are working for repeal of the Comstock Federal law
            corning birth control with obscene literature. Then we have at
            present over 100 birth control clinics in the <place>United
                States</place>. However I can not even direct a woman where she
            may find one of these clinics in a letter sent though mail. Such an
            act would be punishable by five years imprisonment and $5,000 fine.
            The birth control clinics we have are established in accordance with
            state laws.” </p>
        <index level1="religion" level2="MS on"/>
        <p>
            <q who="UNK">“Is there anything you would like to see Corning do to
                help your project.”</q>
        </p>
        <p> “Yes,” <q who="CL">came the quick answer.</q> “I would like nothing
            better than to have an organization or a group of individuals
            establish a birth control clinic in Corning. If they would do so, I
            would be glad to come here, tell them how to go about it and how
            much of a staff they would need. They would have, first of all, to
            secure the services of a qualified doctor. Then the clinic would
            need financial support.” </p>
        <p><q who="UNK">“Wouldn’t you find the religious opposition harder to
                overcome in an up-state city like Corning.”</q> “Possibly. But
            out of 25,000 women we have helped, 22 per cent have been
            Protestants, 32 per cent Catholics, 31 per cent Jewish and the rest
            of no religious faith. 85 per cent have needed hospital care and we
            gave that before accepting them at the clinics.” </p>
        <p>
            <q who="CL">Mrs. Sanger spent many happy moments after her lecture
                renewing old acquaintances and thanking the many friends who
                expressed their regard and appreciation for her and her work.
                She lectures in <place reg="Rochester, NY">Rochester</place>
                tonight.</q>
        </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
