<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/03/07 YG</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-15 CH proof tags</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1936-01-23">23 Jan 1936</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Overpopulation and Birth Control in India</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421084</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">"Over-Population and Birth Control:
                    MRS.SANGER's VIEWS"</title>,
                <title type="journal">The Times of India</title>, Jan 23
                1936</bibl>
            <bibl><title>MSM</title></bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="TI">The Times of India</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">Sanger spoke at the <org reg="Hyderabad Town Hall">Town Hall</org><place>of Hyderabad,
            India</place> on Jan 23, 1936, and this summary was released to a
        number of Indian papers including <title type="journal">Times of
            India</title>, <title type="journal">The Hindu</title> and <title
            type="journal">Bombay Chronicle</title>. <index level1="India"
            level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="overpopulation and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="in India"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Over-Population and Birth Control</head>
        <head type="sub"><person reg="Sanger,Margaret">MRS. SANGER</person>'S
            VIEWS</head>
        <div>
            <p>“The problem of over-population has been extremely acute all over
                the world vis-a-vis the social and economic conditions of the
                people today. Starvation, unemployment, and high infant and
                maternity mortality are a few of its baleful results,” <q
                    who="TI">said Mrs. Margaret Sanger, who is on a
                    brief visit to <place>Hyderabad</place>, in the course of a lecture at the
                    Town Hall, last evening. </q>
            </p>
            <p><q who="TI">She added</q>: “The practice of birth
                control offers the only sure way out of this-the one hope for
                the youth of the future - and the only sure solvent of most
                social and economic ills everywhere.”</p>
            <p><q who="TI">Mrs. Sanger, continuing, said that high
                    medical and other authorities now lent the prestige of their
                    names to the movement, which had hitherto been left in
                    obscurity and treated as highly controversial. Today
                    emigration had ceased to provide an escape from the problem
                    of over population. Only two alternatives remained, namely,
                    death - Nature’s method of birth control- and birth control
                    proper. </q>“To say that birth control means murder is to
                speak without knowledge of facts. It is merely prevention of
                conception of life. How then can the question of murder arise.” </p>
            <p><q who="TI">Proceeding, Mrs. Sanger contrasted the conditions of masses all
                over the world, where large and unlimited families were creating
                legacies in slums increasing unemployment, ignorance,
                starvation, misery and death, with conditions under birth
                control, where families would be regulated with regard to three
                important factors, the health of the mother, the income of the
                father and the standard of living of the family. </q></p>
            <p>“In the former group,” <q who="TI">said Mrs. Sanger,</q>“every social problem is
                daily increasing whereas in the latter the very opposite would
                be the result.” </p>
            <p><q who="TI">In conclusion Mrs. Sanger said that <place>India</place>had her problem of
                overpopulation the same as the rest of the world, though
                slightly in a greater degree, since infant and maternity
                mortality statistics in India were slightly higher than anywhere
                else in the world. it was therefore up to them to ponder over
                the situation and apply the only remedy which showed the way to
                improved health and better standard of living of the family
                community in the country. </q></p>
        </div>
       
    </docBody>
</doc>
