<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-12-04 CH encode</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>
            <person>Margaret Sanger</person>
        </docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1924-05-00">May 1924</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Margaret Sanger's Own Corner</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp431009</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title>, May. 1924, p. 150</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p>Under this column name, the <title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title> published
            letters written to Margaret Sanger with occasional commentary. For others in this series
            see Margaret Sanger's Own Corner, <xref from="421032.xml">Jan. 1924</xref>, <xref
                from="421033.xml">Feb. 1924</xref>, <xref from="301463.xml">Mar. 1924</xref>, <xref
                from="421034.xml">Apr. 1924</xref>, and <xref from="421010.xml">June
            1924</xref>.</p>
        <index level1="sterilization"/>
        <index level1="sterilization" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="client letters"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>MARGARET SANGER'S OWN CORNER</head>
        <p> A Correspondent writes “<q who="UNK">I would like to be sterilized if I could be, and
                would just like to know is meant by it</q>” </p>
        <p> As this is a not Infrequent request, I am including it my answer in my Corner.</p>
        <p> Sterilization is an operation which in the female usually takes the form of
            salpingectomy, that is, cutting the fallopian tubes so that the ova cannot reach the
            uterus, in the male it usually takes the form of vasectomy. That is, cutting the vas
            deferens. The female needs to stay in the hospital a week or ten days, while in the male
            the operation is practically no more than office treatment. Neither operation if
            properly done is dangerous to the patient. </p>
        <p> We do not think sterilization advisable for strong, healthy people, for they may change
            their minds about having children in four or five years’ time. However, is there is
            taint of insanity or epilepsy in either husband’s or wife’s ancestry, sterilization is
            advisable. The operation itself will cause no change in physical, mental or emotional
            life, nor will it deprive either the man or woman of the normal expression of their sex
            lives. </p>
        <p> Any surgeon of good standing can do either operation. He must be convinced of its
            advisability. The prices would parallel those of other operations that are done in the
            particularly locality. </p>
        <closer>
            <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">M S</person>
        </closer>
    </docBody>
</doc>
