<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-01-15 CH encode</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-05-13 JK transcribe</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-21 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1925-05-22">22 May 1925</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>Margaret Sanger Answers Professor Conklin on Quality and
				Population</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp421025</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="journal">Daily Princetonian</title>, May 22, 1925, p. 1 and 5</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name/>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<index level1="overpopulation"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="population and"/>
		<index level1="eugenics" level2="birth control and"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Margaret Sanger Answers Professor Conklin on Quality and Population</head>
		<p>Many of the disagreements and differences of opinion concerning the great racial problem
			of Birth Control grow out of a failure to recognize all the fundamental factors
			involved. In an interview published in the <title type="journal">New York Times</title>
			upon the occasion of the <org
				reg="International Neo-Malthusian and Birth Control Conference, 6th (1925)">Sixth
				International Neo-Malthusian and Birth Control Conference</org>, <person
				reg="Conklin, Edward Grant">Edwin Grant Conklin</person>, head of the <org
				reg="Princeton University Department of Biology">department of biology at
				Princeton</org>, declared that those of us who advocate Birth Control failed to give
			sufficient attention to the fact that it is just as bad to have too few people as it is
			to have too many.</p>
		<p>More than one hundred and twenty-two years have passed since in the second edition of his
			epoch-making “<title type="article">Essay on Population</title>” Rev. <person
				reg="Malthus, Thomas Robert">Robert Malthus</person> pointed out the dangers of
			overpopulation to the world at large and advocated prudential checks and late marriages
			to limit the birth rate. From the beginnings of the Neo-Malthusian movement, the problem
			was approached as a merely <emph rend="italics">quantitative</emph> one. It concerned
			itself with pointing out the dangers of <emph rend="italics">too many</emph> people in
			the world, just as Professor Conklin today has pointed out the danger of <emph
				rend="italics">too few</emph>. It was a problem of birth rates and death rates and
			the establishment of a proper population <emph rend="italics">ratio</emph>. In brief,
			students of the problem were interested primarily in quantity, not quality.</p>
		<p>In contradistinction to the Neo-Malthusian movement, though growing out of it, and
			agreeing with it in the primary necessity of teaching the restriction and intelligent
			control of the reproductive powers, the younger Birth Control movement has emphasized
			the importance of <emph rend="italics">quality</emph> in human life and racial health.
			We have done all in our power to agitate for education in contraception as a means to
			sustain and elevate standards of living, and to prevent healthy stocks or families from
			sinking into poverty, dependency, delinquency and defect. We have emphasized that the
			human race is susceptible to the same cultivation and breeding as plants, trees and
			animals. In this we agree with the eugenists. But whereas Eugenics must perforce attempt
			to control human breeding by a predetermined standard of what is “fit” and what “unfit”
			for reproduction in the race Birth control or “negative” Eugenics, as it has been
			described, realizes the danger of external or paternalistic interference in human lives,
			and aims without any prescriptions of personal liberty, to place in the hands of the
			parents themselves the means of economic and racial salvation. Birth Control does not
			seek to prohibit parenthood, but to arouse men and women to a sharp sense of
			responsibility toward the children they bring into the world. If these children are
			brought into the world through voluntary choice, instead of chance, they will thereby be
			assured of a greater opportunity for development and growth in the world while the
			standard of living in the homes into which they are born will likewise be higher than in
			an overcrowded and economically poorer domicile. </p>
		<p>To encourage people of good inheritance to produce larger and larger families, as
			Professor Conklin does in the interview quoted above, is to approach the problem not
			from the newer and more illuminating <emph rend="italics">qualitative</emph> standpoint,
			but to fall back on the less adequate <emph rend="italics"><supplied resp="MSPP"
					>quantitative</supplied></emph> approach. Our problem is no longer one of “too
			many” or “too few.” It is a problem of quality--of better or worse; of fit and unfit; of
			healthy or diseased stocks; of independent, self-reliant, populations, of dependent and
			defective and delinquent masses; of intelligence or imbecility; of talent and genius or
			half-wit and moron. </p>
		<p>But we view humanity in another light than the eminent Princeton biologist--in a less
			pessimist light, perhaps. We picture humanity at large as a vast reservoir of
			potentialities worthy of future development. Genius, we are convinced lies buried deep
			in the common lot, in the masses of humanity. Given the opportunity, with proper spacing
			and proper attention in childhood through the care of strong, healthy, loving motherhood
			(instead of unwilling overburdened slave motherhood) all these inherent talents might be
			encouraged to develop and by proper appreciation be brought to maturity and fulfillment
			in the world. On the other hand, if we fail to emphasize the necessity of a limited
			reproduction among the “lower types,” we are tacitly encouraging the unlimited
			reproduction among tainted and defective stocks, even against their will. We are
			burdening society with the maintenance of prisons, insane asylums, hospitals and
			institutions for the feeble-minds, prisons for the criminals- who are mostly mental
			defectives or mentally diseased. Instead of spending vast or even adequate
			appropriations for schools, universities and scientific research, instead of encouraging
			undeveloped geniuses and artists and scientists, we are compelled to expand ?one-fourth?
			of the incomes of the states upon the care of prisoners, of the insane, the
			feeble-minded, the delinquent and other incompetents. </p>
		<p>A “cradle competition” between the fit and the unfit, between those of good inheritance
			and those of poor physical and mental endowment will aid humanity not one iota toward
			the solution of the race problem now confronting it. Yet to emphasize, as Professor
			Conklin does a higher rate of reproduction among the cultured and intelligent, is to
			invite these classes to entre such a competition, and thereby to jeopardize the racial
			gain already acquired through the long process of “good breeding” which, in the final
			analysis, is merely another and more generally accepted name for Birth Control. </p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
