<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published interview">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/01/31 YG</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/02/07 CH proof</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/02/07 YG correct</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-11-11 CH clean regs</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1936-02-06">06 Feb 1936</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Interview with the<title type="journal">Rangoon Gazette</title></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421092</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">"Surplus Population:Dr. Margaret Sanger's Remedy"</title>
                <title type="journal">Rangoon Gazette</title>Feb 6 1936 </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="RG">Rangoon Gazette</name>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">This is the second of two interviews published in the <title
            type="journal">Rangoon Gazette</title> on Sanger's arrival in <place>Burma</place>. For
        the first interview see <xref from="421091.xml">February 5, 1936</xref>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to" level3="international"/><index
            level1="Italy" level2="pro-natalism in"/>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="population policies of"/><index level1="overpopulation"
            level2="colonialism and"/>
        <index level1="overpopulation" level2="threat to peace as"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Surplus Population</head>
        <head type="sub">Dr. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>'s Remedy</head>
        <div>
            <q who="RG"><p>Increasing population, the growing need for colonies to accommodate this
                    surplus and finally war to acquire colonies to permit expansion. The remedy for
                    this? Birth Control, replies Dr. Margaret Sanger, the President of the <org
                        reg="Birth Control International Information Centre">Birth Control
                        Information Centre</org>, and leader of the birth control movement
                    throughout the world. Dr. Sanger arrived in <place reg="Rangoon, Burma"
                        >Rangoon</place> on Tuesday from her first trip through <place reg="India"
                        >India</place>and her second tour round the world.</p><p>Dr. Sanger in a
                    further interview with a “Rangoon Gazette” reporter showed how birth control
                    might have averted the wars into which <place reg="Italy">Italy</place>and
                        <place reg="Japan">Japan</place>have plunged.</p></q>
            <p>“In certain countries there has been a gradually increasing surplus. This surplus
                creates labour problems, heightened even further with the growing use of machinery
                and labour saving devices. A country so affected should either scrap its machinery
                or refuse to employ it. </p>
            <p>“A country with a surplus population cannot afford to reduce the standard of living
                and it has to expand and look for more country. This is the excuse put forward by
                Italy and Japan to justify their aggressive acts.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"><place reg="United States">U.S.</place>and Italian Emigrants</head>
            <p>“Italy has been over-populated ever since the United States of America closed its
                doors to Italian emigrants in 1924. Up to this 25 per cent of Italy’s surplus
                population made their homes in America. As soon as immigration was stopped in this
                direction, Italy rattled her sword and began to talk of places in the sun. She
                already had a population which even the Great War did not lessen. In spite of this
                    <person reg="Mussolini, Benito">Mussolini</person>did all he could by offering
                bonuses and prizes to large families to still increase the numbers. She has not
                sufficient resources in the way of iron, coal and oil to build up industries with
                which to engage and feed the surplus population, and textile industries could not
                offer any competition to those of Japan and India. So it was inevitable as the
                population increased that she would begin to clamor of an overseas home- a
                colony.”</p>
            <q who="RG"><p>Is Italy's large surplus population due to Mussolini? Dr. Sanger seems to
                    think so. It is her opinion that the people would have been quite content to
                    limit the number of their families had not Mussolini's greed for power and more
                    land led him to encourage a more prolific birth-rate.</p></q>
            <p>“I was in Italy a few years ago,” Dr. Sanger said, “and people from villages close to
                where I stayed pleaded with me to divulge ways of limiting their families, which
                just goes to prove that they would like to limit their families.”</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"/>
            <p>“The case with Japan is almost identical. She has the same conditions geographically.
                Two thirds of her territory is mountainous. Her native industries are not sufficient
                to feed the population. The doors of immigration were closed to her and she had to
                look round for a place with resources and to take it by force. The result is her
                capture of <place reg="Manchukuo">Manchukuo</place>. Already we see the competition
                Japan is offering in the world market.</p>
            <p>“In Western countries such as <place reg="England">England</place>, the U.S.A. and
                some European countries, we see a lower birth-rate and with it goes a decreasing
                death-rate. The population grows more slowly but on sound and healthy lines, and
                people live to a greater age. In <place>India</place> and other Oriental countries
                it is exactly the opposite.</p>
            <p>“It is an interesting fact that the population of India has increased 34,000 during
                the last ten years. This is the highest increase known. India has the highest
                birth-rate and the highest death-rate. One-fifth of the number of babies born don’t
                live more than one year. Half the number don’t live more than five years.</p>
            <p>“This can be attributed to three causes: Early motherhood, not spacing the children
                sufficiently to allow of the mothers to recuperate, and large families. These three
                factors affect infant mortality in every country in the world. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"><q who="RG">Saving of Lives</q></head>
            <p>“The saving of lives and the prolonging of lives must go hand-in-hand with a
                decidedly lower birth-rate. And, if there was a space of two to three years between
                each child, it would lead to a slower rate of growth.</p>
            <p> “It has been estimated that 150,000 babies are born every day throughout the world.
                Of these only 50,000 lives to see the completion of their first year.</p>
            <p>“We want people to live as long as possible and as fully as their personality permits
                contributing their best to civilization and race. All this will gradually come about
                by birth control applied to a population. Birth control should be disseminated in
                hospitals by Public Health authorities as the practice should be directed among
                those physically and economically unfit to rear families.” </p>
            <q who="RG"><p>Dr. Sanger and Mrs. <person reg="How-Martin, Edith">Edith
                        How-Martin</person>, who is on the Executive Commitee of the Birth Control
                    International Information Centre, London, spent yesterday interviewing medical
                    men and Government medical officials. They held a small meeting at the residence
                    of Mr. and Mrs. <person reg="Tyabji, Mr."><person reg="Tyabi, Mrs."
                        />Tyabji</person>in Lower Pazundaung Road. The meeting was well attended by
                    medical men and women.</p></q>
            <q who="RG"><p>Dr. Sanger and Mrs. How-Martin sail today for <place reg="Singapore"
                        >Singapore</place>.</p></q>
        </div>




    </docBody>
</doc>
