<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Statement">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014-12-18 CH transcribe and encode</prepDate><prepDate>2015-01-7 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1919-04-00">Apr 1919</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>A Letter to the Working Women of America</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp421030</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title>, Apr. 1919</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name/>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>This statement was published as a full-page letter with two donation forms, one for a
			$10.00 share in <title type="journal">Birth Control Review</title> stock, another for
			$1.50 for a one year subscription.</p>
		<index level1="World War I" level2="women and"/>
		<index level1="women" level2="freedom and rights of"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>A Letter to the Women of America</head>
		<p>The war is over. You, the women who were beginning to take and interest in Birth Control
			and its meaning in our social development, were thrown by the war into a multitude of
			new duties. You were unable, while the conflict lasted, to give thought, time or money
			to any movement, no matter how worthy, no matter how pregnant with good to women or to
			society as a whole. </p>
		<p>Bit the war is over, you are back in your homes, with time to rest and reflect. You have
			given two years of energy and devotion to the cause of "the boys over there." Now will
			you not give the same measure of time, energy, money and devotion to "the woment over
			here"?</p>
		<p>Governments have acknowledged universally the tremendous part you have played in winning
			the war. There have been a multitide of official communications, proclamations,
			resolutions and memorials attesting that victory could not have come without you.</p>
		<p>Yet, you who have aided in winning the war, have been but a very small percentage of the
			women of the world. Only those who were unmarried were unable to help. Or <supplied
				resp="MSPP">those</supplied> married women who were not over-burdened with too many
			children. No woman could help who was tied to the domestic machine.</p>
		<p>You were able to give your services because you were free--free through a knowledge of
			Birth Control. Had you been mothers of eight, nine or ten children, you could not have
			gone from place to place, "doing your bit," no matter how much you desired to do so.</p>
		<p>You owe your freedom directly or indirectly to the Birth Control movement and the
			knowledge which is spreads.</p>
		<p>No amount of money could have freed you from the worries, trials and sickeness, or
			children and of yourselves, which a knowledge of Birth Control has spared you. You were
			indeed fortunate, for you are free from these chains</p>
		<p>By nature, and according to the laws of the state and the nation, you should have borne
			at least one child for every two years of you married life. Count up and see how many
			children you would have had, had not the idea of Birth Control been available to
			you.</p>
		<p>Reflect upon the fact that there a millions of overburdened mothers in <place
				reg="United States">America</place> to whom this knowledge is a sealed book--to whom
			freedom such as yours is, therefore denied.</p>
		<p>In gratitude for this knowledge, will you not come to the aid of the women from whom it
			is withheld? Will you not, for every child that you would have had, had you not known
			how to limit your family, purchase one $10 share of stock in The <title type="journal"
				>Birth Control Review</title>?</p>
		<p rend="bold">For every bond you purchase, I promise to free ten women from the bondage of
			ignorance.</p>
		<p>You have purchased Liberty Bonds for the men "over there." Why not "Liberty Bonds" <emph
				rend="bold">now</emph> for the women "opver here."</p>
		<byline rend="bold">MARGARET SANGER, Editor</byline>
	</docBody>
</doc>
