<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/05/02 YG</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1934-11-11">11 Nov 1934</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Interview with the Arizona Daily Star</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421057</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Country of Contradiction, Mrs. Sanger Brands
                Russia</title></bibl>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Arizona Daily Star</title></bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="ADS">Arizona Daily Star</name>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">On 11/16/1934 Sanger spoke on her impressions of Russia to the Technocracy
        Group in Tucson, AZ. At the top of her copy of this article, Sanger wrote "a very bad
        interpretation of my words." No other versions were found. Sanger may have given a similar
        talk to the Technocracy Group in Tucson on Nov. 16, 1934.
        
        <index level1="Soviet Union"/>
        <index level1="Soviet Union" level2="birth control in"/>
    
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head type="sub">Country of Contradictions, <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Mrs.
                Sanger</person>Brands <place reg="Soviet Union"> Russia</place>Breeding Children by
            Millions with No Ability to care for Them, Says Birth Control Advocate in Her First
            Interview Since Return From <place reg="Soviet Union">Soviet</place></head>
        <p><q who="ADS">Russia hoping to make greater scientific strides than any nation, yet with
                fly paper hanging over operating tables. Brutal annihilation of intelligentsia and
                aristocrats, yet creating a new aristocracy of communists and developing minds
                solely for state use, new aristocracy of communists and developing minds solely for
                state use. Breeding thousands of children yet unable to care properly for the
                overwhelming population of today; stridently preaching health, good care of the
                race, yet never checking procreation in diseased, criminal or insane. </q></p>
        <p><q who="ADS">A country in which every man and woman has shoulder to the wheel pushing
                toward the most immense, distant, dream a country ever conceived.</q></p>
        <p>
            <q who="ADS">Ruthlessly experimenting with human lives as no vivisectionist would, yet
                changing human nature, actually cancelling desire for personal possessions,
                permanency, success and distinction if only the state may survive and triumph.
            </q></p>
        <p><q who="ADS">That is the Russia Mrs. Margaret Sanger saw on her recent trip. The country
                becomes less an enigma as one listens to this internationally known woman, whose
                pioneer work in birth and population control have brought her fame. She told of
                Russia’s contradictions and ideals yesterday in the first interview she has given in
                the <place reg="United States">United States</place>since her <place
                    reg="Soviet Union">U.S.S.R.</place>visit. Mrs. Sanger Is spending the winter in
                    <place reg="Tucson, AZ">Tucson</place>, having brought her son, Grant, here for
                sunshine and recovery of health. </q></p>
        <p><q who="ADS">With a</q>confused mind<q who="ADS">in regard to the communistic country,
                Mrs. Sanger set off for six weeks of personal investigation with a group of Harvard
                and Northwestern professors, all </q>decidedly representing the intelligentsia.<q
                who="ADS">She returned somewhat clarified as to many points, disapproving and yet
                wonderingly approving of what is transpiring there. Whatever the personal reaction,
                there cannot help but be wondered at the burning fervency of the people, she said.
            </q></p>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Must Change Ideas </head>
            <p>One needs to overthrow all his ideas and conceptions when entering Russia, for it is
                a new mind and a new world,<q who="ADS">she declared</q>. I had deliberately read
                little of what was happening, hoping I might find out for myself. True, I had
                chanced upon articles, been in conversations where Russia was discussed. I had
                talked with Will Durant, who is opposed to it, and had been told by others I would
                see only what Russia wished me to see. Yet with that proclivity for sticking my nose
                in where perhaps not wanted, I saw not only the prepared, especially decorated show
                cases Russia has on display, but I saw the flies in the soup, the lack of
                sanitation, the absence of what we consider necessities, the shortage of food and
                all the other behind-the-scene details. But in all honesty, I also saw and felt the
                surging inner or deep lying purpose of Russia in her people. Whether she or they can
                achieve their goal, I cannot say, but it will not be through lack of effort.</p>
            <p>Naturally, my interests were those concerning mothers, children, birth control,
                population balance to economic resources and all the facets of those. Yet to pursue
                a study of those, I had to see the factories, the schools, the playgrounds, parks
                and places of amusement, the homes, kitchens, hospitals and nurseries. I believe I
                saw a representative cross-section of Russian life, though I concerned myself with
                my own specialty. Entering by way of <place>Leningrad</place>, from
                    <place>Sweden</place> and <place>Norway</place>, my first impressions were
                shocking. I thought what a disagreeable country Russia was, how uncomfortable to
                travel in, how depressing. The faces of the people were sad, their shoulders
                drooped, their spirits sagged. Yet when I went on to <place>Moscow</place>, to
                    <place>Odessa</place>, to <place>Maxim Gorki</place>, I saw the laughter, the
                happiness and the zeal with which the people pursue their ideals.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Woman Liberated</head>
            <p>Russia is today the country of the liberated woman,<q who="ADS">continued Mrs.
                    Sanger.</q>She is unshackled, on true equality with man--except when pregnant
                when she becomes almost a ward, a charge of the state and is given special
                preference, care and food. She carries a hod of brick on a new construction, lob
                smudged while controlling factory machinery, she tills the soil, reaps and
                threshes.</p>
            <p>All women in Russia work their five days and have one to rest. By the way, there is
                no such thing as our week, the calendar being kept only numerically with no Tuesdays
                or Sundays. All that went out with religion. The free day when one does not work is
                the pivot of the short week. </p>
            <p>Forty per cent of the machines in factories are operated by women. There is no type
                of work they do not do, for they share their equality, bitter and sweet, with men.
                It was <person reg="Lenin, Vladimir">Lenin</person>who declared, ‘women have been the most exploited of all creatures,
                especially by the family, in the home and by the church. They have been exploited
                more than man by industry. The first thing Russia will do is take the chains of
                women. She will be liberated from housework drudgery, be freed from her no pay or
                recognition tasks.’ </p>
            <p>His first move was to get them out of homes, into work on equal terms with men. He
                organized thousands upon thousands of ‘creches’ or nurseries. These are strewn over
                the nation, are in very industry, on every farm, at railroads stations, factories,
                parks. The community kitchen came next. Children were taken to the ‘creches’ in the
                morning, gotten at night. If the parents wished, and the expenses shared alike by
                the two workers. </p>
        </div>

        <div>
            <head type="sub">Marriage Differs </head>
            <p>Russia’s definition of marriage is interesting. Cohabitation is marriage.
                Cohabitation with another when married to one, bigamy. Divorce is simply mutual
                agreement to separate and a card is mailed in to the officials. Should the two not
                agree, the court decides. After separation, the government demands the father give
                one-third his salary to the family. If he separates again, another third goes to the
                children by the second marriage. Thus, on an economic basis, divorce cannot go on
                and is gradually dying out in Russia. </p>
            <p>There are no illegitimate children in the country, as can be seen by the definition
                of marriage. I talked with a woman in Moscow about marriages and asked her what
                happened when men lived with young girls. There was puzzlement on her face. She
                asked again and again, through the interpreter, what I meant by ‘living together,’
                ‘being promiscuous.’ She counciled with some nurses. They could not understand me.
                If I meant cohabitation, then there was no ‘living together,’ but it was marriage.
                Prostitution, which was most prevalent under the old regime, there having been some
                40,000 prostitutes in Moscow alone, is stamped out under the new system and I was
                told that less than 100 such persons could be found in all Russia.</p>
            <p>But returning to children of Russia, it is staggering to learn that (illegible) have
                been born since (illegible) At that rate of production, Russia's population will be
                her undoing (illegible) Her entire population of 164,000,000 is divided into three
                classes; (illegible); Comosols, from 9 to 17, and the Communists, from 17 years on.
                But of her entire adult population there are only 2,500,000 Communists, which
                represents the highest achievement and honor as a citizen and must be worked from
                the pioneer group forward.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Noble Communists</head>
            <p>It is these Communists that represent the new nobility of Russia. But it is a
                nobility based on morality, integrity, honesty, loyalty, unselfishness, and
                proletariat love. Control of temper, absence of pettiness, what we call
                ‘cattishness,’ and selfishness are all achieved through branding these as bourgeois.
                Nothing is so degrading as to be bourgeois. There is no swearing- to say damn, hell,
                God or anything of that sort is to show utter lack of nicety, command of vocabulary.
                In other words, it is bourgeois, and the Russians to shudder to be called that.</p>
            <p><q who="ADS">Vividly did Mrs. Sanger picture her experiences with her penetrating
                    mind, which is at once so unusually intelligent, yet so human and sees the
                    humorous, made one re-see her travels. Questioned again as to whether she saw
                    the show cases with window displays by the government, she commented on five
                    great Russian displays. </q></p>
            <p>There are in Leningrad the institute for motherhood and childhood; the abortitorium;
                the phophylactorium; the night sanatoria and the museum of motherhood and infancy. </p>
            <p>The first of these is a scientific institute for the study and training of women and
                children as biological creatures. They are studied in their physical, mental and
                environmental aspects. </p>
            <p>They are taken up from the ‘ideology’ standpoint, which we might term spiritual. They
                are studied in relation to their home, work, sex, life, and attitude toward the
                state. How woman works these ideals out within herself is the ‘ideology.’ Children
                in this institute are studied under somewhat the same program.</p>
            <p>Russia is carefully studying her children. There may be flies in the nurseries and
                swarming about the eyes of the babies, but Russia will have screens and sanitation,
                she says; and meantime she expects to know more about motherhood and childhood than
                any other nation of the world. </p>
        </div>

        <div>
            <head type="sub">Explains Divorce</head>
            <p>I may pause here,<q who="type">Mrs. Sanger said</q>, to tell what grounds may be
                considered justifiable for divorce. One man sued because of his wife’s hysteria.
                This was on the basis that the constant tempers, pushing, slapping, shoving and
                reprimanding of child was bad environmentally, and she was not a fit mother. The
                court granted the divorce. What we consider immorality for a mother is not important
                there. She may go away and be with a lover, but the child does not know or
                comprehend what happens. But she is unfit when given to hysterics. I wonder if that
                is such unsound reasoning? It seems rather civilized to me. Dr. Lebidova, who is in
                charge of the great institute and is now taking over Russia’s sanitary problems,
                assured me environment for children is more important than the morals, on our basis,
                of the parents.</p>
            <p>The second show place is the arbortitorium. To this thousands of women go, and the
                surgeons have become expert in this type of surgery. If a woman desires not to go on
                with her pregnancy, the situation is remedied. True, the officials try to dissuade
                first mothers from abortions, but if she insists, her wish is granted. The man and
                the woman must share the expense. The woman’s pay goes on, and she remains in the
                hospital three days and at home seven. This freedom comes under the heading of
                ‘individual liberty.’ </p>
            <p>The third show place is the prophylactorium, the most unusual institution, I am sure,
                in the world. It has been the means of doing away with the old order of women
                selling their bodies to foreigners-- they dare not to Russian men, for the man will
                be exiled to <place>Siberia</place>, or at the least, put in jail. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Women Reformed</head>
            <p>At this institute devoted solely to the cause, women are reformed, taught the crime
                against their own bodies, the debasement to themselves and their sex life, which
                they teach should be the finest thing of life, a gift to those with whom they share
                it. They teach that selling the body is a left-over of the bourgeoise times. The
                women are given work, trained for positions and an endeavor made to make them
                Communists-- this on the basis that she is dejected, an outcast and so should have
                the highest honor. In many instances the women are trained as social investigators.
                No, I would not say spies. They know the field and the temptations, so they really
                become missionaries to aid in the reformation of others. The night sanitoria, <q
                    who="ADS">continued Mrs. Sanger</q>, are also interesting. They are for children
                and adults. One continues with either school or work and in the evening goes to the
                sanitoria. There baths are given, cots provided on open air porches, sunlight lamp
                treatments given and proper food provided. At bedtime, after soothing music, they
                sleep the night in the sanitoria. Breakfasting, they go to work or school. This is
                all preventive work, the doctors in all factories and schools keep close check on
                every man, woman and child. The slightest lessening of energy, development of a
                cough and away the persons are sent to the night sanitoria. Should a person not
                respond to this treatment, then they are sent to the Russian Rivers or the Black Sea
                where old palaces of the aristocrats have been turned into workers’ rest homes. All
                expenses paid, the workers rest there a month, or as long as is necessary. </p>
            <p>The last of Russia’s show cases is the museum. In this are housed visual education
                facilities to teach the peasants and all others every phase of human and animal life
                from the embryo throughout life. There are trays showing just what diets should be
                had for every child of whatever age; models of clothes, cribs and toys. The
                inventiveness and correlation of children is developed through the making of toys.
                There is no such thing as manufactured ones. These exhibits compel everyone to learn
                to read. Russia had 85 per cent of her population illiterate, but now they are
                ‘liquidating illiteracy’ and great stress is being placed on learning to read. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="type">Fears Brains</head>
            <p><q who="ADS">By no means all that Mrs. Sanger saw or heard or experienced in Russia
                    could be contained in one newspaper article. For over two hours she spoke of
                    that trip. She held no brief for the destruction of Russia’s great scientists
                    and intellectually superior people, condemning the policy heartily, yet seeing
                    that the mass that came into power feels apprehensive of any mental abilities
                    not developed under the control of the U.S.S.R. ideal. She commented on the
                    nation’s realization that the people must be happy, providing theaters, games,
                    parks and other amusements free. Yet here she commented on Einstein’s discovery
                    of an actress with great talent who was relegated to a farm when her personality
                    became too dominant in the theatre. She told of trying to give her Russian
                    interpreter two pairs of silk stockings and a wrist watch because of the girl’s
                    splendid service and impending marriage. These the girl declined because “I
                    would not be happy having them while the others have none. We shall all have
                    them someday. Now I could not take them.”</q>
            </p>
            <p><q who="ADS">Mrs. Sanger said that it is astonishing the admiration the Russians have
                    for Americans. </q>You feel the surge of their admiration toward you,<q
                    who="ADS">she said, but at once recalled another incident. She and her son,
                    Stuart, and the interpreter were passing a group of children, who pointed at the
                    party and remarked: “Ah, there go some of the dying race.” They referred, Mrs.
                    Sanger said, to the dying race of capitalism. It is to America hat the Russians
                    look because of our</q>constant travel, our richness, our commerce, our
                leadership in the world and our learning.</p>
            <p>She spoke of the tremendous building-home program going on now, saying that Russia
                had gone through her great industrial period and is now emerging into consideration
                of housing, sanitation and happiness of the people. Later they will move into the
                art period, so now throw up only temporary tenements not expected to last or be
                attractive. Special emphasis is being placed on the training of young minds,
                especially in languages that will give Russia intercourse with the world in matters
                of business and governmental relations. The entire trip, she said, was an experience
                never to be forgotten. </p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
