<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published statement">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-04-02 JK initial tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-12-11 CH proof tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-12-11 CH enter corrections</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docAuthor>Chester D. Bahn</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1922-12-26">26 Dec 1922</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>
                <supplied resp="MSPP">Press Statement on Engagement Rights</supplied>
            </titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421175</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Breaking of Engagements is Defended</title>, <title
                    type="journal">Belleville News Democrat</title>, Dec. 26, 1922, p. 6.</bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="BND">Belleville News Democrat</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <p><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger</person> spoke to the press on men's and women's
            rights to break engagements. She later lectured to the <org>Syracuse Women's
                Congress</org>; no draft or final version of her talk was found. </p>
        <index level1="divorce"/>
        <index level1="marriage"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="freedom and rights of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Breaking of Engagements is Defended</head>
        <head type="sub">Better Before Than After Marriage: Mrs. Sanger.</head>
        <byline>by <person reg="Bahn, Chester D.">Chester D. Bahn</person>, International New
            Service Staff Correspondent</byline>
        <dateline><place reg="Syracuse, NY">Syracuse, N.Y.</place>, <date value="1922-12-26">Dec.
                26</date>--</dateline>
        <p>“Women have claimed and won equality with men before the law. They should grant men the
            same privilege of breaking the engagement that they have claimed and used.”</p>
        <q who="BND">
            <p>That is the way Mrs. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>, birth
                control advocate, answered <person reg="Bowen, Marjorie">Marjorie Bowen</person>,
                famous British novelist, who recently declared that men should be required to keep
                marriage engagements and women should retain the right, under law, to sue for breach
                of promise damages.</p>
            <p>Mrs. Sanger fired her answering broadside at the British writer while here to lecture
                before the Women’s Congress in Syracuse.</p>
        </q>
        <p>“It is far better to break before than after marriage,” <q who="BND">warned Mrs. Sanger.</q> “It is of the
            utmost importance for both that the man be madly in love with the girl. If he changes
            mind, or if he learns that he has ceased to care, both are happier if he breaks it off.
            So far as legal action is concerned, I fail to see why the man should not have the same
            privilege that women frequently exercise. It hurts a woman’s vanity--just that--to
            loser her fianc&eacute;. It would hurt her far more to seek divorce.</p>
        <p> “Women have claimed and won equality with men before the law. They should grant men the
            same privilege of breaking the engagement that they have claimed and used.</p>
        <p> “Happiness in marriage depends far more on the man’s love for the woman than on the
            woman’s love for the man. Unless each step forward in their love-lives is earnestly
            desired by both the marriage is doomed. </p>
        <p>“Marriage should be a consummation of mutual desire. As for forcing a man to marry--that
            is ridiculous and almost impossible. Marriage calls for the highest mutual love, and
            love cannot be forced. You can’t legislate it into existence.” </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
