<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-06-26 CH proof tags </prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1925-04-15">15 Apr 1925</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Letter to the <title type="journal">Survey Magazine</title></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421981</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">From Mrs. Sanger</title><title type="journal">The
                    Survey</title>Apr. 15, 1925, p. 116</bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>

            <name id="PINGE"><person reg="Pinchot, Gertrude Minturn">Pinchot, Gertrude
                    Minturn</person></name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>For a draft version see the Library of Congress Microfilm, 130:614.</p>
        <index level1="Committee on Maternal Health"/>
        <index level1="National Birth Control League"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="neo-Malthusian arguments for"/>
        <index level1="France" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="France" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau"/>
        <index level1="birth control clinics and leagues" level2="research benefits of"/>
        <index level1="physicians" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="definitions of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="medical community and"/>
        <index level1="birth control methods" level2="research"/>
        <index level1="birth control movement" level2="disputes within"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>From <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Mrs. Sanger</person></head>
        <p>To THE EDITOR: The failure of an investigator for the <org>Committee on Maternal
                Health</org> to obtain medical "facts" concerning the practice of contraception in
                <place>France,</place>
            <place reg="Netherlands">Holland,</place>
            <place>England,</place> and in <place reg="New York, NY">New York city,</place> has led
            Mrs. Gertrude Minturn Pinchot to express surprise (<title type="journal">The
                Survey,</title> March 15, 1925, p. 751) at <q who="PINGE">"the scanty amount of
                exact information on the subject."</q> The <q who="PINGE">"surprises"</q> of this <q
                who="PINGE">"birth control"</q> information are evidently based upon a misconception
            of the term <q who="PINGE">"medical fact."</q></p>
        <p>One basic "medical fact" has been overlooked or neglected by Mrs. Pinchot and the
            Committee on Maternal Health of which she is spokesman. This fact is that
            physiologically and hygienically contraception is feasible and practical: it may be as
            scientific as the ordinary technique of surgery and medical therapeutics. The
            accumulation and correlation of statistics will eventually support this fundamental
            medical fact, but the present scarcity of case-records which Mrs. Pinchot laments in no
            way confutes it. I have reason to believe that such records do exist; but even if they
            did not, no impartial investigation would be logically warranted to conclude upon such
            an assumption that practical education in contraception has been a failure. In France,
            according to Mrs. Pinchot, <q who="PINGE">"more than sixty interviews with those who
                should know most demonstrated that the knowledge of it is underground, indefinite,
                and has never been gathered."</q> Are we therefore to assume that the practice of
            birth control is not an accepted custom of the French people? We have no need of
            statistics or "medical facts" to convince us of French practice of contraception. Its
            acceptance has become so basic in the mores of France that even the present campaign for
            "repopulation" is tacitly based upon an acceptance of the conscious control of
            procreation, and the duty to vary this control from patriotic motives.</p>
        <p>On the basis of the investigator's report from Holland, Mrs. Pinchot objects to the use
            of the word clinic to describe the birth control centers established there under the
            direction and instruction of the late <person reg="Rutgers, Johannes">Dr.
                Rutgers,</person> founder of the <org reg="Nieuw Malthusiaansche Bond"
                >Neo-Malthusian Band.</org> For more than forty years, Dr. Rutgers trained women of
            the lower middle class by a few lessons and a reasonable pamphlet of instruction, as
            Mrs. Pinchot admits. The Band's printed report carries the names and addresses of three
            physicians, four midwives and forty-three "practitioners"-a total of fifty in all, from
            whom contraceptive instruction may be obtained. Because this work is independent of
            hospitals or medical supervision, Mrs. Pinchot erroneously assumes it to be negligible.
            As in all European countries, the practical Neo-Malthusian education has been a lay
            movement. The matter of contraception is looked upon as a matter of hygiene, prophylaxis
            and economics, and only in abnormal or pathological cases a matter for medical
            advice.</p>
        <p>In this country, on the contrary, we have never underestimated the medical aspects of the
            problem. <org>The American Birth Control League</org> has sought the cooperation of the
            best medical thought, and has received a gratifying response. In establishing its
            clinical research department, the League deliberately refrained from the temptation of
            accumulating data of the type Mrs. Pinchot calls <q who="PINGE">"dependable."</q> The
            League realized the danger of jumping to satisfying conclusions upon such specialized
            records since the research was limited by the limitations of our laws to abnormal cases.
            Our aim has been experimental, tentative, pioneering, aiming to help the women who
            appeal to us, rather than to accumulate details which might lead to speciously
            "scientific" conclusions. Whatever our shortcomings, we have at least succeeded in
            breaking down the traditional apathy of the intellectually superior classes in arousing
            the interest of an increasing number of sympathetic and understanding physicians. The
            cost of this venture has not been $26,000, as Mrs. Pinchot states, but approximately
            $16,000.</p>
        <p>We agree that statistics and scientific analysis are important. We recognize that the
            cooperation of the medical profession is essential. We have never sought to usurp the
            function of the physician. As soon as the American medical profession signifies its
            desire to assume the burden of technical instruction, we shall be able to concentrate
            upon the educational and legislative aspects of this great problem. Patiently we await
            and shall warmly welcome such action. But let us not conclude erroneously, upon the
            limited evidence offered, that birth control is merely a medical problem. The whole
            social and spiritual destiny of the human race is bound up with it.</p>
        <p>MARGARET SANGER</p>
        <p>President of American Birth Control League, Inc., New York</p>


        <p/>
    </docBody>
</doc>
