<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published interview">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014-06-26 MM</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-05 CH proof tags, enter corrections</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-28 EK correct proof</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1916-04-25">25 Apr. 1916</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>Interview with the <title type="journal">Chicago Daily
				News</title></titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp421976</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>"<title type="article">Mrs. Sanger Defies Critics; Tells Aims</title>," <title
					type="journal">Chicago Daily News</title> April 25, 1916, p. 3. </bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="CDN">Chicago Daily News</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>Sanger gave this interview at The <org>Congress Hotel</org> in <place reg="Chicago, IL"
				>Chicago</place> after her speech to the <org>Chicago Women's Club</org> was
			cancelled. For a draft of one of her speeches in Chicago see <xref from="232132.xml"
					>"<title>Chicago Address to Women</title>," Apr-May, 1916</xref></p>
		<index level1="birth control clinics and leagues"/>
		<index level1="free speech and free press"/>
		<index level1="Post Office (U.S.)"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>MRS. SANGER DEFIES CRITICS; TELLS AIMS</head>
		<head type="sub">Pioneer in "Birth Control" Move. Derides Postal Department's Censorship.</head>
		<div type="section">
			<p><q who="CDN">Mrs. Margaret Sanger, pioneer of the "birth control" movement in <place
				reg="United States">America</place>, is in <place reg="Chicago, IL">Chicago</place> today. Smiling and
				unperturbed she sat in her room at the <org>Congress hotel</org> and told a reporter for
						<title type="journal">The Daily News</title> the story of the last three
					years of her life, during which, she asserted, she had been "</q>persecuted<q
					who="CDN">" by the <org reg="United States Government">United States
						government</org> and hounded by spies and agents. seeking to obtain
					information concerning her social and personal activities. Mrs. Sanger says she
					was denied permission to speak before the <org>Chicago Women's Club</org>, but that she
					will proceed with her plans to address Chicago audiences at two meetings
					elsewhere.</q></p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">Admits Postal Law Violation.</head>
			<p>"I make no bones of the fact that I have violated that section of the federal law
				which forbids sending through the mails elleged objectionable matter having to do
				with birth control" <q who="CDN">she declared, calmly.</q> "In that connection I
				should like to emphasize this--that I believe the <org
					reg="United States Post Office">post office department</org> is overriding its
				functions in becoming an ethical and moral institution, instead of remaining what it
				should be--a public servant. I feel that it is becoming a great menace to the
				liberties of the people.</p>
			<p>"My message to Chicago chiefly is this: I am desirous of establishing a free clinic
				in your stockyards district. Once begun, it would be self-supporting, and that
				district needs it. Knowledge of birth control is so important that it must be in the
				hands of the women before even suffrage or any other forward step is taken."</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">Tells of Work Among Clubs.</head>
			<p><q who="CDN"/>Mrs. Sanger told of her work among girls clubs and elsewhere and of the
				work of ten large birth control leagues in various cities that are working for a
				repeal of the federal statute covering the case of Mrs. Sanger's literature.</p>
			<p>"These leagues are arousing an interest that is vital,"<q who="CDN"> she said.
				</q>"Understand, this is the only civilized country in the world that makes it a
				crime to give information about birth control. And do not misunderstand our cause.
				We do not advocate illegal operations and that sort of thing. Our work is conducted
				on a high plane; it has the backing in <place>England</place> of such men as <person
					reg="Wells, H.G.">H. G. Wells</person>, <person reg="Bennett, Arnold">Arnold
					Bennett</person>, <person reg="Carpenter, Edward">Edward Carpenter</person>,
					<person reg="Ellis, Havelock">Havelock Ellis</person> and <person
					reg="Murray, Gilbert">Gilbert Murray</person>. They think it is splendid that
				the two most important forward movements of recent years--birth control and twilight
				sleep--have had such a welcome in America. Our work is international. We are allied
				with Leagues in England, <place reg="Netherlands, the">Holland</place> and
					<place>France</place>."</p>
			<p>Mrs. Sanger will speak  tonight at the <org>West Side auditorium</org>, Taylor street and  Racine avenue, and next sunday evening at the <org>Little theater</org>.</p>
			<p/>
		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
