<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/04/23 VS initial tags</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1942-06-10"> 10 June, 1942</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Statement on Birth Control and the Women's Army Auxiliary Corps</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421951</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Birth control urged for WAAC by Sanger</title><title
                    type="journal"> Philidelphia Daily News</title> June 10, 1942</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="PDN">Philidelphia Daily News</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Sanger's statement on the Women's Army Auxiliary Corps was picked up by
            multiple newspapers, including the <title type="journal">New York Times
            Herald</title>.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="medical justifications"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="employment of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Birth control urged for WAAC by Sanger</head>
        <dateline>June 10 <date value="1942-06-10 "/> New York<place/></dateline>
        <div>
            <q who="PDN"><p> The government should give members of the <org>women’s army auxiliary
                        corps</org> “preventive measures against pregnancy, just as it gives them
                    protection against smallpox,” <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret
                        Sanger</person>, the nation’s prime advocate of birth control, urged
                    today.</p></q>
            <p>
                <q who="PDN">She coupled the suggestions with a dire warning that otherwise the
                    no-babies rule of the WAAC will become</q> “a <person reg="Frankenstein, Victor"
                    >Frankenstein</person> monster which will turn and wreck the corps.”</p>
            <p>
                <q who="PDN">Miss Sanger, founder and honorary president of the <org>Planned
                        Parenthood Federation of America</org> was referring to the WAAC regulation
                    that any member of the corps who becomes pregnant will be immediately
                    discharged.</q> “Abortions and illegitimacy are bound to result if the
                government doesn’t recognize human nature,” <q who="PDN">she said.</q></p>
            <p>
                <q who="PDN">Asserting that</q> “women should not be exposed to coming down with a
                baby any more than to coming down with yellow fever,” <q who="PDN">Miss Sanger
                    continued.</q></p>
            <p> “Women in the army should receive the same instruction and the same protection as
                men soldiers. The women’s army will grow to great usefulness or disintegrate on the
                old-fashioned problem of woman as the child bearer and sex convenience – which is
                her status in the <org reg="National Socialist German Workers' Party">Nazi</org>
                countries.</p>
            <p> “It is up to women to make a clear, concise and courageous statement of their
                position at this time, before it is too late, and demand protection and equal
                treatment with men in this matter.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> More of Her Argument</head>
            <p> “If she does not rise to this responsibility, with a courageous and scientific
                attitude about her sex, she will set back the cause of women’s rights hundreds of
                years. Women cannot afford to let the women’s army be wrecked on prudery or outworn
                notions.”</p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
