<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">

    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-03-12 JK intiial tag</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1938-10-05">05 Oct 1938</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Speech to the Mothers' Health
                    Association of the District of
                Columbia</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421909</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Margaret Sanger Calls on U.S. to Offer
                    Birth Control Service</title>,<title type="journal">Herald
                    Tribune</title>, Oct. 6, 1938, <title type="article">Mrs.
                    Sanger Assails D.C.</title>, <title type="journal"
                    >Washington Post</title>, Oct. 6, 1938, <title
                    type="article">U.S. Urged to Aid in Birth Control</title>,
                    <title type="journal">Washington Herald</title>, Oct. 6,
                1938.</bibl>
            <bibl><title>MSM</title> C16:421</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="HT">Herald Tribune</name>
            <name id="WP">Washington Post</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger </person>spoke
        under the auspices of the <place reg="Washington, D.C."
            >Washington</place>
        <org>Mothers' Health Association</org> at the <org
            reg="Young Women's Christian Assocation">YWCA</org>'s <org>Barker
            Hall</org>. Also appearing was <person reg="Willson, Prentiss">Dr.
            Prentiss Willson</person>, <person reg="Tucker, Francis Bland">Rev.
            F. Bland Tucker</person>, <person reg="Ballard, Frederick A."
            >Frederick A. Ballard</person>, and <person reg="Willson, Edith E."
            >Edith E. Willson</person>. No complete version of the speech has
        been found; the text below comes from three different newspapers. <index
            level1="Young Women's Christian Association"/><index
            level1="United States" level2="population policies of"/><index
            level1="birth control" level2="suppression of"/><index
            level1="birth control" level2="legalization of"/><index
            level1="birth control" level2="in Washington D.C."/><index
            level1="birth control movement"/><index
            level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="MS on"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Margaret Sanger Calls on <place reg="United States">U.S.</place>
            to Offer Birth Control Service</head>


        <head type="sub">Federal Health Agencies, She Says, Should Help Any
            Mother Too Poor to Pay Physician’s Fee</head>

        <p><q who="HT"> Speaking at the <org>Young Women’s Christian
                    Association</org> Hall under the auspices of the Mothers'
                Health Association, Mrs. Sanger said evidence showed that the
                public was in favor of birth control.</q> “Public opinion polls,
            resolutions by organizations whose membership totals many millions
            of citizens, editorials in leading magazines, indicate what the
            public wants,” she said. </p>
        <p>“But when the matter is put up squarely to government officials who
            should properly inaugurate birth-control services on a nationwide
            scale, we run into an impenetrable wall of inertia and subterfuge.” </p>
        <p>“The <org reg="Works Progress Association">W. P. A.</org> was asked
            to include birth-control information to mothers in the home-nursing
            service and medical clinics carried on under its public health
            program,” Mrs. Sanger recalled. </p>
        <div>
            <head>Mrs. Sanger Assails D.C. Baby Deaths</head>
            <head type="sub">Speaks at Y.W.C.A. </head>
            <head type="sub">Asks Birth Education</head>
            <head type="sub">Urges Federal Aid</head>
            <head type="sub">Attacks U.S. Policies </head>
            <p>
                <q who="WP">Washington should have vastly greater facilities for
                    the spread of birth control information to help combat its
                    “disgraceful” infant mortality and maternal death rate, Mrs.
                    Margaret Sanger, advocate of birth control declared last
                    night at a meeting of the Mothers' Health Association.</q>
            </p>
            <p><q who="WP">Mrs. Sanger asserted that,</q> “right here in the
                Capital of our great country the maternal death rate is twice as
                high as that in <place>England</place> and
                <place>Wales</place>.”</p>
            <p>
                <q who="WP">Implicitly in her address, and expressly afterward,
                    Mrs. Sanger denounced the “tragic” failure of <place>United
                        States</place> government agencies to educate the public
                    in respect to birth control.</q>
            </p>
            <p><q who="WP">It is time to consider the increase</q> “not of our
                population but of its quality,” <q who="WP">she asserted,
                    observing that</q> “we are bringing down the level of
                intelligence in this country to the average menial equipment of
                a juvenile of 14. That’s something for a democracy to think
                about.”</p>
            <q who="WP">
                <p> Looking forward to a “consciously conceived” race, Mrs.
                    Sanger proposed a six-point program to her audience, which
                    consisted overwhelmingly of women:</p>
                <p><list>
                        <item>Sterilization of persons with transmissible
                            disease. </item>
                        <item>Women with tuberculosis, heart or kidney disease,
                            goiter, etc., should be “safeguarded from pregnancy”
                            until they are cured. </item>
                        <item>Normal parents who have subnormal children should
                            be discouraged from having more. </item>
                        <item>Every woman should have right to space birth of
                            her children from two to three years.</item>
                        <item>Parents “unable to care for two children should
                            not be encouraged to have nine.” </item>
                        <item>Doctors should be free to give “any man or woman
                            information so they can adjust their lives in
                            marriage and not have children the first two
                            years.”</item>
                    </list></p></q>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head>.S. Urged to Aid in Birth Control </head>
            <head type="sub"> Margaret Sanger Asks Service for All
                Mothers</head>
            <p> “As an American citizen I demand--and I hope that this
                organization joins with me in demanding-- that <org
                    reg="Government of the United States of America"
                    >Government</org> agencies charged with the responsibility
                of caring for the health and welfare of the American people
                should provide birth control service for all mothers who wish it
                and are too poor to pay the fees of private physicians. </p>
            <p>“To do less is not only a denial of democracy, it is cruel and
                inhuman.” </p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
