<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published statement">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-06-25 CH proofed </prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1953-04-08">8 Apr 1953</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied>Statement at <org>El Paso Planned Parenthood Center</org></supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421972</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Planned Parenthood Crusader Has Quiet Visit in El Paso</title> Apr. 9, 1953</bibl>
            
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="EPHP">El Paso Herald Post</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><index level1="family planning, principles of"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="descriptions of"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="nursing and"/>
        <index level1="birth control movement" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="birth control movement" level2="international"/>
        <index level1="Planned Parenthood Federation of America"/>
        <index level1="planned parenthood"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Planned Parenthood Crusader Has Quiet Visit In <place reg="El Paso, TX">El Paso</place></head>
        <byline>By <person reg="Pasternoster, Carolyn">CAROLYN PASTERNOSTER</person></byline>
        <p><q who="EPHP"><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Mrs. Margaret Sanger,</person> world-famous crusader for planned parenthood, spent a peaceful day in El Paso Wednesday after years of being called a "public nuisance," serving a jail term and a flight to <place>Europe</place> to avoid prosecution.</q></p>
        <q who="EPHP"><p>The 69-year-old leader of the birth control movement moves with an agility that belies her age and in her outspoken manner demonstrates the way she has fought public criticism since 1909.</p>
        <p><q who="EPHP">The daughter of a <person reg="Higgins, Anne Purcell">woman</person> who died in her early 40s after the birth of her 11th child, Mrs. Sanger early became interested in planning families in respect to the mothers' health, the father's earning power, and the family standard of living. She jumped into the fight to educate the world in 1909 after an incident that occurred during her nursing days, when as a trained nurse, she was called to a tenement house to attempt to save the life of a destitute <person reg="Sachs, Sadie">woman</person> who had tried to stop the coming of another child. The woman died and Mrs. Sanger decided to give her life to</q> "striking at the root of the evil, too many births without the facilities to care for the children."</p>
        <p>"Birth control doesn't mean limitation or the interference with life after conception," Mrs. Sanger explained. "Rather it is family planning. We should eliminate from the birth rate those carrying inheritable or transmissable diseases. If parents knew they had these tendencies, I don't know one who would take the risk."</p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger, the mother of <person reg="Sanger, Stuart">two</person> <person reg="Sanger, Grant">sons</person> who are doctors, and grandmother to eight, was the founder of the <org reg="International Planned Parenthood Federation">American Birth Control League,</org> the original planned parenthood group. She is now honorary director of the <org reg="Planned Parenthood Federation of America">National Planned Parenthood Association</org> and North American president of the <org>World Federation.</org></p>
        <p>She said her prime interest now was to foster the work of the international group. She recently attended a <org reg="International Conference on Planned Parenthood, Third">world conference</org> in <place>India</place> where 42 countries were represented. With 5 million new babies a year born in India and an inadequate food supply, Mrs. Sanger stresses the importance of the association's government-approved work.</p>
        <p>In August, Mrs. Sanger will attend the <org reg="International Conference on Planned Parenthood, Fourth">fourth international meeting of the planned parenthood group</org> to be held in <place reg="Stockholm, Sweden">Stockholm.</place> There plans will be made for the furtherance of the educational work throughout the world, so that</p></q> <p>"one section of the world will not outweigh the others in population."</p>
        <q who="EPHP"><p><org>The Planned Parenthood Federation</org> now has 523 clinics with representation in every state in the union, with the educational work now being included in the public health units in seven states.</p>
        <p>Chief aim of the group is to have all public health units in the country continuing the work, Mrs. Sanger said.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger was the overnight guest of <person reg="Goetting, Betty Mary">Mrs. Charles Goetting,</person> 7832 La Senda Drive and will return to <place reg="Tucson, AZ">Tucson, Ariz.,</place> her home for the past 15 years Thursday.</p></q>
        
    </docBody>
</doc>
