<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article ">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/04/30 VS initial tagging</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="(1942-03-03) ">3 March, 1942</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Debate on War Babies</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421959</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">War Babies: Is This the Time For Them?</title><title
                    type="journal"> Salt Lake News</title> March 3, 1942</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="SLN">Salt Lake News</name>
            <name id="GRUSI">Gruenberg, Sidonie</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">Sanger participated in a debate over whether the time was right to
        increase the numbers of children. She was opposed by Sidonie Gruenberg of the Child Study
        Association, who argued that people who wanted to have children should not be swayed by the
        fact of war. This article was also published in the Hutchinson Kansas News, 3/24/1942, p. 5.
            <index level1="birth control" level2="and war"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="war and"/>
        <index level1="Birth Control Federation of America"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="population growth and"/>
        <index level1="children" level2="rights of"/>
        <index level1="Europe" level2="overpopulation and"/>
        <index level1="England" level2="birth rate in"/>
        <index level1="Germany" level2="birth rate in"/>
        <index level1="family planning, principles of"/>
        <index level1="Italy" level2="birth rate in"/>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="birth rate in"/>
        <index level1="marriage" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="reproductive responsibility"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="birth rate in"/>
        <index level1="war" level2="marriage and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>War Babies: Is This the Time For Them?</head>
        <div>
            <q who="SLN"><p> Should American parents fear to have more children now because of the
                    danger and insecurity caused by the greatest of history’s wars?</p></q>
            <q who="SLN"><p> From coast to coast they are raising that query. </p></q>
            <q who="SLN"><p> So the question was laid before two well known authorities. </p></q>
            <q who="SLN"><p> First was Mrs. <person reg="Gruenberg, Sidonie">Sidonie
                        Gruenberg</person>, head of the <org>Child Study Association</org> and
                    author of <title type="article">“We, the Parents,”</title> which won the 1940
                        <title type="journal">Parent’s Magazine</title> award for outstanding
                    service to parents and the home. </p></q>
            <q who="SLN"><p> Second was Mrs. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret
                    Sanger</person>, head of the <org reg="Birth Control Federation of America"
                        >American Federation of Birth Control</org>, who has battled for years - and
                    even been in jail - for her beliefs that women should have the freedom to
                    control the size of their families. </p></q>
        </div>
        <div>
            <p><supplied resp="MSPP"> [Parts of this article were omitted if they did not include
                    Mrs. Sanger in the conversation.] </supplied></p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <q who="SLN"><p> Mrs. Sanger, child of a large family, the mother of two physician sons
                    and a daughter who died at five, gave her views on the question by long distance
                    telephone from <place reg="Tucson, AZ">Tucson</place>, <place>Arizona</place>.
                </p></q>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Mental Hazards </head>
            <p> “It is a very bad time to have children,” <q who="SLN">she said.</q> “There are
                three reasons. First, the administration is trying it’s utmost to get people worried
                about the future. It wants us all to have a serious attitude about the insecurity of
                the future. Such a feeling creates a wrong condition under which to have children.
                It’s a known fact that many of the children born in this country after their
                parents’ arrival from <place>Europe</place> as immigrants have had menial
                retardation because of the mental insecurity of the parents upon their arrival. </p>
            <p> “Second, glandular upsets of the mothers during a period of worry and anxiety affect
                the unborn child. </p>
            <p> “And finally, in case the children should be born healthy, we have the nutrition
                question, to say nothing of the mental atmosphere of deprivation in the home.” </p>
            <p> “Every mother in this country who wants to have a healthy normal child should wait
                until there is assurance of security for the child and parents too.”</p>
            <q who="SLN"><p> Dr. Gruenberg has an answer to the question of adequate nutrition for
                    wartime babies.</p></q>
            <p>
                <q who="GRUSI">“I believe that it is part of national defense,”</q>
                <q who="SLN">she said,</q>
                <q who="GRUSI">“to establish milk stations and school lunches to make sure that
                    children born in wartime should have adequate food.”</q></p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> World Outlook </head>
            <q who="SLN"><p> Meanwhile, let’s see how many babies are actually being born. Figures
                    on the birthrate (the numbers of live births per 1,000 population) show there
                    has been a steady decrease in the birthrate in all civilized nations since 1880
                    until the last few years. In the <place>United States</place> (after a long
                    decline which hit a low of 16.6 in 1933) it moved up to 17.6 in 1938 and in 1941
                    showed a marked increase to 19.0, said to be largely due to wartime marriages
                    and business upswing. <place>England</place>’s birthrate has shown a very small
                    decrease since 1938, when it was 15.1 and provisional records show still more
                    decline- to about 14.2- for 1941. </p></q>
            <q who="SLN"><p>
                    <place>Germany</place>’s birthrate fell like a waterfall in a record low of 14.7
                    in 1933, spurted upward to 18.0 in 1934 and continued the increase to 20.4 in
                    1940- a rise credited to <person reg="Hitler, Adolf">Hitler</person>’s steps to
                    encourage the birth of more children. <place>Italy</place>’s birthrate has shown
                    a systematic decline for many years and <person reg="Mussolini, Benito"
                        >Mussolini</person>’s effort to arrest it have met with only slight success
                    in the last few years. It moved from 22.4 in 1936 to 23.7 in 1938 and back to
                    23.4 in 1939. Japan, with the largest birthrate of all (averaging from 30.6 in
                    1937 to 26.7 in 1938-) an unusually long skid for so short a time. No later
                    figures are available on <place>Japan</place> now. </p></q>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
