<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech ">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-04-02 JK initial tags</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1948-11-02 ">02 Nov 1948</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Statement on
                    Overpopulation</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421936</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">"Too Many People Says Founder of Planned
                    Parenthood"></title>
                <title type="journal">El Paso Herald Post</title> Nov. 2,
                1948.</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="EPHP">El Paso Herald Post</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">It is unclear where <person reg="Sanger, Margaret"
            >Sanger </person>was when she made this statement, reported in the
            <title type="journal">El Paso Herald Post</title>. <index
            level1="Europe" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Europe" level2="MS on"/><index
            level1="planned parenthood"/><index
            level1="Planned Parenthood Federation of America"/><index
            level1="overpopulation" level2="MS on"/><index
            level1="International Planned Parenthood Federation"/><index
            level1="population control" level2="MS on"/><index
            level1="population growth" level2="regulation of"/>
        <index level1="population growth" level2="standard of living and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Too Many People, Says Founder of Planned Parenthood</head>

        <p><q who="EPHP">Mrs. Margaret Sanger, founder of now worldwide
                    <org>Planned Parenthood</org>, said that starvation will
                face the <place>United States</place> as well as the rest of the
                world within 10 years if populations are not controlled. She
                said that food conservation programs are not enough to solve the
                problem because there are too many people in the world in
                relation to its food-producing capacity.</q> “It has been
            estimated that the standard of living in the United States started
            to decline about 1940,” Mrs. Sanger said. </p>

        <div>
            <head type="sub">Food Scarcity in England</head>

            <p>“In August I attended an international conference in<place>
                    England</place> on ‘Population and World Resources in
                Relation to the Family.’ Food and population exports from 34
                countries, including five from <place>Germany</place>, give a
                depressing description of the world food supply with relation to
                the number of mouths there are to eat it. “England, which is
                certainly not the worst off of<place reg="Europe"> European
                    nations</place>, already has twice as many people as it can
                feed. In Germany, whose food situation is the worst of any
                European country west of the Iron Curtain, great masses of
                people are starving, a fact which hardly ever gets public
                notice.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">U.S. Population Up</head>

            <p> “The United States now has just enough land to feed its own
                citizens. But in the past two years the population made a net
                increase of 5 million people. We must restrict our population by
                adequate birth control methods if we are to avoid starvation.
                “In the <place reg="El Paso, TX">El Paso </place>area, a man
                making $2500 a year is doing well if he can bring two children
                into the world and put them through high school. Unfortunately
                there are many, many instances where families around here have
                six or more children which they cannot support well. Other
                people have to support them with taxes, which means that they
                themselves can support less children. </p>
        </div>

        <div>
            <head type="sub">Center Here 11 Years</head>

            <p>“The women of El Paso who have backed the Planned Parenthood
                Center deserve to have a monument erected in their honor for the
                struggle they have made to spread the principles of birth
                control in this city.”</p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
