<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "file:/S:/TRANSCRIPTIONS/XML%20Drafts/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published interview">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/06/26 MM</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>
            <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
        </docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1953-01-04">4 Jan 1953</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>
                <supplied resp="MSPP">Interview with the Arizona Daily Star</supplied>
            </titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>421968</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Arizona Daily Star</title> 01/04/1953</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">This article included three photographs, two of Sanger at the Third
        International Conference on <org>Planned Parenthood</org>, one with <person
            reg="Desai, G.N.">G.N. Desai</person> and one of Sanger at the podium, and one of
            <person reg="Sanger, Nancy">Nancy Sanger</person>, her niece. She was interviewed on her
        return from the conference.<index level1="birth control" level2="access to"
            level3="international"/><index level1="Japan"
            level2="birth control laws and legislation in"/><index level1="Japan"
            level2="overpopulation and"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Awareness of Birth Control Growing World-Wide, States Pioneer in Field, Margaret
            Sanger Slee</head>
        <p>"It is everywhere evident that the awareness of the need of birth control in Asia is far
            ahead of the material to meet that need," commented Mrs. Margaret Sanger Slee, leader of
            the international birth control movement, on the overpopulation problem of Asia.</p>
        <p>As her ship docked at <place reg="Yokohama, Japan">Yokohama</place>, Mrs. Slee was
            impressed with the change in architecture. "A city which one had been oriental is now
            completely western," she remarked. "More people seemed to be in modern dress, also."
            "The attitude of the Japanese people has changed," Mrs. Slee stated. "Formerly it was
            the desire for a number of children to guarentee the living of the old, and now it seems
            to be the desire for only two children in a family."</p>
        <p>"The government (of <place>Japan</place>) recently legalized birth control, the first in
            the world to take this step. Unfortunately an adequate education program has not been
            worked out, one which stresses the important fact that abortion is not contraception,
            that there are better and safer ways of spacing pregnancies and limiting families," Mrs.
            Slee stated in a recent article on Japan which appeared in the Dec. 13 issue of the
                "<title>Nation</title>".</p>
        <p>"Nowhere in the world is there more need for planned parenthood than in Japan. The
            population, which was too great in 1922 for the land to support, was then 66 million.
            But now 85 million people are depending on the land for their welfare," she said.</p>
        <p>"Japan is compact," Mrs. Slee remarked, "and the cruel ravages of war are not noticable.
            She still has her shrines and temples, her flower gardens, tea-houses and beautiful
            theaters. She is still a land of beauty, curtesy, color and charm."</p>
        <p>Mrs. Slee talked with 50 young women doctors who were eager for information.
                "<place>Singapore</place> and <place>Hong Kong</place>," she said "have clinics
            established under the British government."</p>
        <p/>
    </docBody>
</doc>
