<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/03/14 YG</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-15 CH prrof tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-05-02 JK correct tags</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1935-12-31">31 Dec 1935</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Address to the <org reg="All-India Women's Conference"
                    >All-India Women's Conference</org></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421905</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">"Birth-Control: Women's Conference Debate: Need for Rural Reconstruction"</title>, <title
                    type="journal">The Hindu</title>, Dec 31 1935</bibl>
               </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="TH">The Hindu</name>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">Sanger was asked to address the All-India Women's
        Conference before a vote on a resolution calling for birth control
        instruction through clinics. The resolution passed. For other speaker
        comments see "Birth Control," The Hindu, Jan 1, 1936. <index
            level1="India" level2="birth control movement in"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="population policies of"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="overpopulation and"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="women in"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>BIRTH-CONTROL</head>
     

        <dateline><place reg="Trivandrum, India">Trivandrum</place><date value="1935-12-31">Dec. 31</date>
            </dateline>
        <div>
            <p><q who="TH">The question of imparting instruction in methods of
                    birth-control through recognised clinics evoked considerable
                    discussion at this morning's session of the All-India
                    Women's Conference.</q>
            </p>
            <p><q who="TH">The resolution (which as already reported was passed
                    by a majority) reiterated the conference's previous
                    resolutions supporting the necessity for instruction in
                    methods of birth-control through recognised clinics and
                    called upon all constituencies for the conference to make
                    special efforts to induce municipalities and other
                    organizations for maternity and child welfare to open
                    centres to impart such knowledge to those who were in need
                    of it. </q></p>
            <p><q who="TH">The resolution was moved by <person reg="Chandy, Anna">Mrs. Anna
            Chandy</person> (<place reg="Travanacore, India">Travanacore</place>). 
                She said that the Travancore
                    constituency had passed a resolution that clinics were
                    undesirable as very little was known about clinics. All were
                    agreed as to the necessity for contrl of births and there
                    was difference of opinion regarding the means. <person reg="Gandhi, Mohandas K.">Mr. Gandhi</person>
                    and other religious leaders advocated contenence, but many felt
                    that this was impossible for ordinary people. She discussed
                    the opposition view and stated that clinics could refuse
                    information to unmarried women if it was thought tha tit
                    would spread immorality among unmarried women. Travancoreans
                    had more confidence in the morality of their unmarried women
                    and in the larger interests of the nation, benefits of the
                    system must be availed of. It was not as harmful as yearly
                    births. </q></p>
            <p><q who="TH"><person reg="Ray, Renuka Mukherjie">Mrs. S.N. Ray</person>(Bengal), seconding the resolution,
                    stressed the fact that the question was not whether to
                    impart this knowledge or not as it was being diffused widely
                    through newpapers and advertisements, but it was to decide
                    whether scientific knowledge was to be imparted or to allow
                    harmful results on account of ignorance of methods.
                    Birth-spacing was not birth-prevention. </q></p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">OPPOSITION VIEW</head>
            <p><q who="TH"><person reg="Watts, Miss Dorothia Henriett">Miss D.H. Watts</person>(Travancore) opposing, said <place>India</place> was
                    on the threshold of new life and to start extreme measures
                    woudl be harmful to the country and the State. The
                    Conference was nine years old and had plenty of work to do.
                    The stability and existence of the Conference should not be
                    risked by extreme steps. None was against the word
                    "birth-control." But they were opposed to the word as it was
                    used at present. Brahmins of ancient India had small
                    families, but they did not use artificial means. If they
                    system was good, why was there so much propaganda? Spiritual
                    strength was acquired by self-control and not indulgence.
                    National discipline was impossible with
                self-indulgence.</q></p>
            <p><q who="TH"/><person reg="Menon, Lakshmi N.">Mrs. Lakshmi N. Menon</person><place reg="Lucknow, India">(Lucknow)</place> answered the
                objections raised by Miss Watts and said that there was no hope
                of improving the lives of people if the population was not
                limited. Control did not mean prevention. Continence was
                impossible for the masses. All good causes needed propaganda.
                They wanted a healthy race which can provide for its
                children.</p>
            <p><q who="TH"><person reg="Rosemeyer, M. I.">Miss Rosemeyer</person>(Travancore), opposing, said that
                    contraception was used as a method to escape control.
                    <person reg="Roosevelt, Franklin D.">President Roosevelt</person>had called it racial suicide.</q></p>
            <p><q who="TH"><person reg="Sukthankar, Dr.">Dr. Sukthankar</person><place reg="Bombay, India">(Bombay)</place> said that the resolution was
                    innocent and it wanted only centres opened for those who
                    needed it. The <org>Bombay Municipality</org>had failed to pass a
                    resolution for the establishment of clinics. But men were
                    responsible for this and women suffered. She pleaded for a
                    rationalistic consideration of the matter.</q></p>
            <p><q who="TH"><person reg="Damodaran, Mrs.">Mrs. Damodaran</person><place reg="Madras, India">(Madras)</place> said she would go even as far
                    as to say that even unmarried girls adopted these methods,
                    they were better than the methods at present in use.</q></p>
            <p><q who="TH">Children were god's gifts and how could they be
                    properly received if they were born every year?</q></p>
            <p><q who="TH"><person reg="Nair, Mrs. Kutten">Mrs. Kutten Nair</person><place reg="Cochin, India">(Cochin)</place>, supporting the motion,
                    emphasised that birth control was next to self-control. Was
                    it morality to bring for weaklings? Religious leaders must
                    have courage to protest against <person reg="Mussolini, Benito">Mussolini</person>who wanted large
                    families as fodder for cannons and not against a method of
                    saving mothers.</q></p>
            <p><q who="TH"><person reg="Mistri, Jarbanoo E.">Miss Mistri</person>(Bombay) pleaded for moderation and said
                    that medical opinion was in favour of giving advice to those
                    in real need on medical grounds.</q></p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">RACIAL SUICIDE</head>
            <p><q who="TH"> <person reg="Owerkirck, Louise C.">Miss Owerkirk</person>, opposing, quoted statistics to show
                    that the rate of increase of population was 19 per cent
                    while the rate of increase of agricultural productivity was
                    29 per cent and industrial productivity was 189 per cent. So
                    there was no ground to show that population outstripped
                    production. The danger was suicide of the race and birth
                    control was not accepted by the whole of the civilised
                    world. She pleased for adopting Indian methods.</q></p>
            <p><q who="TH"><person reg="Pillai, P. Thanu">Mrs. P. Thanu Pillai</person> (Travancore) opined that it
                    would lead to immorality.</q></p>
                <p><q who="TH"><person reg="Kale, Mrs.">Mrs. Kale </person><place reg="Nagpur, India">(Nagpur)</place> quoting <person reg="Viswesvarayya, M.">Sir M. Viswesvarayya</person> 
                    pleaded for birth control.</q></p>
            <p><q who="TH"> <person reg="Isaac, Ratnamma"></person>Dr. Ratnamma Isaac (<place reg="Mysore, India">Mysore</place>) narrated her experience
                    of clinics in <place reg="Bangalore, India">Bangalore</place>and said information was given to
                    all who came into maternity wards.</q></p>
            <p><q who="TH"><person reg="Gomez, E.">Miss Gomez</person>(Travancore) disapproved of birth
                    control.</q></p>
            <p><q who="TH"><person reg="Cherisn, Accamma">Mrs. Cheriyan</person>(Travancore) wanted that the standard
                    of life of the masses should be raised.</q></p>
            <p><q who="TH">Mrs. Sanger congratulated the conference on the
                    atmosphere of the discussion. She would ask how many
                    children the opposers had. Most of them had none. She was
                    the mother of three and one of eleven children and trained
                    nurse and had worked for 21 years for birth control.</q></p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">MRS. SANGER'S ADDRESS</head>
            <p>
                <q who="TH">Mrs. Sanger observed that those who opposed the
                    resolution mostly represented the Christian religion and
                    brought forward the argument of immorality. Christianity had
                    been in existence for over two thousand years and had almost
                    complete power in the world. If after all that, they could
                    not trust women with knowledge, then that teaching had
                    failed.</q>
            </p>
            <p><q who="TH">In one clinic with over 50,000 attending, less than
                    one per cent were unmarried. It was quite possible to check
                    those who came to clinics.</q></p>
            <p><q who="TH">Continuing, she observed that in India the population
                    had increased faster than in any other country. Where there
                    was widespread misery and lack of food, there was
                    overpopulation. To prevent the infant mortality, three
                    factors had to be considered, namely, father's wages,
                    spacing of family and the place of the child in the family.
                    In India out of first-born children, 22 per cent died, of
                    the fourth-born, 23 per cent, of the seventh-born 33 per
                    cent, the tenth 41.3 per cent, of the eleventh 51.4 per
                    cent, and of the twelfth 59.7 per cent. The birth and death
                    rates were highest in India. While the average longevity
                    was increasing in European countries, it was decreasing in
                    India. </q></p>
            <p><q who="TH">Proceeding Mrs. Sanger pointed out that birth-control
                    had reduced infant and maternal mortality and that
                    continence could not be imposed on those who were not ready
                    for it. She read the following quotation from a book
                    published with the approval of the<org> Roman Catholic
                    Church</org>.</q></p>
            <p>"First of all, we have the right to expect that married lives of
                many couples will be vastly enriched with values, physical,
                psychic, and moral, of married life as it was intended by the
                Creator. Burdens that test human endurance to the utmost limit
                and to which all too many succumb will be lightened. I speak of
                burdens of poverty, inadequate income, of unemployment which
                makes it impossible for parents to give their children and
                themselves food, clothing, housing, education and recreation
                which they are entitled to as children of God. I speak of
                psychological burdens, burdens of depleted physical energy and
                exhausted vitality, resulting from previous birth or
                miscarriage, burden of adverse conditions of the heart, kidneys
                or other organs and other conditions that threaten the life of
                the mother in case of pregnancy. I refer to psychic burdens of
                uncontrollable fear, anxiety and irritability, of rebellion
                against <name type="diety">God</name> and His Church for seeming to make demands beyond
                human nature and beyond human powers to endure."</p>
            <p><q who="TH">The name of the book was <title type="book">"Rhythm babies when parents
                    are ready"</title> by <person reg="Latz, Leo J.">Leo J. Latz</person>.</q></p>
            <p><q who="TH">The resolution was put to vote and carried by 82 to
                    25 votes. The conference then adjourned.</q></p>

        </div>

    </docBody>
</doc>
