<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/04/23 initial tags</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1941-09-06">6 September, 1941</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Interview with the New York Herald Tribune</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421952</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Totaliterians Called U.S. Foes of Birth
                    Control</title><title type="journal">New York Herald Tribune</title> 6
                September, 1941</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="NYHT">New York Herald Tribune</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Nearing the twenty-fifth anniversary of the first birth control clinic,
            Sanger recalls the birth control movement as well as comments on her exhibits being
            banned from the New York State Fair, Mineola Fair, and a fair in Detroit.</p>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="arrests and imprisonment"/>
        <index level1="Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau" level2="raid of"/>
        <index level1="birth control clinics and leagues"/>
        <index level1="Birth Control Federation of America"/>
        <index level1="Brownsville Clinic" level2="raid and trials"/>
        <index level1="jails and imprisonment"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, William" level2="arrest, trial and imprisonment"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>'Totalitarians' Called <place reg="United States">U.S.</place> Foes of Birth
            Control</head>
        <p>
            <q who="NYHT">Mrs. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>, pioneer
                advocate of birth control education and chairman of the <org>Birth Control
                    Federation of America</org>, said yesterday that she had information that there
                was an organized campaign under way, instigated by</q> “the totalitarian countries,”
                <q who="NYHT">to wreck the birth-control movement in the United States.</q></p>
        <p>
            <q who="NYHT">The protests which led to the barring of a birth-control exhibit at the
                    <org>New York State Fair</org> at <place reg="Syracuse, NY">Syracuse</place>
                last week and the more recent barring of exhibits at the <org>Mineola Fair</org> at
                    <place reg="Mineola, NY">Mineola</place>, L.I., and at a fair at <place
                    reg="Detroit, MI">Detroit</place>, are the first outward signs , she said,
                of</q> “an insidious campaign to break up our movement.”</p>
        <p> “You are going to see it more and more,” <q who="NYHT">she asserted,</q> “closing up our
            clinics, stopping our meetings and banishing our exhibits.”</p>
        <q who="NYHT"><p> The fifty-seven-year-old leader of the movement, which on Oct. 16 will
                celebrate the twenty-fifth anniversary of the opening of the <org
                    reg="Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau">first birth control clinic</org>,
                in the United States, said that she was frankly alarmed at the situation.</p></q>
        <q who="NYHT"><p> Sitting in the library of the <org>Margaret Sanger Bureau</org>, 17 West
                Sixteenth Street, she said that she was not yet prepared to offer concrete evidence
                of her charge that the latest action against her movement was the result of
                subversive influence from abroad. The only way to fight it, she asserted, was for
                birth-control advocates to redouble their efforts to make birth-control advice part
                of the regular public health system.</p></q>
        <p>
            <q who="NYHT">Asked what interest the totalitarian countries would have in interfering
                with birth-control here, Mrs. Sanger explained that the question of population is
                one very close to the European dictators.</q> “They know,” <q who="NYHT">she
                said,</q> “that if birth-control is done away with here misery and poverty will
            abound in this country and only in countries where such conditions exist can a
            dictatorship take hold.”</p>
        <q who="NYHT"><p> The birth-control pioneer was particularly bitter at the action of
                Lieutenant Governor <person reg="Poletti, Charles">Charles Poletti</person> who, as Acting Governor, issued the ruling which
                resulted in the barring of the exhibit at the New York State Fair and indirectly in
                the taking of similar action at the Mineola Fair, which will be open from Sept. 9 to
                Sept. 13.</p></q>
        <p>
            <q who="NYHT">Characterizing Mr. Poletti’s ruling that the birth-control advocates seek
                to contravene state law as</q> “the most stupid interference with the movement in
            twenty-five years,” <q who="NYHT">Mrs. Sanger said that by his ruling</q> “he played
            directly into the hands of totalitarian interests in this country.”</p>
        <q who="NYHT"><p> As a result, she stated, what was planned as a celebration on the
                forthcoming twenty-fifth anniversary will take the form of a nation-wide protest.
                Everywhere where there are groups affiliated with the Birth Control Federation of
                America there will be protests on the anniversary date, she announced.</p></q>
        <q who="NYHT"><p> Mrs. Sanger recalled the opening of the first birth-control clinic on Oct.
                16 1916, at 46 Amboy Street, in the Brownsville section of <place reg="Brooklyn, NY">Brooklyn</place>. In the four
                days that it remained open before the police closed it, she said, she, her sister,
                Mrs. <person reg="Byrne, Ethel">Ethel Byrne</person>, both of whom were nurses, and a few associates spoke to 480 women
                who flocked to the little clinic for advice. Somewhat wistfully, Mrs. Sanger
                recalled that she and her sister “did” thirty days in the <org>Queens County jail</org> when
                they lost the test case which grew out of their arrest at the clinic. Now, she
                reported, there are 619 clinics throughout the country.</p></q>
    </docBody>
</doc>
