<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-04-15 JK initial tag</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1935-10-31 ">31 Oct 1935</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Interviews with the London Daily
                    Express, Daily Mirror, and News
                Chronicle</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421923</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">"Marry Young"</title>,<title
                    type="journal">Daily Express</title>, Oct. 31, 1935, <title
                    type="article">Cocktail-Drinking Women-Bad Mothers"</title>,
                    <title type="journal">Daily Mirror</title>, Oct. 31, 1935,
                    <title type="article">"Ideal Family"</title>,<title
                    type="journal">News Chronicle</title></bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="DE">Daily Express</name>
            <name id="DM">Daily Mirror</name>
            <name id="NC">News Chronicle</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger</person> gave
            press interviews in <place reg="London, England">London</place> en
            route to<place> India</place>. Text has been taken from the <title
                type="journal">Daily Mirror</title>, <title type="journal">Daily
                Express</title>, and the <title type="journal">News
                Chronicle</title>.</p><index
            level1="Birth Control International Information Centre"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="birth control clinics and leagues in"/>
        <index level1="All India Women's Conference"/><index
            level1="conferences" level2="All India Women's Conference"
            level3="1935-36 (10th)"/>
        <index level1="motherhood"/><index level1="family size" level2="MS on"
            /><index level1="Family Limitation"/><index level1="child spacing"
            /><index level1="birth control" level2="in marriages"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Marry Young</head>
        <p>“If young people marry early but take their time before having
            families,” <q who="DE">she said, in an interview in London
                yesterday,</q> “they are able to plan that adjustment which is
            so important in marriage. </p>
        <p>“An only child is a tragedy--especially for the child. I consider
            that ‘spacing’ of three years between each child is ideal.” </p>
        <div>
            <head>Cocktail-Drinking Women-Bad Mothers</head>
            <q who="DM"><p>Cocktail-drinking, slimming young women inevitably
                    make bad mothers- unless they receive frank scientific
                    advice before marriage.</p>
                <p> This is the view of Mrs. Margaret Sanger, president of the
                        <org>Birth Control International Information
                        Centre</org>, who would like every engaged couple to be
                    told the “facts of life.”</p></q>
            <p>“In <place>New York</place>,” <q who="DM">she told me,</q>
                “50,000 young people of both sexes are initiated into the
                mysteries of sex every year at the clinic run by my
                organization. </p>
            <p>“My advice to these young couples is: ‘Want a child from the very
                start of marriage, so that it is ushered into the world with an
                invitation instead of being an unwanted guest.’</p>
            <p>“We feel that an only child is a tragedy. ‘Spacing of three years
                between children is the ideal. Young people should be encouraged
                to marry early, but take their time before they begin to have
                their families. </p>
            <q who="DM">
                <p>This kindly woman’s face grew grave when she told me that
                    time and time again she has been confronted by young women
                    on the brink of marriage, whose nerves have been destroyed
                    by alcohol, slimming and late nights.</p></q>
            <p> “This lack of discipline,” she said, “is common to most
                countries. It is largely the parents’ fault. We have merely to
                point out the serious danger to the future race to find that
                these young people respond and renounce their rackety
                parties.</p>
            <p>“The only consolation is that girls who deliberately blind
                themselves to these perils often have no children; seldom more
                than one.”</p>
            <q who="DM">
                <p> In a few days Mrs. Sanger is sailing to India, where she is
                    to be a guest-speaker at the <org>All India Women’s
                        Conference.</org>
                </p></q>
            <p>“I must make it clear,” she said, “that I am not going to India
                to persuade everybody to have a small family. I want rather to
                convince them of the desirability-- for themselves and
                posterity-- of having families of the right size and right
                quality.” </p>
            <byline>By a Special Correspondent</byline>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head>Ideal Family</head>
            <q who="NC">
                <p>Happier homes, fewer divorces, and more stable and permanent
                    marriages would result if there were an interval of at least
                    two years between marriage and the birth of the first
                    child.</p>
                <p>This is a conviction expressed to me by Mrs. Margaret Sanger,
                    inventor of the phrase “birth control,” founder of the <org
                        reg="American Birth Control League">first birth control
                        organization in <place reg="United States"
                            >America</place></org> where she is one of the
                    best-known women.</p></q>
            <p>“It is all important that the newly married should get acquainted
                and become adjusted to each other. Children are a secondary
                consideration in the early years of marriage,” she said to me. </p>
            <q who="NC"><p>Figures in the <place>United States</place> show that
                    when children are “postponed” on account of the wife
                    continuing to work there has been a reduction of the divorce
                    total, according to Mrs. Sanger.</p>
                <p>The ideal marriage, she went on, would be between a man of 23
                    and a woman of 22. The woman would continue her job for two
                    or three years before having a child.</p>
                <p>The family could consist of three children, born at intervals
                    of three years.</p></q>
            <p>
                <q who="NC">It is tragic to have only one child, she believes.
                    But for the average family today a fourth child </q>“can
                ruin the whole structure of the family,” <q who="NC">and a fifth
                    child</q> “is enough to drive women to drink.”</p>
            <p>“Economists have not begun to realize the possibilities in early
                marriages and small families,” she declared.</p>
            <p><q who="NC">She pointed out the</q> “splendid national
                investment” <q who="NC">it would be to encourage early marriages
                    with the prospect of children “postponed” until the young
                    couple</q> “got economically on their feet.”</p>
            <p><q who="NC">Each family would need new quarters and a</q>
                “complete new set of household equipment.” <q who="NC">This
                    would </q>“boost things generally.”</p>
            <p>“In the East I have found very little religious prejudice against
                birth control,” said Mrs. Sanger, "and no moral prejudice
                whatsoever.” </p>
            <p>“If young people marry early but take their time before having
                    families,”<q who="NC"> she said, in an interview in London
                    yesterday, </q>“they are able to plan that adjustment which
                is so important in marriage. </p>
            <p> “An only child is a tragedy--especially for the child. I
                consider that ‘spacing’ of three years between each child is
                ideal.” </p>
        </div>



    </docBody>
</doc>
