<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed interview">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-04-15 JK initial tag</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-14 CH proof/enter tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-04-23 JK correct tags</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1937-02-17">17 Feb 1937</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Interview with the United
                    Press</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421921</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Alice Park papers, Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace.</bibl>
            <bibl><title>Library of Congress Microfilm 83:457</title></bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="MSPP">Margaret Sanger Papers Project</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Sanger gave this interview with <person
                reg="Heilman, E.J.">E.J. Heilman </person>in <place
                reg="Chandler, AZ">Chandler, Arizona</place> on Feb. 17. The
            published version found had no newspaper information on it. For a
            typed version see <org>Library of Congress</org> Microfilm 83:457. </p>
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Federal"
            /><index level1="birth control"
            level2="distribution of information about"/><index
            level1="Comstock Laws"/><index
            level1="birth control clinics and leagues" level2="in US"
        /></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Birth Control Battle Won, Leader Says</head>
        <byline>by <org>United Press</org></byline>
        <dateline>
            <date value="/1937/-02-19"/>Feb. 19, <place reg="Phoenix, AZ">
                Phoenix, Ariz.</place></dateline>
        <p><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Mrs. Margaret Sanger</person>, famous
            crusader for birth control, told the United
                Press today the organization she heads would discontinue
            its attempt to change <org
                reg="United States Government">Federal
            </org>laws banning dissemination of birth control information or
            appliances.</p>
        <p>“We shall close our <place reg="Washington, DC"
                >Washington</place> lobby, which has been maintained for several
            years, about March 1,” she said. “We believe it no longer is
            necessary to attempt to change the law in view of the recent <org
                reg="United States Court of Appeals For the Second Circuit"
                >Circuit Court of Appeals</org> decision which held birth
            control appliances and information may be sent through the mails or
            in interstate commerce.”</p>
        <p>At the same time, Mrs. Sanger predicted, the number of birth control
            clinics in the <place>United States</place> would be doubled by the
            end of 1937 as result of the court ruling. </p>
        <p> “There are now 320 clinics in this country,” she said. “I believe
            there will be double that number by the end of this year because it
            is no longer necessary to ‘bootleg’ information or appliances.”</p>
        <p> The decision to which Mrs. Sanger referred was one which held that
            the <person reg="Comstock, Anthony">Comstock </person>Law of 1873,
            relating to dispatch of “obscene” materials or writings through the
            mails or in interstate commerce, did not apply to birth control
            information or appliances. The Court held such information or
            appliances could be interpreted as health measures. </p>
        <p> The test case involved shipment of a quantity of birth control
            devices from <place>Japan</place> to a <place reg="New York, NY">New
                York</place> <person reg="Stone, Hannah Mayer">woman physician</person>. </p>
        <p> Mrs. Sanger said a newly-discovered, inexpensive contraceptive she
            announced last year still was under laboratory tests in New York. </p>
        <p>The contraceptive, based on rice or corn starch, was designed, she
            said, “for the masses who cannot afford the commercial
            contraceptives now available to those in better circumstances, and,
            as a result, are overburdened with children they cannot care for
            properly.” The material, she said, now is being used in
                <place>India</place> and <place>China</place>, but will not be
            released in this country for at least a year. </p>
        <p> Mrs. Sanger is spending the winter in an exclusive resort in <place
                reg="Chandler, AZ">Chandler, Ariz.</place> She said she would go
            to <place reg="El Paso, TX">El Paso, Tex.</place>, in about a week
            to open a new birth control clinic. </p>
        <p>She appeared before a <org
                reg="United States House of Representatives">House</org>
            legislative committee late yesterday to speak in favor of a bill
            proposing to repeal <place>Arizona</place> law which forbids
            advertisements or contraceptives. </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
