<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-04-07 JK initial tag</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1941-08-29">29 Aug 1941</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>
                <supplied resp="MSPP">Statement on Ban on Birth Control Exhibits in New
                    York</supplied>
            </titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421944</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Mineola Fair Cancels Birth Control Exhibit</title>, <title
                    type="journal">New York Herald Tribune</title>, Aug. 29, 1941.</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="NYHT">New York Herald Tribune</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="Birth Control Federation of America"/>
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Federal"/>
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="State"/>
        <index level1="birth control clinics and leagues" level2="in US"/>
        <index level1="public health" level2="birth control and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head><place reg="Mineola, NY">Mineola</place> Fair Cancels Birth Control Exhibit</head>
        <p><q who="NYHT">Meanwhile, <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Mrs. Margaret Sanger</person>,
                pioneer advocate of birth control education and chairman of the <org>Birth Control
                    Federation of America</org>, <place reg="New York, NY">501 Madison
                    Avenue</place>, issued a statement bitterly attacking <person
                    reg="Poletti, Charles">Mr. Poletti</person>’s action as “absurd” and indicating
                “how misinformed” he is “in this field of public health.” She urged citizens of the
                state to demand a review of the case and a reconsideration of the ban, saying
                that</q> “it is important to the welfare of the citizens of <place>New York</place>
            State” <q who="NYHT">that Mr. Poletti’s action be rescinded</q>.</p>
        <p><q who="NYHT">Noting that Mr. Poletti had ruled that the planned exhibit was</q>
            “calculated to contravene or change the declared policy of the state under S1145 of the
            state law,” <q who="NYHT">Mrs. Sanger said: </q></p>
        <p>“As far back as 1918, <person reg="Crane, Frederick">Judge Crane</person>, in his
            memorable decision, pointed out at that S1145 of the New York State laws specifically
            exempts physicians from the restrictions of S1142 which Mr. Poletti cites, and
            recognizes the right of the medical profession to provide contraceptives ‘for the cure
            or prevention of disease.’</p>

        <p> “Such an exemption is all what birth control advocates have ever sought from restrictive
            laws, so obviously there is no need to attempt to amend existing New York State laws, or
            to urge any change in the existing policy which Mr. Poletti mentioned. </p>
        <p>“In 1936 a similar interpretation of the <org reg="United States Government"
                >Federal</org> law also recognized the right of the medical profession to provide
            contraceptives ‘to promote the health or well-being of their patients,’ and therefore
            there has been no need for any legislative effort of any kind to be carried on by the
            Birth Control Federation of America, Inc., at this time. </p>
        <p>“We have been informed that Mr. Poletti’s stand was taken as a result of protests by
            representatives of the <org>Roman Catholic Church</org>. </p>
        <p>“If this be so, we protest as undemocratic and inimical to public welfare the fact that
            pressure of a minority religious group can effectively the majority if the citizens of
            New York State from information they desire on a subject considered of sufficient
            importance as a health measure to be included in the State Public Health programs of
                <place reg="North Carolina">North</place> and <place>South Carolina</place> and of
                <place>Alabama</place> and in 209 health department programs in thirty-nine states.” </p>
        <p>
            <q who="NYHT">Mrs. Sanger said that the exhibits simply would have informed the public
                of the benefits of birth control by graphically calling attention to the advantages
                of planned families so that more families might avail themselves of services and
                advice physicians are legally entitled to give.</q>
        </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
