<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "file:/S:/TRANSCRIPTIONS/XML%20Drafts/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published statement">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/06/19 MM</prepDate>
        <docAuthor><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret
            Sanger</person></docAuthor>
        <docDate value="(1959-12-27) ">Dec 27 1959</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Statement on President Eisenhower's Views on Government
                and Population Issues</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421983</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>"<title type="article">Mrs. Sanger Challenges Ike on Birth
                    Curb Issue</title>" <title rend="underline">Tuscon Daily
                    Citizen </title> 12/28/59</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="EISDW">Eisenhower, Dwight</name>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">Sanger appeared on Channel 13 in Tuscon to discuss
            <person reg="Eisenhower, Dwight">President Eisenhower</person>'s
        statement on American family planning assitance to foreign nations: <q
            who="EISDW">"I cannot imagine anything more emphatically a subject
            that is not a proper political or governmental activity or function
            or responsibility."</q><index level1="foreign aid"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="international"/><index
            level1="Japan" level2="overpopulation and"/><index level1="India"
            level2="overpopulation and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head><title type="article">Mrs. Sanger Challenges Ike On Birth Curb
                Issue</title></head>
        <byline>By Leslie Ernenwein</byline>
        <p>Mrs. Margaret Sanger, birth control advocate, challenged President
            Eisenhower last night to debate the question of governmental
            participation in planned parenthood for nations requesting help.</p>
        <p>"He needs to be straightened out on this," Mrs. Sanger said. "It is
            disgraceful that our country does not respond when a poor,
            overpopulated country asks for aid."</p>
        <p>She said that Eisenhower set back the birth control movement by his
            recent refusal to help overpopulated countries settle their problems
            by planned parenthood. </p>
        <p>"Such countries do not know what to do," she said. "They want our
            health and welfare departments to show them what to do. If we are
            serious in wanting peace we should be glad to help them."</p>
        <p>Eisenhower, she said, knows only war.</p>
        <p>"He doesn't realize that the question of war or peace is primarily a
            question of population," Mrs. Sanger said. "He goes gallivanting off
            to various countries to talk peace. But he knows nothing about
            population problems in those countries--especially<place>
                India</place>.</p>
        <p><place>Japan</place>, she said, has reduced the birthrate 50 per cent
            since 1957 by practicing planned parenthood.</p>
        <p>"The movement started here in 1920 and met great resistance by the
            warmongering politicians. But the Japanese people kept at it even
            though some of them were jailed for sponsoring birth control."</p>
        <p>Does she believe the President will agree to a debate, or grant her
            an interview?</p>
        <p>"He certainly should," Mrs. Sanger said. "He's an intelligent man,
            but he just doesn't know about this problem. He has been
            misinformed. He has been influenced by the opposition--by the Irish
            Catholic bishops."</p>
        <p>She said that the Draper report, requested by Eisenhower, had
            indicated that we should assist on request those nations needing
            population control. But Eisenhower apparently has rejected the
            report, after initially accepting it, she said. </p>
        <p>"If he will debate the question and learn something about this
            problem I am confident that he would change his views," Mrs. Sanger
            said. </p>
        <p>"We cannot have peace without halting the population explosion which
            is currently occuring in various countries such as India."</p>



        <p/>
    </docBody>
</doc>
