<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published interview">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/03/07 VS initial tagging</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/03/14 VS finished tagging</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/03/20 CH proof tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/03/26 VS correct tags</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docAuthor>Gretta Palmer</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1938-12-00">Dec 1938</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Margaret Sanger: Crusader (Interview with Gretta Palmer)</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421925</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Margaret Sanger: Crusader</title><title type="magazine">The
                    Commentator</title>Dec. 1938, pp. 68-73</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="PALGR">Palmer, Gretta</name>
            <name id="GOLEM">Goldman, Emma</name>
            <name id="FRENCH">language</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">Interview between Margaret Sanger and Gretta Palmer <index
            level1="American Birth Control League"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="legalization of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="religion and"/>
        <index level1="Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau"/>
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Massachusetts"/>
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Comstock Act"/>
        <index level1="Birth Control Review, The"/>
        <index level1="Catholic Church" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="law breaking and direct action"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="background of"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="freedom and rights of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Margaret Sanger: Crusader</head>
        <byline>Proving that the man or woamn who knows his own mind can't be stopped short of
            success</byline>
        <div>
            <q who="PALGR"><p><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person> is a small
                    wisp of a woman on the platform, but her energies, her sympathy, and her
                    red-headed persistence are of heroic size. She is a fighter – a zealot – a
                    fanatic, no doubt of that; yet her armory of weapons includes such blarney as
                    was unknown to the grimmer women crusaders of our own time. As a result no
                        <person reg="Nation, Carrie">Carrie Nation</person> or <person
                        reg="Pankhurst, Emmeline">Emmeline Pankhurst</person> every got as much fun
                    out of the movement these solemn ladies promoted as the slight Irishwoman whose
                    life has been dedicated to the somewhat indelicate subject of birth
                control.</p></q>
            <q who="PALGR"><p> How did she ever come about? What power took this stonecutter’s
                    daughter from upstate <place>New York</place> and turned her into a force
                    agitating the public of her time?</p></q>
            <p> “Glands,” <q who="PALGR">answers Mrs. Sanger tersely.</q></p>
            <p>
                <q who="PALGR">She was always set apart from the women whose lives are normally
                    inconspicuous by ferocious energy. After her marriage to <person
                        reg="Sanger, William">William Sanger</person>, running a house, recovering
                    from threatened tuberculosis, bringing up her three children, and dabbling in
                    women’s club activities took up, she says today,</q>“perhaps one-tenth of my
                energy.” <q who="PALGR">Such women as this have three choices open to them: they may
                    become fanatically fine housekeepers and mothers or they may take a job or they
                    may attach themselves to a Cause. Margaret Sanger chose a Cause.</q></p>
            <q who="PALGR"><p> And what a cause! It seemed not only forlorn, in the ‘teens of this
                    century, but so scandalous a choice that its mere mention was not “nice.” It led
                    inevitably to abuse, ostracism, raids, and jail sentences.</p></q>
            <q who="PALGR"><p> “What kept you going?” I asked her.</p></q>
            <p> “To stop, when I had once begun, would have been as impossible as to stop the sun,”
                    <q who="PALGR">she said.</q> “I just kept on, from interest and the knowledge
                that I was right.”</p>
            <q who="PALGR"><p> Self-confidence such as hers is rare – so rare that its possessors
                    are inevitably catapulted onto the front pages of the world. The best medical
                    men of her time were against her – and she had only a trained nurse’s experience
                    to pit against theirs. The morality of the churches and of society opposed her:
                    but she never faltered. Her closest affections were endangered by the struggle –
                    she still was not held back. She had no money with which to prosecute what was
                    sure to be an expensive, long-drawn-out campaign. What of that?</p></q>
            <p> “I don’t really know how most of my ventures in this work were ever financed,” <q
                    who="PALGR">said Mrs. Sanger, vaguely.</q> “I do things first and somehow or
                another they get paid for. If I had waited to finance my various battles for birth
                control, I do not suppose they would have become realities. I saw the thing to do,
                and did it, and inevitably, without fail, the money came to pay for it.”</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <q who="PALGR"><p>Single-mindedness is, I suppose, the strongest weapon any human being
                    can have. The true fanatic is never deterred from his purpose, nor drawn into
                    other movements. Margaret Sanger might have found congenial companions in the
                    fight for woman’s rights or in the movement towards easier childbirth. Both of
                    these causes were close to her own, and if she had attached herself to them she
                    need not have set out on so solitary a path. But hers was a definitely-marked
                    crusade: one which, if necessary, she would wage without followers or disciples.
                    But she must proceed with it – no turning back was ever possible.</p></q>
            <p> “I never had a moment’s discouragement,” <q who="PALGR">said Mrs. Sanger,
                    brightly.</q> “I knew that the great majority who opposed me were wrong.
                Obstacles were in my path – but they could all be removed, and were. No effort of
                the will was ever necessary.”</p>
            <p>
                <q who="PALGR">Consider Margaret Sanger in 1912, when she approached a group of
                    feminists and radicals, in the hope that they would give her idea support.
                </q>“They laughed at me – and why not?” <q who="PALGR">she says.</q> “I was
                considered a conservative person. I was not trained in the arts of the propagandist,
                I had no money with which to start a rousing campaign. I was not a trained writer or
                speaker, never having lifted my voice in public above the throng. I had no social
                position. I had no influential friends. I was digging deep into an illegal subject,
                alone and unaided.</p>
            <p> “Wherever I turned, from every one I approached, I met the same answer, ‘Wait!’
                ‘Wait until women get the vote!’ ‘Wait until the Socialists are in power!’ ‘Wait for
                the Social Revolution.’ ‘Wait for the Economic Revolution.’ Thus I lost my faith in
                the social schemes and organizations of that day.”</p>
            <p>
                <q who="PALGR">She wished, you see, to bring contraceptives and a knowledge of their
                    use to the masses. That was her simple, concrete, improbable plan. She was not
                    impressed by the fact that <person reg="Comstock, Anthony">Anthony
                        Comstock</person>’s obscenity laws forbade her to send a word of the banned
                    subject through the mails. She brushed aside the fact that all Christian sects
                    frowned on family limitation as a sin. She had none of the respect for the laws
                    and culture and social institutions of her time which dominates the life of most
                    men and women.</q> “The times,” <q who="PALGR">she said firmly,</q> “are wrong.
                And I am right.”</p>
            <q who="PALGR"><p> Her achievements, over a period of twenty-five years, have been
                    astounding. The talents and abilities which she lacked at the start were easily
                    acquired; with that terrible drive behind her, Mrs. Sanger soon learned enough
                    of medicine to argue the case with physicians, enough of public speaking to
                    address large audiences. She taught herself to write, and to lobby, to raise
                    funds and to parry questions of law with experts in the field. Given enough
                    single-minded intensity of purpose, all the other needed abilities may be added,
                    as required.</p></q>
        </div>
        <div>
            <q who="PALGR"><p>The story of her beginnings has been told often: of how her nursing in
                    the slums convinced her of the desperate need among the poor for some method of
                    preventing untimely births; of her European study-trip, in which she learned
                    that such a method was common enough in <place>France</place>; and of her return
                    to <place reg="United States">America</place> to discuss family limitation in
                        <title type="journal">The Woman Rebel</title> – which immediately brought
                    the first dramatic period of raids and jail sentences.</p></q>
            <q who="PALGR"><p> It was in this period that her marriage to William Sanger ended,
                    largely because of her interest in her cause had crowded out all other emotions
                    and preoccupations. It was at that time that the first <org
                        reg="Brownsville Birth Control Clinic">Brownsville clinic</org> was opened –
                    and closed by law. It was then that the <title type="journal">Birth Control
                        Review</title> began its stormy publication career, and that the use of
                        <org>Town Hall</org> was denied her by <place reg="New York, NY">New
                        York</place> police officers.</p></q>
            <p>
                <q who="PALGR">The radicals began to jump on the bandwagon, when they saw that birth
                    control was stirring up a vast amount of publicity. <person reg="Goldman, Emma"
                        >Emma Goldman</person>, the anarchist, had said to Mrs. Sanger a few years
                    before,</q> “<q who="GOLEM">You’re only a <foreign lang="FRENCH"
                        >bourgeoise</foreign>. Go home and mend your husband’s socks.</q>” <q
                    who="PALGR">Now she jumped into the movement, flagrantly broke the law by giving
                    contraceptive information from the lecture platform, and got herself arrested
                    without need.</q></p>
            <p> “Birth control as a movement,” <q who="PALGR">says Mrs. Sanger today,</q> “has
                succeeded in spite of many of its followers, and the embarrassment they caused
                it.”</p>
            <p>
                <q who="PALGR">Her own feeling about publicity was very different.</q> “There are
                three great tests to character,” <q who="PALGR">she believes:</q> “sudden wealth,
                sudden power, and sudden publicity. The last can be devastating. I knew, or rather
                felt, this power. I made it a rule never to buy the daily papers when its publicity
                was high. I never read what was written about myself. I had a definite, clear vision
                of the way I was to go, and I refused to be influenced by criticism or by personal
                approval.”</p>
            <q who="PALGR"><p> This sense of vocation, after all, was the greatest strength this
                    slight, humorous pioneer had. Directed toward almost any goal, it must have
                    carried her far. Such superb self-confidence and faith in any vision was bound
                    to win in a world made up of persons more confused and open to the conversion
                    than she. The success stories written by the lives of such crusaders as Mrs.
                    Sanger are more informative as human achievements than the biographies of
                    railroad presidents; the obstacles in her path were far greater than theirs, but
                    she had far greater faith than they in her ability to deal with them. And so she
                    won.</p></q>
            <q who="PALGR"><p>Mrs. Sanger never asked for advice. She never consulted her old
                    friends, and she refrained from making new ones.</p></q>
            <p> “When my friends deserted me and became cold, I felt a curious sense of release,” <q
                    who="PALGR">she says.</q> “For until they freed me, I was afraid that my actions
                might hurt them. When they broke off the friendship, I no longer felt bound. Even my
                enemies were useful – they gave me the best publicity that the movement ever
                received. The growth of the movement has to a considerable extent thrived on our
                skill in taking advantage of the stupid tactics of our enemies.</p>
            <p> “I just kept going, night, and say. My belief, faith – call it what you will – gave
                me a feeling of tremendous power. It seemed at times to open locked doors. It
                attracted the right people: it gave me the physical strength to dictate hundreds of
                letters through one ill-paid secretary, to interview dozens of people each day, to
                write articles, to write and deliver lectures, debates – in spite of a daily
                temperature, low but constant, and a decreasing bank account.”</p>
            <p>
                <q who="PALGR">“Faith” as a formula worked. It worked so well that her program went
                    through with hardly a hitch. She had planned, early in her campaign, to be</q>
                “first an agitator, who would stir up the minds of the influential public; then, an
                organizer, corralling followers; lastly, a lobbyist, changing the legislation to fit
                our needs.”</p>
            <q who="PALGR"><p> In the third, or final phase, dissension arose. Birth control, in
                    1928, had become a respectable “charity.” Many of the women who were officers of
                    the <org>American Birth Control League</org> felt that t fight for federal
                    legislation was undesirable – that education in the states and the opening of
                    clinics, where state laws allowed, were the more important tasks.</p></q>
        </div>
        <div>
            <p>Mrs. Sanger was militant still, and her own group, the <org>National Committee on
                    Federal Legislation for Birth Control</org> came into being.</p>
            <p> “To me,” <q who="PALGR">Mrs. Sanger has said,</q> “this cause was a living
                inspiration and interest. It was not a hobby. It was no mere filler in a busy social
                life. Its interest came first in my waking consciousness and was my last thought at
                night.</p>
            <p> “To the other members of the Board, it was only one of many other interests.
                Husbands, children, dressmakers, servants, charities, church, entertainment, all had
                claims on those who now began to dictate to me the policy the League was to
                take.”</p>
            <q who="PALGR"><p> The ten-year breach may soon be closed. The legislative drive has
                    ended, for a <org>United States Circuit Court</org> ruling in 1935 now permits
                    physicians to impart birth control information in states where the local laws do
                    not prohibit it. No federal law is now needed, according to the leaders in the
                    movement. It seems quite likely that the two groups will soon co-ordinate their
                    work.</p></q>
            <p>
                <q who="PALGR">Mrs. Sanger’s present work is concentrated on <place
                        reg="Washington, D.C.">Washington</place>, none the less. She hopes to
                    induce the federal government to include birth control clinics in the public
                    health movement. The recent congressional appropriation for health and welfare
                    work should, she believes, have a portion earmarked for her movement, to be
                    carried on under governmental auspices.</q> “It is futile,” <q who="PALGR">she
                    says,</q> “to go on patching up humanity. We must prevent such tragedies as
                tubercular births and maternal deaths that need not have occurred. The place to
                prevent them is in the birth control clinic.”</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <q who="PALGR"><p>Opposition to the movement has grown more limited and it has decreased
                    in ferocity. At first, all respectable society disapproved. Nowadays, the
                    stronghold of the opposition is the <org>Roman Catholic Church</org>. Other
                    religious bodies have broadened their attitude toward birth control, but the
                        <title type="book">Papal Encyclical</title> on the subject forbids the use
                    if contraception by the devout.</p></q>
            <p>
                <q who="PALGR">Such opposition, however, is normal to Mrs. Sanger. She has seen so
                    many desperate, hopeless struggles won that she is temperamentally incapable of
                    giving up on this issue. She realizes the difficulty of getting governmental
                    clinics, so long as Dr. <person reg="Parran, Thomas, Jr.">Thomas Parran,
                        Jr.</person>, a Roman Catholic, is the nation’s chief health officer. She
                    deplores the latest ruling of the state of <place>Massachusetts</place>, which
                    forbids physicians to give out birth control information to a woman, even to
                    save her life. This, she says, is the only backward step any state has taken in
                    the years since she has been in the movement. It means that the women of
                    Massachusetts</q> “are bound by a more reactionary law than the women of any
                other country in the world.”</p>
            <q who="PALGR"><p> Today there are over 400 birth control clinics in the country; 70,000
                    women have past through the portals of Mrs. Sanger’s own <org
                        reg="Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau">Clinical Research Bureau</org>
                    on West 16th Street, <place reg="New York, NY">New York</place>, and many of
                    them, she believes, have been saved from criminal abortions or from death in
                    childbirth. The movement has the indorsement of 970 organizations and 325,000
                    individuals. This country is now as well-equipped with clinics as
                        <place>England</place> and the <place reg="Scandinavia">Scandinavian
                        countries</place>, which have led the world. Mrs. Sanger must be aware of
                    the fact that she has accomplished a very great deal by her single-hearted
                    determination, no matter how high the cost to her personal life.</p></q>
            <q who="PALGR"><p> Was it worth while?</p></q>
            <p> “For me, yes,” <q who="PALGR">she says.</q> “My life so far has been extremely
                satisfactory. I could never have felt satisfied or complete if it had been limited
                to domestic duties. These things satisfy some women; not others.</p>
            <p> “In order to dare to stand alone one must feel an emotional drive toward a certain
                course, and be sustained by a logical impetus, as well. If the drive is all
                emotional, a crusader may become too fanatical to accomplish what he intends. In my
                case, both my emotions and my intelligence were involved. I felt that I was the only
                person in this country who saw the need for birth control. I knew that I was right,
                and that I <emph rend="italics">must</emph> go to work, with a will.”</p>
            <p>
                <q who="PALGR">In 1931, Margaret Sanger wrote <title type="book">My Fight for Birth
                        Control</title>. She ended the book on this note:</q> “Life has taught me
                one supreme lesson. If we are really to live at all, if we are to enjoy the life
                more abundant, we must put our convictions into action. My remuneration has been
                that I have been privileged to act out my own faith.”</p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
