<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-04-02 JK initial tags</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1949-05-05 ">05 May 1949</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Education for Planned
                    Parenthood</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421931</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">"Margaret Sanger Takes Stand Against
                    Socialized Medicine"</title><title type="journal">San Angelo
                    Evening Standard</title>May 6, 1949.</bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="SAES">San Angelo Evening Standard</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger</person> gave
        this address at a state meeting of the <org>Planned Parenthood League of
            Texas</org>, held in <place reg="San Angelo, TX">San Angelo</place>,
        at the <org>Cactus Hotel</org> on May 4 and 5. <index
            level1="planned parenthood"/><index level1="birth control movement"
            level2="MS on"/><index level1="birth control movement"/><index
            level1="Italy" level2="overpopulation and"/><index
            level1="overpopulation" level2="MS on"/><index level1="Japan"
            level2="overpopulation and"/><index
            level1="physically disabled and diseased" level2="birth control and"
        />ndex level1="population growth" level2="regulation of"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Margaret Sanger Takes Stand Against Socialized Medicine</head>
        <byline>by <person reg="Wiggins, Alliene">Alliene Wiggins</person>
            Standard-Times Staff</byline>

        <p><q who="SAES">Mrs. Sanger advised those interested in the planned
                parenthood movement to avoid and prevent socialized medicine.
                The stand against socialized medicine was made incidentally as
                she spoke at luncheon on the work of the organization and of her
                foreign field work in <place>Europe</place>.</q></p>
        <p>
            <q who="SAES">Mrs. Sanger began her address by saying 40 per cent of
                the people of the world today are not being fed properly. This
                problem combined with that of overpopulation, is of prime
                importance in the world today.</q></p>
        <p>
            <q> who="SAES">Citing <place>Germany</place>, <place>Italy</place>,
                and <place>Japan</place> as examples of nations forced to seek
                lands to provide resources for their over-supplied citizenry,
                Mrs. Sanger pointed out that today the population of Japan is
                increasing at more than a million a year-- this in a country
                smaller than the state of <place>California</place> and with few
                resources. These people will have to be supported for the next
                20 or 25 years, and unless the birth rate is curtailed the
                problem will be an endless one.</q></p>
        <p>
            <q who="SAES">In countries such as Japan, a national educational
                program on birth control should be introduced. To show the
                eagerness of the people for a solution to this problem, Mrs.
                Sanger told how, in 1921, landing in a port in Japan, she was
                greeted by a group of Japanese women who had heard a radio
                broadcast of her’s concerning birth control. These women told
                her they were not interested in most women’s rights movements
                but Mrs. Sanger’s reform was one keenly needed by their country
                women. However the military leaders in Japan, interested in
                building up armies, opposed the presentation of any methods
                limiting population. </q></p>
        <p><q who="SAES">Mrs. Sanger defined birth control as the</q> “conscious
            control of the birth rate by means which prevent the conception of
            life.” <q who="SAES">Thus. life is not destroyed because life is
                never conceived. Conscious control is not a limitation because
                controls are placed on all phases of modern life. For example,
                traffic is controlled but it still comes and goes.</q></p>
        <q who="SAES">
            <p> Mrs. Sanger believes that the control of the birth rate is what
                is lacking throughout the world today.</p>
            <p>Three of the prime aims of the planned parenthood movement were
                given by Mrs. Sanger. To prevent people who have transmissible
                diseases from having children is one of the greatest questions
                in the world. Institutions are full of people who should never
                have been conceived. Feeble-minded, defective people should in
                many cases be sterilized as a protection to society by
                preventing the continued birth of misfits who will become state
                wards. Standards as to health and mental ability are placed on
                immigrants coming into our country, but there are no
                stipulations as to the fitness of the individuals within this
                country who reproduce and help populate the land. </p>
            <p>Another aim of birth control is to let mothers, who have a
                temporary disease such as tuberculosis, recover before another
                pregnancy occurs. One-fourth of the women who die from pregnancy
                during a disease knew they have the disease before becoming
                pregnant. </p>
            <p>The spacing of children, which Mrs. Sanger believes has helped
                the movement more than anything else, was the third aim
                mentioned. Babies should be spaced according to the health of
                the mother, and the number of babies should depend upon the
                earning ability of the father. She quoted from a medical journal
                that stated that spacing resulted in stronger babies and
                healthier mothers. For the young couple entering marriage, birth
                control gives them an opportunity to adjust themselves to
                marriage before starting their family.</p></q>
        <p>
            <q who="SAES">There is</q> “no other organization today so important
            to our children or our children’s future,”<q who="SAES"> Mrs. Sanger
                believes. The movement will</q> "build sounder marriages, better
            health, and a better world; laying the foundation for the greatest
            civilization the world has ever known.” </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
