<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published interview">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-06-24 MM </prepDate>
        <docAuthor><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1959-03-06">6 Mar 1959</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Interview with the Honolulu Bulletin</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421982</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>Honolulu Star Bulletin</title>03/06/59</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>This is an interview Sanger gave to the newspaper</p>
        <index level1="Catholic Church" level2="birth control and"/><index level1="Catholic Church"
            level2="MS on"/><index level1="birth control methods" level2="pill"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Catholic Leaders Called Short-Sighted on Birth Control</head>

        <p>She asserted in an interview in her Reef Hotel penthouse suite that "the <org>Catholic
                Church</org> is the only one against us. All the other churches are definitely in
            favor of our program.</p>
        <p>"The Catholics' reasons are politically, not religiously, motivated.</p>
        <p>"And members of the church are expected to follow blindly.</p>
        <p>"But not all of them do," she asserted and claimed there are "just as many Catholic women
            subscribing to brith control methods as there are women outside the church."</p>
        <p>She noted "mothers--Catholic or otherwise--are all the same. They want to be healthy and
            have healthy children. Fathers, too, are all the same. They want their wives alive and
            healthy."</p>
        <p>She said it is widely used in the U.S. today with "very few side effects. Occasionally I
            have heard of a woman getting a headache from it."</p>
        <p>"Like all contraceptives, the pill is 100 per cent effective if it's used, not forgotten
            on the shelf," she stated.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger, who has been champoining the cause of birth control for over 40 of her
            70-plus years, sees the need for more research in getting an even easier
            contraceptive.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger said her interest in birth control was sparked when as a nurse she was "in
            touch with all the misery unplanned parenthood brought." </p>
        <p>"The problem is most pressing in the Orient" she said, noting that results are "very
            encouraging. The governments take a big interest in the matter. <place>India</place>,
            for instance, has allotted $10 million toward the program."</p>


        <p/>
    </docBody>
</doc>
