<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-06-26 CH transcribe and encode poor photocopy</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1932-01-19">19 Jan 1932</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Speech at Corning, New
                    York</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421906</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Mrs. Sanger Pleads for Sound Mind and
                    Bodies for Every Child</title>, <title type="journal"
                    >Corning Leader</title>, Jan. 20, 1932</bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="CL">Corning Leader</name>
            <name id="WELAL">Welington, Anna Ballard</name>
            <name id="HUGVI">Hugo, Victor</name>
            <name id="INGWI">Inge,William Ralph</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Sanger gave a speech in Corning, N.Y, her
            birthplace. The complete speech was not found and the text below was
            summarized by the press. For an interview Sanger gave the same
            night, see <xref from="421044.xml">Interview with the Corning
                Leader</xref></p><p>The left margin of the first column was
            extremely light and difficult to transcribe.</p><index
            level1="birth control" level2="class-based"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="economic benefits and risks of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="civilization and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="economic benefits and risks of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="population and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="socio-economic benefits of"/>
        <index level1="birth rate" level2="population growth and"/>
        <index level1="Catholic Church" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="eugenics" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="eugenics" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="overpopulation" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="&quot;unfit&quot; to reproduce" level2="descriptions of"/>
        <index level1="&quot;unfit&quot; to reproduce" level2="social burden of"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="health of"/>
        <index level1="women" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Mrs. Sanger Pleads for Sound Mind and Body for Every Child</head>
        <head type="sub">Former Corning Girl, Birth Control Advocate, is Greeted
            by Large Audience at First Address Here; Hour Has Struck for Idea
            She States</head>
        <q who="CL">
            <p>It was a dramatic moment in the life of Mrs. <person
                    reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person> formerly
                Margaret Higgins <gap extent="few words" reason="illegible"/>
                city Tuesday evening at the <org>Baron Steuben Hotel</org> for
                the first time in her life this internationally famous advocate
                of birth control gave a lecture on the project to which she is
                devoting her life in her <place reg="Corning, NY">home
                    town</place> before former schoolmates and friends of her
                    <gap extent="few words" reason="illegible"/> There were over
                300 present, crowding the hotel ballroom to capacity.</p>
            <p>While everyone dreams of leaving to their home town and returning
                some day rich or famous to dazzle friends but seldom do our
                dreams reach such an actual fruition as marked Margaret Higgins
                triumphant return to her own city. Leaving her poor, <gap
                    extent="few words" reason="illegible"/> and unknown, she
                returned on Tuesday not only comfortably welloff insofar as this
                world's <gap extent="few words" reason="illegible"/> are
                concerned, but more importantly, an international figure.
                Sanger, the recipient of enviable <gap extent="few words"
                    reason="illegible"/> and a speaker of extraordinary poise,
                charm and ability. </p></q>
        <p><q who="CL">A slender woman whose clearly defined features are
                crowned by a mass of auburn hair, Mrs. Sanger delivered her
                message in a manner whose forcefulness was inten<gap
                    extent="few words" reason="illegible"/> by her quiet
                calmness. <person reg="Wellington, Anna Ballard">Mrs. <gap
                        extent="few words" reason="illegible"/>
                    Wellington</person>, who was a guest at a tea at Mrs.
                Sanger's <gap extent="few words" reason="illegible"/>this past
                summer and who was impressed by her short talk on this affair,
                introduced the guest graciously, saying</q> "<q who="WELAN">Mrs.
                Sanger needs no introduction in Corning. It is with pleasure
                that I present her at this time</q>." </p>
        <p><q who="CL">Thanking Mrs. Wellington for her kindness and courage in
                arranging for the meeting, Mrs. Sanger said </q>"I have always
            had the hope that someone or some group woudl want me to come back
            to tell of the work I have been doing for the past 17 years. It was
                <person reg="Hugo, Victor">Victor Hugo</person> who said '<q
                who="HUGVI">There is no force in the world so great as that of
                an idea whose hour has struck.</q>' The hour of birth control
            has struck. No other subject of equal importance had been left so
            long in obscurity and in the past few years no other subject has
            shown such a leap, not only natioally, but internationally. </p>
        <p>"Officials seemed to think it should not be discussed by a group of
            intelligent adults. Ten years ago had I endeavored to talk here on
            that subject I do not doubt but that I would have been met at the
            door by a group of policemen. <person reg="Shaw, George Bernard"
                >George Bernard Shaw </person>says it is the most brilliant idea
            of the century."</p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger quoted <person reg="Wells, H. G.">H. G. Wells</person>,
            who favors birth control measures and <person
                reg="Inge, William Ralph">Dean Inge</person>, the gloomy dean,
            who told the <org reg="Lambeth Conference">bishops conference at
                Lambeth</org> that the '<q who="INGWI">subject has arrived and
                come to stay. The thing for church to do is not to fight back
                but to try to direct it so the force may become a constructive
                good.</q>'"</p>
        <p>To me this is a signal of a new social awakenening. Birth control and
            the conscious control of the human race by means that prevent a
            destruction of human life. It is prevention: you do not destroy.
            There is no more interference with <gap extent="few words"
                reason="illegible"/> as if you remain single. Control doesn't
            mean you have to limit the size of your family. You control your
            furnace adjusting it to the temperature of the weather but that
            doesn't mean you have to diminish the fire. So it is in controlling
            the number of your children. You have the number you want.</p>
        <p>There are three considerations that should enter into the case.
            First, the mother's health should be considered. She should not have
            children in a way that is going to ruin her health. Second, the
            father's earning capacity must be considered. Statistics show that
            as the father's earning capacity goes down, the infant mortality
            rate increases. Third, the standard of living you wish to maintain
            should be taken into consideration.</p>
        <p>"Birth control gives you the conscious control of the birth rate.
            Children are born because their parents want them, not because they
            are accidents or the casual consequence of reckless abandon. Whey
            you hear people say '<q who="UNK">why control the birth rate. What
                we need is the equal distribution of the necessities of
                life.'</q> There has always been control of the population and there are
            only two ways of doing this: either by increasing the death rate or
            decreasing the birth rate. Whether we like it or not we will not
            control the population through increased death rates. Civilization
            has progressed beyond this.</p>
        <p>Nature has been the most ruthless advocate of birth control. Nature
            has thrust to the wall the old, the weak, the maimed, the mentally
            deficient until she has perfected her type. Now, Christianity, the
            feeling that we are our brother's keeper, will no longer allow these
            people to suffer and die. Civilization thrusts out its hand to the
            physically and mentally deficient, the sick, the aged. We erect
            palatial palaces and keep them alive and enact laws which makes them
            mulitiply <gap extent="few words" reason="illegible"/> their type
            until the defectives are now breeding three time as fast as normal
            mothers. Some years ago out of the population of 165 millions only
            20 millions were classed as intellectuals.</p>
        <p>"Biological and psychological tests showed that 85 millions had minds
            of juveniles under 14 years of age; 45 millions had inferior mental
            growh; 25 millions were very mediocre; and 15 millions were
            feeble-minded.</p>
        <p>"Our institutions are filled and overcrowded and we havent't
            institutions enough to keep them all. One-half is taking care of the
            other half who should never have been born. They do nothing but
            clutter up society and make a complicated life for us all.</p>
        <p>"Legislation has failed to wipe out this great evil, so being
            generous-hearted the American people have tried to eliminate
            suffering. As a result over 15 billion dollars is spent caring for
            diseased defectives and a great deal more than that on crime every
            year.</p>
        <p>"The money for this comes out of your pockets. There are two classes
            of people; I will not call them rich and poor. There is the class
            with controlled birth rate and the class which does not have
            controlled birth rate. You will see in every city of the earth, with
            the exception of the <place reg="Asia">Orient</place>, one group
            which has small familes. The parents have given consideration to the
            monther's health. They have brought into the world few children but
            the great majority live to full maturity. Their children stay
            longest in school and eventually fill the best positions in life.
            Out of this group the good things in life have come, social service,
            child development, the new studies of mankind to help civilization
            and to carry on the torch of learning.</p>
        <p>"You hear the cry that the rich do not have enough children. We can
            do nothing about it until you take the other group off the backs of
            the rich; until you eliminate the situation where women have to
            bring into the world year after year like a grinding machine
            regardless of whether there's a place for them or not. The result is
            slums, over-crowding, high maternal and infant mortaility rate,
            child labor, illness, ignorance, nearly every social problem. And
            you'll never get rid of these results unless you strike at its
            roots; until you give these mothers safe harmless knowledge whereby
            they may control the powers of fertility."</p>
        <p><q who="CL">Mrs. Sanger then told of some of her experiences as a
                nurse in <place reg="New York, NY">New York City</place>. She
                told of the mothers in the slum districts, some of them holding
                what she termed a</q> "three-man job," <q who="CL">working for
                the family sewing, cooking, mending, scrubbing, working either
                nights or in the daytime to bring in money to eke out the
                father's pay, and at the same time preparing to bring a child
                into the world. She described the hopeless poverty and the
                ill-health to which the new-born infant fell heir, the joy of
                the mother when the baby died within a few moments after birth,
                the anxious queries of the mothers asking what they could do to
                prevent a reoccurance of of conception, the lack of scientific
                knowledge, the abundance of back-fence gossip, attempts to
                prevent birth after pregnancy, cases of blood-poisoning,
                eventual deaths of mother or possibly the birth of the baby with
                weak heart or kidneys as a result and finally the distribution
                of the many children to orphanages.</q></p>
        <p>"As a result of these conditions we head the list with the largest
            number of mothers who die needlessly in childbirth. Why? I find
            first the women who have tuberculosis. Four out of every seven
            mothers who die in childbirth have that disease. It is legal to take
            such a woman to a hospital and interrupt pregnancy. Then she is
            returned home to face the same situation again. Poverty and neglect
            are the next causes.</p>
        <p>"There are three essential factors in safe-guarding maternal cases.
            First, as the father's wage goes up, more children live; as it goes
            down, fewer children live. Second, if the children are spaced with
            three or four years between each birth, the mother has an
            opportunity to regain more vitality and the children are more apt to
            live. Third, the place in the family where a child comes determines
            to a certain extent his chance of living. The second child has a
            better chance to live than the fifth; the fifth than the seventh;
            the seventh than the 12th. Sixty per cent of all 12th children die. </p>
        <p>"Now what kind of a world have we? Why should we needlessly bring the
            12th child into the world to die? Yet poor mothers are doomed to one
            or two things. Either they resign themselves to the situation or
            interrupt pregnancy."</p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger said that she has received over a million letters from
            mothers which she summarized as follows: A mother wrote that she was
            about to have her 10th child. Several had died. She didn't want to
            know how to have this child safely. She wanted to know how not to
            have the 11th child.</p>
        <p>"We rescue babies at a terrific cost during the first year. Then we
            begin to carry them on to the fifth year; and we carry them and
            carry them through public schools with lunches and dental clinics
            and special classes until they are ready to work at 14 or 15 and
            then they flock to our factory gates and begin to compete with their
            fathers."</p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger described the cruelty of child labor, pointing to the
            beet fields of <place>Colorado</place> as an example, where infants
            three years old have had to help with the work. The parents are
            unable to earn sufficient to support themselves, but they have been
            allowed to have 11 children in 13 years.</p>
        <p>"In my estimation it is one of the most cruel things in the world to
            allow a child to be born into conditions where there is no
            possiblilty of being allowed to develop. Born in misery with
            diseased bodies and doomed to stay in that condition."</p>
        <p>"You have to learn to be anything from a doctor to a lawyer to a
            cook--except a parent. You may have all the children you want
            regardless of whether they are mentally deficient and if you have
            enough of them you may send a picture of your family to the
            president and he'll send you a medal."</p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger pled for the same consideration for the unborn child that
            is given the American traveler abroad--a passport for babies,
            guaranteeing for every child born in <place reg="United States"
                >America</place> a sound mind and sound body.</p>
        <p>She described the awakening of America to the fact that it must have
            a qualitative population among its immigrants and its laws to
            exclude idiots, morons, mentally deficient, criminals, physically
            deficients.</p>
        <p>"Why do we refuse to be the dumping ground for <place>Europe</place>
            and then let these people increase on the inside?"</p>
        <q who="CL">
            <p>Mrs. Sanger described the two danger spots of the world, created
                by this refusal to allow immigrants. <place>Japan</place> with
                its 65 million people living in a mountainous country about the
                size of <place>California</place> with few natural resources she
                stated was one. This country's birth rate has increased so that
                the country has had to do what the chicken does inside the
                egg--burst its shell. Japan is in <place>Manchuria</place> and
                she's there to stay."</p>
            <p>Italy is the second such country, she said. She predicted that
                with its rapidly increasing birth rate <place>Italy</place> will
                some day be forced to burst and will reach over and take a
                section of its neighbor <place>France</place>. </p>
            <p>Mrs. Sanger said that are three method of birth control:
                continence, which is approved by the <org>Roman Catholic
                    Church</org>; sterilization and mechanical or chemical means
                of contraception.</p>
            <p>She urged that the medical profession take over the burden of the
                third method of birth control and stated that if "the medical
                profession had done its duty all the agitation about birth
                control wouldn't be necessary."</p>
            <p>She gave seven reasons for birth control as follows: 1. any man
                or woman with a transmissable disease should not have children;
                2. any woman having a disease like tuberculosis by which
                pregnancy would endanger her life should not have children until
                the disease is cured; 3. parents should have no more children if
                those they already have are sub-normal; 4. children should be
                properly spaced for the sake of the mother's health and also in
                consideration of the father's income; 5. young people marrying
                during adolesence should not have children until they become
                adults; 6. people should not have children they are unable to
                support, those unable to support two children 10 years ago, now
                have 12 in some cases; 7. people should make more of marriage,
                should consider it as something greater than a mere means of
                propagating the race.</p>
            <p>Concerning the seventh reason for birth control, Mrs. Sanger said
                she belived marriage to be the greatest school for soul
                development; that it had something fundamentally strengthening
                to offer the two adults who participating in it; that young
                people should work together, play together, and learn to know
                and love each other with firmer, stronger ties than existed
                during courtship and honeymoon before they become parents of
                children. She advocated a marriage life of two years before the
                advent of children.</p></q>
        <p>"I want the fear of pregnancy eliminated; I want this increased
            child-bearing of deficient children stopped; I want children to be
            conceived in love and I want young people to look upon their bodies
            as holy temples which can and should be used intelligently for the
            purpose of creaing other life." </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
