<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-04-15 JK initial tag</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1936-04-18">18 Apr 1936</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Tucson Press
                Statement.</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421926</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Mrs. Sanger to Discuss
                    Clinic</title><title type="journal">Arizona Daily
                    Star</title>, Apr. 18, 1936.</bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="ADS">Arizona Daily Star</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger</person> spoke
        to the press in advance of her Speech on Apr. 19, 1936 at the <org
            reg="Young Women's Catholic Association">YWCA </org>on behalf of the
                <org><place reg="Tucson, AZ">Tucson </place>Mothers Health
            Clinic</org>. That speech has not been found. <index
            level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="MS on"/><index
            level1="birth control movement" level2="MS on"/><index
            level1="birth control laws and legislation"
            level2="Postal Code and Regulations"/><index level1="conferences"
            level2="All India Women's Conference" level3="1935-36 (10th)"
            /><index level1="birth control"
            level2="distribution of information about"/><index
            level1="birth control" level2="access to"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Mrs. Sanger to Discuss Clinic</head>

        <p>
            <q who="ADS">Although birth control clinics, once the object of
                indignant police raids, have multiplied with public approval
                until there are now 235 in the <place>United States</place>,
                Margaret Sanger, founder of the modern American movement, won’t
                be happy until congress has exempted nearly 7000 hospitals and
                clinics</q> “from the punishments of the federal law,” <q
                who="ADS">she said today. </q></p>
        <q who="ADS"><p>The immediate object of birth control forces is to have
                the bill now in the hands of the senate judiciary committee, of
                which <place>Arizona</place>’s <person reg="Ashurst, Henry F."
                    >Senator Ashurst</person> is chairman, reported out for open
                debate on the floor of congress, Mrs. Sanger said. </p><p>The
                bill would permit shipment by <org
                    reg="United States Postal Service"><place>U.S.</place>
                    mail</org> and common carriers of birth control information
                and supplies to physicians, hospitals and clinics in states
                where laws permit. </p></q>
        <p>“We have never wanted to go into politics,” <q who="ADS">Mrs. Sanger
                said yesterday,</q> “but with the lives of countless mothers and
            the happiness of countless families at stake, it looks as if we may
            be forced to. At present, we are urging friends of our movement to
            press their representatives for action, and to determine the
            attitude of candidates before election day.”</p>
        <p> “During the present period in our history, it is possible to
            illustrate vividly that families least-fitted economically to have
            large families are the ones most ignorant of control methods,” <q
                who="ADS">Mrs. Sanger said quoting statistics compiled by the
                    <org>Milbank foundation</org> which show the birth rate
                among unemployed and relief work families is 65 per cent higher
                than for the remaining of the population.</q></p>
        <p><q who="ADS"> When the government must support these unlimited
                families through expenditure of billions of dollars,</q> “we are
            beginning to substitute the benevolence of the state for the
            responsibility of parents, a tendency dangerous to our form of
            government,” <q who="ADS">Mrs. Sanger said.</q></p>
        <q who="ADS"><p> The <org>All India Women’s conference</org>, which she
                addressed, voted 85 to 24 in favor of establishing clinics in
                the country,</p></q>
        <p>“I found these women outspoken, fearless in acknowledging issues as
            they are possessed of the will and courage to face the consequences
            when principles are at stake,” <q who="ADS">Mrs. Sanger said.</q>
        </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
