<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type=" Published speech ">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-04-02 JK initial tag</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1916-04-01 ">01 Apr 1916</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Statement Before United States
                    Speaking Tour</supplied>t</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421933</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">"Birth Control Advocate is on Way to
                    Chicago: Will Explain Doctrine"</title><title type="journal"
                    >The Day Book</title> Apr. 1,1916, p. 8.</bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="TDB">The Day Book</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger </person>gave
        this statement in <place reg="New York, NY">New York</place>, before
        traveling to <place reg="Chicago, IL">Chicago</place>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="in Chicago"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/><index
            level1="birth control movement" level2="international"/><index
            level1="birth control movement"/><index
            level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="New York "
            /><index level1="birth control clinics and leagues"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>BIRTH CONTROL ADVOCATE IS ON WAY TO CHICAGO-WILL EXPLAIN
            DOCTRINE</head>

        <dateline>
            <date value="/----/-04-01"/>April 1, <place>New
            York</place></dateline>
        <p><q who="TDB">Freed of the charge, in Uncle Sam’s federal indictment,
                that she sent vile and obscene matter through the mails in her
                birth control propaganda magazine, “<title type="journal">The
                    Woman Rebel</title>,” Mrs. Sanger left here today to visit
                and organize birth control societies among the women of all the
                larger cities in the <place>United States</place>.</q></p>
        <p><q who="TDB">Mrs. Sanger is on her way now to Chicago, where she will
                conduct meetings of women, make speeches about birth control and
                organize a society of women to perpetuate birth control
                propaganda after she has gone on to other places. Mrs. Sanger
                will travel west to the coast cities and then east again by
                another route. </q></p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger hopes, by stirring up the interest of American wives and
            mothers, to make their influence cause the repeal of state and
            federal laws prohibiting the dissemination of birth control
            information.</p>
        <p><q who="TDB"> In cities where there are no restrictions of this kind
                Mrs. Sanger hopes to establish clinics, similar to birth control
                clinics in European cities, where women of the working districts
                can apply for instruction in birth control. In addition to
                nurses who can instruct in birth control, these clinics will
                have a staff that will teach the care of infants.</q></p>
        <p><q who="TDB"> Mrs. Sanger said before she departed today that no
                legislative power in the world can keep the women of America
                from learning and practicing birth control. </q></p>
        <p>“Because,” she added, “it is the logical and sensible and humane
            thing to do, law or no law.</p>
        <p> “No woman should be compelled to bring a baby into the world unless
            she is physically fitted to properly endow the child with a good
            brain and body; and unless she is blessed with the resources to rear
            and educate the child and give it a fair chance to make its way in
            the world.</p>
        <p> “That is what birth control knowledge is for; to show women under
            what conditions it is best for them to bear children.</p>
        <p> “Birth control does not necessarily make for either larger or
            smaller families; it simply insures, through the mother’s knowledge,
            a square deal and a fair chance for whatever children are born.</p>
        <p> “In <place>Europe</place>, birth control is sanctioned by the
            governments. </p>
        <p>“In the United States it is blindly condemned by law; laws that are
            lauded by certain influential and prominent citizens who secretly
            practice birth control while publicly denouncing it.”</p>
        <p><q who="TDB"> Mrs. Sanger was indicted in her United States court
                here in January for alleged indecent birth control propaganda
                statements in her magazine. New York society women, led by such
                well known individuals as Miss <person reg="LaFollette, Lola"
                    >Lola LaFollette</person> and others, accompanied Mrs.
                Sanger to court when she went to plead to the indictment; then
                afterward caused the case to be given wide publicity. </q></p>
        <p><q who="TDB">The government dismissed the indictment against Mrs.
                Sanger before the case came to trial.</q></p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
