<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">

    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-03-12 JK initial tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-14 CH proof tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-03-26>JK correct tags</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docAuthor>John Hutchinson</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1938-10-20">20 Oct 1938</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Speech to the Memphis Birth Control
                    Committee</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421908</idno>
        <sourceDesc>

            <bibl><title type="article">Birth Control Seen As Benefit To Nation
                    </title><title type="journal">Memphis Commerical
                    Appeal</title> Oct. 21, 1938</bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="MCA">Memphis Commerical Appeal</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger </person>spoke
        at The <place reg="Memphis, TN">Memphis</place>
        <org>Fairgrounds Casino</org>, a meeting sponsored by the <org>Memphis
            Birth Control Committee</org>, attended by an estimated 900 people.
        Other speakers were Dr. <person reg="Pride, William T.">W. T.
            Pride</person>, Dr. <person reg="Loaring-Clark, Alfred">Alfred
            Loaring-Clark</person>, and Dr. <person reg="Sibley, Josiah">Josiah
            Sibley</person>. For notses for this speech that includes data on
            "<title type="article">Blighted Areas of City in Tenn</title>.," see
        MSM S71:1043. <index level1="&quot;unfit&quot; to reproduce"
            level2="MS on"/><index level1="birth control"
            level2="socio-economic benefits of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="suppression of"/><index
            level1="birth control" level2="definitions of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"
            /><index level1="society" level2="responsibility and"/>
        <index level1="&quot;unfit&quot; to reproduce" level2="social burden of"
        /></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>BIRTH CONTROL SEEN AS BENEFIT TO NATION</head>
        <head type="sub">Large Crowd Hears Mrs. Sanger at Casino</head>
        <head type="sub">Seven Reasons Outlined</head>
        <head type="sub">Views Birth Regulation as Way to Raise Intellectual
            Level of Nation-Memphians Speak on Programs </head>
        <byline>By <person reg="Hutchison, John">John
            Hutchison</person></byline>
        <p>“We are spending billions annually because of slums, crime and
            truancy,” she said, “But we are not attacking the fundamental
            problem. Crime alone costs every person in the <place>United
                States</place> $125 a year.” <q who="MCA">Most of the criminals
                come from “blighted areas” where parents are unable to limit
                their families to a size they can care for, she declared.</q>
        </p>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Knowledge Should Be Spread </head>
            <q who="MCA">
                <p> Dissemination of birth control knowledge by public health
                    agencies, reaching poor families, is a necessary
                    governmental function, she said. Normal persons whose
                    offspring would be a valuable asset to the <place
                        reg="United States">Nation</place> are unable to rear
                    families because they must bear the burden of sustaining
                    millions of poor, feeble-minded and unfit children of
                    parents who should practice birth control, she
                asserted.</p></q>
            <p> “The normal family cannot rear children because it must pay for
                this vast army by taxation,” she said. “If mothers were not
                enslaved by child-bearing and fathers were not burdened with
                supporting large families, the general level of intellect would
                rise, taking a burden off the entire group.”</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Definition Given </head>
            <q who="MCA"><p> Mrs. Sanger’s address opened with a definition of
                    birth control as the conscious control of the birth rate by
                    prevention of, not interference with, conception. She said
                    there was no intent to interfere with or destroy life.
                </p></q>
            <p>“When anyone says birth control is murder he shows colossal
                ignorance of biology,” she said. “Birth control does not allow
                life to begin. There is no moral difference between birth
                control and continence in that respect.”</p>
            <q who="MCA">
                <p>Everywhere today there is control, she pointed out, in
                    traffic, currency, agriculture. Man differs from the animal
                    in that he is conscious of actions and consequences and man
                    will begin a new civilization when he learns to apply that
                    consciousness to reproduction. </p></q>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Reasons Outlined</head>
            <q who="MCA"><p>The slight, red-haired woman who has given 25 years
                    of her life to her cause, outlined seven reasons for
                    contraception: <list>
                        <item>1. The man or woman capable of transmitting a
                            mental disease must practice birth control or be
                            sterilized. She said if she were dictator she would
                            offer an old-age pension to any mentally unfit
                            person who would submit to sterilization. </item>
                        <item> 2. A temporary disease in a woman may be so
                            disturbed by child birth that pregnancy causes her
                            death. </item>
                        <item> 3. Normal parents sometimes give birth to
                            abnormal children.</item>
                        <item> 4. Every woman should have the right to “space”
                            her babies three or four years apart, for her own
                            health and that of children. </item>
                        <item> 5. Although early marriage is desirable, children
                            should be postponed by young parents until the
                            parents have outgrown adolescence. </item>
                        <item> 6. Parents shouldn’t have children they can’t
                            support. They shouldn’t have children who will have
                            no other field of employment but the unskilled work,
                            now overcrowded. </item>
                        <item> 7. Proper regulation of family size will raise
                            the intellectual level of the Nation, because in the
                            small family there is opportunity for parents to
                            train their children, and to have time to improve
                            themselves.</item>
                    </list></p></q>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
