<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "file:/S:/TRANSCRIPTIONS/XML%20Drafts/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>20143/07/08 MM</prepDate>
        <docAuthor><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret
            Sanger</person></docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1946-05-15">15 May 1946</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Dinner Speech to the <org><place>Arkansas</place>
                    Eugenics Association</org></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421995</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>"<title type="article">Birth Control Seen As Way To World
                    Peace</title>" <title type="newspaper">Arkansas
                    Gazette</title>5/16/46</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">Sanger gave a speech at a dinner at the Hotel
        Frederica in <place reg="Little rock, AK">Little Rock</place>. <index
            level1="birth control" level2="international"/><index level1="war"
            level2="marriage and"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Birth Control Seen as Way To Peace</head>
        <p>There will never be world peace until birth control is practiced on a
            world-wide basis, Mrs. Margaret Sanger of <place reg="New York, NY"
                >New York city</place>, honorary chairman of the <org>Planned
                Parenthood Federation</org>, said here yesreday. She stopped in
            Little Rock to check on the birth control clinic here and to renew
            acquaintances with <person reg="Cornish, Hilda">Mrs. Ed
                Cornish</person>, 4816 Country Club boulevard. </p>
        <p>Birth control practices need to be taught in <place>Germany</place>
            and <place>Japan </place>to prevent the two countries from
            continuing to be the spawning grounds of wars, Mrs. Sanger said.
            "Women of Japan have requested permission from <person
                reg="MacArthur, Douglas">General MacArthur</person> for me to
            come there and install birth control centers," she said.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Sanger also is director of the world's largest birth control
            research clinic located in New York city.</p>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Lists Three Objectives</head>
            <p>She said the federation has a three-fold purpose: To teach
                contraceptive practices, to aid sterility cases and to conduct
                marriage counselling services. Aiding sterility cases is a new
                program of the federation, Mrs. Sanger said.</p>
            <p>"Our organization is not opposed to people having children," she
                explained. "What we want to do is to teach family spacing," she
                said. Children should be spaced at least two to three years
                apart to give the mother a chance to rear the child and to give
                her a chance to recover completely from the previous birth."</p>
            <p>Marriage counseling service is given to aid men returning from
                the war who find that home is not what it used to be, she said.,
                "We try to prevent them from winding up in a divorce court by
                aiding in their readjustment," she said. "We aid them not by
                psychiatry but by applying plain common sense."</p>
            <p>She became interested in birth control problems in 1916 and
                helped to organize the national federation that now has 630
                chapters. Mrs. Sanger was last in Little Rock in 1940 and spoke
                at a meeting here in 1939. She and Mrs. Cornish have been
                friends since their sons attended Yale University together. Mrs.
                Cornish has been affiliated with the federation since 1931 and
                now is chairman of the state organization.</p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
