<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/03/04 VS initial tagging</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/03/13 CH proof tags</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/03/14 VS correct tags</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docAuthor>Marcet Haldman-Julius</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1931-05-23">23 May 1931</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Impressions of Margaret Sanger and Her Talks on Birth Control</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421924</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journals">The American Freeman</title></bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <name id="HUGVI">Hugo, Victor</name>
            <name id="HALMA">Haldeman-Julius, Marcet</name>
            <name id="ALLSO">All Soul's Unitarian Church</name>
            <name id="HARWA">Harding, Warren G.</name>
            <name id="SACSA">Sachs, Sadie</name>
            <name id="LAWS">Laws Concerning Birth Control in United States</name>
            <name id="SANWI">Sanger, William</name>
            <name id="STOMA">Stopes, Marie</name>
            <name id="SULMA">Sullivan, Mary</name>
            <name id="CONHA">Content, Harold A.</name>
            <name id="CLAHE">Clayton, Henry DeLamar</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">This article summerizes Sanger's talks in Kansas City during February
        1931, her life, and her meetings with <person reg="Haldeman-Julius, Marcel">Marcel
            Haldeman-Julius</person>. <index level1="abortion" level2="laws and legislation"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="definitions of"/>
        <index level1="birth control methods" level2="efficacy of"/>
        <index level1="Conneticut" level2="birth control" level3="laws and legislation"/>a <index
            level1="Europe" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control"/>
        <index level1="race suicide"/>
        <index level1="Sadie, Sadie (story)"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="background of"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="descriptions of"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, William" level2="arrest, trial and imprisonment"/>
        <index level1="sex education"/>
        <index level1="United States" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Woman Rebel" level2="suppression of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Impressions of <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person> and Her Talks
            on Birth Control</head>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"><place reg="Kansas City, MO">Kansas City</place>’s Liberal Center –
                Where Mrs. Sanger Spoke</head>
            <q who="HALMA"><p> The sixth of February, 1931, marked the beginning of a new epoch for
                    the women in Kansas City. On that day, in <org>All Souls’ Unitarian
                    Church</org>, which many of its members and friends prefer to call The Liberal
                    Center, Margaret Sanger, avoiding all ambiguity, gave a plain, straightforward
                    talk on the technique of contraception.</p></q>
            <p><supplied resp="MSPP">Three paragraphs on the history of the Liberal Center have been
                    omitted.</supplied></p>
            <q who="HALMA"><p> When Margaret Sanger spoke for the <org>University Extension
                        Center</org> course, in Dr. <person reg="Jenkins, Burris">Burris
                        Jenkins</person>’ church, she spoke on the wider aspects of Birth Control in
                    a lecture entitled “<title type="lecture">The Problem of Population</title>,”
                    but it is indicative of the Liberal Center’s forthright stand on all questions
                    that she was asked to get right down to cases and talk there on practical
                    methods of contraception. And this is precisely what she did.</p></q>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Margaret Sanger</head>
            <q who="HALMA"><p> When I entered Margaret Sanger’s sitting room at the <org
                        reg="Muehlebach Hotel">Muehlbach Hotel</org> in Kansas City, there arose
                    from the couch a shimmering, gracious woman whose red-gold hair was shot with
                    grey and whose eyes made me wonder at once whether or not she was Irish. They
                    made me think of deep pools dappled with sunlight, for sadness and wisdom seemed
                    to lie beneath the interest and happiness of the moment.</p>
                <p> “This woman has been through a lot, but her life has fallen into pleasant ways,”
                    I thought to myself as we shook hands.</p>
                <p> The contact of her palm against mine told me more: she was a warm cordial
                    approachable person. Even before she had put on her smart (oh very, very smart)
                    green velvet turban-like hat that matched the green velvet jacket which, in its
                    turn, exactly matched the color of the large green ring she wore, and slipped
                    into a beautiful mink coat, I knew that I liked her and that in the truest sense
                    we should be able to talk with each other.</p>
                <p> “She loves pretty things,” was my mental comment, which I corroborated later
                    when I went into her bedroom to take off my wraps. The frou-frous and the dainty
                    appointments on her dressing table all told me in unmistakable language that she
                    was a decidedly dainty, fastidious woman. She has a trim figure, too! Of medium
                    height, her slenderness is well rounded. She looks what she is – the swanky,
                    youthful mother of two grown sons. (<person reg="Sanger, Stuart">One of
                        them</person> graduated last year from <org reg="Yale University"
                    >Yale</org>, <person reg="Sanger, Grant">the other</person> finished this year
                    at <org reg="Princeton University">Princeton</org>) Although a full lifetime of
                    achievement lies behind her, Margaret Sanger is still only in her forties and
                    can look forward to thirty or more years of continued effort.</p>
                <p> There were six of us at dinner: Mr. and Mrs. Birkhead, <person
                        reg="Burkhart, Dr.">Dr.</person> and <person reg="Burkhart, Mrs.">Mrs.
                        Burkhart</person> (active members of the Liberal Center), Margaret Sanger
                    and myself. Before we had reached dessert I was aware that Mrs. Sanger was by
                    temperament and conviction a thorough-going liberal. She is not, as are some of
                    the most valiant fighters for one or another form of freedom, interested only in
                    the ends she herself hopes to achieve. All injustice touches her on the quick.
                    The talk among us flowed heart-warming and mind-stimulating. By the time we were
                    back in Mrs. Sanger’s sitting room I had become more and more curious to know
                    just how she had started this (for so long!) single-handed fight to strike off
                    the chains of ignorance which still make life a nightmare for many married women
                    whose lives, otherwise, would be happy.</p>
                <p> The Birkheads and the Burkharts were eager to hear too and although Margaret
                    Sanger is the sort of woman who is far readier to talk about her plans for
                    future legislation and her ideas than about herself, she is very gracious and,
                    gradually, she unfolded the story of her brave and often bitter struggle. It is
                    a struggle that has ended in victory to the extent that she has established the
                        <org reg="Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau">New York Birth Control
                        Clinic</org> which has given contraceptive information to more than twenty
                    thousand women, practical contraceptive instruction to over one thousand regular
                    M. D.’s, and has served as a beacon light to other communities so that now there
                    are over fifty clinics in the country. (There should be at least one in every
                    county seat.) But she is still in the thick of the battle, for the <name
                        reg="United States Criminal Code, Section 2117">Penal Code</name> of the
                    Federal Statutes still forbids the sending of contraceptive articles through the
                    mail, by express, or by any common carrier.</p>
                <p> For the article which is to be purchased now by any college boy at practically
                    any drug store is not primarily for the use of contraception. When this end is
                    effected it is merely a fortunate side issue. (Nor is the article very effective
                    or satisfactory for this purpose, its failure running to something like 61
                    percent of carefully tabulated cases in which it was relied upon.)</p>
                <p> The article is to protect the noble male of the country from contracting disease
                    in his amatory adventures. A lot the <org>United States government</org> or the
                    State Legislature care whether or not as the result of these adventures, a woman
                    finds herself with child. If she does, that is just her hard luck. But then we
                    can no longer blame the men who have placed the law against contraceptive
                    information on the statute books since, now that women have an equal voice in
                    the government, they, themselves, do practically nothing to have these
                    outrageous laws erased. If they are ever erased and this country can stand on a
                    par with other civilized countries, such as <place reg="Netherlands"
                        >Holland</place>, <place>England</place>, and <place>France</place> – naming
                    only three – it will be because, for the sake of other women and their unborn
                    children, Mrs. Sanger has been willing to submit to arrest, to stand trial, to
                    spend days in jail and even to endure a year’s exile from her family. Not that
                    she thinks of herself as heroic. On the contrary, she quotes modestly enough the
                    saying “<q who="HUGVI">There is no force so great as an idea when its hour has
                        struck.</q>”</p></q>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">A Social Conscience and Its Result</head>
            <q who="HALMA"><p> Margaret Sanger, who was the seventh of a family of eleven children,
                    grew to womanhood in an atmosphere of liberal views and tolerance for <person
                        reg="Higgins, Michael Hennessey">her father</person> was an ardent admirer
                    of the great single taxer, <person reg="George, Henry">Henry George</person>,
                    and the great free thinker, <person reg="Ingersoll, Bob">Bob Ingersoll</person>.
                    She became a trained nurse, married a <person reg="Sanger, William">young
                        artist</person> and soon had three children: two sons and <person
                        reg="Sanger, Peggy">a daughter</person>. Because money was none too
                    plentiful in the little family, Mrs. Sanger continued her nursing and she might
                    have gone straight on with it had she not, logically enough after her
                    up-bringing, joined the <org>Socialist Party</org>. For a time she was one of
                    its women organizers.</p>
                <p> Then, quite by chance, she was asked to be one of the three to bring down to
                        <place reg="New York, NY">New York</place> some of the destitute children of
                    the <place reg="Lawrence, MA">Lawrence, Massachusetts</place>, textile strikers.
                    Her helpers were two Italian Socialists. Imagine it – three people to handle
                    more than two hundred, cold, hungry, excited children! Almost automatically,
                    because her training as a nurse had taught her to keep reference sheets,
                    Margaret Sanger began to keep data on her little charges. This one, she noted
                    down, had no underwear; that one had no shoes. As she found how desperate their
                    need was, her pen scribbled faster, her notes took on more point. She would see
                    to it, she resolved, that these facts reached the ears of the people sympathetic
                    to the strikers.</p>
                <p> When she arrived safely in New York with her brood, a large group of Italians
                    were there to meet them. Everyone was singing the “International” hymn. Here
                    were the workers’ children! In a delirium of enthusiasm the Italians tossed the
                    youngsters to their shoulders and, still singing, strode off with them.</p></q>
            <p>
                <q who="HALMA">Later there was an orderly hearing at <place reg="Washington, D.C."
                        >Washington</place>. </q>(“<person reg="Gompers, Samuel">Sammy
                    Gompers</person> was there,” <q who="HALMA">she said</q>, “shaking with rage.”)
                    <q who="HALMA">Mrs. Sanger had come at the request of the late <person
                        reg="Berger, Victor L.">Victor L. Berger</person>, who explained to the
                    committee that she had helped bring down the children from Lawrence.</q></p>
            <p> “<q who="HARWA">Tell us something about this</q>,” <q who="HALMA">commanded <person
                        reg="Harding, Warren G.">Warren G. Harding</person>, then only a Senator
                    from <place>Ohio</place>, as deeply as intended.</q></p>
            <q who="HALMA"><p> And Margaret Sanger told. She informed the committee that out of 248
                    children whose fathers worked in the wooden mills, 238 of the children had no
                    underwear at all and only four had overcoats.</p></q>
            <p> “It was,” <q who="HALMA">she said to me,</q> “As if I had thrown a bomb, for
                Schedule K had just gone through putting a tax on wool.”</p>
            <q who="HALMA"><p> But the words which began to reverberate in her ears were the ever
                    recurrent, “Why <emph rend="italics">do</emph> people have so many children when
                    they can’t clothe them? <emph rend="italics">Why</emph> do people have so many
                    children when they can’t feed them? <emph rend="italics">Why do people have so
                        many children?</emph>”</p>
                <p> Meanwhile there was a general attitude of “Wait – just wait!”</p>
                <p> “Wait – just wait,” said the Socialists of the country. “Just wait until we come
                    into power.” (This, if I remember correctly, was in 1912.)</p>
                <p> Meantime Margaret Sanger’s work took her often to New York’s east side and still
                    that refrain, slightly changed, rang through her heart: “Why <emph
                        rend="italics">must</emph> people have so many children? When they can’t
                    take care of them? When they can’t take care of them? When they don’t want them?
                    Why? Why?”</p></q>
            <p>
                <q who="HALMA">For often and often when the uninvited, unwanted babies were born
                    into Margaret Sanger’s hands from the rebellious and bitter mothers, there was
                    no clothes for these bits of humanity; there was not even any place in which to
                    lay them. So Margaret Sanger would wrap the forlorn little boy or girl in the
                    tatters of a blanket and lay it in a soap-box, hastily requisitioned for this
                    purpose. Perhaps after a few minutes of attention to the mother, still suffering
                    with after-pains, Mrs. Sanger would step to look at the new baby and find that
                    it had quietly stopped breathing. Told, the mother, already frantic with trying
                    to feed and keep from nakedness the children she had grown to love, would
                    murmur,</q> “<q who="UNK">Oh, thank <name type="deity">God</name>!</q>”</p>
            <q who="HALMA"><p> Margaret Sanger thought of these things as only a sensitive person,
                    herself a woman and a mother, would; as only a person could who had seen with
                    her own eyes the stark privations into which the children were born, and heard
                    with her own ears the birth moans of the mothers martyred by ignorance.</p>
                <p> And then, perhaps, she would be invited to assist at a new arrival in one of the
                    many parts of New York where a new baby sends its next of kin into a little orgy
                    of celebration; where the telegram announcing the baby’s advent is the awaited
                    signal for the immediate family to become warm with self-congratulations and to
                    pass the drinks. For if there is nothing, nothing so tragic in all its
                    implications as the birth of an unwanted “too many” child, there is nothing so
                    joyous, so inducive of sweet, overwhelming happiness, as the arrival of one who
                    is wanted and will be cherished.</p>
                <p> Margaret Sanger has the gift of understanding. (I was correct in my guess that
                    she is Irish.) An April woman, smiles and tears crowd close together in her
                    heart. She thought. She pondered. She rejoiced with those who could rejoice and
                    – to the everlasting good of womanhood – had suffered with those whose travail
                    was not only of the body but of the mind and the tortured mother-heart.</p>
                <p> For, to appreciate what Margaret Sanger has done and what she is trying to do,
                    you must in your imagination suffer with them too. And you must bear in mind
                    more than the pain of the involuntary, unwilling mothers. You must think of the
                    children themselves. As Margaret Sanger saw them. As they worried her mind. And
                    tormented her dreams.</p>
                <p> For, I could tell by the way she lifted her hand how tormented she has been.
                    Pain was in that eloquent gesture as she recalled those long-gone days.</p>
                <p> Imagine yourself a nurse. Imagine yourself hearing those words “Thank God!” from
                    the still-anguished lips of a woman who hears of the death of her own baby, and
                    then imagine yourself called again in perhaps ten weeks, or four of five months,
                    to attend the same woman who, in grim desperation, has deliberately terminated
                    her own pregnancy.</p>
                <p> Terminated it, not because she was hard, but because all that was fine in her
                    had not yet been crushed. Because already, in her crowded rooms, there were four
                    and five people in a bed; because in one of them perhaps her own lovely little
                    girls, who could have no privacy, no feeling of modesty, were sleeping with “the
                    boarder” taken in because the few cents he paid were so desperately needed.
                    Because already there was no place for her children to go. Because no matter how
                    her heart cried out in protest, she had to push them out – down to the sidewalk
                    from which, as she very well knew, they would, in turn, be pushed and crowded
                    into the street. Pushed. Pushed – only too often in the end into the jails and
                    reformatories or penitentiaries. And more children coming all the time – all
                    because of the lack of one simple well-fitted inexpensive article that lasts a
                    woman over a year.</p>
                <p> Abortions – which among the laity means, incorrectly, only the deliberate
                    terminating of pregnancy – were a common thing on the east side of New York.
                    Margaret Sanger took care of case after case.</p>
                <p> And that wasn’t all. As soon as a nurse would arrive in a tenement the women of
                    the neighborhood would come to see her. This one would bring her a little bowl
                    of soup. Another would bring a cup of tea; a third would come bearing a bit of
                    fish prepared in delicious old world fashion. The soup, the tea, the fish, all
                    of them were – bribes. They were coaxing, these women, pleading for knowledge of
                    how to keep themselves from getting with child.</p></q>
            <p> “They seem to feel,” <q who="HALMA">said Margaret Sanger</q>, “as if you had some
                mysterious secret up your sleeve and wouldn’t give it to them.”</p>
            <q who="HALMA"><p> And Margaret Sanger, trained nurse though she was, could not help
                    them. She saw their suffering of body and distress in mind. She <emph
                        rend="italics">felt</emph> it and yet she, who was so used to alleviating
                    suffering, could do nothing for them.</p>
                <p> And then – something happened. Her emotions which had lain like the charges in a
                    gun were suddenly turned into effective bullets. The trigger was pulled – by the
                    death of one particular woman.</p>
                <p> This was not the first woman Margaret Sanger had seen die from the self-induced
                    abortion. But in the New York Clinic alone, because of that one woman’s death,
                    20,000 women have been freed from the ignorance that was her curse. Her death,
                    tragic as it was, has brought about is bringing about, woman’s release from the
                    fear that still haunts, so grimly, the overwhelming majority of marriages. She
                    died, crucified on the cross of ignorance, and through her death and its
                    reaction upon Margaret Sanger, as brave as she is sensitive, as clear-headed as
                    she is tender-hearted, thousands of other women lived.</p></q>
            <p>
                <q who="HALMA">The first time Margaret Sanger attended <person reg="Sachs, Sadie"
                        >this woman</person>, she had in grim determination penetrated her own flesh
                    with a knitting needle and the result was infection. She was only about
                    twenty-five and her husband about twenty-eight. Already they had three children.
                    Margaret Sanger and her assistant nurse were obliged to keep her packed in ice,
                    which meant they had to carry it up three flights of stairs.</q> “It was the
                kind of case,” <q who="HALMA">Margaret Sanger explained, </q>“in which you even
                slept with your finger on the patient’s pulse. But we pulled her through.”</p>
            <p>
                <q who="HALMA">She was nervous and said to the doctor, </q><q who="SACSA">“Well I
                    suppose if I have another baby it will go pretty hard on me.”</q>
                <q who="HALMA">(Mrs. Sanger made us fairly see the hunted look in the woman’s
                    eyes.)</q></p>
            <p>
                <q who="HALMA">The doctor’s answer was: </q><q who="UNK">“Now, don’t you cut any
                    more capers.”</q></p>
            <p>
                <q who="SACSA">“But what shall I do?”</q>
                <q who="HALMA">she asked, agony in the question.</q></p>
            <p>
                <q who="UNK">“You know what to do,”</q>
                <q who="HALMA">he returned.</q>
                <q who="UNK">“Tell <person reg="Sachs, Jake">Jake</person> to go sleep on the
                    roof.”</q></p>
            <p> “She turned to me,” <q who="HALMA">said Mrs. Sanger.</q> “‘<q who="SACSA">He is a
                    man,</q>’ she whispered. ‘<q who="SACSA">He doesn’t understand, but you are a
                    woman; you do. Tell me.</q>’”</p>
            <q who="HALMA"><p> But at this time nothing was organized, the whole problem of
                    voluntary family limitation was a subject not to be discussed out of primitive
                    life. <emph rend="italics">No one could tell this woman anything.</emph> So,
                    less than three months later, Mrs. Sanger and the same doctor and the same other
                    nurse were all called back again. This time the woman died.</p></q>
            <p> “That was the end,” <q who="HALMA">Mrs. Sanger explained, by which she meant that it
                    was the vital beginning point of her effective efforts. </q>“I didn’t care if I
                went to jail. I didn’t care if I had to leave <person reg="Sanger, William">my
                    husband</person> and children. You can’t imagine what happened to me! From a
                domestic person, happy with my family, I became a fanatic. I was like something shot
                out of a gun.”</p>
            <p>
                <q who="HALMA">Her friends sympathized with her point of view, but argued, </q>“<q
                    who="UNK">Margaret, you are married. You have little children – <emph
                        rend="italics">let someone else do it</emph>.</q>” <q who="HALMA">Even her
                    Irish father, who had not been to New York for forty years, came down to see if
                    she didn’t need a rest and offered to send her to a sanatarium! But she was not
                    to be balked. She simply announced that she was going to do something about the
                    Comstock laws which said, and still say, that no information upon contraception
                    or contraceptive articles can be sent through the mail, by express, or by any
                    common carriers. Moreover, as Mrs. Sanger points out in her pamphlet on “<title
                        type="book">Laws concerning Birth Control in the United States</title>,”
                    Section 211 </q>“<q who="LAWS">Makes it unlawful for one physician to send
                    through the mails the result or benefits of his practice or research. To send an
                    applicant for information the address of any legally operating Birth Control
                    Clinic is also illegal, according to the present Federal Statutes.</q>” <q
                    who="HALMA">The penalty is</q> “<q who="LAWS">not more than $5,000, or
                    imprisonment for not more than five years, or both...</q>”</p>
            <q who="HALMA"><p> What worried Mrs. Sanger was that she knew nothing as a nurse which
                    she did not know as a wife. All her knowledge had been picked up here and there,
                    not in an orderly fashion as the information of a woman like herself, well
                    informed on other medical facts, should have been.</p>
                <p> She gave up nursing, and leaving the support of the family of five entirely up
                    to her artist husband, settled to study.</p>
                <p> She went to the <org reg="New York Academy of Medicine Library">New York medical
                        library</org> to dig out some information on contraceptives, <emph
                        rend="italics">but in all that vast library she could not find one single
                        word on the subject</emph>. Then she traveled to <place reg="Boston, MA"
                        >Boston</place> to search the library there, but again she found nothing on
                    the most vital subject in the world to women. From Boston she went to the <org
                        reg="Library of Congress">Congressional Library</org> at Washington. At last
                    she did find one article – just one and a left-handed one at that, which had
                    appeared in the <title type="journal">Atlantic Monthly</title>. It was by
                        <person reg="Ross, Edward Alsworth">E. A. Ross</person>, a professor of
                    Sociology, and was on “Race Suicide” – on the other side of the question. (Since
                    then he has reversed his opinion and has written “<title type="book">Standing
                        Room Only</title>”.)</p></q>
            <p> “I thought,” <q who="HALMA">explained Mrs. Sanger to me, with a wise, whimsical
                    smile that seemed to hold in it many an unshed tear, </q>“that all this was
                entirely original with me.”</p>
            <p>
                <q who="HALMA">Meanwhile her husband had won a prize at the Beaux Arts that would
                    take him to France, and she was told </q>“<q who="SANWI">Why, Margaret, they
                    know all about it in France.</q>”</p>
            <p> “So,” <q who="HALMA">she explained to us, </q>“to France we went and the children
                went too. Although in order to go we had to mortgage everything we had.” <q
                    who="HALMA">(At this time the little Sangers were about ten, five, and three
                    years old.)</q></p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">What She Learned Abroad</head>
            <q who="HALMA"><p> She found that in <place>France</place> the doctors fitted women with
                    the very necessary article with that silly, progress-challenging,
                    tragedy-producing law still on the statute books of this country makes illegal
                    if sent through the mails, by express or by any common carrier; that in France
                    all contraceptive supplies could be purchased, freely. One had only to ask for
                    them as one would ask here for aspirins or a hot water bottle</p>
                <p> Nor was this all: <emph rend="italics">The Syndicalists in France gave out
                        contraceptive information with their labor propaganda</emph>. Moreover, in
                    all their labor lectures they gave diagrams and lists of places where the
                    necessary articles could be bought.</p>
                <p> Those six months in France were fruitful ones, indeed, for Margaret Sanger and,
                    through her, for the women of the United States. She amassed facts and figures,
                    made, in short, a complete survey, and came back to the United States with the
                    material for her now historic little pamphlet “<title type="book">Family
                        Limitation</title>.”</p></q>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">On the Firing Line</head>
            <q who="HALMA"><p> But it was one thing to have the material for the pamphlet, quite
                    another to get it printed. In fact it took nearly a year to accomplish this.
                    Margaret Sanger literally walked “the sidewalks of New York” in search of some
                    one who was able and willing to help her.</p></q>
            <p> “<q who="UNK">Well, now, Margaret,</q>” <q who="HALMA">this one and that would say,
                    </q>“<q who="UNK">do you want me to go to Sing Sing?</q>”</p>
            <q who="HALMA"><p> All the time <person reg="Comstock, Anthony">Anthony
                        Comstock</person>, who was privileged to open any letter, was snooping
                    about. Of that she was positive. She couldn’t blame people for refusing to help
                    her. Yet she was determined to get her recently accumulated knowledge to those
                    who needed it. After she was nearly exhausted she decided to see if she could
                    get the work done in France.</p>
                <p> Then, suddenly, a Russian (who today is Chief of Police in <place
                        reg="Moscow, Soviet Union">Moscow</place>, but was then a linotype operator
                    in New York), said he would help her. Each evening, after the other men had left
                    the shop, he stayed and set the type. But even after the type was set there
                    remained the problem of getting the pamphlets printed, of getting them stitched,
                    and then of finding a safe place in which to store them.</p></q>
            <p> “Meanwhile,” <q who="HALMA">Margaret Sanger explained, </q>“I had to have some
                window dressing, so I started <title type="journal">The Woman Rebel</title>, a
                monthly magazine, that had for its motto ‘No Gods, No Master.’ That little Woman
                Rebel came out to fight <name reg="Section 211 of the Penal Code">section 211 of the
                    Penal Laws</name> of the Federal Statutes.”</p>
            <q who="HALMA"><p> Nine issues were published and, of the nine, seven were suppressed.
                    Nine articles were declared indictable and for each indictment the penalty was
                    five years, which meant that, if Mrs. Sanger were convicted, she could be
                    sentenced to forty-five years penal servitude. She made up her mind that if she
                    was going to jail for forty-five years she was going to make a terrible racket.
                    She would cannonade the public conscience with the thunder of her pamphlets.</p>
                <p> You must understand that she was not arrested for giving contraceptive
                    information. She simply kept baiting the law. One article called “<title
                        type="article">The Marriage Bed</title>” had nothing in it at all beside
                    sound hygiene. But Comstock was bringing the indictments.</p>
                <p> By this time a group of kindred spirits had gather around Margaret Sanger. They
                    would meet regularly, at appointed spots, in the early morning and put the
                    little magazine into different mail boxes.</p></q>
            <p> “It was,” <q who="HALMA">she explained,</q> “just to keep the tom-toms beating while
                I was really trying to get the pamphlets on ‘Family Limitation’ printed and stored.
                There were 100,000 of these in preparation.”</p>
            <q who="HALMA"><p> “Where did you get the money to do all this?” I asked. It seemed she
                    scraped it from here and there and even took all the money the children had
                    inherited or had been given for their education for by this time Margaret Sanger
                    was lashed to the straight, tall mast of an ideal which in her mind justified
                    everything.</p>
                <p> The miners in <place reg="Butte, MT">Butte, Montana</place> ordered 10,000 of
                    these pamphlets and the miners in <place>West Virginia</place> ordered 10,000
                    more. She had them all wrapped and addressed ready for simultaneous release.
                    Some were shipped to <place reg="Pittsburgh, PA">Pittsburgh</place>, some to
                        <place reg="Chicago, IL">Chicago</place> and some to <place
                        reg="San Francisco, CA">San Francisco</place> for distribution from these
                    points, as well as from New York. By the time she was indicted the very last of
                    the pamphlets were out of the printer’s hands. Her plans were complete.</p>
                <p> In August, 1914, the world went to war and it was in September of that year that
                    Mrs. Sanger was indicted on nine counts because of nine different articles in
                    The Woman Rebel. She asked for a month’s postponement of her case which was to
                    be tried in the <org reg="United States Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit"
                        >Federal Courts of New York City</org>.</p></q>
            <p>
                <q who="HALMA"><person reg="Content, Harold A.">The District Attorney</person>, a
                    man whose name, ironically enough, was Content, agreed to this postponement. But
                    in less than two weeks, really in just about ten days, she received a telephone
                    message saying: </q>“<q who="CONHA">Your case is called. Please appear in
                    court.</q>” <q who="HALMA">Arrived there she found that Content had entirely
                    changed his attitude.</q></p>
            <p>
                <q who="HALMA">Mrs. Sanger would consult with her lawyers and have them advise her,
                    but she would not have any lawyer speak for her before the judge. Her position
                    was that she was an American citizen who had done nothing wrong, and who
                    therefore needed only to tell the plain truth in order to clear herself. It was
                    a naive attitude. She appeared and explained she was as yet unprepared; that the
                    judge had agreed she should have a full month’s postponement. </q>“Now,” <q
                    who="HALMA">she explained to us,</q> “if you throw a stone in New York City,” <q
                    who="HALMA">you would hit one of my Irish relatives. And one of them, an
                    employee of the postoffice, said to me: </q>“<q who="UNK">They are going to
                    railroad you, Margaret. You had better get the best lawyer you can!</q>”</p>
            <p>
                <q who="HALMA">The judge would not consent to postpone her case for more than a
                    single day. When, the next morning, it was called, Content answered </q>“<q
                    who="CONHA">Ready.</q>”</p>
            <p> “But I am not ready, judge,” <q who="HALMA">insisted Mrs. Sanger.</q></p>
            <p> “<q who="CLAHE">You were told to get ready,</q>” <q who="HALMA">said <person
                        reg="Clayton, Henry DeLamar">the judge</person>. </q>“<q who="CLAHE">The
                    state will pay for an attorney for you.</q>” <q who="HALMA">At which point the
                    district attorney exclaimed: </q>“<q who="CONHA">She’s posing! Just
                posing!</q>”</p>
            <p>
                <q who="HALMA">Then the judge became very severe: </q>“<q who="CLAHE">Whether you
                    are ready or not, Mrs. Sanger, we are going on with this case tomorrow at ten
                    o’clock.</q>”</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Exile</head>
            <p>
                <q who="HALMA">It was a terrible moment in Margaret Sanger’s life. What to do?
                    Should she go to trial before her case was prepared or – should she flee? She
                    had been allowed to come and go on her own recognizance. If she had given bail
                    it would have been easier to leave, but she was on her honor, besides it was a
                    terrible wrench to tear herself away from her three children, and her husband
                    who was a better artist than he was provider . (Fortunately Margaret Sanger had
                    a sister, Mrs. <person reg="Byrne, Ethel">Ethel Byrne</person>, who could and
                    did mother the little Sangers during the long year and three months that Mrs.
                    Sanger was away.)</q> “Besides,” <q who="HALMA">she said frankly,</q> “everybody
                thought I was just losing my mind and many people thought I was simply courting
                publicity.”</p>
            <q who="HALMA"><p> So she fought her battle – weighing odds against odds, her future
                    usefulness against her present sense of duty – while the clock ticked off the
                    precious minutes. Then suddenly she made up her mind. At five minutes before
                    midnight she boarded the train leaving for <place reg="Montreal, Canada"
                        >Montreal</place>, from which city she sailed, under an assumed name, for
                    England, without a passport and while that country was at war!</p>
                <p> “But how on earth,” I asked, “did you get into England without a
                passport?”</p></q>
            <p> “I told them that I didn’t know I had to have one,” <q who="HALMA">she
                smiled.</q></p>
            <p>
                <q who="HALMA">The passengers, it seemed, were friendly. (I have already told you,
                    Margaret Sanger has charm.) They took up the cudgels for her; and the captain
                    too, was won over by her true explanation that even if she had known about the
                    passport </q>“she had no time in which to secure one.” <q who="HALMA">At all
                    events she was permitted to enter England and to remain there in peace.</q></p>
            <q who="HALMA"><p> Meanwhile, on shipboard, she wrote the judge a letter in which she
                    explained that by refusing her reasonable request for a month’s postponement of
                    her case he had compelled her to take a year’s postponement, thereby
                    inconveniencing her greatly. She further stated that when she returned to the
                    United States she would report for trial. It was, too, while she was in the
                    middle of the ocean that a hundred thousand of the “Family Limitation” pamphlets
                    went to miners and to working people in different sections of the United States.
                    Also, one went to her trial judge and one to the district attorney.</p>
                <p> In England she found, as she had in France, that contraception information and
                    articles were sold and dispensed as a matter of course. She met <person
                        reg="Shaw, George Bernard">Bernard Shaw</person>, <person reg="Wells, H. G."
                        >H. G. Wells</person> and other interesting men, besides learning many
                    things which she never would have known had she not gone to England. In that
                    country she spent many hours at the <org>British Museum</org> where she read
                    constantly on the subject nearest her heart.</p>
                <p> In Holland, where the Birth Control movement was and is more thoroughly
                    organized than anywhere else, she did more than read. She took a three months’
                    course in contraception under Doctor <person reg="Rutgers, Johannes"
                        >Rutgers</person>, who was at the head of the family limitation movement in
                    that country. She couldn’t get into <place>Germany</place> because of the war,
                    but she did travel down into <place>Spain</place> and studied and made surveys
                    there as well as in England.</p>
                <p> Meanwhile, during Mrs. Sanger’s stay in England, Comstock set a trap for Mr.
                    Sanger. A very dilapidated man came to him with a tale that his wife was ill
                    after their seventh child. Couldn’t and wouldn’t Mr. Sanger give him that little
                    pamphlet that told how not to have more children? Not having any on hand, Mr.
                    Sanger went to the bother of borrowing one and gave it to the stranger. The man
                    asked how much he should pay for it, to which Mr. Sanger told him that he could
                    have it free of charge. Very shortly the stranger returned with Anthony
                    Comstock. The result was that Mr. Sanger himself spent thirty days in jail,
                    which, as it was not his fight, was pretty rough.</p>
                <p> Perhaps this is as good a moment as any in which to tell you that – although I
                    did not get this directly from Margaret Sanger herself – it is generally
                    understood that gradually Mr. and Mrs. Sanger’s interests drifted apart. He was
                    an artist and his heart was in his work. She was a woman motivated by her acute
                    sense of social injustice. Their paths simply diverged until eventually they
                    faced this fact, without any unfriendliness . Mrs. Sanger has since married Mr.
                        <person reg="Slee, James Noah H.">J. H. Slee</person>, an able business man
                    who is in close sympathy with her efforts and, I gather from this and that, has
                    smooth many stones from her path.</p></q>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Holland’s Lesson – Clinics Needed Here</head>
            <q who="HALMA"><p> It was while Mrs. Sanger was in Holland that she realized that the
                    problem of bringing correct contraceptive knowledge to the rank and file of
                    people involved much more than free speech and the free distribution of
                    literature on the subject. Not only was the task of trying to put the facts into
                    English that our foreign population could understand almost too difficult – for
                    even our native born women needed to learn a new vocabulary – but the clinics in
                    Holland had opened Margaret Sanger’s eyes. She realized she had been on the
                    wrong track. All her friends thought she had grown conservative, <emph
                        rend="italics">but Margaret Sanger now knew that what this country needed
                        was not talk but clinics where a woman could be properly fitted and supplied
                        with the precise article which her particular case demanded</emph>. Margaret
                    Sanger came back to this country determined she would open a clinic in New York
                    City.</p>
                <p> For, drawn by her deep and inner need to see her family, she did come back. She
                    was anxious, also, to observe first hand what the situation was. She found
                    public opinion discouragingly unchanged.</p>
                <p> But first there was the matter of that old case against her to be settled. True
                    to her word, she reported to her trial judge. With her she had brought a letter
                    to <person reg="Wilson, Woodrow">President Wilson</person> and the people of the
                    United States. It was signed by Bernard Shaw, H. G. Wells, <person
                        reg="Bennett, Arnold">Arnold Bennett</person>, <person reg="Murray, Gilbert"
                        >Gilbert Murray</person>, <person reg="Carpenter, Edward">Edward
                        Carpenter</person>, and <person reg="Ellis, Havelock">Havelock
                        Ellis</person>.</p>
                <p> The letter she brought ran something like this:</p></q>
            <p> “<q who="STOMA">We, the undersigned, are pleading on behalf of Mrs. Sanger who has
                    seen the miseries of women in her country as we have seen them in ours.</q>” <q
                    who="HALMA">It also pointed out that England had settled the matter of the need
                    for widely spread contraceptive information thirty years before at the trial of
                        <person reg="Besant, Annie">Annie Besant</person> and <person
                        reg="Bradlaugh, Charles">Charles Bradlaugh</person> and suggested that one
                    could scarcely prosecute a woman with such noble ideas as Mrs. Sanger’s.</q></p>
            <p>
                <q who="HALMA">When her case came up, every morning the letters protesting about it
                    would pile in to the judge, who filled waste basket after waste basket with
                    them. He didn’t bother to read them but nevertheless they had their influence.
                    He would say testily, </q>“<q who="CLAHE">Take that Sanger mail away.</q>” <q
                    who="HALMA">In the end President Wilson recommended to the attorney general that
                    the indictments be quashed, and they were.</q></p>
            <q who="HALMA"><p> And in the midst of her struggle for others Margaret Sanger had to
                    face a deep personal sorrow – her little daughter died.</p></q>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">The First Clinic</head>
            <q who="HALMA"><p> Mrs. Sanger and her sister, Mrs. <person reg="Byrne, Ethel Higgins"
                        >Ethel Byrne</person> (also a trained nurse), chose for the location of the
                    first clinic in the United States, the district in <place reg="Brooklyn, NY"
                        >Brooklyn</place> (Brownsville) that had the highest degree of infant
                    mortality, from where there were more appeals for charity than from any other
                    district in New York; in which more children, in proportion to the number in the
                    district, applied for labor certificates.</p>
                <p> This time Margaret Sanger had to deal with the Irish bull dogs. To them the very
                    words “birth control” had an indecent sound, seemed, indeed, to smack the houses
                    of prostitution. For ten days everything went on smoothly. Nearly 500 women came
                    to hear the precious new knowledge from these valiant nurses (Mrs. Sanger and
                    Mrs. Byrne), and the interpreter who helped them. But it was inevitable that the
                    police – and newspaper reporters and cameramen – should notice the line of baby
                    carriages that stretched in a line around the block. As a result all three women
                    were arrested for violating Section 1142 of the New York State Laws. Both Mrs.
                    Sanger and Mrs. Byrne were sentenced to jail for thirty days. They carried the
                    case to the court of appeals because they wanted to get an interpretation of the
                    law on this subject. Their convictions for violating <name
                        reg="Section 1142 of the New York State Penal Code">Section 1142</name> were
                    affirmed, but the decision handed down by Judge <person reg="Crane, Fredrick E."
                        >Charles R. Crain</person> of the Court of Appeals of New York State, <emph
                        rend="italics">made it clear that under Section 1142 of the same laws any
                        licensed physician practicing in the state of New York can give
                        contraceptive information for the prevention or cure of
                    “disease.”</emph></p>
                <p> Mrs. Sanger and Mrs. Byrne, thinking at the time they would be sent to jail,
                    together told the <title type="newspaper">New York World</title> that they were
                    going on a hunger strike. But Mrs. Byrne was sent first by herself to the
                    work-house on <org>Blackwell Island</org>. The New York World’s <person reg="Unknown">reporter</person> was the only one
                    allowed to see her. He had an assistant attorney’s credentials and while the
                    other newspapers consistently misrepresented Mrs. Byrne’s case, he told the
                    truth about it from day to day – giving all the details of the long, terrible
                    eleven days she endured without food or water. By the end of that time she was
                    so ill that, in order to save her life, Governor <person
                        reg="Whitman, Charles Seymor">Whitman</person> granted her a full pardon and
                    she was taken from the work-house in an ambulance. But her sufferings had
                    focused public attention on the case and aroused lethargic public opinion. As
                    the other charge only was for selling “<title type="book">What Every Girl Should
                        Know</title>,” she was let off with only a $25 fine. When her case was
                    appealed the court ruled that there was no reason why the book should not be
                    sold.</p>
                <p> Six years later, in April 1929, the New York Birth Control Clinic was again
                    raided, but this time there were no jail sentences for those in charge of it. A
                    decoy had arrived – a woman who said she had three children, one five years old,
                    one three, and one eleven months. She went through the usual routine, had a
                    gynecological examination and a complete check-up by a second doctor. A week
                    later she returned with several plainclothesmen, stated that she was Police
                    Woman <person reg="Sullivan, Mary">Mary Sullivan</person>; that as a matter of
                    fact she had two grown children; that there was nothing the matter with her, and
                    that the doctors should have known it. Then she made a big mistake. In her
                    official capacity, she grabbed her “history cards.”</p></q>
            <p>
                <q who="HALMA">Dr. <person reg="Stone, Hannah Mayer">Stone</person> and Dr. <person
                        reg="Pissoort, Elizabeth">Pissoort</person>, in charge of the clinic at the
                    time, were hustled into a patrol wagon. Babies were crying. Women were
                    pleading,</q> “<q who="UNK">Don’t tell my name! Oh, don’t!” I don’t want my name
                    in the papers! I don’t want my husband to know that I am here.</q>” <q
                    who="HALMA">All was in confusion.</q></p>
            <p>
                <q who="HALMA">Fortunately, at this critical moment, Mrs. Sanger arrived and assured
                    the women they need have no fears. She warned Mary Sullivan that she had better
                    be careful and let those history cards alone or she would get into trouble. To
                    which the police woman retorted, </q>“<q who="SULMA">I in trouble? What about
                        <emph rend="italics">you</emph>?</q>”</p>
            <q who="HALMA"><p> As a matter of fact, Mrs. Sullivan was demoted, and <person
                        reg="Whalen, Grover Aloysius">Whalen</person>, the police commissioner, was
                    loud in his protests that she had acted without any order from him. When the
                    case came to trial, it was shown that although the decoy may have believed
                    herself to be in perfect health her condition was such that until it was
                    rectified a pregnancy and child-birth would have been very dangerous for her.
                    Furthermore, the press and public opinion were friendly to the clinic, and the
                        <org>New York Academy of Medicine</org>, incensed because their sacred
                    “cards” had been touched, took a firm attitude. The case was dismissed.</p>
                <p> It is a far cry from that first clinic, which only gave advice, to the fifty
                    well-equipped, well-staffed ones, now in daily use, in the United
                States.</p></q>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">The Talk at the Liberal Center</head>
            <q who="HALMA"><p> As Mrs. Sanger stood in that pretty little stone building, looking
                    down at her intent audience, I studied it from the chair on the platform behind
                    her.</p>
                <p> In the entire auditorium there were only women. Most of them were under
                    forty-five although there were some whom I judged to be in their sixties and
                    even a very few in their seventies, interested perhaps because of daughters of
                    grand-daughters, or because of the wider aspects of the question. For <emph
                        rend="italics">the technique of contraception is the most vital subject in
                        the whole world to women</emph>. It involves and modifies woman’s love for
                    her mate to such an extent that whether this may be blasted or bloom to a
                    beautiful fruition, depends upon her knowledge or ignorance of simple facts of
                    birth control. The whole question of voluntary family limitation connects up,
                    too, with the problems of poverty, of disease, of child-labor, of maternal
                    mortality, of infant mortality, of delinquency, of divorce, and of war.</p>
                <p> It is something that concerns Catholic women as well as Protestant and
                    Freethinkers. <emph rend="italics">For whatever the attitude of the
                            <org reg="Roman Catholic Church">Catholic Church</org> as a church may be, the attitude of the big
                        majority of Catholic girls and women is exactly that of their non-Catholic
                        sisters – they are eager to know how to space their children wisely and to
                        bring into the world only the number for which they can care for
                        well.</emph> It is a question that concerns one race as much as another, and
                    rich and poor alike. It is in fact perhaps the only question in which every
                    grown woman is equally interested, whether she wishes to be the mother of
                    fourteen children, of five, of the conventional two, or to have no family at
                    all. Yet I am quite sure that not more than a dozen – if that many – of those
                    several hundred women ever before had heard a forthright lecture on how
                    conception could be prevented. Margaret Sanger spoke plainly and accurately,
                    although with perfect taste, illustrating her talk simply but clearly by
                    diagrams and by chart, and in certain instances with the actual articles
                    themselves. For there is nothing in the statutes of <place>Missouri</place> that
                    prevents her from <emph rend="italics">telling</emph> any one all that she told
                    that eager audience.</p>
                <p> First, calmly but convincingly, she discussed the absurdity of advising
                    continence to the point of having sexual intercourse only when children are
                    wished. She stressed the fact that even one union a year would be enough to
                    result in a baby every year. In this way a couple could easily acquire a family
                    too large for the woman to bear with continued health, or the man to support.
                    Then she discussed the harmful psychological effects which result from the
                    repression of natural sex expression when two people live in the close intimacy
                    of marriage. With a simple little story, beautifully told for illustration,
                    Margaret Sanger made the women in that audience feel that marriage without the
                    full embrace, when mutual impulse impels toward it, is a mockery.</p>
                <p> She took up the question of sterilization, explaining exactly what it meant; for
                    a woman a major operation; for a man, an operation which takes something like
                    twenty minutes and after which he is able to be at work in two days. She made
                    the point that if, because either husband or wife had a serious transmittable
                    disease, a couple should not bring children into the world and decided that
                    sterilization was the method by which they wished to assure this result, then
                    the partner through whom the disease would be transmitted should be the one to
                    undergo the operation. Sterilization of either man or woman does not interfere
                    with the full expression of both partners.</p>
                <p> Then having led her audience along step by step, establishing in their minds
                    confidence both in her fairness of attitude and in her precise knowledge, she
                    discussed the two ways in which the husband may try to prevent conception. She
                    explained how ineffective both methods are likely to be and how unsatisfactory
                    they both are from a psychological and emotional viewpoint. (In fact out of
                    different methods used by 400 cases recently tabulated at the New York Birth
                    Control Clinic those who had used the method which depends on no mechanical
                    mean, rated 66 percent of failures and both partners had found their union lost
                    much of its beauty.) In the other method, which is the one most commonly relied
                    upon in this country, the percentage of failures was 61 percent and the sense of
                    physical and mental communion lessened instead of increased by its use.</p>
                <p> Besides, both these methods place a woman at the mercy of her partner whose
                    interest in being careful seldom quite equals her own. For if they are
                    determined not to have children and conception doe take place it is she who must
                    go through he physical pain as well as the mental anxiety of an abortion. And
                    right here let me make it clear that abortions are just what the Birth Control
                    Clinics help women to avoid. (To prevent conception and to interrupt a
                    pregnancy, once conception has taken place, are two very different matters.)</p>
                <p> She discussed the value of cleanliness. (The percentage of failures with this
                    method is 80 percent.)</p>
                <p> She came to the methods which the wife may use. But she showed by diagrams why
                    the one most commonly employed by peasant women in France and in other European
                    countries (and perhaps one of the three most generally sued by the average woman
                    in this country) is so often ineffective. (Its percentage of failures in this
                    400 tabulated cases was 64 percent.) She discussed the harmfulness of a certain
                    permanent mechanical device (which this same tabulation rates with 73 percent of
                    failures) of all metal devices, and showed that no faith can be put in woman’s
                    so-called “safe period.”</p>
                <p> And last she came to the articles which are effective, harmless and which in no
                    way blunt the sensations, but which, since they come in six or seven widely
                    different sizes, must be fitted by a competent physician.</p>
                <p> Fortunately scattered over the whole United States, there are men and women,
                    ranking high in the medical profession, who are both willing and competent and
                        <emph rend="italics">legally entitled by the laws of the respective
                        state</emph> to meet this need. These doctors are listed, and there is no
                    law which prohibits your writing to ask anyone if he or she can recommend to you
                    a good doctor in your vicinity. Nor, providing nothing is said about
                    contraception in the answer, does any law prevent the name of a modern,
                    progressive doctor being supplied to you. There are moreover a good many people
                    in the vanguard of the Birth Control Movement who have the courage to take
                    chances for the sake of their convictions.</p>
                <p> (Don’t be too angry with your family physician if he refuses you information on
                    this subject – quite probably he doesn’t know any but the ineffective methods
                    that are in common, more or less unsatisfactory use!) According to the pamphlet
                    issued by the <org
                        reg="National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control">Committee
                        on Federal Legislation for Birth Control</org> there are 31 states in which
                    physicians may freely give you contraceptive information and this, not only on
                    health or economic grounds but merely because you wish it. They are:
                        <place>Alabama</place>, <place>Arkansas</place>, <place>Colorado</place>,
                        <place>Delaware</place>, District of Colombia, <place>Florida</place>,
                        <place>Georgia</place>, <place>Illinois</place>, <place>Indiana</place>,
                        <place>Iowa</place>, <place>Kentucky</place>, <place>Maryland</place>,
                        <place>Nebraska</place>, <place>New Hampshire</place>, <place>New
                        Mexico</place>, <place>North Carolina</place>, <place>North Dakota</place>,
                    Ohio, <place>Oklahoma</place>, <place>Oregon</place>, <place>Rhode
                        Island</place>, <place>South Carolina</place>, <place>South Dakota</place>,
                        <place>Tennessee</place>, <place>Texas</place>, <place>Utah</place>,
                        <place>Virginia</place>, <place>Vermont</place>, West Virginia,
                        <place>Wisconsin</place> and <place>Wyoming</place>.</p>
                <p> There are 11 states in which the physician may legally give information on
                    prevention of conception but cannot publish such information. They are
                        <place>Arizona</place>, California, <place>Idaho</place>,
                        <place>Maine</place>, <place>Michigan</place>, <place>Montana</place>,
                        <place>Pennsylvania</place>, <place>Washington</place>,
                        <place>Louisiana</place>, <place>Missouri</place> and
                    <place>Nevada</place>.</p>
                <p> This means that in 42 states the only reason there are so few Birth Control
                    Clinics is that women are too apathetic to move in their own interest. At this
                    writing, for instance, there is not one Birth Control Clinic in the whole state
                    of Missouri – although it seems highly probably that as a result of Mrs.
                    Sanger’s talk Kansas City will have one soon.</p>
                <p> In two states physicians may legally give information on prevention of
                    conception for cure and prevention of “disease.” These two are
                        <place>Minnesota</place> and <place>New York</place>.</p>
                <p> Then there are four doubtful states: <place>Connecticut</place>,
                        <place>Kansas</place>, <place>Massachusetts</place> and <place>New
                        Jersey</place> – but although a physician can give contraceptive information
                    in Connecticut <emph rend="italics">it is the only state in the union which
                        forbids the actual use of contraceptives</emph>. There is one state – just
                    one, <place>Mississippi</place> – in which physicians may not give information
                    on prevention of conception. Mississippi in the south and Connecticut in the
                    north are, in this respect, the two most backwards states.</p>
                <p> Yet understand – while Margaret Sanger broke no law, as she lectured to that
                    eager audience, if someone had taken down her lecture in shorthand and
                    transcribed it and I had mailed it, for instance, to my husband or sent it to
                    him by express, I should have laid myself liable to a fine of not more than
                    $5,000 or not more than five years’ imprisonment or both.</p>
                <p> And this will be true as long as Section 211 of the Federal Statutes and its
                    companion section in express companies remain unchanged. (The <org
                        reg="General Federation of Women's Clubs">national Federation of Women’s
                        Clubs</org> has gone on record to approve Mrs. Sanger’s effort to have these
                    laws amended.)</p>
                <p> In order to devote her whole time to this end she resigned in 1928 from the
                    presidency of The <org>American Birth Control League</org>, which believes, as I
                    understand it, that each state should bring about broad and sane laws, while
                    Mrs. Sanger and the Committee on Federal Legislation believe that the very first
                    step should be to get the Federal Statutes amended, so that physicians shall be
                    allowed complete freedom to sue their discretion. In her opinion, as yet, the
                    dissemination of contraceptive information should be confined to this
                    profession.</p>
                <p> If the interest of those Kansas City women was any indication of the attitude of
                    the women throughout the country she could succeed.</p>
                <p> After the hour’s lecture, there followed a solid hour of question. Some were
                    asked, some were written. They poured out so steadily into my hands from the
                    ushers that I could scarcely separate the duplications. It would have taken Mrs.
                    Sanger several hours to reply even to one of each kind.</p>
                <p> And all through that talk she did more than simply give precise contraceptive
                    information many must have caught a new vision of what the sex relation may mean
                    when both partners are free from all mental anxiety. She gave them a new vision
                    of what it <emph rend="italics">should</emph> mean or not be entered into at
                    all. And for the first time many – although they had children – saw just how
                    those children lay in the mother’s womb. (I wish you could have seen the intent,
                    interested expression on some of the faces as they studied the chart kindly lent
                    by the redoubtable Dr. <person reg="Clendening, Logan C.">Logan C.
                        Clendening</person>!) It seems too obvious for comment that a woman should
                    know the basic facts about bother her own body and her husband’s. (One reason so
                    many mothers fail with their sons is because they can tell them so little when
                    the need for knowledge is most urgent.)</p></q>
            <p>
                <q who="HALMA">Nor was that all. When Mrs. Sanger touched on frigidity and its
                    causes what I saw in some of those faces, too absorbed to be self-conscious,
                    drove a quick pain through my heart. I wished at moments that, instead of
                    speaking to an audience of women, she were addressing their husbands. For what
                    use was it to say </q>“A woman must be wooed” <q who="HALMA">if that same
                    woman’s husband has grown too matter-of-fact, is too ignorant, too lazy, or too
                    selfish to put himself to the bother of the wooing so essential to a woman’s
                    fullest pleasure and response.</q></p>
            <q who="HALMA"><p> Of course in <place reg="Soviet Union">Russia</place>, as Mrs. Sanger
                    pointed out, every word of her talk could have been given to a mixed audience.
                    But the inhibitions of this country can only be overcome step by step.</p>
                <p> And Margaret Sanger is doing much to overcome them. (Besides the lectures she
                    gives so steadily she has written What Every Girl Should Know, <title
                        type="book">What Every Mother Should Know</title>, <title type="book">Woman
                        and the New Race</title>, <title type="book">Happiness in Marriage</title>,
                        <title type="book">Pivot of Civilization</title>, <title type="book">Mother
                        in Bondage</title> – and some others of which I am unaware.) Her talk
                    through which there sparkled a sweet humor, lifted her audience to heights and
                    gave them glimpses of a finer plane of living.</p></q>
            <p>
                <q who="HALMA">As, at last, the people poured out of the building, one woman, better
                    informed than many, was heard to say to her companion, </q>“<q who="UNK">Do you
                    think most of that was really new to the majority?</q>” “<q who="UNK">My
                    dear,</q>” was the quick answer, “<q who="UNK">it is difficult ever to
                    overestimate the ignorance of the average woman.</q>” <q who="HALMA">And this is
                    true. Her ignorance and her inertia are abysmal.</q></p>
            <q who="HALMA"><p> Otherwise, woman would rise in the strength of her numbers and, with
                    the cooperation of the men who value love more than lust and wish to secure the
                    greatest inspiration and physical happiness out of what can be the most
                    beautiful and uplifting of all relationships, she would demand, as Margaret
                    Sanger does, that the path should be made clear for the knowledge that is so
                    essential to the well-being of humanity.</p></q>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
