<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article ">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-02-27 JK initial tag</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1940-02-27">27 Feb 1940</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>
                <supplied resp="MSPP">Letter to the Editor of the Baltimore
                    Evening Sun</supplied>
            </titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421947</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">She Rubs Her Eyes</title>, <title
                    type="journal">Baltimore Evening Sun</title></bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="WHIJA">Whistler, James McNeill</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="United States" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="birth control clinics and leagues" level2="in US"/>
        <index level1="birth control movement" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="infant"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="maternal"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>She Rubs Her Eyes</head>

        <p>To the Editor of the <title type="journal">Evening Sun</title>- Sir: </p>
        <p>I have recently returned from<place> Mexico</place> and find among
            the material awaiting my attention a copy of your editorial of
            January 29, headed <title type="article">“Is <person
                    reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person> Rubbing Her
                Eyes?” </title>Yes, truly she is.. at the fact that the latest
            <org>Gallup</org> poll reports that seventy-seven per cent of the American
            people at the present time not only approve of birth control but now
            recognize its necessity as a <org reg="United States Government">Government</org> health service... also to
            read that the <person reg="Roosevelt, Sara">mother of the President
                of the <place>United States</place></person> “sat in” at a birth
            control luncheon and heard stated publicly, what she doubtless
            already knew privately, that the <person reg="Roosevelt, Eleanor"
                >President’s wife</person> believed in birth control. </p>
        <p> Yes, Mr. Editor, the landscape has changed and I am reminded of
                <person reg="Whistler, James McNeill">Mr. Whistler</person>’s
            statement when a friend commented on the similarity of a scene they
            were looking at to one of Mr. Whistler’s etchings. The painter
            remarked, <q who="WHIJA">“Yes, yes, nature is coming up.”</q></p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Editor, I am keeping my fingers crossed. Birth control has
            made certain progress, but oh how long it has taken to do so little!
            Only 500 clinics established in a country of 130,000,000 people. And
            it has taken twenty-four years for this to be done. </p>
        <p>Birth control is so obviously right and humane that the wonder to me
            all these years has been, “What’s the matter with people in high
            places? Why don’t they speak out and stand up for an idea so
            fundamentally sound?” I’ve been rubbing my eyes for twenty-three
            years in wonder at the lack of interest that public health officials
            displayed... Now during the past year, <place>North Carolina</place>
            has announced its birth-control program. <place>South
                Carolina</place> has recently followed... Other states, we hope,
            will soon dare to follow. </p>
        <p> But in the meantime, we shall continue to lose 159,000 mothers and
            babies each year, sixty per cent, of them needlessly, as <person
                reg="Parran Jr., Thomas">Dr. Parran</person> has himself stated.
            Mothers will bear children too close together, lessening their own
            chances for survival, as well as their babies’; pregnancies will end
            in abortions, the cause of twenty-five per cent of our maternal
            deaths; children will be crowded out of life by others arriving too
            soon. Add to all this senseless waste of mothers who do not die, but
            live on, damaged in body and spirit, ever in fear and dread from
            year to year. </p>
        <p>These same conditions which prompted some of us to try to save these
            women from their misery twenty-five years ago still exist, and are
            known to all who read: yet, except for a few privately interested
            groups, little help is given these women- none at all by our
            national health agencies. </p>
        <p>Margaret Sanger</p>
        <p><place reg="Tucson, AZ">Tucson, Ariz.</place>, Feb. 27 </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
