<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-05-07 JK initial tag</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1940-02-19 ">19 Feb 1940</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>
                <supplied resp="MSPP">Speech to the Mothers Health
                    Clinic</supplied>
            </titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421948</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Fight on Larger Battleground Forecast by
                    Margaret Sanger</title><title type="journal">Arizona
                    Republic</title>Feb. 20, 1940.</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="AR">Arizona Republic</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><index level1="Birth Control Federation of America"/>
        <index level1="National Birth Control League"/>
        <index level1="population control" level2="MS on"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Fight on Larger Battleground Forecast By <person
                reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person><index
                    level1="Southern States"/><index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
            <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Federal"/>
            <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="MS on"/>
        </head>

        <q who="AR">
            <p>The fight of the <org reg="Birth Control Federation of America"
                    >National Birth Control Federation</org> now has won as much
                as it can win while supported only by individual capital;
                therefore it is beginning a campaign to establish birth control
                as a part of the public health setup of counties and states
                throughout the nation, Margaret Sanger declared in a speech to
                approximately 100 <place reg="Phoenix, AZ">Phoenix </place>women
                yesterday afternoon. </p>
            <p>Much important work has been done in the past years and is being
                done by the federation, Mrs. Sanger said. </p>
        </q>
        <p>
            <q who="AR">Any doctor in the country, she declared, now may furnish
                his patients with contraceptive information; he may send such
                information through the mails; he may receive through the mails
                books and supplies, so that </q>“there is perfect freedom for
            the medical profession which we, as laymen, got for them.”</p>
        <p>
            <q who="AR">Much, however, also remains to be done, in the opinion
                of Mrs. Sanger. The speaker told her audience that conditions of
                poverty and disease almost too shocking to believe exist in the
                Southwest and throughout the South; that the</q> “low level of
            life in the midst of this rich country” <q who="AR">is made worse
                because</q> “children keep coming” <q who="AR">regardless of
                whether the parents are able to support them. </q></p>
        <p>
            <q who="AR">She pointed out that, while many states have laws
                decreeing a certain amount of pasture land per head of cattle to
                make sure the land is not over-grazed- no provision is made to
                ensure enough food per human being; that while the government
                makes efforts to see that no cattle are bred from diseased
                stock-frequently the most children are born from diseased and
                undernourished human beings.</q>
        </p>
        <p> “The greatest interest and encouragement we have met,” <q who="AR"
                >Mrs. Sanger said, was in camps of low-wage migratory workers,
                where nurses have been sent recently to distribute contraceptive
                information, although most previous education of this kind was
                done in city slums. In these camps, she said, approximately
                55,000 women have received such information.</q>
        </p>
        <p><q who="AR">Birth control, Mrs. Sanger continued, is beginning to
                reach the strata of life </q>“where it should have been taught
            20 years ago.” </p>
        <p>“We feel we have won out in a legislative way,” <q who="AR">the
                speaker continued.</q> “We have guided the movement in the
            direction of better public health; but it needs to go farther.”</p>
        <p> “Large areas of eroded land,” <q who="AR">she said, have alarmed the
                government over lack of resources, and </q>“it looks as though
            the coming census will reveal the <place>United States</place> as
            overpopulated, amazing as this may seem.” <q who="AR"
                >Overpopulation, she explained, means that the country will not
                be able to support itself with its own resources. This is a
                problem she continued, which has troubled the <place>Old
                    World</place> for many years. </q></p>
        <p><q who="AR">Mrs. Sanger expressed her belief that the current
                condition in Europe is the result of</q> “the breeding of
            generations past.”</p>
        <p>“We have been seeing for 10 years that <place>Germany</place>,
                <place>Italy</place> and <place>Japan</place> were the three
            danger spots,” she said; “now this is proving correct; and they will
            continue to be danger spots until some of these problems are talked
            about and settled intelligently. The problem of population can be
            solved. </p>
        <p>“I believe that birth control- which is control, not interference
            with life, not destruction- means the ruling of intelligence. The
            source of a great number of troubles today is that intelligence is
            not allowed to rule.”</p>
        <p>
            <q who="AR">Birth control, according to Mrs. Sanger,</q> “does not
            take the place of other philanthropic and beneficial movements
            today, but it must come first. It is the foundation.”</p>
        <p><q who="AR">The world, she declared,</q> “cannot exist peacefully
            until population is controlled; when that is achieved we can begin
            to have peace on earth, good will toward men- and spread that
            message over the face of the earth.” </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
