<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/05/02 YG</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1935-05-17">17 May 1935</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Interview with the Idaho Statesman</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421943</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Margaret Sanger, Leading Advocate of Birth Control, Arrives
                    in Boise</title></bibl>
            <bibl><title type="journal">Idaho Statesman</title></bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="IS">Idaho Statesman</name>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="politicians and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="class-based"/>
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="MS on"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>, Leading Advocate of Birth
            Control, Arrives in <place reg="Boise, ID">Boise</place>.</head>
        <p><q who="IS">Margaret Sanger, dressed in the latest of spring prints with white sports hat
                and coat, at the <place>Hotel Boise</place>Thursday did not appear to be the
                crusader who had spent a month in jail and been arrested eight other times, in her
                zeal for birth control legislation.</q></p>
        <p><q who="IS">Mrs. Sanger will speak at the <org reg="Young Women's Christian Association">
                    Y.W.C.A.</org>this evening at 8 o'clock.</q></p>
        <p>I feel, <q who="IS">she said</q>,that since legislation on birth control is now pending
            in <place reg="Washington, DC">Washington</place>, the subject should be heard by the
            voters, both sides of it. At my meeting in Boise I shall be glad to hear objections from
            any who may be present, and shall try to answer them.</p>
        <p><q who="IS">Mrs. Sanger opened the first clinic in the <place>United States</place>for
                the dissemination of birth control knowledge in <place>New York City</place>. She
                was arrested, served 30 days in jail, and took her case to the highest court, where
                she won. At the present <place>New York State</place>, she says, is the only states
                in which doctors have the right to give this knowledge.</q></p>
        <p>I find my strongest advocates among the social service workers,<q who="IS">added Mrs.
                Sanger,</q> and when you realize that with 4,000,000 families on relief, there were
            over 233,000 children born into these homes during the past year, you will see what an
            economic problem it is. We are trying to help correct the existing misunderstanding of
            our measure now before congress. It is to amend a law that passed 60 years ago and gives
            hospitals, clinics and physicians the legal right to dissiminate information to correct
            poverty, overcrowding, child labor, infant mortality and other social problems.</p>
        <p><q who="IS">A group met Mrs. Sanger and <person reg="Alexander, Julia">Mrs. Neil
                    Alexander</person> of Washington, D.C. at Hotel Boise Thursday and there will be
                another no-host luncheon today at 12 o'clock at the <place>Owyhee Hotel</place>.
                This is open to any persons interested in meeting Mrs. Sanger and Mrs.
                Alexander.</q></p>
        <p><q who="IS">Mrs. Sanger will leave Boise Sunday.</q></p>
        <p/>
    </docBody>
</doc>
