<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "file:/S:/TRANSCRIPTIONS/XML%20Drafts/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/06/19 MM</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="(1959-11-12) ">12 Nov 1959</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Birth Control in Japan</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421984</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Birth Control in Japan</title>, <title
                    type="journal">The Reporter</title>, Nov. 12, 1959</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">This clipping has no citation information, from a
        newspaper called <title rend="underline">The Reporter</title>.<index
            level1="Japan" level2="overpopulation and"/><index level1="Japan"
            level2="population policies of"/><index level1="Japan"
            level2="birth control in"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>BIRTH CONTROL IN JAPAN</head>
        <p><emph rend="bold">To the Editors:</emph> In February I visited
                <place>Japan</place> on my way to <place>India</place>. I met
            with a number of women who wnated me to stay and help them. As I had
            not planned to do that I said that I would return. So after I had
            returned to <place reg="Tuscon, AZ">Tuscon</place> and settled up my
            affairs, especially with my doctors, I went off to Japan, taking
            four teen-agers, two of them my granddaughters, and their friends.
            The girls lived in a Japanese home and traveled through Japan,
            always living in Japanese hotels, and have many Japanese songs that
            they sing very well.</p>
        <p>Japan's birth rate, which was cut down fifty per cent in 1958, is
            really a great encouragement to all of us. We must not forget, too,
            that while <person reg="MacArthur, Douglas">Douglas
                MacArthur</person> was in power, he allowed the Eugenics
            Protection Law to remain, and certainly did not encourage the people
            of Japan to abolish that law. The Japanese people love children, but
            as one woman said, <q>"We do not love those that we do not
                know."</q></p>
        <p>They are doing all they can to encourage contraception and to reduce
            abortion, but, and it is a big "B" with "but," they have a problem,
            not as great as India's but still a problem nevertheless.</p>
        <p>MARGARET SANGER, President</p>
        <p><org>International Planned Parenthood Federation</org></p>
        <p>Tuscon, Arizona</p>
        <p/>
    </docBody>
</doc>
