<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-07-02 AS encoded</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-08-15 CH proof and edit</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1916-05-02">2 May 1916</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Speech to the Detroit Jewish Socialist
                    Branch</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421975</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Limit Families: Better Humanity</title>, <title
                    type="journal">Detroit News</title>, May 2, 1916, p. 32</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="DN">Detroit News</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Sanger spoke at St. Andrew's Hall in Detroit. For possible drafts from
            this speaking tour, see <xref from="128002.xml">"Woman and Birth Control,"</xref>
            <xref from="101859.xml">"Birth Control and Society,"</xref> and <xref from="128003.xml"
                >"Condemnation is Misunderstanding" Apr-June, 1916</xref> and <xref
                from="236132.xml">"Chicago Address to Women," Apr-May, 1916.</xref></p>
        <index level1="birth rate"/>
        <index level1="Roosevelt, Theodore" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="Michigan" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="morality of"/>
        <index level1="Netherlands, the" level2="birth control clinics in"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="infant"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"
            level3="negative consequences of"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>"LIMIT FAMILIES: BETTER HUMANITY"</head>
        <p>"<person reg="Roosevelt, Theodore">Theodore Roosevelt</person> boasted in <place
                reg="London, England">London, Eng.,</place> that as a result of his having been
            president, the birth rate in the <place>United States</place> would go up, because of
            his denunciation of the so-called race suicide. You all remember what a furor his
            advocacy of larger families made and how openly everybody discussed the subject.</p>
        <p>"Nobody called Roosevelt immoral for advocating larger families. I wonder if you will
            call me immoral for advocating small families?"</p>
        <q who="DN"><p>Thus <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret H. Sanger</person> took issue
                squarely with the doughty colonel at <org reg="St. Andrew's Hall">St. Andrew's
                    hall,</org> 111 Congress street east Tuesday night. The auditorium and balconies
                were completely filled, with about as many women as men. There were few of the
                well-to-do present.</p>
            <p>The audience was about equally divided between the radicals seen at all advanced
                thought lectures in <place reg="Detroit, MI">Detroit</place> and men and women who
                probably had never before heard a socialist speak, but wanted to be informed on the
                subject of birth control.</p>
            <p>There were many babies with their mothers present and the fact that they were lent
                emphasis to the remarks of Mrs. Sanger. There were, too, a good many young
                people.</p>
            <p>Mrs. Sanger is tall, plain in appearance, with a remarkably clear voice. She spoke
                under the auspices of the <org reg="Unidentified">Jewish socialist branch</org>. She
                considered the subject of birth control from the moral, as distinguished from the
                political or business phases.</p></q>
        <p>"Which is more moral," she asked, "to delude the working women into producing fodder for
            cannon and the munitions makers or to teach them how to prevent producing more mouths
            than they can feed?</p>
        <p>"The United States and <place>Japan</place> are the only so-called civilized countries in
            the world where it is not permitted to teach women birth control," said Mrs. Sanger. "In
                <place reg="Netherlands">Holland,</place> 35 years ago, they established clinics to
            teach this subject to women and now the infant mortality rate is reduced to the absolute
            minimum.</p>
        <p>"In <place reg="New York, NY">New York</place> we see children between the ages of three
            and five years cooped in dark basements making paper flowers or rolling cigarettes. That
            is because the few pennies they can earn are desperately needed for the family
            wants.</p>
        <p>"In the south children are forced to factories or fields when they should be visiting the
            old swimming hole.</p>
        <p>"I must think of working men as merely so much produce thrown into the labor market,
            subject to the law of supply and demand. As long as the women of the workers are kept in
            ignorance of birth control they must continue to glut the market, making men cheap and
            enforcing a low scale of living, a scale that will only make matters worse as generation
            succeeds generation, each growing weaker and less capable of forcing their way to a
            higher standard."</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
