<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-04-02 JK initial tags</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1916-01-13 ">13 Jan 1916</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>
                <supplied resp="MSPP">Statement before the Woman Rebel Trial</supplied>
            </titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421934</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">"Threat of Prison Won't Stop 'Woman Rebel' From Advocating
                    Birth Control."</title><title type="journal">The Day Book</title> Jan. 13, 1916,
                p. 14.</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="SANMA">Sanger, Margaret</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="Woman Rebel, The"/>
        <index level1="Woman Rebel, The" level2="birth control and"/>
        <index level1="Woman Rebel, The" level2="legal case"/>
        <index level1="Woman Rebel, The" level2="suppression of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="arrests and imprisonment"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Comstock law"/>
        <index level1="Europe" level2="women in"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="arrests and trials"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>THREAT OF PRISON WON’T STOP “WOMAN REBEL” FROM ADVOCATING “BIRTH CONTROL”</head>

        <dateline><date value="/----/-01-13"/>Jan. 13, <place reg="New York, NY">New
            York</place>--</dateline>
        <p>The woman rebel has just rebelled again! The apostle of birth control, the alleged author
            of scores of illegal pamphlets, <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret H.
                Sanger</person>, has announced that she is going to stand trial, undefended in a
            federal court here Tuesday, Jan. 18. She must face a charge of circulating improper
            literature, preferred against her a year ago by the late <person reg="Comstock, Anthony"
                >Anthony Comstock.</person></p>
        <p>Is Uncle Sam going to jail Margaret Sanger for an offense of which, her friends declare,
            every single newspaper and magazine in the nation which has discussed her case is just
            as guilty as she? </p>
        <p>That is the dilemma which confronts the authorities today. Everybody, it seems, would be
            happier if she would only compromise and let the whole thing blow over!</p>
        <p>"<q>">Why is it,</q>” Mrs. Sanger was asked, “<q who="SANMA">that you have come back from <place>England</place>
            to undergo all the trouble now being stored up for you in the way of prosecution and
            imprisonment?</q>”</p>
        <p>“<q who="SANMA">For the very reason,</q>” answered Mrs. Sanger, “<q who="SANMA">that the affair might blow over. The great
            issue is to raise the question of birth control out of the gutter of obscenity, where my
            opponents have put it, and to get it into the light of intelligence and human
            understanding.</q>" </p>
        <p>“<q who="SANMA">Few people know how rapidly, under the surface, the birth control movement is
            developing.</q>" </p>
        <p>“<q who="SANMA">My reports from the west say that thousands of birth control pamphlets are being
            distributed there among the working people. They are being photographed, typewritten,
            mimeographed, even copied painfully out by hand, so that the information they contain
            may be spread from family to family.</q>"</p>
        <p> “<q who="SANMA">I am going to stay in the fight, if I can, until the methods of birth control,
            recognized as legal, hygienic and moral in every other civilized nation, are made legal
            in this country also, and all the vile laws which class discussion of them as obscene
            are swept from the statute books.</q>" </p>
        <p>“<q who="SANMA">I hope that my case may have the same result in this country as did that of <person
                reg="Besant, Annie">Annie Besant</person> in England. She was arrested a generation
            ago and found guilty. But the publicity given her case was such an aid to the birth
            control propaganda that England at last recognized it.</q>”</p>
        <p> Mrs. Sanger is to be prosecuted under the postal laws, not on the charge of
                circulating the information as to methods of birth control, but simply for having
                written articles advocating it. These articles appeared in her magazine, <title
                    type="journal">The Woman Rebel</title>. 
        </p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
