<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014-06-20 CH initial tag,</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-09 CH proof tags, enter</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-06-20 KH transcription, indexing, tagging</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1923-08-06">6 Aug 1923</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Press Statement in Denver</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp421971</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>
				<title type="article">Birth Control Advocate Says Faith and Striving for Ideal Keeps
					One Young and Beautiful</title>, <title type="journal">Denver Post</title>, Aug.
				6, 1923, p. 16 </bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="DP">Denver Post</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>Sanger spoke to the press before her talk at the Dever Women's Club luncheon on August 6,
			1923. That speech was not found.</p>
		<index level1="American Birth Control League"/>
		<index level1="Japan"/>
		<index level1="Japan" level2="censorship in"/>
		<index level1="Japan" level2="government of"/>
		<index level1="Denver Woman's Club"/>
		<index level1="war" level2="overpopulation and"/>
	</headNote>

	<docBody>
		<head>BIRTH CONTROL ADVOCATER SAYS FAITH AND STRIVING FOR IDEAL KEEPS ONE YOUNG AND
			BEAUTIFUL</head>
		<q who="DP">
			<p>To keep young and to remain beautiful, one should acquire a great purpose in life,
				and establish in the heart a great faith.</p>
			<p>This recipe sprang into mind Monday when, after seven years’ absence, Mrs. <person
					reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>, leader of the <org
					reg="American Birth Control League">National League for Birth Control</org>,
				came into view younger and lovelier than on her first visit to <place
					reg="Denver, CO">Denver</place>.</p>
			<p>Since her last visit in 1916, Mrs. Sanger has suffered imprisonment many times to
				prove the faith she holds. She has thru sincerity and persistence drawn a velvet
				glove on the iron hand of the law in many states; she has, in spite of the refusal
				of the <org reg="United States, Government of">United States government</org> to
				vise her passport and over the protest of the <org reg="Japan, Government of"
					>Japanese government</org>, entered <place>Japan</place> as an honored guest of
				its younger statesmen, its thoughtful women and the masses of the people, and women
				them to her standard.</p>
			<p>And now, via <place>Alaska</place>, she has come to <place>Colorado</place> for a
				real vacation and rest. </p>
			<p>Before mentioning the cause near her heart, Mrs. Sanger said she did not wonder that
					<person reg="Harding, Warren G.">President Harding</person> succumbed to illness
				on his western tour.</p>
		</q>
		<p>“The president was doubtless very weary when he set out from <place reg="Washington, DC"
				>Washington</place>,” she said. “He had hoped for rest in Alaska. It is a wonderful
			country, but no place to go for a rest, for there at this time of the year is perpetual
			daylight. It is daylight, and that gets behind the eyes into the brain and plays havoc
			with one’s nerves, making sleep impossible to the stranger.”</p>
		<q who="DP">
			<p>Mrs. Sanger insists she sees daylight ahead of her cause. The sort of daylight that
				does not play havoc with the brain, but sets it to work of the good of humanity.</p>
		</q>
		<p>“When I went to Japan,” <q who="DP">she said,</q> “I chose the <name type="ship"
				reg="Taiyo Maru">boat</name> on which the Japanese delegates to the <org
				reg="Washington Naval Congress">armament congress</org> were returning. I had been
			refused a vise to my passport to Japan, but I was not discouraged. I met the delegates,
			and at their request, gave a lecture on war and population. Afterward, they used the
			wireless to urge the Japanese government to invite me to land and to make arrangements
			for a series of lectures in Japan. This the government refused to do. Also the <name
				reg="Schidmore, George Hawthorne">American consul</name> refused to make a request
			that I be permitted to land. However, in Japan, the people are stronger than the
			government, and the people made it possible for me to go ashore and to lecture.”</p>
		<p>As a result, Japan has a league and two birth-control clinics, and statesmen, women, and
			the masses as represented by labor and trades unions, students, all classes, indeed, are
			determined that Japan must have fewer and better people.”</p>
		<p>“The thoughtful people of Japan realize that it is as foolish to glut the market with a
			human output as to glut it was an over supply of other produce. Hence their interest in
			and enthusiasm for the message I carried.”</p>
		<q who="DP">
			<p>The same cordial reception was granted Mrs. Sanger in <place>China</place> and
					<place>Korea</place>.</p>
			<p>No apostle of any cause has paid more dearly for her loyalty than has this
				gentlewoman with the buoyant voice, lovely eyes and stubborn chin.</p>
			<p>As a nurse serving the poor in the tenement districts of <place reg="New York, NY"
					>New York</place>, a location she selected when she left <org
					reg="Claverack College and Hudson River Institute">college</org>, she came to
				know the miseries resulting from large families in poverty-stricken home. And
				following the death of a <person reg="Higgins, Anna Purcell">mother</person> who had
				borne twelve children for whom she had nothing, Mrs. Sanger vowed herself to
				educating the world as to the injustice of such a state of affairs.</p>
			<p>Nine times Mrs. Sanger has heard prison doors swing shut behind her and for thirty
				days, on one occasion, she remained in jail to prove the constitutionality of the
				law on which her sentence rested.</p>
			<p>Days have changed since she drew that tattered covering over the dead face of the
				victim to child-bearing in the squalid tenement, and Mrs. Sanger declares her
				doctrine that a child has at least the right to be well-born is sweeping the
				earth.</p>
			<p>At noon Monday Mrs. Sanger was guest at the <org reg="Denver Woman's Club">Woman’s
					club</org> luncheon. She lectured later. She also will be a guest of honor at
				the luncheon to be given Saturday to Miss <person reg="Paul, Alice">Alice
					Paul</person>, vice president of the <org reg="National Woman's Party">National
					Woman’s party</org>.</p>
		</q>
	</docBody>
</doc>
