<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-04-15 JK initial tag</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1937-07-19">19 Jul 1937</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Statement on National Committee on
                    Federal Legislation for Birth Control
                Report</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421918</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">"More Clinics Urged for Birth
                    Control"</title>, <title type="journal">New York
                    Times</title>, Jul. 19,1937, <title type="article">Auto
                    Caravans Urged to Help Birth Control"</title>, <title
                    type="journal">New York Herald-Tribune</title> Jul. 19,
                1937. </bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="NYT">New York Times</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">Sanger released a press statement to coincide with an
            <org
            reg="National Committee for Federal Legislation for Birth Control "
            >NCFLBC</org> report. Quotes were drawn from coverage in the <title
            type="journal">New York Herald Tribune </title>and <title
            type="journal">The New York Times</title>. <index
            level1="National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control"
            /><index level1="Comstock Laws"/><index
            level1="birth control movement" level2="MS on"/><index
            level1="birth control methods"/><index level1="birth control"
            level2="distribution of information about"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>More Clinics Urged for Birth Control</head>
        <p>“This decision,” <q who="NYT">wrote Mrs. Sanger, referring to the
                    <org
                    reg="United States Court of Appeals For the Second Circuit"
                    >Circuit Court ruling,</org>
            </q>“has opened the way to a far more fundamental goal-- the
            inclusion of birth control in public health programs and the
            carrying of contraceptive information to neglected mothers in
            isolated regions. We must help the mothers who as yet are not
            reached through public health channels. We urge caravans of
            education and help fo mountain women, farm women, mothers in distant
            homesteads, mothers in all districts, city and country, who are
            neglected. </p>
        <p> “We should send an organization of birth-control-instructing nurses
            to visit the homes of these underprivileged mothers. Just as members
            of the <org reg="Visiting Nurse Associations of America">American
                Visiting Nurses Association</org> have gone into the homes to
            help through bedside work, so would we like to see an army of
            equipped, sympathetic, understanding nurses take up this task of
            educating and instructing mothers in contraceptive techniques and
            thus free them from the constant fear which haunts their lives.” </p>
        <div>
            <head>Auto Caravans Urged to Help Birth Control</head>
            <p>“Only by adequate effort to save the lives of women and to
                promote maternal and child health can the community atone for
                the deaths of a million mothers during the six decades while the
                    <person reg="Comstock, Anthony">Comstock</person> laws were
                interpreted as preventing birth control even under medical
                auspices. Those who won the legal fight for birth control must
                now move fast, and keep moving; for women and children are still
                needlessly dying. Their lives may be saved if contraceptive
                facilities become adequately available in every community.” </p>
        </div>

    </docBody>
</doc>
