<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published statement">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014-12-18 CH encode</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-21 EK proof</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-22 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1916-06-16">16 Jun 1916</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied>Statement on Arriving in Portland Oregon</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp421971</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Mrs. Sanger Here</title>, <title type="journal">Portland
					Oregonian</title>, June 17, 1916</bibl>

		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="SANMA">Sanger, Margaret</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>The press recorded some of Sanger's statements made during an interview at the Hotel
			Portland. </p>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="morality of"/>
		<index level1="birth control clinics and leagues"/>
		<index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="biographical information"/>
		<index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="speaking tours" level3="1916 (United States)"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Mrs. Sanger Here</head>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">Advocate of Birth Control to Be at Helig Monday.</head>
			<p>A bright, womanly little woman stepped from the train late yesterday. You wouldn't
				have picked her out as one who was radical or in any way unusual--if courage of
				one's conviction may be regarded as unusual.</p>
			<p>It was <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>, exponent of birth
				control, the woman who was arrested in <place reg="New York, NY">New York
					City</place> for publishing and sending through the mails her magazine, the
					<title type="journal">Woman Rebel</title>, a publication exploiting birth
				control.</p>
			<p>Several members of the local league met Mrs. Sanger and escorted her to the
					<org>Hotel Portland</org>, where, after finding a cool spot and being initiated
				to loganberry juice in an iced drink, she gave an interview.</p>
			<p>Her broadest views, her strongest message she will give on Monday night when she has
				promised to speak in the <org>Helig Theater</org>.</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">Tour is Extension of Effort.</head>
			<p>This lecture tour is her first attempt at big public work. Heretofore she gave
				informal talks to groups of girls in New York City, instructing them in hygiene and
				sanitation. She is a trained nurse, a mother of <person reg="Sanger, Grant"><person
						reg="Sanger, Stuart"><person reg="Sanger, Peggy"> three
						children</person></person></person>, aged respectively 12, 8 and 6 and she
				is a social worker of wide experience. The children are now with <person
					reg="Sanger, Henrietta Wolffberg">grandma Sanger</person>. She says she has seen
				the misery of poverty and sickness in her visits as a nurse and she made up her mind
				to "<q who="SANMA">get at the cause of the trouble.</q>"</p>
			<p>“<q who="SANMA">I have been called in turn a vile female, a person with a barnyard
					philosophy, a <name type="deity">God</name>-send, the greatest woman of the
					century, the counterpart of <person reg="Lincoln, Abraham">Abraham
						Lincoln</person>, and a horrible creature,</q>” said Mrs. Sanger. “<q
					who="SANMA">Rather conflicting epithets, but I go on doing what I believe to be
					right, carrying a message of help, as I believe it to be.</q>”</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">"Blue Laws" Wanted Repealed.</head>
			<p>“<q who="SANMA">I am of the opinion that a greater knowledge of birth control will
					raise the standard of morality instead of lowering it, and I am making an appeal
					to the Western women voters to help in my campaign to repeal the puritanical
					laws as they exist. They are a relic of the dark ages.</q>”</p>
			<p>Mrs. Sanger thinks that young couples who are in love should marry early--provided
				they really are in love. Girls should be told the things that are vitally important,
				says Mrs. Sanger.</p>
			<p>She declares that modern society's attitude toward the unmarried woman is a disgrace
				to civilization. With knowledge given in a wholesome, sensible way there would be
				less immorality, is Mrs. Sanger's opinion.</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">Censorship Blamed for Ills.</head>
			<p>“<q who="SANMA">There is altogether too much censorship,</q>” said “<q who="SANMA"
					>the women rebel.</q>”</p>
			<p>The system of censorship she deems “<q who="SANMA">appalling and a menace to
					liberty.</q>”</p>
			<p>“<q who="SANMA">We have censored and suppressed and repressed and all the time we
					should be getting at the foundation--character-building. We wouldn’t be so
					silly, puritanical and narrow if we had a little more common sense.</q>” Mrs.
				Sanger averred.</p>
			<p>“<q who="SANMA">I don’t want to hitch birth control with any of the isms. I want it
					to be on a sane basis.</q>” This is the one thing she most hopes for, she says.
				She wants to help women to develop her intellectuality, to have some time for the
				children she has already and to do away with the “old fogey” idea that any
				discussion of out of the ordinary topics is “obscene.”</p>
		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
