<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article ">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/04/16 VS initial tagging</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1936-11-14 ">14 November, 1936</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Twenty Years of Defeat and Victory</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421920</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Margaret Sanger Backs Cause Before City Club</title><title
                    type="journal">Rochester Times-Union</title> November 14, 1936</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="RTU">Rochester Times-Union</name>
            <name id="RDC">Rochester Democrat &amp; Chronicle</name>
            <name id="THC">Town Hall Club of New York City</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">Sanger spoke before the <org>Rochester City Club</org> at the <org>Hotel
            Seneca</org>. No other versions found. Sanger gave a speech with the same title in
            <place>Chester, PA</place> at the <org>New Century Club</org>. <index
            level1="birth control" level2="and marriage"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="class-based"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="international"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="morality of"/>
        <index level1="birth control clinics and leagues"/>
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Postal Code and Regulations"/>
        <index level1="India" level2="birth control movement in"/>
        <index level1="Italy" level2="population policies of"/>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="population policies of"/>
        <index level1="poverty" level2="family size and"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person> Backs Cause Before City Club;
            urges New Laws to Emancipate Women</head>
        <div>
            <p>
                <q who="RTU">Red-haired, vivacious Mrs. Margaret Sanger, petite untiring commander
                    of the birth control movement, told Rochester City Club today that</q> “birth
                control is a matter of public health and preventive medicine and not a problem which
                private enterprise can solve.”</p>
            <q who="RTU"><p> She spoke in Hotel Seneca ballroom. Mrs. Sanger launched the American
                    drive for birth control in 1914. </p></q>
            <p>
                <q who="RTU">The dynamic leader of what is now a world-wide movement aimed to
                    emancipate women and strengthen many of the races of the earth, Mrs. Sanger
                    urges</q> “immediate amendment of the <name reg="United States Penal Code"
                    >present federal laws</name> which tie the hands of the physician and obstruct
                an adequate and scientific national birth control program.”</p>
            <p>
                <q who="RTU">More than 1,000 organizations representing 20,000,000 people in this
                    country have indorsed her efforts to change</q> “obsolete federal laws,” <q
                    who="RTU">she says.</q>
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Lines Up Forces. </head>
            <q who="RTU"><p> Mrs. Sanger is now lining up her forces for a fifth attempt at putting
                    over the Federal legislative program. Defeated four times, the program asks
                    comparatively little of the government, according to Mrs. Sanger.</p></q>
            <p> “I think our defeats have come about from a too conservative policy on our own
                part,” <q who="RTU">she said this morning.</q> “We have not asked for enough, I
                think we should ask for more.”</p>
            <q who="RTU"><p>
                    <org>The National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control</org> will
                    ask <org reg="United States Congress">Congress</org> that the <org
                        reg="United States Postal Service">United States mails</org> and common
                    carriers be opened to doctors, hospitals, medical colleges and licenced
                    clinics.</p></q>
            <q who="RTU"><p> Enthusiastic over the co-operation of the some 250 birth control
                    clinics in this country, Mrs. Sanger points with growing pride to the momentum
                    the movement is gaining abroad, especially in the <place reg="Asia"
                        >Orient</place>.</p></q>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Attacks Fascism</head>
            <q who="RTU"><p> She brands Fascist forms of government as weakening their own
                    populations and pushing the status of women back to the lowest ebb since the
                    dawn of Christianity. Despite efforts of Fascist governments to promote
                    wholesale propagation of their subjects the birth rate in both
                        <place>Italy</place> and <place>Japan</place> is decreasing, Mrs. Sanger
                    declared.</p></q>
            <q who="RTU"><p> In <place>India</place> and in <place>China</place> the birth control
                    movement is gaining rapid headway, she said, pointing to India as one of the
                    chief fields for work in the movement. Mrs. Sanger recently returned from India,
                    where, in the course of nearly four months, she gave 104 lectures.</p></q>
            <q who="RTU"><p>
                    <person reg="Gandhi, Mahatma">Mahatma Gandhi</person>, whom Mrs,. Sanger saw for
                    three days at <place reg="Wardha, India">Wardha</place>, agrees entirely with
                    the birth control movement in principle, she said, adding that Gandhi’s
                    political power has waned considerably although his spiritual power is still
                    vitally evident.</p></q>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Problems to be Solved</head>
            <q who="RTU"><p> Gandhi believes, she said, that India should cease producing multitudes
                    of children until the health of the nation, the stupendous food problem and the
                    inroads of disease have been solved.</p></q>
            <q who="RTU"><p> Work in the Orient is facilitated by absence of laws, spiritual and
                    governmental, opposed to the movement, Mrs. Sanger said.</p></q>
            <q who="RTU"><p> In company with Mrs. <person reg="Fry, Marion W.">Luther C.
                        Fry</person>, birth control leader in Monroe County, Mrs. Sanger visited the
                        <place reg="Rochester, NY">Rochester</place> center this morning. She is a
                    guest at the home of Mrs. <person reg="Gannett, Mary T. L.">Mary T. L.
                        Gannett</person>, 15 Sibley Place.</p></q>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head> Mrs. Sanger Makes Please for Birth Control Urging Amendment to Present U.S. Law
                Information Needed for Public Health, City Club Told </head>
            <q who="RDC"><p> Public health measures and birth control legislation march hand in
                    hand, Mrs. Margaret Sanger, champion of women, told the City Club yesterday at
                    luncheon in Hotel Seneca.</p></q>
            <p> “When public health measures are enacted to allow all classes to live in better
                health, to decrease mortality rates and to lengthen life,” <q who="RDC">she
                    said,</q> “it becomes absolutely necessary to control the number of births by
                similar measures. Otherwise we shall have a heavily overpopulated country.”</p>
            <q who="RDC"><p> Dissemination of birth control information is a public problem, she
                    declared, and federal legislation will be introduced at the impending session of
                    Congress to provide a scientific and adequate national program for limitation of
                    births. </p></q>
            <p> “I urge the immediate amendment of the present federal laws which tie the hands of
                the physician and obstruct an adequate and scientific national birth control
                program,” <q who="RDC">she said.</q> “More than 1,000 organizations with millions of
                members have endorsed our efforts to change these obsolete federal laws and 100,000
                individuals have personally pledged support.” </p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Names Three Conditions</head>
            <q who="RDC"><p> The crisp-spoken little woman who was greeted by the police when she
                    arrived in Rochester to speak before the City Club 20 years ago laid down a
                    triple set of conditions which determine the number of children which any family
                    can bear. Determining factors are: (1) number which a family can support; (2)
                    number which a mother can bear and care for; (3) number within which a family
                    can maintain its standard of living. </p></q>
            <q who="RDC"><p> Birth control does not necessarily mean limitation, Mrs. Sanger said,
                    although it is desirable for the population of the United States to remain
                    stationary for 20 years until the various groups present in the country are
                    assimilated. </p></q>
            <q who="RDC"><p> Opposition and apathy spring from the so-called “leaders,” she said, in
                    the campaign for control of population. The masses don’t need education to
                    accept its philosophy, but rather ask scientific methods of practice, she said.
                    Officials in government office are either opposed or fearful of expressing a
                    public opinion on the subject, she declared. </p></q>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Cites General Demand</head>
            <q who="RDC"><p> As evidence of the fact that the poorer classes demand birth control
                    education uniformly despite religious teachings, she pointed to the proportions
                    of women who appear at <place reg="New York, NY">New York</place> centers.
                    Protestant religions contribute 33 per cent, Catholic 32 per cent and Jewish 31
                    per cent, she said.</p></q>
            <q who="RDC"><p> Theories of opposition which hold that birth control “destroys life”
                    are fallacious, she said.</p></q>
            <p> “The mere prevention of the fusion of two life cells can no more be classes as
                destruction of life than remaining unmarried or living in continence,” <q who="RDC"
                    >Mrs. Sanger flared.</q></p>
            <q who="RDC"><p> That birth control would reduce the white race while other races
                    increase is a false argument against it, she said. Birth control has been
                    introduced, is being taught and is being increasingly practiced in Japan, China
                    and India, she declared.</p></q>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub"> Cites Toll of Women</head>
            <q who="RDC"><p> Women are losing their lives by bearing more children than is
                    physically feasible; children are dying needlessly because of lack of care; and
                    families are reduced to poverty, Mrs. Sanger charged, because the world fails to
                    take action in regard to birth control.</p></q>
            <q who="RDC"><p> Questioned in the City Club forum about the influence of birth control
                    information among unmarried persons and its relation to immorality, she charged
                    that birth control will produce neither morality nor immorality. Morality or its
                    opposite comes from the human himself, she said, mere information will have no
                    bearing upon it.</p></q>
            <p>
                <q who="RDC">Mrs. Sanger yesterday was named winner of the award of the honor
                    offered annually by the <org>Town Hall Club of New York City</org> for the</q><q
                    who="THC"> “most conspicuous contribution to the enlargement and enrichment of
                    life.”</q></p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
