<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/07/15 AS encoded</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-08-15 CH proof and enter</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1916-06-14">14 Jun 1916</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied>Speech to the California Civic League</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp422036</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Birth Control Lectures End</title>, <title type="journal"
                    >San Francisco Examiner</title>, June 14, 1916, p. 7.</bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="SFE">San Francisco Examiner</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>For a draft of the speech Sanger likely gave, see “<xref
                from="128002.xml">Woman and Birth Control</xref>," Apr-July 1916. She likely altered
            it given the fact that California women had the vote in 1916.</p>
        <index level1="California" level2="birth control movement in"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="MS on"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>BIRTH CONTROL LECTURES END</head>
        <q who="SFE"><p><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person> says she looks to
                the women of <place>California</place> to take the first steps that will place this
                country on the same basis with European countries in the matter of birth
                control.</p>
            <p>She declared yesterday in her talk before the <place reg="Oakland, CA"
                    >Oakland</place> center of the <org>California Civic League</org> in <org>Hotel
                    Oakland</org> that the women of California, with the power of suffrage, could
                bring about the repeal of the laws against the dissemination of information about
                birth control, and by so doing could set the pace for the whole country along this
                line.</p></q>
        <p>"This is my last appearance here," said Mrs. Sanger. "I leave to-morrow for <place
                reg="Portland, OR">Portland,</place> on my way to the East again. I shall return in
            October and I hope that by that time you women will have made decided progress toward
            getting the laws repealed that now forbid your physician to tell you the vital facts of
            life.</p>
        <p>"When I return to California and find that California women have accomplished this I
            shall immediately begin the installation of scientifically conducted clinics, where this
            information can be given to the working women-in other words, to those who need it most
            and who find it hardest to obtain."</p>
    </docBody>
</doc>
