<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published statement">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-07-03 MM</prepDate>
        <docAuthor><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1914-04-11"><supplied resp="MSPP">11 Apr 1914</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Statement on Woman Rebel Case</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp422005</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Free-Thinking Editor Defies Government to Suppress Her
                    Paper</title>, Unidentified newspaper. April 11, 1914</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p/><index level1="Woman Rebel, The" level2="suppression of"/><index
            level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/><index
            level1="children" level2="rights of"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>FREE-THINKING EDITOR DEFIES GOVERNMENT TO SUPPRESS HER PAPER</head>
        <p>"I intend to continue making public my ideas through my paper if I have to go to jail for
            it."</p>
        <p>"No Gods; no masters," is the motto of "<title type="journal">The Woman Rebel</title>,"
            which, Mrs. Sanger says, is published for "an advanced, thinking frankly speaking
            feminine clientile"</p>
        <p>"Inform the working people and you will place a great weapon in their hands" she declared
            to-day to an <title type="journal">Evening Journal</title> reporter. It is a woman's
            duty to have an ideal and to speak and act in defiance of conventions.</p>
        <p>Over on the other side, I noticed the difference in the manner in which children are
                <unclear resp="MSPP">treated</unclear> In <place>Scotland</place> you see a woman
            with a flock of children at her heels crying for bread. In almost all of the cities,
            children are treated as dogs and not as individuals. In <place>France</place>, where it
            is lawful to give out information of this character, everyone seems glad to have
            children, but not too many of them. Every encouragement is given to childbirth.</p>
        <p>"Over here we seem to have no consideration for children. We breed them wholesale,
            especially in the poorer sections of the city where children amount to no more than dogs
            in the street. </p>
        <p>"I believe that woman has been enslaved by the machinery of the world, by sex
            conventions, by motherhood, by wage slavery, by middle-class morality, by superstition,
            and by custom. Too many children in a poor family mean starvation and children that are
            of no account."</p>
        <p/>
    </docBody>
</doc>
