<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech"> 
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/07/03 MM</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-12-09 CH proof tages and enter</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>
            <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
        </docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1919-11-02">7 Nov 1919</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>
                <supplied resp="MSPP">Speech at the Alkrama Theatre</supplied>
            </titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp422004</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>"<title type="article">Mrs. Sanger Told The Women A Thing or Two</title>" <title
                    type="journal">Independent</title> Nov. 7, 1919, p. 1</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="ECI">Elizabeth City Independent</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>For another version of the speech, see "<xref from="233034.xml"
                >Breaking into the South</xref>," Dec. 1919.</p>
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation"/>
        <index level1="Southern States"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>MRS. SANGER TOLD THE WOMEN A THING OR TWO</head>
        <head type="sub">Unique Climax to First Birth Control Meeting in The South, at <place
                reg="Elizabeth City, NC">Elizabeth City</place> Last Sunday</head>
        <div type="section">
            <q who="ECI">
                <p>When laws prohibiting the dissemination of scientific birth control information
                    are swept away and women are free to control the size of their families,
                    prostitution will cease to be a cancer upon the social body; the race will be
                    stronger, healthier, happier and longer lived. This was one of the arguments for
                    family limitation or scientific birth control advanced by Mrs. <person
                        reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>, of <place
                        reg="New York, NY">New York City</place>, in an address to a mixed audience
                    of 800 or more persons at the <org>Alkrama Theatre</org> in this city Sunday
                    afternoon.</p>
                <p>It was the first public meeting for the discussion of the subject of birth
                    control ever held in the south. The audience that greeted Mrs. Sanger was
                    recruited from every walk of life and many came from miles away, braving
                    inclement weather to hear the message. It was a timid audience at first, an
                    audience that seemed to fear being shocked. But Mrs. Sanger's charming
                    personality put the audience at ease at once and she carried it with her for an
                    hour and a half. </p>
                <p>At the conclusion of her lecture about 200 women remained and crowded around her
                    to ask questions. She had told them that the time had come for women to assert
                    themselves and refuse to wreck their health and happiness by being mere
                    child-breeding machines. And the women wanted to know just how they could do
                    this. Out of her practical experience of fourteen years as a trained nurse,
                    supplemented by her researches in the clinics of several European countries,
                    Mrs. Sanger told the women what they wanted to know. A more astounding, a more
                    revolutionary thing probably never occurred in the staid, conservative old state
                    of North Carolina.</p>
                <p>No, the police did not interfere with Mrs. Sanger. They couldn't. There is no law
                    on the statute books of <place>North Carolina</place> to prevent the dissemination of birth
                    control information by word of mouth. Doctors and lawyers have made the people
                    believe that such laws existed in this state, but North Carolina is one of five
                    states in the union in which the old time law makers forgot to enact a law to
                    prohibit the giving of such information.</p>
                <p>Probably no speaker, excepting speakers for the <org>Red Cross</org> and kindred
                    philanthropies, ever had a more sympathetic audience than that which heard Mrs.
                    Sanger. Mrs. Sanger is an unusual woman, a feminist who has endured years of
                    misunderstanding without getting soured. Thru all of her harsh experiences she
                    has emerged still fresh, sweet, modest and radiant with human kindness and
                    genuine good will. Only such a personality could have discussed the delicate
                    subject of birth control before a mixed audience in a small southern town.</p>
                <p>Mrs. Sanger told her audience that 300,000 babies died in the first year of their
                    infancy in this country each year. She told them that 1,000,000 cases of
                    abortion were reported annually by the medical profession; thousands of mothers
                    braving death itself rather than go thru the agony of bearing unwanted children.
                    She gave the audience out of her experience as a trained nurse many stories of
                    wretched and quarrelsome wives and motehrs, husbands and children unloved and
                    knowing none of the beauties of home life and mother love because the mother was
                    sick and worried and fretted eternally with too many children.</p>
                <p>Mrs. Sanger declared that when information was available to all women, there
                    would be more marriages and earlier marriages with a consequent disappearence of
                    the social evil; that millions of young men and women who wanted to marry were
                    evading the responsibility and resorting to immoral meanas of satisfying their
                    sex life, only because they could not see their way clear to enter into a
                    contract that meant children for which they were not able to provide. She said
                    that in this new era of civilization women are taking places side by side with
                    men in every occupation and department of life and women can not accept this new
                    responsibility without being permitted to say when they should or should not
                    become mothers.</p>
                <p>Mrs. Sanger made a strong plea for the small family of two, three or four
                    children. She declared that any able bodies man could support a wife and two
                    children, whereas many were broken in the struggle to feed the mouths of five or
                    six or nine.</p></q>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">Spoke to Negroes</head>
            <p><q who="ECI"/>Speaking to a colored audience at <org>Corner Stone Baptist Church</org> on Martin Street Sunday evening, Mrs.
                Sanger told the Negroes that they especially should limit the size of their families
                if they would better their own economic condition. She said the Negro cheapened his
                own labor and his own productive power by overbreeding. "You make anything cheap by
                making it plentiful," <q who="ECI">declared the speaker.</q> "And human life is not
                an exception." </p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
