<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Interview">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/07/08 AS encoded</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-08-15 CH proof and edit</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1923-04-08">08 Apr. 1923</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Interview with the New York World</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp422035</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Mrs. Sanger's Birth Control War Carried Around the
                    Globe</title>, <title type="journal">New York World</title>, Apr. 8,
                1923.</bibl>
            <bibl>
                <title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Collected Documents</title> C16:196</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="NYW">New York World</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">Sanger gave this interview in the office of the American Birth Control
        League in New York City. <index level1="birth control clinics and leagues" level2="in US"/>
        <index level1="Brownsville Clinic"/>
        <index level1="children" level2="rights of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="civilization and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="morality of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="propaganda and publicity"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="suppression of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>MRS. SANGER'S BIRTH CONTROL WAR CARRIED AROUND GLOBE</head>
        <p><q who="NYW">WHEN <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person> attempted to
                establish the <org reg="Brownsville Clinic">first Birth Control clinic</org> in
                    <place reg="United States">America</place> a few years ago, the <org
                    reg="New York Police Department">New York police</org> came down on her with a
                heavy hand. Mrs. Sanger and her assistants were arrested and lengthy legal battles
                ensued. Undaunted and undiscouraged, Margaret Sanger set out to change current
                opinion. From the Brownsville district in <place reg="Brooklyn, NY">Brooklyn</place>
                she has carried her message of fewer but better babies completely around the world,
                and finally into the legislative halls of <place reg="Albany, NY"
                >Albany.</place></q></p>
        <p><q who="NYW">Next week, April 10, there will be a hearing in the <org
                    reg="New York State Assembly">Assembly Chamber</org> of a bill to amend the laws
                of the State so that Mrs. Sanger may be enabled to open as many Birth Control
                clinics as she pleases. It will surely be a triumphant moment for her should this
                bill be enacted. For Margaret Sanger has challenged <org
                    reg="United States Government">Federal and State governments</org>. Her books
                have been burned in <place reg="London, England">London,</place> barred from the
                United States mail. <org reg="Japan Government">The Imperial Japanese
                    Government</org> refused her a passport to the land of the cherry blossoms. The
                Japanese people protested, and Margaret Sanger made a triumphant entry into <place
                    reg="Tokyo, Japan">Tokyo.</place></q></p>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">Name Household Word.</head>
            <q who="NYW">
                <p>Her name is a household word in <place>Japan</place> and <place>China,</place> as
                    it is in <place>England</place> and the United States. Sentenced a few years ago
                    to a month's term for distributing Birth Control information, she has eventually
                    won the support of such wealthy and prominent society folks as Mrs. <person
                        reg="Lamont, Florence Haskell">Thomas Lamont,</person> Mr. and <person
                        reg="Chadbourne, Marjorie Curtis">Mrs.</person>
                    <person reg="Chadbourne, Thomas L.">Thomas L. Chadbourne,</person>
                    <person reg="Kahn, Addie Wolff">Mrs. Otto H. Kahn</person> and others prominent
                    in the social and financial world.</p></q>
            <p>"When we started our educational campaign ten years ago, advocating fewer but better
                children," <q who="NYW">declared Margaret Sanger the other day in the offices of the
                        <org>American Birth Control League,</org> No. 104 Fifth Avenue,</q> "we were
                almost childishly naive. We didn't know there were laws which practically
                conscripted the poor mothers of the <place reg="New York">State of New York</place>
                to the unceasing toll of compulsory maternity.</p>
            <p>"Our efforts were all to aid the poor, overburdened mothers of the East Side and the
                congested districts. To my surprise I discovered that there was the blindest and
                most unreasoning prejudice of officialdom against the theory or the practice of
                Birth Control. Thousands and thousands of women appealed to me for help. Twenty-five
                thousand women were dying every year because this knowledge had been refused them.
                Yet every effort to break down the bars of prejudice and ignorance was hampered.
                Birth Control was immoral; it would break up the home. Such were the arguments used
                against it.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">Changing Opinion.</head>
            <p>"I found out that I could not reach the poor women who were crying to me for Birth
                Control information, until the whole current of public opinion had been
                changed."</p>
            <q who="NYW"><p>Since then, says Margaret Sanger, all her efforts have been to awaken
                    public opinion, not only at home but in <place>Europe</place> and in the <place
                        reg="Asia">Orient</place> as well, to the benefits and the morality of Birth
                    Control. The first step in this gigantic task has been to educate the educators,
                    to mobilize the moulders of public opinion.</p></q>
            <p>"We have discovered that there were four steps to our goal: agitation, education,
                organization and legislation. In view of the enormity of the work confronting us, a
                small band of earnest and disinterested women, our progress has been rapid. Whatever
                the outcome of the bill that has been introduced at Albany, which comes up for a
                hearing early this month, its educational value cannot be underestimated.</p>
            <p>"Great and discouraging as the obstacles have been, we have succeeded in enlisting
                the whole-hearted support of the finest intellects of the English-speaking world.
                With such eminent English thinkers as <person reg="Wells, H. G.">H. G.
                    Wells,</person> and <person reg="Ellis, Havelock">Havelock Ellis,</person>
                <person reg="Inge, William Ralph">Dean Inge</person> of <org>St. Paul's
                    Cathedral,</org> London, <person reg="Dawson, Bertrand">Lord Dawson,</person>
                the <person reg="George VII (England)">King</person>'s physician; <person
                    reg="Keynes, John Maynard">John Maynard Keynes,</person> the distinguished
                economist, and <person reg="Russell, Bertrand">Bertrand Russell,</person> throwing
                the weight of their authority into our cause, enlightened public opinion in
                    <place>Great Britain</place> is with us. England leads the world in hospitality
                and fairness to new ideas. I say this despite the fact that an early pamphlet of
                mine has been ordered burnt by a London Police Magistrate.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">Suppression a Boomerang.</head>
            <p>"Such efforts at suppression are, however, boomerangs; they are invaluable to our
                cause as propaganda. Instead of suppressing, they arouse widespread interest and
                support."</p>
            <q who="NYW"><p>It was a study of the Birth Control clinics of <place reg="Netherlands"
                        >Holland,</place> which have been functioning for many years, that convinced
                    Margaret Sanger that personal, hygienic instruction should be given by
                    physicians to women applying for Birth Control information instead of attempting
                    to teach through the printed word. This conviction led to an investigation of
                    the State laws concerning contraceptives. Mrs. Sanger discovered that even duly
                    registered physicians were forbidden by law to offer contraceptive advice, even
                    parents with inheritable diseases were refused such advice in hospitals and
                    public dispensaries.</p>
                <p>Asked if it was her intention to open clinics if the law were changed, Mrs.
                    Sanger replied in the affirmative.</p></q>
            <p>"It may be wrong to speak of these as clinics. We would like to establish free and
                friendly bureaus where the overburdened mothers of the poorer classes might come for
                advice and sympathy. Licensed physicians alone would be permitted to take charge of
                the technical and medical part of the work.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">Care of Babies.</head>
            <p>"But that would be but one aspect of the many benefits to be derived from such
                motherhood centres. We would give these mothers not merely contraceptive advice; we
                would show them in terms all could understand that they must take care of the babies
                they have already brought into the world, so that each child might have a fine
                opportunity of developing into a strong, sturdy man or woman, vigorous enough to
                carry on the torch of our civilization.</p>
            <p>"There is a good deal of chatter nowadays about Americanization. We cannot develop a
                fine race on this great Continent of ours unless we look into the future. We must
                think not only of our own children but the children and the grandchildren of our
                boys and girls.</p>
            <p>"As long as we willfully, as a Nation, waste the most precious resources we have-our
                child life-let us hold our tongues about the dangers of Birth Control. The advocates
                of Birth Control place a higher value on the life of a child than do its opponents.
                We want every child born in this country to bring with it the heritage of health and
                a fine vitality. There is the true wealth of our country.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">For Thoroughbreds.</head>
            <p>"Let us breed a race of thorough-breds! You cannot measure the greatness of a country
                by its industrial resources, in dollars and cents, or financial power. You can
                measure it only in the fine types of manhood and womanhood you produce, in the
                beauty and happiness of your children, in the talent and genius of poets,
                philosophers and artists."</p>
            <p>"Let us Americans give up that lamentable habit of counting our greatness only by the
                dollar sign, only in the number of billions of dollars, or millions of inhabitants
                we have."</p>
            <q who="NYW"><p>The objection was made by the interviewer that perhaps the classes most
                    in need of Birth Control could not be taught to exercise it, due to mental
                    defect, irresponsibility or recklessness.</p></q>
            <p>"Until we have responded to the piteous appeals of thousands upon thousands of
                normal, intelligent wives who already realize their responsibility and their duty
                toward their children born and unborn," replied Margaret Sanger, "such an objection
                is, neither immediate nor important. We believe that the feeble-minded and the
                incurable mental defective should not be permitted to increase and multiply. Every
                new instrument invented to further civilization has been opposed as dangerous and
                inimical to mortality. There are all sorts of automobile accidents every day-but we
                do not look upon motor cars as immoral. Airplanes have caused the death of hundreds
                yet we do not condemn them as unnatural."</p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
