<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-07-02 AS encoded</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-08-15 CH proof and edit</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1922-02-19"><supplied resp="MSPP">19 Feb 1922</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">The Necessity for Birth Control in the United
                    States</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp422010</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Mrs. Sanger's Talk Gets By Police Censors</title>, <title
                    type="journal">San Francisco Chronicle</title>, Feb. 19, 1922, p. 3</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="SFC">San Francisco Chronicle</name>
            <name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Sanger spoke before 1200 people in a mass meeting sponsored by
                <org>American Women's Independence Committee</org> at California Hall in <place
                reg="San Francisco, CA">San Francisco.</place> 625 Polk Street 94102.</p>
        <index level1="race suicide"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="class-based"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="infant"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="maternal"/>
        <index level1="motherhood"/>
        <index level1="California" level2="birth control movement in"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="international"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="conferences on"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>MRS. SANGER'S TALK GETS BY POLICE CENSORS</head>
        <div type="section">
            <p>"Birth control does not mean race suicide," <q who="SFC">declared <person
                        reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger,</person> head of the <org
                        reg="American Birth Control League">Birth Control league,</org> in an
                    address yesterday afternoon before an audience in <org reg="California Hall"
                        >California hall.</org> "</q>Scientific birth control has already operated
                in a number of countries such as <place reg="Netherlands">Holland,</place>
                <place>New Zealand</place> and others, for sufficient time to demonstrate that
                instead of race suicide the percentage of infant survivals has been greatly
                increased with a better type and class of manhood and a decrease in population."</p>
            <p><q who="SFC">The speaker traced the history of birth control, maintaining that it was
                    not a new idea. She said it was, in fact, one of nature's fundamental laws, as
                    is the natural course of events without the interference of science, nature will
                    weed out the sick, the old and feeble and the diseased to make room for the
                    strong and healthy.</q></p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">DESCRIBES TWO GROUPS</head>
            <p><q who="SFC">Mrs. Sanger declared that the human race has divided broadly into two
                    classes, the large family group and the small family group. She insisted that in
                    the latter group are to be found culture, leisure, wealth and two or three
                    children, who are brought up under the best conditions, sent to universities and
                    given every advantage in life. In the large family group, according to the
                    speaker, are found poverty, misery, the tenement life, infant and maternal
                    mortality and the breeding place of all today's vital sociological
                problems.</q></p>
            <p>"Yet it is from the former group that the greatest clamor comes against giving to the
                latter group the information which allows the small family group to be what it is,"
                    <q who="SFC">said the speaker.</q></p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">DEFENDS BIRTH CONTROL</head>
            <p>"Not only do we want to protect society from further propagation of the sick and
                insane," said Mrs. Sanger, "but we want to make motherhood a conscious and voluntary
                act, giving her a chance to develop her own indviduality and that of her
                children.</p>
            <p>"You have been told that birth control is against the laws of <name type="deity"
                    >God</name>. I say to you that if you, as an indivudal, believe in God as a
                divine intelligence who has endowed you with the power to think and to reason, then
                you certainly are at liberty to apply that intelligence according to the dictates of
                your conscience.</p>
            <p>"Every advance in science has been attacked in this same manner. It is against the
                laws of nature for a man to shave, to cut his hair, to walk on two legs instead of
                four, to ride in street cars, or to submit to an operation to save his life, just as
                much as it is against those laws for him to practice birth control," <q who="SFC"
                    >said the speaker</q>.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">WANTS SCIENTIFIC CLINICS</head>
            <p>"What we need at present is scientific clinics at which the fundamentals of birth
                control can be taught. We should get away from the backyard gossip and through the
                    <unclear>clinic</unclear> bring to the poor woman who cannot afford to pay for
                it under the present conditions the same information that the rich woman gets
                today."</p>
            <p><q who="SFC">The speaker denied that birth control would result in race suicide. She
                    maintained that the maternal instinct is so great in women that they will
                    perform the sacred duty of bearing and rearing children, but that with control
                    an established fact the work will be done under conditions which are best for
                    both mother and child.</q></p>
            <p><q who="SFC">Mrs. Sanger told of being excluded from <place>Japan,</place> but
                    expressed the hope that this ban would eventually be lifted. She emphasized the
                    need of the doctrine in Japan, saying,</q></p>
            <p>"When the pressure of population gets too great in any country there can be but two
                ways of relief. One is war, with its attendant loss of life and possible increase in
                territory in the case of the victor and the other is through scientific birth
                control. Of the two, I believe that the latter is by far the better way."</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">WILL GO TO <place>ENGLAND</place></head>
            <p><q who="SFC">The speaker said that she will continue her journey to the <place
                        reg="Asia">Orient,</place> lecturing in <place>China</place> and
                        <place>India,</place> and going on to England, where she will attend an <org
                        reg="International Neo-Malthusuan and Birth Control Conference, 5th"
                        >international conference on birth control.</org></q></p>
            <p><q who="SFC"><person reg="Parson, Mary">Mrs. Mary Parson</person> acted as chairman
                    of the meeting, introducing the speaker. During the questioning which followed
                    the regular lecture a woman in the audience asked, </q>"<q who="UNK">is there
                    any book now published which gives inside information on birth control</q>"</p>
            <p><q who="SFC">Mrs. Sanger smiled and, nodding toward the door of the hall,
                    answered,</q> "There are two policemen standing at the door who would be very
                glad to know the answer to that question."</p>
            <p><q who="SFC">A detail of plain clothes offiers was present at the meeting. <person
                        reg="Eisenhart, Katherine">Mrs. Katherine Eisenhart</person> was a member of
                    the detail. No action was taken by the officers to stop the lecture or to
                    prevent the distribution of pamphlets, which were given out at the door.</q></p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
