<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger" "file:/S:/TRANSCRIPTIONS/XML%20Drafts/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published statement">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/07/08 MM</prepDate>
        <docAuthor><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret
            Sanger</person></docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1953-09-28">28 Sept 1953</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Statement on Her Swedish Trip</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp422008</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="newspaper"><place>Arizona</place> Daily
                    Star</title> 08/28/1953</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">Sanger spoke to the press on arriving back in <place
            reg="Tuscon, AZ">Tuscon</place> after attending the Fourth
        International Conference on Planned Parenthood in <place>Stockholm,
            Sweden</place>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="international"/><index
            level1="Sweden"/><index level1="planned parenthood"/><index
            level1="Italy" level2="overpopulation and"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Birth Control Leader Ends Swedish Trip</head>
        <byline>Margaret Sanger Slee Tells of Country's Parenthood Plan</byline>
        <p>"<place>Sweden</place> and the other Scandinavian countries are much
            more highly educated in sex matters than America," according to Mrs.
            Margaret Sanger Slee, who returned to Tuscon last night after
            becoming president of the International Planned Parenthood
            federation last week in Stockholm.</p>
        <p>She arrived by plane from <place reg="Tulsa, OK">Tulsa,
            Okla.</place>, where she became fatigued from motoring from
                <place>New York</place> with her Tuscon friend and companion,
                <person reg="McNamee, Dorothy">Dorothy McNamee</person>.</p>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Outstanding Advocate</head>
            <p>The world's outsanding advocate of planned parenthood declared
                that Sweden planned parenthood organization has more than
                100,000 members, and is subscribed to financially by the
                king.</p>
            <p>She said the Swedish nation has backed the organization for many
                years and with money raised through dues is actively extending
                the program to Lapland.</p>
            <p>The planned parenthood conference held great interest in Sweden,
                she said, and was top news in papers there all week, sharing
                page one headlines with the Kinsey report on reviews which
                appeared during the conference.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Conference Work</head>
            <p>The work of the conference, which was the fourth international
                assembly of the federation, was to establish a constitution. She
                said that a legal reveiw of the constitution will be made soon
                in America by the national organization's attorneys. It will
                then be availible to the public.</p>
            <p>Mrs. Slee visited cities in <place>Finland</place>,
                    <place>Norway</place> and <place>Denmark</place> as well as
                in <place>England</place>, and said she was surprised to find
                her name so well known.</p>
            <p>She said her task as president of the federation is to "explore"
                the site of the next conference, which will be held in two
                years; set an agenda, and raise the money for the conference.
                Invitations to become host to the next conference have already
                been extended by <place>Holland</place> and
                <place>Japan</place>, she said.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">600 Clinics</head>
            <p>From a start in 1916, more than 600 clinics have been launched in
                America, of which more than 500 are still in existence. Tuscon's
                clinic is lcoated at 28 East Corral street.</p>
            <p>Work of the organization and its new constitution will next be
                discussed in Tuscon by <person reg="Rau, Rama">Lady Rama
                    Rau</person>, of India, with whom Margaret Sanger was
                co-president of the federation during the past two years. Lady
                Rau will speak before the Sunday Evening Forum Oct. 25. </p>
            <p>Mrs. Sanger commented that <place>Italy</place> as well as some
                other European countries have long been known to demographers as
                a "danger spot," with serious problems in respect to the living
                space for its population.</p>
            <p>Ambassador to Itality <person reg="Luce, Clare">Clare
                    Luce</person> recently wrote an article for Newsweek and
                other national magazines that Italy needs a solution to her
                population problems.</p>
            <p>Commenting on the article, Mrs. Sanger said, "Mrs. Luce is too
                intelligent a woman not to already know the solution to that
                problem."</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">Now Practiced</head>
            <p>She said planned parenthood is now being practiced
                surreptitiously in Italy. A doctor was recently arrested in
                Italy for giving planned parenthood information, she said, but
                he was acquitted. That is a good start," she said "The Italian
                people are intelligent, she commented, "It is just a matter of
                getting in there and replying to their questions."</p>
            <p>Mrs. Slee said she plans to remain in Tuscon for an extended time
                before she accepts speaking engagements in connection with her
                office. she has lived in Tuscon for many years at 65 Sierra
                Vista drive. </p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
