<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-06-25 CH proofed </prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1923-03-01">1 Mar 1923</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Speech to the North Harlem Community Forum</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp422012</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Birth Control Advocate Speaks to Large Audience at Public Library</title> Mar. 7 1923</bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="NYAN">New York Amsterdam News</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Sanger spoke to the North Harlem Community Forum at the 135 Street branch of the <org>New York Public Library</org> on March 1.</p>
        <index level1="New York" level2="birth control laws and legislation"/>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="birth control laws and legislation in"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of" level3="negative consequences of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="class-based"/>
        <index level1="infanticide"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="population and"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Birth Control Advocate Speaks to Large Audience at Public
        Library</head>
        <q who="NYAN"><p><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Mrs. Margaret Sanger,</person> whose activities for birth control has brought her world wide attention, spoke last Thursday to a large audience in a meeting held by the North Harlem Community Forum, at the <place reg="New York, NY">135th St. Branch Public Library.</place> She spoke on her recent trip to the <place reg="Asia">Orient</place> and told of her work in general.</p>
        <p>The women of <place>China</place> and <place>Japan</place> are very keen for their emancipation, she said, much more so than American women.</p></q> <p>"I am deeply disappointed in the women of America," she said, "they have the vote but have accomplished almost nothing toward their emancipation."</p>
        <q who="NYAN"><p><div type="section"><head type="sub">Too Many Children.</head></div></p></q>
        <p>"The women of the Orient are retarded by having too many babies," she said, "and they are beginning to understand this. They are eager for birth control. When I landed in <place reg="Yokohama, Japan">Yokohoma</place> a delegation of Japanese women came to see me and their spokesman said, <q who="UNK">'When your message came it was the light that we had long sought in vain.'</q> Even the ricksha man welcomed my message. Out of 105 leading newspapers 81 carried front page articles about birth control. Of course, the <org reg="Japan, Government of">Japanese Government</org> is oppposed to it."</p>
        <q who="NYAN"><p>She told of pathetic instances of American mothers who had applied to her for birth control information and of how she could not help because of the law preventing the dissemination of such information. She said 6,997 mothers had applied to her for information.</p>
        <p><div type="section"><head type="sub">Rich Have Birth Control.</head></div></p></q>
        <p>"American women are divided into two classes," said the speaker, "those who have birth control and those who have not. Rich women can get all the knowledge on this subject they want, and if it is good for them it is also good for the poor, who cannot afford to rear large families, like the rich.</p>
        <p>"Mankind has always practised birth control. Infanticide and foeticide dates back to the earliest ages. In ancient <place>Greece,</place> <place>Egypt,</place> and <place>Sparta</place> unwelcome babies were exposed for 45 hours and if they survived were permitted to live. In China today girl babies are thrown into the canals. The modern system of birth control aims to restrict excessive populations in a more humane way. It also saves the strength and energy of the mother for her other duties, and for the care of such children she may already have."</p>
        <q who="NYAN"><p>Several policemen were on hand to see that Margaret Sanger issued no birth control information.</p></q>


        <p/>
    </docBody>
</doc>
