<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Statement">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-06-24 MM </prepDate>
        <docAuthor><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1922-02-21">
            <supplied resp="MSPP">21 Feb 1922</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Statement on Japanese Visa</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp422011</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>San Fransisco Chronicle</title> 02/21/1922</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Sanger spoke to <place reg="San Fransisco, California">San
                Francisco</place> reporters about the possibility of traveling to
                <place>Japan</place>.</p>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="speaking tours" level3="1922 (Japan)"/><index
            level1="Japan" level2="overpopulation and"/><index level1="Japan" level2="censorship in"
        />
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>MRS. SANGER TO SAIL TOMORROW FOR FAR EAST</head>
        <div>
            <p>No matter what may be the views of the Japanese government on the delicate subject of
                birth control, Mrs. Margaret Sanger, head of the <org
                    reg="American Birth Control League">Birth Control League</org> in the United
                States, has no intention of being deterred from entering Japan on that account.</p>
            <p>Mrs. Sanger, who is visiting San Fransisco, was much encouraged yesterday by an
                Associated Press dispatch from Tokyo announcing that the Japanese government has no
                objection to her landing in the country provided she does not attempt to disseminate
                her ideas.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">IS NOT SURPRISED</head>
            <p>"I am not surprised," she said. "When the Japanese authorities here refused to vise
                my passport my <place>New York</place> office at once got into communication with
                    <place reg="Tokyo, Japan">Tokyo</place>, and undoubtedly the moderation of the
                official order has been brought about by pressure in the Japanese capital by the
                more liberal group there. Well, I'm glad of it, and besides all this excitement
                about my not being permitted to land will stir interest in what I have to say.
                That's good advertising."</p>
            <p>Mrs. Sanger will carry out her original intention, she said, and sail for Japan
                aboard the T.K.K. liner Taiyo Maru tomorrow. She will be the guest of <person reg="Kato, Shidzue">Baroness
                Ishimoto</person>, leader of the brith control movement in Japan, while in Toyko.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">OVERPOPULATION BIG PROBLEM</head>
            <p>Birth control ought to result in Japan in a movement which will have an important
                indirect bearing on world peace, in Mrs. Sanger's opinion.</p>
            <p>"By helping to prevent overpopulation," she explained, "birth control will remove the
                immediate pressure which is one of the chief causes of conflicts between nations.
                Japan's greatest problem is overpopulation."</p>
            <p>Yesterday's Associated Press dispatch from Tokyo pointed out that the refusal to vise
                Mrs. Sanger's passport was on the ground that propaganda along the line she proposed
                was illegal in Japan and an improper subject for public discussion. Instructions
                sent here by the foreign office, however, were not to be interpreted as meaning that
                she would be denied admission to the country.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head type="sub">TO FORBID LECTURE</head>
            <p>Japan's intention, according to <person reg="Akamatsu, Yusuke">Yusuke Akamatsu</person>, chief of the immigration section of
                the foreign office, was to warn Mrs. Sanger that she would not be permitted to
                lecture, and to forestall any complaint that she did not know the Japanese attitude
                in advance.</p>
        </div>

    </docBody>
</doc>
