<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published interview">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014/05/28 MM</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-12-19 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1916-05-19">19 May 1916</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Press Interview in St. Louis</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422019</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Mrs. Sanger Tells of Her Propaganda for Birth
					Control</title>, <title>St. Louis Star</title>, May 20, 1916</bibl>
			<bibl><title type="article">Mrs. Sanger Here to Spread Gosepl of Birth Control</title>,
					<title type="journal">St. Louis Post-Dispatch</title>, May 19, 1916</bibl>
			<bibl><person reg="Martyn, Marguerite">, </person><title type="article">Mrs. Sanger, Who
					Defies Federal Law, Outlines Her Work for Birth Control Among the Poor</title>,
					<title type="journal">St. Louis Post-Dispatch</title>, May 21, 1916.</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="SLS">St. Louis Star</name>
			<name id="MARMA">Martyn, Marguerite</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP"><p>On her arrival in <place reg="St. Louis, MO">St. Louis</place>, Sanger
			spoke to reporters. These comments were published in three articles, one by the St.
			Louis Star and two from the St. Louis Post-Dispatch. Repeated portions of the interview
			were not included. </p>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="morality of"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="propaganda and publicity"/>
		<index level1="Netherlands, the" level2="birth control in"/>
		<index level1="working classes" level2="birth control and"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<div type="section">
			<head>MRS. SANGER TELLS OF HER PROPAGANDA FOR BIRTH CONTROL</head>
			<dateline><supplied resp="MSPP"><date value="1916-05-20">May 20,
				1916</date></supplied></dateline>
			<q who="SLS"><p>Mrs. Sanger says she has no message for the rich woman, or even the
					middle class woman--as she believes both already are in possession to a great
					extent of the information she is giving women of the working classes and of
					foreign birth.</p></q>
			<p>"Every woman wants this information," <q who="SLS">she said today.</q> "And as long
				as I believe this to be the case, I shall continue to defy the federal
				authorities.</p>
			<p>"When I was indicted it was on the charge that my pamphlet '<title type="book">Family
					Limitation</title>' was 'obscene.' When the indictment was dropped, the federal
				authorities intimated that it was because I virtually had agreed not to use the
				mails further.</p>
			<p>"But I did not agree, and they knew I would not refrain from the use of the mails. I
				told them at the time that no true woman could retain her self-respect if she
				permitted herself to be frightened off, and that I intended to spread my propaganda.
				And I have continued to do so."</p>
			<p>"No workingman is able to support more than two children." <q who="SLS">Mrs. Sanger
					said.</q> "The workingman makes an average salary of $10 a week. On this he
				cannot afford to let his wife bring into the world more than two children. He cannot
				take care of them."</p>
			<q who="SLS"><p>Mrs. Sanger was asked if she did not believe it better for those who
					were unwilling to assume the responsibilities of parenthood to remain
					unmarried.</p></q>
			<p>"Decidedly no," <q who="SLS">she replied.</q> "I think it is much more moral for a
				fine young man to take a girl as wife, and raise two or three children to be decent,
				moral, upright citizens. But if they can have other children only by jeopardizing
				the futures of all, by throwing some into charitable institutions and others into
				jail, is not my plan of helping them to hold down the size of the family much
				better?"</p>
			<p>
				<q who="SLS">"But suppose you are putting means into people's hands of bringing race
					suicide?" it was suggested. </q>
			</p>
			<p>"I hardly think we need consider that," she said. All women who are fit to be mothers
				want to be mothers. The majority are willing to be the mother of two or three
				children, or even more, according to their circumstances.</p>
			<p>"As for the women who do not want to be mothers and would use this knowledge to
				prevent such a happening--is such a woman fit to bring a child into this world?
				Wouldn't she bear an unloved boy or girl? Children must be born right; and one of
				the first principles of being born right is to be born of love and longing."</p>
			<p>"Only persons fogyish in their views ever advance that argument." <q who="SLS">she
					said. </q>"It has nothing to do with Christianity."</p>
			<p>"I decided to avoid imprisonment," <q who="SLS">she said</q> "at least until I had
				given out my information. One hundred thousand copies of a pamphlet '<title
					type="article">Family Limitation</title>,' were prepared and distributed and I
				sailed for <place>England</place>.</p>
			<p>"There I discussed my work with many prominent persons and it was indorsed by such
				thinkers as <person type="Wells, H. G.">H. G. Wells</person> and <person
					reg="Bennett, Arnold">Arnold Bennett</person>, the novelists; <person
					reg="Ellis, Havelock">Havelock Ellis</person>, noted sociologist; <person
					reg="Carpenter, Edward">Edward Carpenter</person> and <person
					reg="Murray, Gilbert">Gilbert Murray</person>--the latter a professor at <org
					reg="Oxford University">Oxford</org>.</p>
			<p>"My sole desire has been to throw the matter open for discussion. I am not so anxious
				actually to put means of birth control in women's hands, as to have the world of men
				and women stop and think and determine for themselves if it will not be better for
				all to have this information."</p>
			<p/>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head>MRS. SANGER HERE TO SPREAD GOSPEL OF BIRTH CONTROL</head>
			<dateline><supplied resp="MSPP"><date value="1916-05-19">19 May 1916
				</date></supplied></dateline>
			<p>"I was prompted by my experience as a nurse and as a mother to take up this
				propaganda. In my work as a nurse on <place reg="New York, NY">New York</place>'s
				East Side I saw that there was overbreeding of the least desirable elements, which
				was not making for a racial improvement.</p>
			<p>If I had been all the time on the East Side I might have become hardened to the
				conditions, as others do, but I returned each night to my own home and my three
					<person reg="Sanger, Stuart"><person reg="Sanger, Grant"><person
							reg="Sanger, Peggy">babies</person></person></person>, and the contrast
				inspired me to do what I could to improve conditions among the poor by limitation of
				their families.</p>
			<p/>
			<p>"Birth control does not lead to race suicide. I studied the problem four years in
				England, Holland, <place>France</place> and <place>Spain</place>. In <place
					reg="Netherlands">Holland</place> there are <unclear resp="MSPP"
				>52</unclear>clinics where married women are taught by nurses how to exercise birth
				control. This has been done for 30 years. The result is that Holland has the lowest
				general death rate in <place>Europe</place>. The infant mortality in <place
					reg="Amsterdam, Netherlands">Amsterdam </place>and <place
					reg="The Hague, Netherlands">The Hague</place> is lower than in any other city
				in the world. There are fewer births, but the babies that are born have a better
				chance to survive, and the population goes on increasing.</p>
			<p>"<place>New Zealand</place> has had birth control clinics for 20 years, and the
				infant mortality in that country is also low. Commercialized vice is almost unknown
				in both countries.</p>
			<p>"In <place reg="United States">this country</place> there has never been a clinic for
				the instruction of married women. I want to see them established in every city.
				Interest has been manifested by St. Louis nurses and social workers, and something
				has been done toward organizing a branch of the <org>National Birth Control
					League</org>, which has already spread to 12 states. </p>
			<p>"Unfortunately there is a Federal statute which forbids the use of the mails to
				disseminate such information, and there are hindering laws in some of the states.
				The object of the National Birth Control League is to bring about the repeal of
				these laws, so that nurses and doctors can be free to give instruction.</p>
			<p>"In European countries, except Holland and New Zealand, the information is
				disseminated improperly. I want it done here properly, by doctors and nurses. Such
				information will go far toward preventing the illegal operations which cause the
				death of thousands of women.</p>
			<p>"The objection is made that the dissemination of this knowledge will encourage
				immortality. But the women of the upper classes have possessed this knowledge and it
				will hardly be said that the knowledge has encouraged immortality among them."</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head>Mrs. Sanger, Who Defies Federal Law, Outlines Her Work for Birth Control Among the
				Poor</head>
			<dateline><supplied resp="MSPP"><date value="1916-05-21">21 May
				1916</date></supplied></dateline>
			<p>"Be sure to say that I am married and have three children," <q who="MARMA">was her
					first remark.</q> "My <person reg="Sanger, William">husband</person> is an
				artist. When we were first married he still was having quite a struggle to get
				along. So I continued at my profession and we waited five years before we decided to
				have a baby.</p>
			<p>"My <person reg="Sanger, Henrietta Wolffberg">husband's mother</person> came to live
				with us then, so I could go on working. We waited another five years before we asked
				for and received another baby. By this time we had become so safely established that
				as soon as my arms began to yearn to be filled again, inside of <unclear resp="MSPP"
					>30</unclear> months, our last baby was born.</p>
			<q who="MARMA"><p>How do you limit the channels into which your information shall go? I
					asked of her.</p></q>
			<p>"With the organization of responsible communities, who can investigate each
				individual case," <q who="MARMA">she responded.</q></p>
			<p>"Personally, I think everybody is entitled to all the know,ledge that is availible,
				as it is abroad.</p>
			<p>"It is therefore necessary that those committees be comprised of reputable physicians
				or nurses. I prefer nurses as disseminators of the information myself, because they
				have the opportunity for more individual observation. But medical men object.</p>
			<p>"And my great aim, of course, is eventually to get the endorsement of the <org
					reg="American Medical Association">National Medical Association</org>.</p>
			<p>"It was in my work as a trained nurse I so often was confronted with this problem
				that I decided finally to rebel.</p>
			<p>Much of my work was in the slums. It seems to me the responsibility is ours, not the
				ignorant mothers' nor the brutal fathers',"<q who="MARMA"> she said.</q></p>
			<p>"It is becoming more and more customary for women of the working class to continue at
				their wage earning after marriage. And surely this is an improvement upon the day
				when women were obligated to marry in order to be supported. Why shouldn't the young
				wife as well as the young husband help in the first establishment of a home? The
				birds prepare their nests together.</p>
			<p>"And you observe too, they do not think of having a family without a nest to rear it
				in.</p>
			<p>"I have been watching with great satisfaction the outcome of my theories among many
				happy young pairs in the factory towns where I have talked or sent my
				pamphlets."</p>
			<p>
				<q who="MARMA">"Isn't there always the danger that the wife may become reconciled to
					her childlessness and the husband reconciled to her contributing to the income,
					and the personality of a family become more and more remote?" I suggested.</q>
			</p>
			<p>"No," <q who="MARMA">she responded, her eyes suffused with tenderness, even a little
					blinded, I thought, by sentiment.</q></p>
			<p>"On the contrary, every normal married couple want children. A child planned for and
				prepared for and waited for until a full sense of responsibility is arrived at is
				certainly appreciated."</p>
		</div>

	</docBody>
</doc>
