<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published interview">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014/05/21 CH inital transcription</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-05-21 MM encode</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-12-18 CH proof and enter tags</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1916-10-22">22 Oct 1916</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Interview on the Brownsville Clinic</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422022</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Spread Birth Control</title>, <title type="journal"
					>Washington Post</title>, Oct. 22, 1916</bibl>

		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="WP">Washington Post</name>
			<name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>Sanger was interviewed in a <place reg="New York, NY">New York</place> hotel a few days
			after the <org reg="New York City Police Department">New York City Police</org> raided
			the <org>Brownsville clinic</org>. This interview was published in multiple newspapers,
			including: "<title type="article">Mrs. Sanger Says Moss Is Growing in the Birth
				Law</title>," in <title type="journal">Wilkes-Barre Times</title>, Oct. 21, 1916, p.
			1.</p>
		<index level1="Brownsville Clinic" level2="raid and trials"/>
		<index level1="Brownsville Clinic"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="morality of"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="socio-economic benefits of"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>SPREAD BIRTH CONTROL</head>
		<dateline>New York. <date value="1916-10-21">Oct. 21</date>.--</dateline>
		<div>
			<p>"The poor, century-behind-the-times public officials of this country might just as
				well forget their moss-grown statutes and accept birth control as an established
				fact. My new national plan makes it as inevitable as night and day."</p>
			<p>
				<q who="WP">Mrs. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>, short and
					smiling, with a tinge of red in her hair and more than that in her eye, sat in
					her little two-by-four hotel bedroom and said that here today. Within the last
					48 hours she has established semisecretly in this city the first out-and-out
					birth control clinic in the <place>United States</place>, the law, a Federal
					indictment and numerous arrests all over the country to the contrary
					notwithstanding.</q>
			</p>
		</div>

		<div>
			<head type="sub">Simply Oral Clinic.</head>
			<p>"The police are hunting my clinic today," she went on. "They can't find it. If they
				should, they can't hurt it. It is an oral clinic, and the law says nothing about not
				spreading birth control information orally. If they do try to interfere I am legally
				prepared to carry a hard and bitter fight to the highest tribunal in the land with
				the best legal talent there is."</p>
			<p>"Four more secret clinics will be running in New York within a week. In less than a
				year there will be clinics in <place reg="Washington, DC">Washington</place>, <place
					reg="Cleveland, OH">Cleveland</place>, <place reg="Detroit, MI">Detroit</place>,
					<place reg="St. Paul, MN">St. Paul</place>, <place reg="Minneapolis, MN"
					>Minneapolis</place>,<place reg="Milwaukee, WI"> Milwaukee</place>, <place
					reg="Denver, CO">Denver</place>, <place reg="St. Louis, MO">St. Louis</place>,
					<place reg="Los Angeles, CA">Los Angeles</place>, <place reg="San Francisco, CA"
					>San Francisco</place>, <place reg="San Diego, CA">San Diego</place>, <place
					reg="Portland, OR">Portland</place>, <place reg="Seattle, WA">Seattle</place>,
					<place reg="Spokane, WA">Spokane</place> and <place reg="Butte, MT"
					>Butte</place>. They are every one organized and ready to open the minute I say
				the word. The Washington clinic will open within a few days."</p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<head type="sub">Women Show Interest.</head>
			<p>"Do the women like it? Say, you ought to go down in the neighborhood we have
				canvassed with secret circulars in the last 48 hours. The women have been coming in
				by the dozens. You can hear them calling from house to house in the congested
				districts: <q who="UNK">'Oh, Mrs. Rosenbaum, you ought to see this, this is
					something fine.'</q>"</p>
			<p>"Within two years every man and woman in this country will know how many children
				they can afford to have. And when they know that, I predict that two generations of
				birth control will wipe out all the slums, eliminate the birth of mental defectives,
				minimize the number of humans in insane asylums and automatically put a stop to
				child labor and prostitution."</p>
			<p>"I say it will wipe out child labor because statistics show that 97 per cent of our
				child labor is recruited from families that are too large to be cared for by the
				parents."</p>
		</div>

		<div>
			<head type="sub">Will Aid Morality.</head>
			<p>"I say it will wipe out the worst of prostitution, because statistics prove that 95
				per cent of the girls taken from lives of prostitution and placed in industrial
				homes come from poor parents with nine or more children."</p>
			<p>"Poverty doesn't force these girls into prostituion, but the lack of attention they
				get, with so many children at home, and the general sordid tone of their lives,
				naturally leads them to such a life."</p>
			<p>"My friends and myself are going to bring the people of this country to realize that
				a man making only $15 a week cannot afford to marry, much less have children. And
				they'll learn that the average workingman's family should not exceed two children,
				even under the most favorable physical conditions."</p>
			<p>"This is the work the law and public officials are trying to stop. The poor, blind
				officials really are not to blame. They don't live along in every-day life: they
				simply live in their law books: and as the law is a century behind the times, so are
				the officials."</p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<head type="sub">League in This City.</head>
			<p>
				<q who="WP">Confirmation of Mrs. Margaret Sanger's announcement that Washington is
					soon to have a birth control clinic was made yesterday by officers of the
						<org>Washington Birth Control League</org>. But it will differ, they say,
					from that Mrs. Sanger has in operation in New York, in that it will not be
					secret. Announcement will be made of the time and place through the
					newspapers.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="WP">So long as they do not circulate printed matter, the officer said, they
					will be within the law. And they are condicting a fight for the repeal of the
					"laws which put this country about a century behind the time."</q>
			</p>
		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
