<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Statement">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-06-26 CH proof tags</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1924-03-17">17 Mar 1924</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Statement on Second Marriages</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp422017</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>"Old Loves Best and Second Marriages are Happiest says Mrs. Sanger," unidentified
                newspaper. Mar. 17, 1924</bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="UN">Unidentified Newspaper</name>

        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="love" level2="concept of"/>
        <index level1="marriage"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Old Loves Best And Second Marriages Are Happiest Says Mrs. Sanger</head>
        <q who="UN"><p>Older men make the best lovers.</p>
            <p>So says <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger,</person> noted advocate of
                birth control. News of her marriage to <person reg="Slee, J. Noah">J. Noah
                    Slee,</person> 62-year-old millionaire, leaked out the other day.</p>
            <p>The two were married in 1922, following Mrs. Sanger's return from her world tour in
                the interests of birth control. It had taken just a year and a half of eloquent
                pleading on the part of the elderly millionaire to convince her that she could take
                up the repsonsibilities of married life again as well as run a</p>"cause." <p>But
                finally, Mrs. Sanger did say "yes" and now the portrait of a good-looking,
                gray-haired man adorns her desk.</p></q>
        <p>"Second marriages are happiest," she says, "and older men make the best lovers. If you
            were hunting someone to manage a business wouldn't you want someone with experience?</p>
        <p>"American sentiment has always extolled the young love which promises to last forever and
            forever. But love is a growth and a succession of experiences. It is just as foolish to
            promise to live forever as to promise to love forever.</p>
        <p>"A man who has given his early years to building up a career is hungry for romance. Every
            woman is hungry for romance-far, far more than any man suspects. There is more chance of
            her having the hunger satisfied by an older man than by a younger man.</p>
        <p>"An older man has experience back of him. A young man has only book ideals to guide him.
            He suffers disillusionment when he gets another person within four walls and sees that
            she isn't behaving according to any of the rules."</p>


        <p/>
    </docBody>
</doc>
