<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/06/17 AS</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1916-04-27">27 April 1916</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Speech at the <place reg="Milwaukee, Wisconsin">Hotel
                Wisconsin</place></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp422018</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="journal"><org>Milwaukee Leader</org></title></bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="ML">Milwaukee Leader</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p> </p><index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
        <index level1="mortality rates" level2="infant"/>
        <index level1="Roosevelt, Theodore" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="Wisconsin" level2="birth control"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="morality of"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="arrests and imprisonment"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>SCORES U.S. LAW WHICH BARS TALK ON BIRTH CONTROL</head>
        <q who="ML"><p><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Mrs. Margaret Sanger,</person>
                <place>New York,</place> persecuted for spreading information in the cause of birth
                control, told her story to <place reg="Milwaukee, Wisconsin">Milwaukee</place>
                physicians, club women, suffragists, and others Thursdsay night, in the gold room of
                the Hotel Wisconsin. Policemen and plain clothes men were on hand but Mrs. Sanger
                was not molested.</p></q>
        <p>"Three hundred thousand babies die every year in the <place>United States</place> from
            poverty and neglect, while 600,000 parents remain in ignorance of how to prevent the
            coming of 300,000 more babies to die of poverty and neglect," <q who="ML">said Mrs.
                Sanger.</q></p>
        <q who="ML"><p><div type="section">
                    <head type="sub">WEALTHY WOMEN KNOW</head>
                </div></p></q>
        <p>"Women of wealth know how to regulate birth and have practiced it for 25 years. The
            government forbids the teaching of this knowledge to the working class, and when the
            patient is poor the doctor religiously abides by the law. Poor women want this knowledge
            just as badly as do their wealthier sisters.</p>
        <p>"Am I to be persecuted, slandered and subjected to all sorts of indignities for helping
            these poor souls while <person reg="Roosevelt, Theodore">Theodore Roosevelt</person> can
            go up and down the land shouting and urging them to have larger families? He is not
            molested-no, he is landed to the skies. While I, a woman, am arrested for preventing my
            sisters from producing an unlimited supply of cannon fodder for munition makers and
            professional jingoes.</p>
        <p>"Every department in life is open to discussion and research excepting birth, and woe
            unto him who dares explore that forbidden valley! The scientist may go elsewhere at his
            will and bring back to the public the fruits of his research, but no matter how pure his
            motive, or how high his ideal, slander, imprisonment and persecution at the hands of our
            benevolent government await him who dares invade the forbidden valley. We are as
            ignorant of creation as were our primitive ancestors.</p>
        <p>"The arguments of immorality which they use against us are identical with those used in
            the early struggles against higher education for women. That did not make women
            immoral-we are beginning to see that. We are going to have birth control some day, and
            it will make women no more immoral than has higher education."</p>


        <p/>
    </docBody>
</doc>
