<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published statement">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-06-26 CH transcribed and encoded</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1922-02-17">17 Feb 1922</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Statement on Denial of Japanese
                Visa</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp422009</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Japan Won't Admit Mrs. Sanger, Head of Birth Control
                    League</title>, <title type="journal">New York Tribune</title>, Feb. 18, 1922,
                    <title type="article">Sanger Tour to Japan Stirs Up Row on Lecture</title>,
                    <title type="journal">Oakland Tribune</title>, Feb. 18, 1922, and <title
                    type="article">Birth Control Leader Fights Japanese Ban</title>, <title
                    type="journal">San Francisco Chronicle</title>, Feb. 18, 1922</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="YADSH">Yada, Shichitar&omacr;</name>
            <name id="NYTR">New York Tribune</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Sanger spoke to reporters after her application for a visa to lecture
            in Japan was denied by the Consul General in San Francisco. The text below comes from
            the New York Tribune, with additional portions taken from the Oakland Tribune and the
            San Francisco Chronicle.</p>
        <index level1="Asia" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Asia" level2="overpopulation and"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="propaganda and publicity"/>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="birth control in"/>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="censorship in"/>
        <index level1="overpopulation" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="overpopulation" level2="threat to peace as"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="speaking tours" level3="1922 (Japan)"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <div type="sub">
            <head><place>Japan</place> Won't Admit Mrs. Sanger, Head of Birth Control League</head>
            <dateline>
                <place reg="San Fransciso, CA">SAN FRANCISCO</place>. <date value="1922-02-17">Feb.
                    17</date>.--</dateline>
            <q who="NYTR">
                <p>The <org reg="Japan, Consul General">Japanese Consulate</org> here late to-day
                    announced that instructions had been received from <place reg="Tokyo, Japan"
                        >Tokyo</place> to refuse a visa to a passport of Mrs. <person
                        reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>, of <place
                        reg="New York, NY">New York</place>, head of the <org
                        reg="American Birth Control League">Birth Control League</org>, who is in
                    San Francisco preparing to start on a tour of the <place reg="Asia">Far
                        East</place>. Lack of the visa will prevent her landing in Japan, it was
                    said.</p>
                <p>The <org reg="Japan, Department of Home Affairs">Japanese Department of Home
                        Affairs</org>, through the <org reg="Japan, Foreign Office">Foreign
                        Office</org>, issued this order according to Consul General <person
                        reg="Yada, Shichitar&omacr;">S. Yada</person>. He said Mrs. Sanger would be
                    allowed to book passage upon a Japanese steamship, but that she could not set
                    foot on Japanese soil. </p>
                <p>Mrs. Sanger to-day, not having the proper passport visa, was refused a ticket on
                    the Japanese steamer <name type="ship">Taiyo Maru</name>, sailing from this port
                    February 21. Mr. Yada indicated to-night there was no objection to the steamship
                    company selling her a ticket.</p>
                <p>Mrs. Sanger announced that she intends to sail aboard the Taiyo Maru whether her
                    passport is vised or not, and take chances of being able to effect a landing in
                    Japan.</p></q>
            <p>"Without a doubt the Japanese government feels my lectures in their universities
                would be in direct opposition to their theories of militarism which they have
                fostered in the past and still continue to foster," Mrs. Sanger said.</p>
            <p><q who="NYTR">Consul General Yada asserted that the Japanese government for some time
                    have been opposed to propaganda</q> "<q who="YADSH">of the sort Mrs. Sanger is
                    reported to spread</q>." <q who="NYTR">He said he presumed that was the reason
                    he had been ordered not to vise her passport.</q></p>
            <p>A few days before departing for San Francisco Mrs. Sanger gave out a statement here
                in which she said the Japanese government had decided to take steps against "the
                yellow peril" by instituting a national birth control policy. Mrs. Sanger said she
                had been in conference with <person reg="Kaji, Tokijir&ocirc;">Dr. Kato</person>,
                chief of the <org reg="Japan, Department of Medical Affairs">Departmnent of Medical
                    Affairs</org> of the <org reg="Japan, government of">Japanese government</org>,
                who had been making a study of the birth control movement in the <place>United
                    States</place>, <place>England</place>, <place reg="Netherlands"
                >Holland</place>, and <place>Germany</place>.</p>
            <p>"Dr Kato told me," Mrs. Sanger said, "that the Japanese government is convinced it
                must establish birth control as a nation-wide movement or at once fight a war of
                aggression on the next generation. Dr. Kato points out the population of Japan is
                now 57,000,000 in an area the size of <place>California</place> and that it is
                increasing at the rate of 800,000 a year.</p>
            <p>"For more that a year I have been receiving visits from representative of the
                Japanese government sent out to study birth control. There have been twenty-five of
                these visits in all, representing various departments of the Japanese
                government.</p>
            <p>"Dr. Kato told me last week that the majority of the Japanese government were now
                convinced of the wisdom of birth control and that it only remained for the principle
                to be intelligently communicated to the Japanese people. It has been recognized that
                over-population is the basis of 'the yellow peril.'"</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head><supplied resp="MSPP">Additional quotes from the <title type="journal">Oakland
                        Tribune</title></supplied></head>
            <p>The <org>Kaizo</org>, an organization of young Japanese thinkers, modern to their
                very finger tips, invited me to visit Japan. They are the same faction that invited
                    <person reg="Russell, Bertrand">Bertrand Russell</person> here. They realize as
                I do that Japan with 67,000,000, as opposed to our 110,000,000 has her most serious
                menace in over-population.</p>
            <p>This tremendous population is crowded into a country about the same size as
                California. Added to this handicap, their increase far out totals their death rate.
                Such advanced thinkers as <person reg="Kato, Shidzue Ishimoto">Baroness
                    Ishimoto</person>, who have sponsored my teachings in Japan and who have asked
                me to lecture to the Japanese social workers, realize just what this over-population
                means. It means war, nothing more or less.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head><supplied resp="MSPP">Additional quotes from the <title type="journal">San
                        Francisco Chronicle</title></supplied></head>
            <p>"The entire circumstance of that government refusing to allow me to visit their
                country has arisen through misunderstanding. I feel quite sure," the lecturer said,
                "and when the real aim and underlying purpose of my teachings are understood by the
                Japanese I am certain that my tour will not be interrupted.</p>
            <p>"At any rate, I shall sail on schedule time and if I am not allowed to land in Japan
                I can at least go to <place>China</place> and <place>India</place> and present my
                lectures there," she continued. "Those governments have placed no obstacles in my
                path, but signed my passports this morning." </p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
