<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Statement">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014-07-02 AS encoded</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014-08-15 CH proof and edit</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1917-03-07"><supplied resp="MSPP">7 Mar 1917</supplied></docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Statement on Release from Prison</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp422002</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Mrs. Sanger Out After Balking at Fingerprints</title>,
                    <title type="journal">New York Call</title>, Mar. 7, 1917</bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="NYC">NY Call</name>
            <name id="ROHA">Halpern, Rose</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Sanger spoke and answered questions at a luncheon at the <org>Hotel
                Lafayette</org> immediately after being released from <org>Queens County
                Penitentiary.</org></p>
        <index level1="Brownsville Clinic"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="arrests and imprisonment"/>
        <index level1="Marion, Kitty"/>
        <index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="arrests"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>MRS. SANGER OUT AFTER BALKING FINGERPRINTS</head>
        <div type="section">
            <q who="NYC"><p><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Mrs. Margaret Sanger,</person> birth
                    control advocate, who completed her 30-day sentence yesterday, won a two-hour
                    fight with the authorities yesterday morning when they attempted to take her
                    finger prints before leaving Queens county penitentiary. Because she persisted
                    in her refusal to submit to this bit of red tape imposed upon ordinary
                    criminals, her sentence was prolonged two hours and a half. Her followers, who
                    had arrived to welcome her at 7:30 o'clock, were kept waiting in the icy wind
                    till 10:30.</p>
                <p>Warden <person reg="McCann, Joseph">Joseph McCann</person> went to Mrs. Sanger
                    the night before her release and told her that by order of <person
                        reg="Lewis, Burdette G.">Commissioner Lewis,</person> she would have to
                    remain under lock and key until she was finger printed. Immediately after her
                    sentence was pronounced and all through her imprisonment Mrs. Sanger had refused
                    to submit to what she regarded as an indignity.</p></q>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub">Struggled for Two Hours.</head>
                <p>"It is time the authorities learned to discriminate between political criminals,
                    those who are fighting for ideals, and cutthroats. <person reg="McCann, Joseph"
                        >Warden McCann</person> has been very nice about it, as he has about
                    everything else during my term here. But they kept after him to get the finger
                    prints. He had to get two keepers, <person reg="Murray, Keeper">Murray</person>
                    and <person reg="Foley, Keeper">Foley,</person> and they were unable to force
                    me. The struggle lasted for two hours, until both the keepers and I were worn
                    out. Then an <person reg="Unidentified">officer</person> came in and said that
                    he had received a telephone message from the commissioner to set me free."</p>
                <q who="NYC"><p>During the three long hours of waiting, Mrs. Sanger's friends paced
                        up and down the icy walks outside. An automobile waited her return to
                        civilization and a patient movie man stood valiantly by his camera and froze
                        his toes while the struggle was waging behind prison walls.</p>
                    <p>Mrs. <person reg="Byrne, Ethel Higgins">Ethel Byrne,</person> who had been
                        sentenced to 30 days at <org reg="Blackwells Island Penitentiary">Blackwells
                            island</org> and who had been released after a hunger strike which
                        lasted 11 days, was eagerly waiting for her sister, oblivious to the
                        cold.</p>
                    <p><person reg="Goldstein, Jonah J.">Jonah J. Goldstein,</person> Mrs. Sanger's
                        attorney, was among those who waited, and Mrs. <person
                            reg="Stuyvesant, Elizabeth">Elizabeth Stuyvesant,</person> at one time
                        sought by the police on a birth control charge; <person
                            reg="Stone, Margaret Grant">Mrs. Eugene P. Stone,</person> sister of
                            <person reg="Grant, Percy Stickney">Dr. Percy Stickney Grant;</person>
                        <person reg="Blossom, Frederick">Dr. Frederick Blossom,</person>
                        <person reg="Todd, Helen">Miss Helen Todd,</person>
                        <person reg="Halperin, Rose">Mrs. Rose Halperin,</person>
                        <person reg="Lesher, Robert A.">Prof. Robert A. Lesher</person> of <org
                            reg="Columbia University">Columbia,</org> Miss <person
                            reg="Patch, Carolyn">Carolyn Patch</person> and Miss <person
                            reg="Marion, Kitty">Kitty Marion.</person></p></q>
            </div>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">Sing the Marseillaise.</head>
            <p><q who="NYC">Miss Marion, who is a militant suffragist from <place>England,</place>
                    and who had hunger struck and been forcibly fed innumerable times, led the
                    assembly in the singing of the <title type="song">Marseillaise</title>.
                    Attracted by the sound, the inmates of the penitentiary clustered at the
                    windows, opening them so that they could hear better. One feebly joined in, but
                    her voice emphasized the cheerless silence of the others.</q></p>
            <p><q who="NYC">When at last, Mrs. Sanger came out amid loud cheers, Mrs. Halperin,
                    president of the <org>Brownsville Mothers Birth Control league,</org> rushed
                    forward and pushed a huge bunch of roses and lilies in her arm.</q>
                <q who="HALRO">"From the Brownsville mothers,"</q>
                <q who="NYC">she said. And, although later in the day, Mrs. Sanger was overwhelmed
                    with flowers from <person reg="Pinchot, Gertrude Minturn">Mrs. Amos
                        Pinchot,</person> and <person reg="Hope, Mrs. Augustus">Mrs. Augustus
                        Hope,</person> she wore her clients' flowers all day.</q></p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <q who="NYC"><p>With loud cheers that her prisoners at the window took up, Mrs. Sanger
                    was driven away to the Hotel Lafayette, where she received the first cup of
                    coffee she had tasted for a month, she said.</p>
                <p>During the luncheon-breakfast she was overwhelmed with questions as to her future
                    plans.</p></q>
            <p>"The fight has been going on all month," she said. "I haven't lost any time. Every
                day, I had clinics among the prisoners. The statement was given out in one of the
                papers, Mr. Goldstein tells me, to the effect that I hadn't opened my mouth about my
                work since I entered the penitentiary. That is not true. Many of the women were
                waiting for me and the information that I had to give them. There isn't a soul in
                Queens County penitentiary that hasn't the information now."</p>
            <q who="NYC"><p>Because Mrs. Sanger has still to face the charge of conducting a public
                    nuisance, she will not be able to go far on the lecture trip that has been
                    planned for her by the <org reg="Birth Control League of America">Birth Control
                        league.</org> She does not expect to travel beyond <place reg="Chicago, IL"
                        >Chicago,</place> although the trip was planned to the Pacific.</p></q>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">Washes Off Prison Air.</head>
            <p><q who="NYC">Yesterday afternoon, Mrs. Sanger splashed ecstatically around in
                        <org>Fleischmann's Baths</org>.</q> "I want to get washed all over," she
                said. <q who="NYC">In the evening she went to see <person reg="Duncan, Isadora"
                        >Isadora Duncan.</person></q></p>
            <p>"Already I feel fit to begin my work again," she said.</p>
            <q who="NYC"><p>Mrs. Sanger will spend the day with her <person reg="Sanger, Grant"
                            ><person reg="Sanger, Stuart">two children</person></person> at <place
                        reg="Lake Grove, NY">Lake Grove, Long Island,</place> where they are
                    attending school.</p></q>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
