<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-01-20 CH transcribe and encode</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1925-01-27">27 Jan 1925</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>Regulation of Fit Children of the World</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp421032</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Mrs. Sanger Says Women Are Slave; Knowledge Barred</title>,
					<title type="journal">Waterloo (IA) Evening Courier</title>, Jan. 28,
				1925</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="WEC">Waterloo Evening Courier</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>Sanger gave this speech before the General Federation of Women's Clubs in Des Moines. The
			speech was not found. For notes from another speech she gave during this trip, see <xref
				from="236564.xml">Des Moines Address Notes</xref>, Jan. 26, 1925.</p>
		<index level1="unfit to reproduce" level2="social burden of"/>
		<index level1="women" level2="enslavement of"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Mrs. Sanger Say Women Are Slaves; Knowledge Barred</head>
		<dateline><place reg="Des Moines, IA">Des Moines</place>, <date value="1925-01-28">Jan.
				28</date>--</dateline>
		<p>"We who advocate the dissemination of such knowledge do not say there should be no
			children, nor do we desiter to regulate the number any family should have. But we do say
			that parents should give to their children a sound heritage, a sound body, and a sound
			mind. We do say that the epileptic, the insane, the feeble minded, should have no
			offspring. We do say no to the temporarily or permanently diseased. And, too, we do say
			that the coming of children should be properly spaced out, not one every year, so common
			in hundreds of families, but not oftener than once in three or four years, so that the
			mother can properly recover from previous child birth.</p>
		<p>"Millions of the women of the <place>United States</place> are in deeper and more
			dreadful slavery than the negroes of the south, because the distribution of sound,
			sensible, scientific knowledge of birth control is forbidden. Yet the church and the
			state neglect them--yes, even cry out against their freedom from the haunting specter
			over them."</p>
		<p>
			<q who="WEC">That was the declaration of Mrs. Margaret Sanger, noted birth control
				advocate, in an address before the <org>Des Moines Federation of Women's Clubs</org>
				at Hoyt Sherman place auditorium yesterday afternoon. The largest audience which has
				attended a meeting of the federation heard Mrs. Sanger's plea for "Regulation of the
				Fit Children of the World."</q>
		</p>
		<p>"This continued refusal to allow the distribution of contraceptive knowledge is the
			greatest waste of physical and economic vitality the nation permits. It fills our
			insane, feeble-minded, epileptic and charitable institutions, it causes inconceivable
			suffering to thousands of women and children who cry out for a fair chance to live as
			normal beings, and we are paying for the ignorance we are bringing upon the nation in
			high infant and maternal mortality, child labor, disease and poverty."</p>
		<p>"<place>Iowa</place> and the United States,"<q who="WEC"> Mrs. Sanger declared,</q> "must
			attack the great social problems at their roots by preventing the propagation of the
			insane, the feeble minded, the epileptic, the diseased and other dependents on the
			state, or social chaos is imminent." </p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
